<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#skk">
   <teiHeader xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of the Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
            <editor ref="part:adgu">
               <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian_transEng01</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
                  <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                  <editor ref="part:adgu">
                     <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                  </editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                     <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                  <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian</idno>
                  <availability>
                     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                     </licence>
                  </availability>
                  <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div corresp="#skk_01">
<p corresp="#skk_01.01">Here, as follows, is what will be taught by the holy man: the way (<foreign>de</foreign>) of one who searches weal.<note>The meaning of <foreign>de</foreign> is ambiguous. Another possibility is to take the third meaning recorded in OJED, viz. ‘in relation to, with regard to, toward, to’, in which case the alternative translation would be ‘what will be taught by the holy man to the one who searches weal’. See Oglobin 2000: 184.</note> As regards what are called the hermits’ holy precepts for society (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</foreign>),<note> See the discussion of the title in the Chapter 6.</note> all people should exert themselves [to follow them]. These are the words of the holy man, revealing the hermits’ holy precepts for society.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.02">These are the ten holy accomplishments (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-krəta</foreign>), which must be adhered to by all people. Anyone who starts to uphold the holy instructions of the accomplishments (<foreign>sasana krəta</foreign>), is destined to be long-lived, to be of long youth,<note>The word <foreign>ñovana</foreign>, which seems to be derived from Skt. <foreign>yauvana</foreign> ‘youth, youthfulness, adolescence, puberty, manhood’, here probably has one of the meanings ‘ageless, long youth, youthful’ (MW, s.v.) that are also inherent in the Skt. word.</note> to have success in paddy fields (<foreign>kuras</foreign>),<note>ASD translate <foreign>kuras</foreign> as ‘<foreign>ternak</foreign>’ (livestock), which seems unlikely. In MdS, <foreign>kuras</foreign> is a verbal base meaning ‘to rince, clean up’. One occurrence in KaPani 737 seems to furnish a clue: <foreign>upamana ṅuṅkuṅ añjiṅ, hayaṅ aya kadaekna, sandigana ṅuruṅ hayam, hayaṅ rampes pamuluna, upamana dina kəbo, hayaṅ nimu pakən ṅuras</foreign> “just as we raise dogs, wishing they are obedient; just as we cage the chickens, wishing their feathers are good; just as, regarding the buffalo, we wish to find them for <foreign>ṅuras</foreign>”. Seeing the relationship <foreign>ṅuras</foreign> with the buffalo, perhaps this word means ‘to plow’)? If so, then the base <foreign>kuras</foreign> most likely means ‘rice-field’.</note> to have success in cultivation,<note>The word <foreign>tahun</foreign> means ‘seasonal plant, i.e. agriculture’ = OJ (OJED: s.v. <foreign>tahun</foreign> 2). Cf. also RS 2.2 <foreign>ṅuniveh kahayvakənaniṅ rāt kabeh, dadyaniṅ tahun, laṇḍuṅaniṅ udan, karuhun kadīrghāyuṣakəna śrī mahārāja</foreign> “and especially he should foster the well-being of the whole world, the success of the crops, the long duration of rains, and in the first place bring about the longevity of the great king”. Among parallels in OS texts, I may cite PNJ 129 <foreign>jadyan kuras jadyan tahun</foreign> “The paddy fields and crops are successfully growing” and TB 35v <foreign>pada ñovana, dadian kuras, dadian tahun, dadian kaneneh</foreign> “All people are youthful, the paddy fields, crops, and livestocks are successfully growing”. Note that <foreign>dadian</foreign> and <foreign>jadyan</foreign> are equivalent, the former a loanword from OJ, the latter its proper OS form <foreign>jadyan</foreign> (from <foreign>jadi</foreign>).</note> to stand firm,<note>I interpret <foreign>dəgdəg tañjər</foreign> as ‘stand firm’. The word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> is probably related to <foreign>adəg</foreign>, so in this case, <foreign>dǝgdəg tañjər</foreign> is a twin form (see Chapter 3, §Morphology). In some texts, we find <foreign>dǝdǝg</foreign> instead of <foreign>dǝgdǝg</foreign> (e.g. in PNJ 150 <foreign>dǝdǝg tañjǝr jaya ñovana</foreign>) so the word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> seems to be a reduplication of <foreign>dǝg</foreign>. The word <foreign>dədǝg</foreign> in MdS means ‘well-built, strongly-built, square built, a fine body’, so it is synonymous with <foreign>tañjǝr</foreign> (MdS <foreign>tanjeur</foreign> ‘standing upright’). Cf.  <foreign>sakadəgdəgna</foreign> ‘according to the individual’ in SKK 5.3. However, it is noteworthy that Hardjadibrata (based on Eringa) notes the idiom <foreign>deugdeug tanjeuran</foreign> ‘where people come from all corners to see’. If this meaning was also prevalent in OS, then an alternative translation might be ‘crammed by visitors’.</note> to win in battle — all people [who do so] will be youthful.<note>The construction <foreign>ñovana na uraṅ reya</foreign> is rather unusual. Hardjadibrata designates this case in MdS as an unsyntactical compound. Maybe emend <foreign>ñovana na</foreign> to <foreign>ñovana</foreign>?</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.03">This is the explanation<note>Based on OJED, <foreign>byakta</foreign> = <foreign>vyakti</foreign> (Skt visible appearance, becoming evident or known) evidence, proof, clarification, explanation; in later texts, esp. <foreign>kidung</foreign>s = <foreign>byakta</foreign>, q.v.</note> of the ‘Ten Holy Accomplishments’: [their are] the shadows of the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>), the reflections of the ten holy paths (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-marga</foreign>), the manifestations of the ten sense faculties (<foreign>dasa-indriya</foreign>), what is needed to make<note> <foreign>di</foreign> here is marking the direct object, like <foreign>ri</foreign> in OJ. On the function of the preposition <foreign>di</foreign> in OS, see Chapter 3, §Note on <foreign>di</foreign>.</note> the distant world and the near world<note>In MdS, <foreign>lamba</foreign> means ‘singular, uncomplicated; simple, (just very) common’, like OJ <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘single (not double), incomplete, halfhearted’. However, in the present context it seems that it is an OS translation of the OJ compound <foreign>bhuvana ləmbana</foreign>, attested in SHH 40.1 <foreign>manon vijñana ṅaranya panonta ri madoh ri bhuvana lǝmbana</foreign>, <foreign>jñānendriya ṅaranya panonta ri maparǝk maṅke pratyakṣa ṅaranya</foreign> “Seeing with discernment (<foreign>manon vijñāna</foreign>) is your means to see what is far in the ‘distant world’, the faculty of knowledge is your means to see what is near, here, which is called the direct perception”. The word <foreign>ləmbana</foreign> or <foreign>lamba</foreign> can be traced to Skt. <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘hanging down’, but also ‘long, large, spacious’ (MW, s.v. <foreign>lamba</foreign>). Another way to analyze <foreign>bhuvana ləmbana</foreign> might be as deriving from <foreign>bhuv-anālambana</foreign>, which should be <foreign>bhv-anālambana</foreign> in correct Skt. (see OJED <foreign>anālambana</foreign>, meaning ‘without relation to an object’), perhaps a suitable way of saying 'distant'. What is clear is that <foreign>bumi lamba</foreign> must mean ‘distant world’, the opposite of <foreign>bumi parək</foreign>. I don’t understand what considerations led ASD to emend <foreign>bumi parək</foreign> to <foreign>bumi tan parək</foreign>. Cf. SC 536 <foreign>bumi lamba bumi parǝk</foreign>.</note> prosperous.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.04">This is what we need to make the wide world prosperous: having well-lit roads, plantations being large, well developed and productive (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>),<note>The expression paka pradana is problematic both in terms of its meaning and of its function in the sentence. This combination occurs more than once in SKK (1.4, 8.1, 10.1) and once in <ref target="#smg_19.02">SMG 19.2</ref>. I have the impression that <foreign>paka</foreign> and <foreign>pradana</foreign> are two separate words, and that <foreign>paka</foreign> should not in this context be understood as a prefix. The word <foreign>paka</foreign>, without <foreign>pradana</foreign>, appears in AG 5r <foreign>si caṅciṅan</foreign>, <foreign>si laṅsitan, si paka, si rajǝn-lǝkǝn, si mva surahan, si preña</foreign>. The combination <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> only appears in lists of good characteristics applying to a servant or to a country. However, the meanings of both words are still unknown. Let us try to determine which meaning might be suitable to the context. As for <foreign>pradana</foreign>, the first derivation that comes to mind is from Skt. <foreign>pradhāna</foreign> ‘(Skt) chief thing or person, the most important or essential part; chiefly, in the first place’, in other words ‘virtuous’. The second, which I find more plausible, is from the Skt. <foreign>pradāna</foreign> ‘giving, presentation; gift’. As for <foreign>paka</foreign>, I suppose that it is to be explained as reflecting Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign> ‘ripening, becoming ripe, ripeness; maturity, perfect development (e.g. <foreign>dhiyas</foreign>, of the intellect), development of consequences (as of an act done in a former life or of any act); completion, perfection’. In this case, the word <foreign>paka</foreign> could mean ‘mature’. We may then ask whether the word Mal. <foreign>peka</foreign> ‘caring, sensitive’ is also etymologically derived from Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign>. The Sundanese and Malay words could alternatively be related to the Hindi word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> (which is traced back to Skt. pakva, another derivative of the root pac). The word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> has gone worldwide in the form of the English word <foreign>pukkah/pucka</foreign> (Hobson-Jobson 1903, s.v.). According to the Hindi dictionary by McGregor (1993), the meaning of <foreign>pakkā</foreign> is ‘1. cooked, boiled …; 2. transfer. ripe, mature, experienced, knowing, astute; …; 8. genuine, real, thoroughgoing, solid, reliable, fixed, standard; …’ and many other positive qualities. If OS paka and Mal. peka were derived from Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign>, it would be surprising that no such word appears in OJ, and this may be a reason to prefer the derivation from a more recent layer of Indo-Aryan vocabulary such as Hindi <foreign>pakkā</foreign>. In sum, I interpret <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> rather loosely as meaning ‘well developed and productive’ if it is said of a country or ‘sensitive and generous’ in the case of human qualities. If we look at the paired series such as <foreign>emet</foreign> and <foreign>imət</foreign>, <foreign>rajən</foreign> and <foreign>lǝkən</foreign>, it appears that the meaning of <foreign>paka</foreign> may be almost synonymous with <foreign>pradana</foreign>, in other words, that <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> may be a ‘twin form’. On this concept of ‘twin form’, see Chapter 3.</note> having clean yards, having well-lit front yards,<note>In the Baduy dialect, <foreign>pipir</foreign> refers to parts of the open land on the back, left, and right of the house, while <foreign>buruan</foreign> refers only to the front side (Judistira K. Garna 1987: 77).</note> also having filled houses, filled rice barns, filled chicken coops, cultivated dry rice-fields, protected taps [of palm trees]. The result is a life full of vitality: having a long-lasting health, having youthful rulers (<foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign>).<note><foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign> literary means ‘one who carry the world’, i.e. ‘the ruler’. Cf. RY 24.124 <foreign>tūs ny ambək saṅ mavaṅ rat ya ta dumulurakən sattvāsiṅ atukar.</foreign></note> Even<note>In MdS, <foreign>saṅkilaṅ</foreign> is a conjunction meaning ‘(al)though, in spite of, notwithstanding; <foreign>sangkilangan</foreign> ‘although’, but in OS it also means ‘and yet, even’. Cf. RR 1696–1599 <foreign>saṅkilaṅ na tuaṅ ais, na pərəbu puspalava, eleh-alah tan pamənaṅ</foreign> ‘even your younger brother, Prince Puspa Lawa, has been utterly defeated’.</note> in the wide [world]: having grasses, trees, climbing plants, bushes; having fresh green (<foreign>hejo lembok</foreign>) plants,<note> For a similar expression, see SKK 18.1.</note> having all trees bearing fruit, having fertile rains<note> Cf. OJ <foreign>laṇḍuh</foreign> ‘uninterrupted, prosperous’ (OJED, s.v.). ASD choose to emend it as <foreign>landuṅ</foreign>, which also means ‘long’ in MdS. </note>, having grown seasonal crops; [those] will bring life for people in general. That is what is called the holy instructions of the accomplished one (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ sasana krəta</foreign>) in the wide world.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.05">These are the ten accomplishments, considered as the shadow of the ten holy virtues. It is the reflection of the ten paths, the manifestation of the ten sense faculties.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.06">This is its explanation. Ears should not listen randomly [to a discussion],<note>See the discussion on <foreign>baraṅ</foreign> as an adverb in Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> if it is not fit to be listened to. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune (<foreign>mala</foreign>), the payment (<foreign>lunas</foreign>)<note>Cf. PR 69r <foreign>agəsna nu luput tapa, visesa dəṅ ajñana, mulaniṅ darma, saṅkan niskala, lunas tan hana, pun</foreign> “after one finished the penance, being supreme with the knowledge, with the root of <foreign>dharma</foreign>, the origin of the immaterial, accomplished without existence”.</note> is punishment [in] hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result, (obtained) from the ears, is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.07">Eyes should not watch randomly [any event], if it is not fit to be watched. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result of watching is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.08">The skin should not be used jerkingly,<note>Cf. <ref target="#smg_07.07">SMG 7.7</ref> <foreign>kulit ma ṅaranna, bogoh saprasa-prasana, lamun ku panas ku tiis, ku meraṅ ku atəl, dipake gulaṅ-gasehan</foreign> “What is called skin, loves to touch whatever it likes. If due to hot and cold, to itching and irritation, the skin is exposed to discomfort”. The word <foreign>gulang-gaséhan</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but cf. MdS <foreign>guling-gasah</foreign> vi. <foreign>guling-gasahan</foreign> ‘toss and turn, toss round and round (so. who is troubled by pain or problems)’. There is also a semantic connection with MdS <foreign>gulang-gapér</foreign>, <foreign>ngagulang-gapér </foreign>‘physically spoil so. (a sick person, lover) (by stroking, massaging, etc.), (molly-)coddle so.; keep on touching and stroking st. (e.g. an ornament o. is attached to)’.</note> due to hot and cold. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the skin is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.09">The tongue should not be wrong [in] what is tasted. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the tongue is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.10">The nose should not smell wrongly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the nose is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.11">The mouth should not speak randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the mouth is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.12">The hands should not grasp randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the hands is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.13">The feet should not step randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the feet is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.14">The anus should not be used rumblingly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the anus is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.15">The vulva and the penis should not be used for seducing,<note>In MdS, the word <foreign>kañcolah</foreign> means ‘want to draw attention through busy behavior’. ASD read <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> and translate it as ‘<foreign>mesum</foreign>’ (perversion), although <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> is unattested in MdS.</note> for [this] is the gate of misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the vulva and the penis is considered best. This is what is called the ten accomplishments. If the ten gates are completely used appropriately, the behavior of all people will be good, let alone the behavior of His Majesty the king.<note>It seems that <foreign>saṅ deva</foreign> in <foreign>saṅ deva ratu</foreign> is equivalent with <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ</foreign>, that is used to refer to the king in general. Cf. <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ haji</foreign> as a honorific name of  Kertanagara in RPG: <foreign>liṅ saṅ hyaṅ haji kr̥tthanagarā.</foreign> Cf. <ref target="#smg_39.03">SMG 39.3</ref>.</note></p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_02">
<p corresp="#skk_02.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_03">
<p corresp="#skk_03.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.07">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.08">Lorem Ipsum</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_04">
<p corresp="#skk_04.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.06">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.07">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.08">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.09">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.10">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.11">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.12">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.13">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.14">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.15">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.16">Lorem Ipsum</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_05">
<p corresp="#skk_05.01"></p>
<p corresp="#skk_05.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_06">
<p corresp="#skk_06.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_06.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_07">
<p corresp="#skk_07.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.03">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_08">
<p corresp="#skk_08.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.06">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.07">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.08">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_09">
<p corresp="#skk_09.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.03">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_10">
<p corresp="#skk_10.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_10.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_10.03">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_11">
<p corresp="#skk_11.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.06">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.07">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.08">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.09">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.10">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.11">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.12">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.13">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.14">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.15">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.16">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.17">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.18">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.19">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.20">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.21">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.22">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.23">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.24">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.25">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.26">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.27">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.28">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.29">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.30">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.31">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.32">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.33">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_12">
<p corresp="#skk_12.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.06">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_13">
<p corresp="#skk_13.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.05">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.06">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_14">
<p corresp="#skk_14.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.04">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_15">
<p corresp="#skk_15.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_15.02">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_16">
<p corresp="#skk_16.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_16.02">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_17">
<p corresp="#skk_17.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.03">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_18">
<p corresp="#skk_18.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.04">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.05">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_19">
<p corresp="#skk_19.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.03">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_20">
<p corresp="#skk_20.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_20.02">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_21">
<p corresp="#skk_21.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.02">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.03">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.04">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_22">
<p corresp="#skk_22.01">Lorem Ipsum</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_23">
<p corresp="#skk_23.01">Lorem Ipsum</p>
<p corresp="#skk_23.02">Lorem Ipsum</p></div></body></text>
</TEI>