<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#siksaguru">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Translation of the Śikṣā Guru</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaGuru_transEng01</idno>
                <!-- Replace by filename following FNC -->
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!-- <notesStmt><note><bibl>Digital translation of <bibl><ptr target="bib:"></ptr></bibl>.<relatedItem target=""></relatedItem></bibl></note></notesStmt>-->
            <!-- provide a notesStmt if you need to add some precision regarding the establishement of the translation -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull> <!-- Copy and paste the titleStmt and publicationStmt of the edition file -->           <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Śikṣā Guru</title>
                    <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                    <editor ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </editor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                        <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaGuru</idno>
                        <availability>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                                <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                                <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                            </licence>
                        </availability>
                        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <!-- if your translation is a copy of already published one: fill a biblStruct -->
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Part mandatory -->
                <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
                <p></p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
            <!-- replace this by a line that has you as @who, that has the @date on which you finished the first basic encoding of the file, and that has the following description of what was finished on that date: "Initial encoding of the file." Then add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div>
    <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_01.01">I will first teach the servant of the dharma as follows. You will succeed in listening to the discussion of the holy dharma and the determined state of the holy gnosis. There is what is called the pure circle of three bodily domains,<note>On the concept of <foreign>trikāya maṇḍala pariśuddha</foreign>, see Chapter 9.XX (§Dharma and Three Bodily Domains).</note> uttered by the teacher to the servant of the dharma. That is possibly the action, speech, and mind. If there is a feeling of loss in your heart,<note>The emendation of <foreign>pṛdayanta</foreign> into <foreign>hṛdayanta</foreign> is not only easily justifiable on palaeographic grounds, but also based on the connection of <foreign>līna</foreign> ‘feeling of lost’ with hati ‘heart’ in several OJ texts. Cf. RY 24.41: <foreign>aḍā kalana līna riṅ hati</foreign>.</note> it is them that should be practiced and restrained. You should just guard them and fix them, for they are  the causes of finding joy and sorrow, good and bad.</p>
             <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_01.02">If your action, your speech and your mind are unrighteous, in that case you surely obtain the wrong. If your action, your speech, your heart are righteous, in that case it is clear that you obtain the virtue. That is why there is a proverb “Thus one repeatedly baths, the water is touched by the original nature of the human: bad meets its bad, good meets its good”.<note>The water metaphor also occurs in SKK 20.2.</note> Likewise is human nature.</p>
             <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_01.03">What are the illustrations with regard to the consequence of this, [namely]: bad from its bad, good from its good? As follows is your analogy:<note>I consider the word <foreign>upadyanta</foreign> to be derived from Skt. <foreign>upādhi</foreign> ‘what is put in the place of another thing, substitute; anything that has the mere appearance, disguise, peculiarity, attribute; limitation, qualification, condition, postulate’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>upadi</foreign>). In this text, it seems that this word is an equivalent of <foreign>lvir</foreign>, so I interpret it as ‘analogy, allusion’.</note> there is what is called the priceless jewel, its value can not be known, being incomparable<note><foreign>tan paprameya</foreign> is denazalitation of <foreign>maprameya</foreign>, which is not recorded in OJED, but it seems to have the same meaning as aprameya ‘immeasurable, countless, unfathomable, incomparable, indescribable, without equal’ (OJED, s.v.).</note> in terms of beauty. The meaning is: the priceless jewel and the most coveted jewel. Is it fitting to be bound to bell-metal, copper, and tin by you? What is the appropriateness [of such a condition]? It is evident that if its splendor and its shine come out, then your binding for the priceless jewel and your tieing for the most coveted gem in such a manner are appropriate.</p>
             <p n="4" corresp="#siksaguru_01.04">As follow is the word of the holy treatise: <quote><foreign>ləpas ca vuṅkunuṅ ceva, adhika udika tatte tatur tathya tuṅgəṅ, tad eva nigaḍyate</foreign>.</quote><note>This "hybrid Sanskrit" passage could not be traced. It is clear that this passage is not entirely in Sanskrit but a mixture of Sanskrit and Old Javanese. The word <foreign>ləpas</foreign> means 'release'; <foreign>vuṅkunuṅ</foreign> only appears in <foreign>pavuṅkunuṅ</foreign>, recorded among the list of <foreign>vatək i jro</foreign>. The reading of C is <foreign>buṅ kuniṅ</foreign> 'yellow bamboo' which is more understandable in meaning, although it is difficult to reconcile with the present context. The word <foreign>adhika</foreign> means ‘superior, eminent, excellent’, but <foreign>udika</foreign> is obscure; <foreign>tatte</foreign> (<foreign>tattve</foreign>?) and <foreign>tathya</foreign> probably convey the meaning of ‘true, truth’, and are probably attributes of <foreign>tatur</foreign> ‘gold’. The word <foreign>tuṅgəṅ</foreign> means ‘steadfast, firm, unmoved, unshaken’. The general meaning of this excerpt that I can guess based on the OJ exegesis is the statement that hair is unsuitable as the binding of a jewel.</note> Because what is considered loose hair is square hair (? <foreign>vulu pasagi</foreign>); there is the <foreign>uḍika</foreign>, the <foreign>tater</foreign>, and the lice.<note> The word <foreign>sorasa</foreign> is not recorded in OJED, but probably it refers to Skt. <foreign>saurasa</foreign> ‘a partic. insect infesting the hair’ (MW, s.v.).</note> Are all of them appropriate to be bound to the priceless jewel and chained to the most coveted jewel? No, it is not like that; they should be bound to the bell-metal, copper, and tin. Why is that appropriate? The binding to the priceless jewel, the chaining to the most coveted jewel, such is the word of the holy treatise: <quote><foreign>ləpas ca vuṅkunuṅ ceva, adhika udika tatte tatur tathya tuṅgəṅ nu yvagyanika</foreign></quote>.
.</p>
             <p n="5" corresp="#siksaguru_01.05">There is what is called the glowing gold,<note><foreign>Santaṅva</foreign> is not recorded in OJED, but the Old Sundanese SMG also has <foreign>santaṅva</foreign>. My interpretation is based on the interchangeability of <foreign>v</foreign> and <foreign>p</foreign> of the Skt word <foreign>santāpa</foreign> ‘burning heat, glow, fire’ (OJED, s.v.).</note> beautiful gold; its value is one <foreign>kati</foreign>. The course of action<note>vrəttya is my conjectural emendation of <foreign>vrәt</foreign> (AB) and <foreign>vr(uḥ)nya</foreign> (C). I take it as an irrealis of <foreign>vṛtti</foreign> ‘mode of being, nature, kind, activity, function; complex formation, compound, style of composition, mode of life, conduct; mode of being, nature.’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>wṛtti</foreign>).</note> will be [as follows]: it is mixed seven times seven [times],<note>The word <foreign>inapisan</foreign> is not recorded in the OJED. It is probably an -<foreign>in</foreign>- form of the second base of <foreign>apisan</foreign> 'to be one, to be united, joined' (OJED, s.v. <foreign>pisan</foreign>). However, I did not find the passive inapisan in the OJ corpus accessible to me. I do  not exclude the possibility to emend it to <foreign>linapisan</foreign> ‘to be layered’. The following combination, <foreign>pituṅ apitu</foreign>, is also not found in the corpus. My translation ‘seven times seven [times]’ is tentative.</note> transforming into the weight of one <foreign>tahil</foreign> of stone. How can it be strong, not undulating, unwavering, when it is set ablaze again? For only in this way is the best quality of all the gold, and then your binding of priceless jewels and your tying of the most coveted jewel are appropriate and good.</p>
             <p n="6" corresp="#siksaguru_01.06">It [i.e. gold] is bound with bell-metal, copper, and tin, its splendor and its shine are not coming out. What are the reasons why they are not appropriate? Wrong innate [disposition], wrong karma, wrong nature. Just so is the holy supreme dharma:<note>The meaning of <foreign>san hyaṅ dharma viśeṣa</foreign> is unclear; it probably refers to the personified holy soul since it is mentioned with avakta ‘your body’.</note> it is a priceless gem. And also your body: it  is the most coveted gem. </p>
             <p n="7" corresp="#siksaguru_01.07">Here is the analogy of bell-metal, copper, and tin: they are not appropriate to be bound to the priceless jewel, [and be]  tied by you to the most coveted jewel.</p> 
             <p n="8" corresp="#siksaguru_01.08">They are as follows: bad actions, improper speech, and impure minds towards all humans — especially toward scholars. The meaning is: bad actions, improper speech, and a dirty mind are really not appropriate; the holy dharma shall be reflected upon; furthermore, protect [it] in your body,<note> One would expect the irrealis or imperative form in this context, so the reading could be emended to <foreign>rakṣa</foreign>.</note> and even more so with respect to holy men.<note>Besides the term <foreign>paṇḍita</foreign>, which I consistently translated as 'scholar,' we find several synonyms to denote the teacher, one of which is vvaṅ <foreign>sādhu</foreign> ‘holy man; saint’, as we see in this paragraph. Another word that is also used as a synonym for <foreign>paṇḍita</foreign> is <foreign>vvaṅ atuha</foreign> (equivalent to Sanskrit <foreign>guru</foreign>?).</note> No, it is not proper [to have improper speech, etc.]: repeatedly your birth [arises]; one stops to desire having a child, having a wife, building a family, having relatives and a mother in law. He is unable to protect [himself] from bad actions, improper speech, a bad mind towards all humans, and especially towards ascetics. How would your protection of your body be appropriate? That is ‘the glowing’ (santaṅva) according to the scholar. It means the glowing gold: the good action, the good speech, the good heart. Those should be protected by [means of] the holy dharma.</p>
             <p n="9" corresp="#siksaguru_01.09">As follows is the reason why it is called the pure circle of three bodily domains, according to the scholar: tri means three. The circle of three bodily domains is pure.<note>From a stylistic point of view characteristic of <foreign>tutur</foreign> genre, the explanation of the gloss <foreign>trikāya maṇḍala pariśuddha</foreign> in this sentence is rather unusual. Normally, each Sanskrit term is described individually. Could it be that all manuscripts are corrupt in this passage? The description of the Old Sundanese version in SMG for the same terminology is more elaborated than that of the SiGu.</note> So it is said. Thus are the three bodily domains, according to the scholar.</p> 
             <p n="10" corresp="#siksaguru_01.10">As follows is the beginning<note><foreign>təmbǝy</foreign> seems to be a typical OJ word in  the manuscript tradition in West Java, occurring instead of the more common <foreign>tambay</foreign> or <foreign>tambe</foreign>. OS texts also have <foreign>tǝmbəy</foreign>. MdS only has its derived form <foreign>mitəmbəyan</foreign> ‘to start’.</note> of the affection of a scholar toward the servant of the dharma. It is pure in good thought. Do it quickly! Do not be tucked in with dirty thoughts.  The heart and mind are pure. Then, purify the mind and the set of your emotions! You should be aware when thinking; you should practice the activity of begging for alms (<foreign>bhikṣālakṣanam</foreign>)<note>The compound <foreign>bhikṣālakṣanam</foreign> is unattested in OJ and my translation, based on the understanding of <foreign>lakṣaṇa</foreign> in its Old Javanese sense of ‘action, doing, practice’ etc. (see OJED s.v.) is tentative.  Alternatively,  it may be rendered as  ‘the one of mendicant (<foreign>bhiksu</foreign>) character’.</note> with full attention.</p>
             <p n="11" corresp="#siksaguru_01.11">Here are your characteristics, O holy man. Do not just be attached to servants. It is evident when the hair has been cut. Cut it [so that] there is no obstruction or hindrance. That is the purity (<foreign>pariśuddha</foreign>): you should cut it before and you should control it. It is what is called †<foreign>r̥kr̥t</foreign>† gold, and making flower offerings with water.<note>All manuscripts have vañva, unattested in OJED. I take it to be a variant of <foreign>bañu</foreign>. However, the irrealis form seems unnecessary. Or should it be read <foreign>vaño</foreign>?</note> In this manner you serve the scholar. Do not commit the sin of violating the guru’s bed (<foreign>gurutalpaka</foreign>),<note> The term <foreign>gurutalpaka</foreign>, 'the teacher's bed', denotes a negative behaviour: AgP 353.19 explains it as marrying (or having sex with) the teacher's wife or the  teacher's child: <foreign>gurutalpaka ṅaranya makastrī rabiniṅ guru</foreign>, <foreign>anakniṅ guru</foreign>. In SiGu, this term is not to be confused with the more common <foreign>guru talapakan</foreign>, meaning the 'teacher's foot sole', or total devotion toward the teacher. See <ptr target="#xml:id=siksaguru_05"/>.</note> [which is] a misfortune for the world; [rather, you] should fear him. You should be devoted and submit to the teacher, you should carry out [acts of] extreme respect toward the teacher, including scholars. [In this manner you] come to the realization of that goal.</p>
             <p n="12" corresp="#siksaguru_01.12">In this manner you are the servant of the scholar, and even more so of the king. Do not be unfaithful toward the king. [You] will be fined and hated. You should be afraid of him, so that you will not be sold and die horribly. You should be loyal to the king: that is why [you] come to the realization of that goal (i.e., avoiding being sold and dying). You<note>This implies the audience of the text involved rāma etc. Alternatively, if the word kasādhyanya indicates the fruit to be enjoyed rather than the realization of the goal of loyalty to the king, one could translate as follows: ‘You [will become] in this manner: an elder (<foreign>rāma</foreign>), a <foreign>kalaṅ</foreign>, a <foreign>gusti</foreign>, a vizir (<foreign>patih</foreign>) in the village (<foreign>banva</foreign>)’.</note> elder (<foreign>rāma</foreign>), <foreign>kalaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>gusti</foreign>, vizir (<foreign>patih</foreign>) in the village (<foreign>banva</foreign>),  [should behave] in this manner. Furthermore, [concerning] the quality (<foreign>dharma</foreign>) of a balanced mind in people like you, you should not have an unbalanced voice<note><foreign>timpaṅ</foreign> means ‘crippled, limp’ (OJED, s.v.). In this context of legal preceding, I interpret it as ‘unbalanced’.</note> in the legal proceeding, do not lean left and right with respect to good and bad qualities. It is not appropriate [as the] behavior of an experienced man, says the holy scriptures. That [wrong behavior] should not be followed by you, that is the reason why [if you follow it] the three domains of body and mind (<foreign>trikāya maṇḍalam cittam</foreign>) are not achieved. Then the servants of the dharma should devote their full attention to what is called ‘the sacred circle of the three pure bodily domains’. It is the beginning of the affection of the scholar toward the servants of the dharma.</p>
         </div>
          
          <div>
              <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_02.01">There is a second [type of] affection of the scholar toward the servant of the dharma, which is called the ten rules (<foreign>daśaśīla</foreign>).<note> About the concept of daśaśīla as a term for the ten organs, see Chapter 9.XX.</note> They are the following: ears, eyes, nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hands, genitals, anus, legs. This<note>In the SiGu, the word ini, not recorded in OJED, is often used instead of nihan. This is probably an Old Sundanese influence, since this word is very frequent in Old Sundanese texts.</note> is what the servant of the dharma should hear.</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_02.02"><foreign>Śrotra</foreign> means ears. What is the sphere of the ears? They serve as a gate to hear the bad and good words. When you hear sweet and fragrant words, your heart becomes comfortable. When you hear a bad word, its fault is evidently unthinkable. Please do not repeat it. A good action for the teacher, that is what the servants of the dharma who are deaf<note>I wonder whether we should render tuli as tuluy ‘immediate continuation’ (see OJED s.v. <foreign>tuli</foreign>  II: ‘see <foreign>tuluy</foreign>’) in this phrase. If it is the intended word, then the translation of <foreign>tuli maṅrəṅə̄ aji saṅ viku</foreign> would be ‘the immediate continuation of hearing the scriptures of hermits’.</note> in hearing the scriptures of the hermit should endeavor to carry out.</p>
              <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_02.03"><foreign>Cakṣuh</foreign> means eyes. What is the sphere of activity of the eyes? To see good and bad, which causes joy and sorrow. How could they (i.e., the eyes) cause joy? They serve as your instrument to see the good deeds. You are without hindrance<note>My interpretation of <foreign>laṅsar</foreign> as ‘unobstructed, without hindrance’ is based on the meaning in MdS (Hardjadibrata, 2003: s.v. langsar), which seems to be adequate with the context. In OJ the meaning is unclear, it is related with <foreign>luṅsur</foreign> ‘come down, slip down’.</note> by means of that. How could that bring sorrow? From them (the eyes, <foreign>saka rika</foreign>), you should see the gold<note>All manuscripts contain the same reading, but the phrase <foreign>mulata mas</foreign> is dubious and problematic. However, the sentence <foreign>mulata mas ri paḍanya janma len saka rika</foreign> is problematic for several reasons. First, the phrase <foreign>mulata mas</foreign> is difficult to understand in this context. Second, while the sequence <foreign>len saka rika</foreign> occurs very often, meaning ‘other than that’, in this context, I am inclined to consider <foreign>len</foreign> as an attribute to <foreign>janma</foreign>, so <foreign>janma len</foreign> would mean ‘other people.’ Indeed, this phrase is rarely found in OJ, but it is attested in BY 15.16: <foreign>yan movaha kita janma len kakanta</foreign>. Cf. also <foreign>vvaṅ len</foreign>, a more common combination than <foreign>janma len</foreign>, occurring in Slo 30j: <foreign>amaṅan ulihnya gumavayakən sakāryaniṅ vvaṅ len</foreign>.</note> of the other fellow human beings. You walk to a public place, you see people with disabilities, leprosy, invalidities, goiter, [a stomach affected by] starvation (? <foreign>buḍaya</foreign>),<note>The word buḍaya is not attested in OJED. My tentative translation is based on a guess from <foreign>budayut</foreign> in MdS ‘having a distended stomach’.</note> defolded,<note>OJED glosses <foreign>tikəl</foreign> as ‘broken (of something straight), broken in two, with a sharp bend or break (in a straight line), esp. of the line of the brows (when cross or angry)’. It is not clear which part of the body it refers to, but it seems to be the hand or the foot.</note> stiff and rigid [limbs],<note> OJED records the word <foreign>kǝkəṅ</foreign> without giving the meaning. However, we find its equivalent <foreign>kəṅkəṅ</foreign> in OS SMG, referring as a kind of hand disease. I interpret it as ‘rigid’, synonymous with stiff, by comparing it with the MdS word <foreign>jengkeng</foreign> adj. ‘(unc.) stiff (like a corpse)’; <foreign>ngajengkeng</foreign> ‘stretched (stiff)’; <foreign>jejengkengan</foreign> ‘keep on stretching (of so. tormented by pain or grief)’ (Hardjadibrata, 2003: s.v. <foreign>jengkeng</foreign>); also with MdJ <foreign>kêngkêng</foreign> ‘sturdy; stiff, rigid’.</note> all kinds of frightening appearance<note>I chose <foreign>bhīmarūpa</foreign> ‘frightening appearance’ on the basis of the shared reading of <ptr target="#B"/> and <ptr target="#B"/>. Even though it is not attested in the OJ corpus at my disposal, this compound is attested in Skt sources, attributed to gods, goddess, humans, and animals. However, one would expect to have <foreign>virūpa</foreign> in this context, which is often mentioned along with the list of deforemd or otherwise sick people. Cf. AgP 51.29-52.12: <foreign>virūpa krūra malina, akuru, atəhər agalak, puṇḍuṅ, maliṅ, kuḍisən; asiṅ vvaṅ melik iriya deniṅ hamə̄ niṅ avaknya</foreign>.</note> that exist in humans, let alone those who are blind and deaf of the eyes and ears. Furthermore, do not hurt somebody who has disable bodies.<note><foreign>chedakṣara</foreign> is not recorded in OJED. I take it as a <foreign>tatpurusa</foreign> compound formed from <foreign>cheda</foreign>, in the OJ sense of ‘injured, hurt, with a defect’ (OJED, s.v.), and Sanskrit <foreign>kṣara</foreign> (unattested in OJED), meaning ‘the body’ (MW, s.v.).</note> You should not be like that. It is called avoiding strong emotion (<foreign>caṇḍaparihāra</foreign>),<note>I translate caṇḍaparihāra as ‘avoiding strong emotion’: cf. <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign>, Skt. ‘fierce, violent, cruel , impetuous, hot, ardent with passion, passionate, angry’; <foreign>parihāra</foreign>, ‘shunning, avoiding, excluding, abandoning’ (MW, s.vv.).</note> for the innate nature and karma<note>I take <foreign>nijakarma</foreign> as a <foreign>dvandva</foreign> compound meaning ‘innate nature and karma’.  See the parallel salah nija salah karma in SiGu 1.6.</note> are not seen. Also, people hurt because of it, that is what the servant of the dharma should pay attention to.</p>
              <p n="4" corresp="#siksaguru_02.04"><foreign>Grhāṇa</foreign> means nose. What is the sphere of activity of the nose? It serves as an instrument to smell fragrant scents (<foreign>surabhi</foreign>), bad smell (<foreign>asurabhi</foreign>), [and] extraordinary smell (<foreign>asādhāraṇa</foreign>).<note><foreign>asādhāraṇa</foreign> is not attested in OJED. It is from Skt. ‘extraordinary’ (MW, s.v.). In this context it means ‘strong smell, extraordinary smell’.</note> <foreign>Surabhi</foreign> means fragrant, <foreign>asurabhi</foreign> means stinky and musty [odor], <foreign>asadhāraṇa</foreign> means singed smell (<foreign>haṅit</foreign>).<note> Instead of emending <foreign>haṅit</foreign> to OJ <foreign>asaṅit</foreign> ‘with the smell of burning (singeing), burnt’, I keep the reading <foreign>haṅit</foreign>, and render it as a West Javanese spelling variant; Cf. MdS <foreign>hangit</foreign> ‘id’.</note> Therefore, the kinds of smells are three. When you smell the fragrance, your heart is happy; when you smell a stinky and musty [odor], your heart is not happy, then<note>I am inclined to consider <foreign>ya</foreign> in <foreign>ya mətu krodhanta</foreign> as an emphatic or deictic particle (OJED, s.v. <foreign>ya</foreign> 1).</note> your anger appears; that is the cause for the inappropriate speech to arise. The three bodily domains of ultimate truth (<foreign>trikāya paramārtha</foreign>)<note> For the term <foreign>trikāya paramārtha</foreign> vis à vis <foreign>trikāya maṇḍala pariśuddha</foreign>, see Chapter 9.XX.</note> are not experienced. That is the reason why the sphere of the nose must be properly paid attention to and seriously cared after by the servants of the dharma. </p>
              <p n="5" corresp="#siksaguru_02.05"><foreign>Jihvā</foreign> means tongue. What is the sphere of activity of the tongue? It serves as an instrument of tasting<note> My emendation paṅrasanikaṅ ‘the instrument to taste’ is based on the common expression in the context of saḍṛasa. Cf. OJ exegesis on Vrh 34, in which we find <foreign>paṅrasa</foreign> with <foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>: <foreign>pinakapaṅrasa pakənanya yan pamukti ṣaḍrasa</foreign>. Alternatively, we could probably emend to <foreign>pamukti</foreign> which has the same meaning.</note> the six flavors, namely: salty (<foreign>lavaṇa</foreign>), spicy (<foreign>kaṭuka</foreign>), bitter (<foreign>tikta</foreign>), sour (<foreign>amla</foreign>), savory (<foreign>kaṣāya</foreign>),<note>In Sanskrit, <foreign>kaṣāya</foreign> means ‘astringent’, but the OJ exegesis gives <foreign>vuduk</foreign> as its equivalent. According to Zoetmulder, <foreign>vuduk</foreign> is ‘fat; also: sweet flavour’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>wuduk</foreign>), I take it as savory to differentiate with sweet. Cf. Malay term <foreign>gurih</foreign> ‘id.’; note also the term <foreign>nasi uduk</foreign>, a kind of dish with rice as a basic, cooked in coconut milk and multitude of spices resulting in a very  fragrant and flavorful rice.</note> sweet (<foreign>madhura</foreign>). These are called the six flavors (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>). <foreign>Lavaṇa</foreign> means salty, <foreign>kaṭuka</foreign> is spicy,<note> I take the meaning of <foreign>lada</foreign> as ‘spicy’ from OS and MdS. In OJ it means  ‘pepper’, as in Proto Malayo-Polynesian.</note> <foreign>tikta</foreign> bitter, <foreign>amla</foreign> sour, <foreign>kaṣāya</foreign> savory, <foreign>madhura</foreign> sweet. Those are called the six flavors (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>). Furthermore, they are all enjoyed by you; you will be oblivious of everything but becoming sick because of them. You shall not do so. Its object (i.e. the tongue) becomes a goal to be realized. That is a sign that you will abandon good works toward the teacher. If so, then the pure circle of three bodily domains is not experienced.</p> 
               <p n="6" corresp="#siksaguru_02.06"><foreign>Vāk</foreign> means words.<note> One would expect <foreign>tutuk</foreign> instead of <foreign>śabda</foreign>, but <foreign>śabda</foreign> as a definition of <foreign>vāk</foreign> in the context of ten organs is attested in KAS 05j <foreign>ka, ikaṅ kāya, vāk, manah. kāya ṅa śarīra, solahniṅ taṅan suku, ya kāya ṅaranya. vāk ṅaranya: śabda. salvirniṅ vuvus ya śabda ṅaranya</foreign>.</note> What is the sphere of activity of the words? Not every word should be followed by you: harsh words [equal] aggressive behavior.<note><foreign>capala asta</foreign> ‘restless hands’ seems to be out of context. In inscriptions, for example Waharu I, <foreign>vāk capala</foreign> and <foreign>capala hasta</foreign> ‘(Skt) with restless hands, rash in coming to blows, aggressive’ are listed among the <foreign>sukha-duhkha</foreign> ‘the vicissitudes of life’: <foreign>rah katəmu riṅ havan, vākcapala, hastacapala</foreign>. Should it be emended to <foreign>vāk capala</foreign>? Cf. Vrh 18.2: <foreign>panasbaran, lobha, capala hasta, capala pāda, vākcapala... lakṣaṇaniṅ citta si rajah</foreign>.</note> In the situation of powerlessness and in trouble, you do not make other human beings feel at ease. However, what you should speak are words that are sweet, gentle, [with] an agreeable [facial] gesture. All kinds of things that make them indifferent to the world, and which are heard in succession by human beings,<note>It seems that <foreign>loka para</foreign> is an equivalent of <foreign>loka parəmpara</foreign> 'uninterrupted, in succession’ (or <foreign>parampara</foreign>; see OJED, s.v. parampara), attested in AgP 352.21: <foreign>hana ujar yogya rĕṅə̄n deniṅ loka parəmpara</foreign>; Cf RY 3.3, which mentions <foreign>parampara</foreign> after the verb <foreign>karəṅə̄</foreign>: <foreign>praśasta karĕṅə̄ parampara ujar narendrâpagəh</foreign>. Alternatively, <foreign>loka para</foreign> could be considered as an equivalent of <foreign>paraloka</foreign> ‘other people’.</note> that is how you guard your words.</p>
              <p n="7" corresp="#siksaguru_02.07"><foreign>Tvak</foreign> means skin. What is the sphere of activity of the skin? To feel and experience heat and cold. The point of this is the effort to restrain the passions<note> In this context, I take the meaning of <foreign>viṣaya</foreign> as ‘passion’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>wiṣaya</foreign> 4.).</note> that emerge from the skin.</p>
              <p n="8" corresp="#siksaguru_02.08"><foreign>Pāṇi</foreign> means hand. What is the sphere of activity of the hand? To join the fingers of the hand,<note><foreign>masaṅguliniṅ</foreign> taṅan literally means ‘to make the fingers of hand as one’ or, in other words,  ‘to join the fingers of hand’; masaṅguli is from <foreign>aṅguli</foreign> ‘(Skt) finger’, but the derivative form saṅguli and verbal form <foreign>maṅguli</foreign> are not recorded in OJED.</note> to join [the hands] when talking to the teacher. Also not to join the hands together with the teacher, and especially not to point the hand toward the face of the teacher; when the food of the teacher should be grasped, it should not be touched with the mouth.<note> In OJED, <foreign>acumbana</foreign> usually means ‘making love, having sexual intercourse, united in love’, but in this context, the Sanskrit meaning ‘to kiss, to touch with the mouth’ (MW, s.v. <foreign>cumb</foreign>) seems more suitable.</note> Or, do not take the teacher’s divine-property (<foreign>drabya hyaṅ</foreign>), let alone of any [kind of] people. This means do not be disloyal<note>MsC has <foreign>paracidra</foreign>, while MsA and MsB have <foreign>palarcidra</foreign>. The latter two manuscripts seem to be influenced by the Old Sundanese. Cf. SMG 2.2 <foreign>hantə ṅǝnah palar cidəra ku paṅəsi huma sakalih</foreign>.</note> if he has a request. There are “sword leaves”<note> The usage of the word <foreign>āsipattra</foreign> ‘sword leaves’ in OJ is usually used in depictions of hell. Here it seems to be an allusion to the misfortune provoked by the teacher. Compare the similar expression <foreign>jagat upadrava</foreign>, one of the ‘terrifying weapon’ possessed by the teacher.</note> in the sacred texts of the hermit. Such is what you should do to guard your hands.</p>
              <p n="9" corresp="#siksaguru_02.09"><foreign>Pāyu</foreign> means anus. What is the sphere of activity of the anus? It is circular (<foreign>utər</foreign>) and joint (<foreign>saṅga</foreign>). Defecating [and] farting [as appropriate] are the ways in which you guard the anus. You should not fart in front of the teacher of men, you should not be in front of people when you defecate. [These behaviors] are not ordered by the teacher, and by all the religious wanderers (<foreign>paramābhyāgata</foreign>).<note>The combination <foreign>paramābhyāgata</foreign> is not attested in OJED; it literally means ‘most respected guest’, which I interpret as a reference to a ‘religious wanderer’.</note> Such are the ways in which you should guard your anus. </p>
             <p n="10" corresp="#siksaguru_02.10"><foreign>Upastha</foreign> means sexual organ. What is the sphere of activity of the sexual organ? To feel sexual pleasure [and] to urinate. The meaning is as follows: to urinate, it should not be done in front of the people, especially those of high birth: male, female, servant, noble man, low, medium, and high. Since its <foreign>maruruca</foreign> (?) is great, the sins of becoming a human being comes out.  What is considered as its sins? You see a man that is sold. His sins are his [way of] seizing women: misbehaving toward friends, misbehaving toward the teachers, taking by force forbidden women. The body vehemently becomes dirty if it is as such.  [That] must be paid attention to by the servants of the dharma.</p>
              <p n="11" corresp="#siksaguru_02.11"><foreign>Pāda</foreign> means the feet. What is the sphere of activity of the feet? To walk wherever is your destination, whether you go to the north, south, west, east, or to sit in a sila position. Then the way to guard the foot is: not kicking, not assuming an impolite posture,<note> See OJED <foreign>aṅraṅkak</foreign> ‘to assume a bold attitude (ready for fighting)’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>raṅkak</foreign>), listing one occurrence from RY 8.61: <foreign>vvil kapvāṅraṅkak caṅciṅañ caṅka-caṅkag</foreign>. Cf. BS 105.14–106.3 <foreign>oṁ sila sila mānuṣa, sila gaṇa maheśvara, amire bhaṭāra brahmā, aṅraṅkak bhaṭāra rudra, akilusū mahādeva, aṅruṅkuk saṅ hyaṅ śaṅkara, sila pas bhaṭāra viṣṇu, atimpuh bhaṭāra śambhu, muruduṅ bhaṭāra śiva, aṅadәg i gunuṅ nāga</foreign>. Can it mean ‘to crawl' as <foreign>merangkak</foreign> in Malay? </note> not [assuming] an unstable posture,<note> The derivative form <foreign>pamagah-magahan</foreign> is not recorded in OJED. Its base, <foreign>agah-agah</foreign>, is plausibly a variant spelling from the base <foreign>haga-haga</foreign> ‘thoughtless, wild, uncontrollable’ (OJED, s.v.).</note> not to lean sideways, not to lie stretched out, not sit by dangling<note><foreign>padvaṅdaṅ</foreign> is not recorded in OJED, but the meaning from MdS <foreign>dongdang</foreign>, <foreign>sidongdang</foreign> ‘sit with both legs dangling to one side’ seems to be appropriate in the present context.</note> the leg in front of the teacher, [or] of all religious wanderers. This [is the way] to guard the foot, [which] should be made the object of full attention by the servant of the dharma.</p>
          </div>
          
<div>
            <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_03.01">As follows is the third affection of the scholar to the servant of the dharma. Here are the five instructions, as they are called, namely:</p>
    <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_03.03">Non-anger (<foreign>akrodho</foreign>) means: it doesn't happen that a servant of the dharma shows his anger in front of the teacher, let alone to all good men. Obedience to the teacher (<foreign>guruśuśruṣā</foreign>) means that you are devoted and obedient to the teacher, never far from the feet of the elders. [It should be] that way if there is an order from the teacher. Furthermore, [you should be] completely pure: the highest reality of three bodily domains should be made the object of your attention, that is good act, good speech, good thought. The pure circle of three bodily domains, together with the ten rules and the five instructions should be made the object of your efforts whether [you are] far or near. Thus is called the obedience to the master. Purity (<foreign>śauca</foreign>) is to clean your hand<note>The verbal form <foreign>masəhan</foreign> is not recorded in OJED (s.v. <foreign>wasĕh</foreign>); it is probably derived from the second base <foreign>vasəhan</foreign>, and the meaning is equivalent with <foreign>masəhi</foreign> ‘to wash, cleanse, purify’.</note> when you hold the food of the teacher, let alone the properties of the scholar. Moderation in food (<foreign>āhāralāghava</foreign>) [means] you are swift [while] eating; [however, if] the balls of rice are big, and [your] eating quickly is uncontrolled,<note>I take the meaning of <foreign>kāmakāra</foreign> to be ‘uncontrolled’, in the light of  its meaning in Skt: ‘the act of following one's own inclinations, spontaneous deed, voluntary action, acting of one’s own free will, free will’ (MW: s.v.). This combination is not attested in the OJ corpus available to me. It is noteworthy that MsC has <foreign>humarak</foreign>, being probably a mistake for <foreign>humaraka</foreign> ‘to eat’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>haraka</foreign>); however, the -<foreign>um</foreign>- form is not recorded in OJED. Another possibility is to interpret <foreign>humarak</foreign> in the light of the Sundanese usage, where <foreign>harak</foreign> means ‘pugnacious, aggressive; (dial.) greedy, covetous, acquisitive’ (Hardjadibrata, 2003: s.v. harak). If MsC contains a correct reading, then the translation would be ‘greedy when you eat quickly’.</note> don’t [act] like that! That is called the belly palace (<foreign>kukṣi pura</foreign>).<note> The sequence kukṣi pura is not attested in OJED; however, each word is known in OJ.</note> How could [that] be the way of eating? It is only the vital breath with control (<foreign>prāṇa sadhāraṇa</foreign>) the daily means of subsistence of one who thinks about the Holy Good. These are what are called the five instructions, which should be made the object of attention by the servant of the dharma.</p> 
</div>
              <div>
                  <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_04.01">As follows is the fourth affection of the scholar to the servant of the dharma. This is what is called the instruction of the dharma, here it is—the śloka about it is as follow:</p> 
                  <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_04.03">The meaning is [as follows]; <foreign>ālekhyam</foreign><note>From Skt. <foreign>ālekhya</foreign> ‘writing, drawing’ (MW, s.v.), unattested in OJ. The attested Skt. word in OJ is <foreign>ālekhana</foreign> ‘id.’.</note> means: do not write on the soil, do not write on the board, let alone on your body, when you serve the teacher, because there are those who are considered men with good characteristics, [but] constantly writing their thighs when talking with the teacher; <foreign>hasitam</foreign>:<note>From Skt. <foreign>hasita</foreign> ‘laughing, jesting, smiling’ (MW, s.v.).</note> not to laugh in the front of the teacher, let alone to make a joke; <foreign>gītam</foreign>: not to sing—by means of that, you do not to claim expertise,<note>All manuscripts share the reading <foreign>vijakṣaṇa</foreign> instead of the more common OJ spelling <foreign>vicakṣaṇa</foreign> ‘(Skt) sagacious, clever, wise, versed in, familiar with, expert in’. The spelling <foreign>vijaksana</foreign> is found in OS texts = MdS.</note> if it is not ordered by the teacher; <foreign>jr̥mbhanam</foreign>:<note>The Sanskrit meaning of <foreign>jr̥mbhanam</foreign> ‘yawning; stretching the limbs, slackness’ (MW, s.v.) does not fit perfectly with the OJ explanation. </note> not to express hunger [and] satiety in the front of the teacher; <foreign>kaṇṭhāravam</foreign>:<note>My conjecture <foreign>kaṇṭhāravam</foreign> is based on the similar <foreign>aksara</foreign>s of <foreign>ṭa</foreign> and <foreign>va</foreign> with <foreign>da</foreign> and <foreign>na</foreign> respectively. The meaning in Skt. is ‘roaring from the throat’ (MW, s.v. <foreign>kaṇṭhīrava</foreign>). The only way to make this passage make sense is to emend to <foreign>paṅhvab</foreign> ‘to yawn’ where the witnesses have different readings (<foreign>paṅvamka</foreign> A, <foreign>paṅvambha</foreign> B, <foreign>paṅomka</foreign> C).</note> not to yawn; †<foreign>akadanǝm</foreign>† do not stretch a body [and emit sounds]<note>The word <foreign>paṅulet</foreign> is a denazalitation of <foreign>maṅulet</foreign> means ‘to stretch (after sleep)’, cf. OS <foreign>kumuliat</foreign>, MdS <foreign>nguliat</foreign>.</note> in front of the teacher;  <foreign>śuddham phalarahasyam</foreign>: not to talk in a selfish manner in the front of the teacher, let alone to pronounce the name “penis”; it is forbidden [to do] so. What is called <foreign>na karotu gurumukhe</foreign>, its meaning is as follows: the servant of the dharma should not do [that].</p>
                  <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_04.04">As follows  is called the instruction of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> (<foreign>dharmaśikṣā</foreign>).</p>
                  <p n="4" corresp="#siksaguru_04.06">The meaning is, <foreign>śalākāñjanam</foreign>: not to use eye-paint in front of the teacher, [or] in front of forbidden women. <foreign>Suravile</foreign>: not to open the mouth<note>My emendation pakrala-krala is based on the word <foreign>karāla</foreign>, attested in OJED, from Skt <foreign>karāla</foreign> ‘opening wide, having a gaping mouth and projecting teeth; formidable, dreadful’; karāladaṅṣṭra ‘having terrific teeth’. It seems to reflect the understanding of the author of the SMG: “<foreign>Suravile</foreign> means to be indifferent: especially when talking and deliberating, one does not apply good manners towards the scholar.”</note> wide when one talks, let alone when one sits in sila position, not to use unguent, not to use powder, if [one is in] a place for the service to the teacher, let alone [where] his water stream springs forth, or [in] the pavilion for welcoming [guests].<note> This sentence is really hard to understand and my translation is tentative.</note> <foreign>Dantagharsā</foreign>: not to chew a quid (<foreign>susur</foreign>) when you speak to the teacher. <foreign>Adhyasta</foreign>:<note>I consider Skt. <foreign>adhyasta</foreign> meaning ‘placed over, disguised, supposed’ which seems to correspond to the OJ explanation. </note> without the ornaments of the performers, [of those] who play musical instruments, and [of] the <foreign>kecaka</foreign> dancers.<note> The word <foreign>kecaka</foreign> (variant: <foreign>kicaka</foreign>) may denote a type of dance, or dancer. See Acri (2014: 23, fn.40) for the interpretation of this word.</note> <foreign>Hārahataḥ</foreign>: not taking a pointed lance [measuring] one <foreign>vilah</foreign>.<note>The word <foreign>savilah</foreign> as a unit is attested in KM: <foreign>hana po dene tan ahiḍep vinalərakən, riṅ rabī, anak, lavan kahula, təmbuṅən ta riṅ priṅ, savilah, yen ikaṅ kayuha, avake gitikən, yen gigire, sukune, manih tan ahiḍep, talenana hayo hasiṅsət</foreign>. Cf. MdS <foreign>sawilah</foreign> ‘id’, Mal. <foreign>bilah</foreign>.</note> <foreign>Prayāsamāgama</foreign>: not to stare at each other with a forbidden woman, let alone the wife of the teacher, [not] to carry civet-cats (<foreign>luvak</foreign>) along with prey, not to occupy oneself constantly with eating and drinking in front of the teacher. That is called the instruction of the dharma (<foreign>dharmaśikṣā</foreign>); [it] should be made the object of the attention of the servant of the dharma.</p>
              </div>
          <div>
              <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_05.01">As follows is the fifth affection of the scholar toward the servant of the law. How is it? As follows:</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_05.03">This is the foot sole of the teacher, <foreign xml:lang="san-Latn">pravakṣyāmi</foreign>: [I] will explain the sacred virtuousness. Yesterday, they are being in the status of the great vehicle (? <foreign>mahāyānam hyatisṭa=ṭānti</foreign>): they, those eminent ones of the past: Buddhist, Shaivist, slave, noble man, inferior, middle, and superior, men or woman, the aim of the sacred virtuousness is to be collected as a book (?, <foreign>vataṅ</foreign>). In the first place, they were taught about the foot soles of the teacher. What is the reason? Thus: the teacher doesn't create misfortune. How so? The foot sole of the teacher was followed by them in the first place. <foreign>Sakābhyāsa praṇamyāsīt</foreign>: if you have followed to the foot sole of the teacher within you, it is indeed praṇamya, i.e. the one who should be venerated properly (<foreign>sǝmbahǝn</foreign>). <foreign>Sǝmbahǝn</foreign> means: [someone] that should be obeyed. The meaning is:</p>
              <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_05.05"><foreign>Anāma</foreign>: the name of the teacher is not obtained (i.e., not to mention). <foreign>Hīnavākyam</foreign>: not speaking about the holy virtue, not slandering the elder [teacher]. <foreign>Siṁharupāñ ca grahaste</foreign>: [you are] seen to show anger toward the teacher. It does not happen like that. <foreign>Saṅ guru saṁghāsanam pritam</foreign>: you have to be quick; if the teacher is met on the way, or if the meeting happens in his own territory, the teacher should be revered. Also, not to speak impetuously to the teacher, let alone to precede the teacher's steps, not being noisy when you take a bath, not to step in the shadow of the teacher, not carrying the teacher on both arms, not drinking the <foreign>tvak</foreign> of the teacher, not smelling the food of the teacher. Do not wear the attire of the teacher, unless it is asked. One should not be careless with the wife of the teacher, children of the guru, father and the senior of the teacher, <foreign>pvasi</foreign> of the teacher, nephew of the teacher, or the teacher's beloved ones, and the teacher’s abandoned wife. Thus is what is called the foot sole of the teacher, that should be made the object of the attention of the servant of the dharma.</p>
          </div>
          <div>
              <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_06.01">This is the sixth affection of the teacher to the servant of the dharma. How is it? As follows: what is called the holy Misfortune of the World. How is it? As follows: bad meets its bad, good meets its good, crooked meets its crooked, straight meets its straight, joy meets its joy. What is indeed the condition of happiness and sorrow of all beings? It is you, not anyone else, the pure circle of three bodily domains. The meaning is: because from the action, speech, and heart is the joy, and the joy and sorrow. You know the cause of the bad conduct which is the cause of misfortune: that is why the good conduct is to be performed, so that [it is] not affected by the misfortune. This is what is called the world of misfortune. It should be made the object of the attention of the servant of the dharma.</p>
          </div>
          <div>
              <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_07.01">There is the seventh affection of the scholar to the servant of the dharma. It is called the holy four powers (<foreign>caduśakti</foreign>) of the scholar. What is the reason why it is called <foreign>caduśakti</foreign>? The four powers mean its powers. They are used as weapons by the scholar. What are they? As follows: the formula of jalakuna (<foreign>cakra jalakuṇa</foreign>), the formula of jalapakṣa, the enveloping formula (<foreign>cakra sambharaṇa</foreign>), the formula of hand like a stars (<foreign>cakra taraṅgabāhu</foreign>).</p>
          </div>
             
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
