<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#skk">
   <teiHeader xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of the Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
            <editor ref="part:adgu">
               <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian_transEng01</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
                  <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                  <editor ref="part:adgu">
                     <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                  </editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                     <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                  <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian</idno>
                  <availability>
                     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                     </licence>
                  </availability>
                  <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div corresp="#skk_01">
<p corresp="#skk_01.01">Here, as follows, is what will be taught by the holy man: the way (de) of one who searches weal.<note>The meaning of <foreign>de</foreign> is ambiguous. Another possibility is to take the third meaning recorded in OJED, viz. ‘in relation to, with regard to, toward, to’, in which case the alternative translation would be ‘what will be taught by the holy man to the one who searches weal’. See Oglobin 2000: 184.</note> As regards what are called the hermits’ holy precepts for society (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</foreign>),<note> See the discussion of the title in the Chapter 6, §The Title.</note> all people should exert themselves <supplied reason="subaudible">to follow them</supplied>. These are the words of the holy man, revealing the hermits’ holy precepts for society.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.02">These are the ten holy accomplishments (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-krəta</foreign>), which must be adhered to by all people. Anyone who starts to uphold the holy instructions of the accomplishments (<foreign>sasana krəta</foreign>), is destined to be long-lived, to be of long youth,<note> The word <foreign>ñovana</foreign>, which seems to be derived from Skt. <foreign>yauvana</foreign> ‘youth, youthfulness, adolescence, puberty, manhood’, here probably has one of the meanings ‘ageless, long youth, youthful’ (MW, s.v.) that are also inherent in the Skt. word.</note> to have success in paddy fields (<foreign>kuras</foreign>),<note> ASD translate <foreign>kuras</foreign> as ‘<foreign>ternak</foreign>’ (livestock), which seems unlikely. In MdS, <foreign>kuras</foreign> is a verbal base meaning ‘to rince, clean up’. One occurrence in KaPani 737 seems to furnish a clue: <foreign>upamana ṅuṅkuṅ añjiṅ, hayaṅ aya kadaekna, sandigana ṅuruṅ hayam, hayaṅ rampes pamuluna, upamana dina kəbo, hayaṅ nimu pakən ṅuras </foreign>“just as we raise dogs, wishing they are obedient; just as we cage the chickens, wishing their feathers are good; just as, regarding the buffalo, we wish to find them for <foreign>ṅuras</foreign>”. Seeing the relationship <foreign>ṅuras</foreign> with the buffalo, perhaps this word means ‘to plow’)? If so, then the base <foreign>kuras </foreign>most likely means ‘rice-field’.</note> to have success in cultivation,<note> The word <foreign>tahun</foreign> means ‘seasonal plant, i.e. agriculture’ = OJ (OJED: s.v. <foreign>tahun</foreign> 2). Cf. also RS 2.2 <foreign>ṅuniveh kahayvakənaniṅ rāt kabeh, dadyaniṅ tahun, laṇḍuṅaniṅ udan, karuhun kadīrghāyuṣakəna śrī mahārāja </foreign>“and especially he should foster the well-being of the whole world, the success of the crops, the long duration of rains, and in the first place bring about the longevity of the great king”<foreign>.</foreign> Among parallels in OS texts, I may cite PNJ 129 <foreign>jadyan kuras jadyan tahun </foreign>“The paddy fields and crops are successfully growing” and TB 35v  <foreign>pada ñovana, dadian kuras, dadian tahun, dadian kaneneh </foreign>“All people are youthful, the paddy fields, crops, and livestocks are successfully growing”. Note that <foreign>dadian</foreign> and <foreign>jadyan</foreign> are equivalent, the former a loanword from OJ, the latter its proper OS form <foreign>jadyan</foreign> (&lt; <foreign>jadi</foreign>).</note> to stand firm,<note>I interpret <foreign>dəgdəg tañjər</foreign> as ‘stand firm’. The word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> is probably related to <foreign>adəg</foreign>, so in this case, <foreign>dǝgdəg tañjər</foreign> is a twin form (see Chapter 3, §Morphology). In some texts, we find <foreign>dǝdǝg</foreign> instead of <foreign>dǝgdǝg</foreign> (e.g. in PNJ 150 <foreign>dǝdǝg tañjǝr jaya ñovana</foreign>) so the word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> seems to be a reduplication of <foreign>dǝg</foreign>. The word <foreign>dədǝg</foreign> in MdS means ‘well-built, strongly-built, square built, a fine body’, so it is synonymous with tañjǝr (MdS tanjeur ‘standing upright’). Cf. <foreign>sakadəgdəgna</foreign> ‘according to the individual’ in SKK 5.3. However, it is noteworthy that Hardjadibrata (based on Eringa) notes the idiom <foreign>deugdeug tanjeuran</foreign> ‘where people come from all corners to see’. If this meaning was also prevalent in OS, then an alternative translation might be ‘crammed by visitors’.</note> to win in battle — all people <supplied reason="subaudible">who do so</supplied> will be youthful.<note> The construction <foreign>ñovana na uraṅ reya</foreign> is rather unusual. Hardjadibrata designates this case in MdS as an unsyntactical compound. Maybe emend <foreign>ñovana na</foreign> &gt; <foreign>ñovana</foreign>? </note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.03">This is the explanation<note> Based on OJED, <foreign>byakta</foreign> = <foreign>vyakti</foreign> (Skt visible appearance, becoming evident or known) evidence, proof, clarification, explanation; in later texts, esp. <foreign>kidung</foreign>s = <foreign>byakta</foreign>, q.v.</note> of the ‘Ten Holy Accomplishments’: <supplied reason="subaudible">their are</supplied> the shadows of the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>), the reflections of the ten holy paths (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-marga</foreign>), the manifestations of the ten sense faculties (<foreign>dasa-indriya</foreign>), what is needed to make<note> <foreign>di</foreign> here is marking the direct object, like <foreign>ri</foreign> in OJ. On the function of the preposition <foreign>di</foreign>in OS, see Chapter 3, §Note on <foreign>di</foreign>.</note> the distant world and the near world<note> In MdS, <foreign>lamba</foreign> means ‘singular, uncomplicated; simple, (just very) common’, like OJ <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘single (not double), incomplete, halfhearted’. However, in the present context it seems that it is an OS translation of the OJ compound <foreign>bhuvana ləmbana</foreign>, attested in SHH 40.1: <foreign>manon vijñana ṅaranya panonta ri madoh ri bhuvana lǝmbana</foreign>, <foreign>jñānendriya ṅaranya panonta ri maparǝk maṅke pratyakṣa ṅaranya</foreign> “Seeing with discernment (<foreign>manon vijñāna</foreign>) is your means to see what is far in the ‘distant world’, the faculty of knowledge is your means to see what is near, here, which is called the direct perception”. The word <foreign>ləmbana</foreign> or <foreign>lamba</foreign> can be traced to Skt. <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘hanging down’, but also ‘long, large, spacious’ (MW, s.v. <foreign>lamba</foreign>). Another way to analyze bhuvana ləmbana might be as deriving from bhuv-anālambana, which should be <foreign>bhv-anālambana</foreign> in correct Skt. (see OJED <foreign>anālambana</foreign>, meaning ‘without relation to an object’), perhaps a suitable way of saying 'distant'. What is clear is that <foreign>bumi lamba</foreign> must mean ‘distant world’, the opposite of <foreign>bumi parək</foreign>. I don’t understand what considerations led ASD to emend <foreign>bumi parək</foreign> to <foreign>bumi tan parək</foreign>. Cf. SC 536 <foreign>bumi lamba bumi parǝk</foreign>.</note> prosperous.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.04">This is what we need to make the wide world prosperous: having well-lit roads, plantations being large, well developed and productive (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>),<note>The expression <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> is problematic both in terms of its meaning and of its function in the sentence. This combination occurs more than once in SKK (1.4, 8.1, 10.1) and once in <ref target="#smg_19.02">SMG 19.2</ref>. I have the impression that paka and pradana are two separate words, and that paka should not in this context be understood as a prefix. The word paka, without pradana, appears in AG 5r <foreign>si caṅciṅan</foreign>, <foreign>si laṅsitan</foreign>, <foreign>si paka, si rajǝn-lǝkǝn, si mva surahan</foreign>, <foreign>si preña</foreign>. The combination <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> only appears in lists of good characteristics applying to a servant or to a country. However, the meanings of both words are still unknown. Let us try to determine which meaning might be suitable to the context. As for <foreign>pradana</foreign>, the first derivation that comes to mind is from Skt. <foreign>pradhāna</foreign> ‘(Skt) chief thing or person, the most important or essential part; chiefly, in the first place’, in other words ‘virtuous’. The second, which I find more plausible, is from the Skt. <foreign>pradāna</foreign> ‘giving, presentation; gift’. As for paka, I suppose that it is to be explained as reflecting Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign> ‘ripening, becoming ripe, ripeness; maturity, perfect development (e.g. dhiyas, of the intellect), development of consequences (as of an act done in a former life or of any act); completion, perfection’. In this case, the word <foreign>paka</foreign> could mean ‘mature’. We may then ask whether the word Mal. <foreign>peka</foreign> ‘caring, sensitive’ is also etymologically derived from Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign>. The Sundanese and Malay words could alternatively be related to the Hindi word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> (which is traced back to Skt. pakva, another derivative of the root pac). The word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> has gone worldwide in the form of the English word <foreign>pukkah/pucka</foreign> (Hobson-Jobson 1903, s.v.). According to the Hindi dictionary by McGregor (1993), the meaning of <foreign>pakkā</foreign> is ‘1. cooked, boiled …; 2. transfer. ripe, mature, experienced, knowing, astute; …; 8. genuine, real, thoroughgoing, solid, reliable, fixed, standard; …’ and many other positive qualities. If OS <foreign>paka</foreign> and Mal. peka were derived from Skt. pāka, it would be surprising that no such word appears in OJ, and this may be a reason to prefer the derivation from a more recent layer of Indo-Aryan vocabulary such as Hindi <foreign>pakkā</foreign>. In sum, I interpret paka pradana rather loosely as meaning ‘well developed and productive’ if it is said of a country or ‘sensitive and generous’ in the case of human qualities. If we look at the paired series such as emet and imət, rajən and lǝkən, it appears that the meaning of <foreign>paka</foreign> may be almost synonymous with pradana, in other words, that <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> may be a ‘twin form’. On this concept of ‘twin form’, see Chapter 3.</note> having clean yards, having well-lit front yards,<note>In the Baduy dialect, <foreign>pipir</foreign> refers to parts of the open land on the back, left, and right of the house, while <foreign>buruan</foreign> refers only to the front side (Judistira K. Garna 1987: 77).</note> also having filled houses, filled rice barns, filled chicken coops, cultivated dry rice-fields, protected taps <supplied reason="subaudible">of palm trees</supplied>. The result is a life full of vitality: having a long-lasting health, having youthful rulers (<foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign>).<note><foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign> literary means ‘one who carry the world’, i.e. ‘the ruler’. Cf. RY 24.124 <foreign>tūs ny ambək saṅ mavaṅ rat ya ta dumulurakən sattvāsiṅ atukar.</foreign></note> Even<note> In MdS, <foreign>saṅkilaṅ</foreign> is a conjunction meaning ‘(al)though, in spite of, notwithstanding; <foreign>sangkilangan</foreign> ‘although’, but in OS it also means ‘and yet, even’. Cf. RR 1696–1599 <foreign>saṅkilaṅ na tuaṅ ais, na pərəbu puspalava, eleh-alah tan pamənaṅ</foreign> “even your younger brother, Prince Puspa Lawa, has been utterly defeated“.</note> in the wide <supplied reason="subaudible">world</supplied>: having grasses, trees, climbing plants, bushes; having fresh green (<foreign>hejo lembok</foreign>) plants,<note>For a similar expression, see SKK 18.1.</note> having all trees bearing fruit, having fertile rains,<note> Cf. OJ <foreign>laṇḍuh</foreign> ‘uninterrupted, prosperous’ (OJED, s.v.). ASD choose to emend it as <foreign>landuṅ</foreign>, which also means ‘long’ in MdS.</note> having grown seasonal crops; <supplied reason="subaudible">those</supplied> will bring life for people in general. That is what is called the holy instructions of the accomplished one (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ sasana krəta</foreign>) in the wide world.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.05">These are the ten accomplishments, considered as the shadow of the ten holy virtues. It is the reflection of the ten paths, the manifestation of the ten sense faculties.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.06">This is its explanation. Ears should not listen randomly <supplied reason="subaudible">to a discussion</supplied>*, if it is not fit to be listened to. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune (<foreign>mala</foreign>), the payment (<foreign>lunas</foreign>)* is punishment <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result, (obtained) from the ears, is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.07">Eyes should not watch randomly <supplied reason="subaudible">any event</supplied>, if it is not fit to be watched. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result of watching is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.08">The skin should not be used jerkingly,<note>Cf. <ref target="#smg_07.07">SMG 7.7</ref> <foreign>kulit ma ṅaranna, bogoh saprasa-prasana, lamun ku panas ku tiis, ku meraṅ ku atəl, dipake gulaṅ-gasehan</foreign> “What is called skin, loves to touch whatever it likes. If due to hot and cold, to itching and irritation, the skin is exposed to discomfort”. The word <foreign>gulang-gaséhan</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but cf. MdS <foreign>guling-gasah</foreign> vi. <foreign>guling-gasahan</foreign> ‘toss and turn, toss round and round (so. who is troubled by pain or problems)’. There is also a semantic connection with MdS <foreign>gulang-gapér</foreign>, <foreign>ngagulang-gapér </foreign>‘physically spoil so. (a sick person, lover) (by stroking, massaging, etc.), (molly-)coddle so.; keep on touching and stroking st. (e.g. an ornament o. is attached to)’<foreign>.</foreign></note> due to hot and cold. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the skin is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.09">The tongue should not be wrong <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> what is tasted. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the tongue is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.10">The nose should not smell wrongly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the nose is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.11">The mouth should not speak randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the mouth is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.12">The hands should not grasp randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the hands is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.13">The feet should not step randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the feet is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.14">The anus should not be used rumblingly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the anus is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.15">The vulva and the penis should not be used for seducing,<note>In MdS, the word <foreign>kañcolah</foreign> means ‘want to draw attention through busy behavior’. ASD read <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> and translate it as ‘<foreign>mesum</foreign>’ (perversion), although <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> is unattested in MdS.</note> for <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the vulva and the penis is considered best. This is what is called the ten accomplishments. If the ten gates are completely used appropriately, the behavior of all people will be good, let alone the behavior of His Majesty the king.<note>It seems that <foreign>saṅ deva</foreign> in <foreign>saṅ deva ratu</foreign> is equivalent with <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ</foreign>, that is used to refer to the king in general. Cf. <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ haji</foreign> as a honorific name of  Kertanagara in RPG: <foreign>liṅ saṅ hyaṅ haji kr̥tthanagarā.</foreign> Cf. <ref target="#smg_39.03">SMG 39.3</ref>.</note></p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_02">
<p corresp="#skk_02.01">The following are called the ten devotions (<foreign>dasa-prəbakti</foreign>):<note>Cf. OJ <foreign>prabhakti</foreign> (= <foreign>bhakti</foreign>) ‘devotion, attachment, worship, love’.  No sauch word has survived in MdS. It is important to note that the list in this section contains eleven levels, not ten. Is the item of the gods devoted to ancestors an interpolation? Or is God excluded from the list of <foreign>dasa-prəbakti</foreign>? We have the correspondent hierarchy in the RPG 17a: <foreign>kunaṅ dr̥vya muleha riṅ gusti, gusti muleha riṅ taṇḍa, taṇḍa muleha riṅ mantri, mantri muleha riṅ ratu, ratu muleha riṅ vikū, vikū muleha riṅ deva, deva muleha riṅ hyaṅ, hyaṅ muleha riṅ śūnya</foreign> “As to property, it should honour its <foreign>gusti</foreign> (master), the <foreign>gusti</foreign> should honour the <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> (headman), the <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> should honour the <foreign>mantri</foreign> (mandarin), the <foreign>mantri</foreign> should honour the <foreign>ratu</foreign> (prince), the <foreign>ratu</foreign> should honour the <foreign>viku</foreign> (priest), the <foreign>viku</foreign> should honour the <foreign>deva</foreign> (god), the <foreign>deva</foreign> should honour the <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign> (Holy Spirit), the <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign> should honour <foreign>śūnya</foreign> (Supreme Non-Entity)” (Pigeaud 1960, I: 190; III: 135).</note> first, a child devoted to the father; 2, a wife devoted to <supplied reason="subaudible">her</supplied> husband; 3, a servant devoted to the officers (<foreign>pacandaan</foreign>);<note>The word <foreign>pacandaan</foreign> seems to be the group of officers. Cf. OJ <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> ‘a group of officers (= <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign>, q.v. ?) (OJED, s.v. <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> 2). It is important to note that the examples in OJED are cited from the <foreign>Raṅga Lave</foreign>, i.e. a text known to author of SKK, RL 5.12: <foreign>rahadyan pacuh amuvus, iya ujarira voṅ, agra-pāvakāraneki, iku atut, caṇḍa kaṅ muṅgu iṅ untat</foreign> “The venerable smile and speaks, and his word to the people of Agra-Pāvakārana, the <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> who is in the back  should be followed”; see also  <foreign>caṇḍamantri</foreign>, an entry that only cites data from <foreign>Tantri Kədiri</foreign> 4.3b <foreign>hiṅan iṅ parimaṇḍala dudug iṅ lor vetan kidul pascima ry uṅgvan ikaṅ satus caṇḍamantri, ndatan pinucap dohnira sakiṅ balamantrinira kapat</foreign>; 4.4a: <foreign>lila tumandiri punpunan sovaṅ-sovaṅ nimittaniṅ krəteṅ puri mevəh ry ananiṅ catus canḍamantri</foreign>. Is there any connection with <foreign>parvaṇḍan</foreign> in Old Malay? See Cœdès 1930.</note> 4, a pupil devoted to <supplied reason="subaudible">his</supplied> master; 5, a farmer devoted to the soldier;<note>The word <foreign>vado</foreign> ‘soldier, troop’ is not recorded in MdS. Cf. OJ <foreign>vadva</foreign> or <foreign>vado</foreign> from Skt <foreign>badva</foreign> ‘large number, multitude subject, follower, (the lesser) troops’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>vadvā</foreign>).</note> 6, a soldier devoted to the minister; 7, a minister is devoted to the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>;<note><foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> is problematic. The most possible base word is <foreign>taṅgan</foreign>, but it is not found in OJ and OS. Should it be understood as <foreign>taṅan</foreign> ‘hand’. If it is so, then the literal meaning of <foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> would be ‘who are giving hand, the helper’. Cf. CRP 173–175 which depicts <foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> who accompany the princesses: <foreign>saha nu aṅkat ti həla, tan liyan giraṅ naṅganan, nu naṅganan para putri nu gəlis</foreign> “Who is the one who walks in front? None other than the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign> the beautiful princesses”.</note> 8, the one who naṅganan devoted to the governor;<note>In OJ texts such as the <foreign>Pararaton</foreign> and <foreign>kiduṅ</foreign>s, the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> occupy the highest position in the palace after the king, who appeared during the Mahapahit period. Maṅkubumi's position as second in command after the king is also confirmed in Sundanese sources. Apart from this paragraph, in the RR, Sombali is the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> of king Bibisana, and occupies the highest function after the king. See SKK 11.8 regarding the duties of maṅkubumi in the Sundanese context of the 15th century.</note> 9, the governor devoted to the king; 10, the king devoted to the gods; the gods devoted to the ancestors. They are called the ten devotions. 10.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_03">
<p corresp="#skk_03.01">This is what should be practiced, the message from the true sage. ‘<foreign>Oṅ</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">I give</supplied> homage to Śiva! My veneration <supplied reason="subaudible">goes</supplied> to the Holy Five <foreign>tathagatas</foreign>!’ <foreign>Pañca</foreign> means five, <foreign>tata</foreign> means speech, <foreign>gata</foreign> means passion.<note>The relation between <foreign>gata</foreign> and <foreign>raga</foreign> ‘body’ is obscure. We could interpret <foreign>gata</foreign> as ‘those that are left’, and <foreign>raga</foreign> as ‘passion’. In this case, the translation would be “those that are left are passions”. But it seems more persuasive to take <foreign>gata</foreign> as intended to stand for Skt./OJ <foreign>gātra</foreign> ‘body’ (MW, s.v.; OJED, s.v.). The word <foreign>gātra</foreign> is attested in Kuñj 28: <foreign>ikaṅ cetana, ya ta ikaṅ gave tr̥ṣṇa, ya ta misanakən ikaṅ ātma pat, ya ta dadi kinimpəlakən, ya matəmahan ri śarīra gātra</foreign> “The consciousness, it is the product of craving, it has as relatives the four souls, it becomes a solid object, it becomes the body and the limbs”. It is important to note that the one of the mss. of the <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> comes from West Java.</note> Those ones should be well maintained, all of them. The five syllables (<foreign>pañcaksara</foreign>) are the masters of men. The meaning is: the five syllables are manifest, being  seen, experienced,<note>The word <foreign>kavrətan</foreign> is derived from <foreign>vrətta</foreign> Skt. ‘Set in motion; occurred, happened; past; matter, affair; action, conduct’. However, the manuscript has <foreign>-on</foreign> instead of <foreign>-an</foreign>, probably intended to make a correspondent sound with <foreign>katoṅton</foreign>. Cf. JM 18.22 <foreign>diucap tan kaucap, tan katoṅton, tan kavrətan, tan karagap, tan kasikəp, tan kagaməl, tan karasa</foreign> “it is said without being spoken, not being seen, not being experienced, not being touched, not being catched, not being grasped”.</note> observed, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> perceived by the senses. The master is the one to be asked by the people. That is why they are called the masters of men. As for ignorance,<note>I take <foreign>saṅmoha</foreign> as a Sanskrit derivative <foreign>sammoha</foreign> ‘stupefaction, bewilderment, confusion, insensibility, unconsciousness, ignorance, folly, illusion of mind’, not as a person <foreign>saṅ moha</foreign> ‘the one who is ignorant’. Cf. OJ <foreign>samoha</foreign> ‘id’. Could it be that the phenomenon of <foreign>ṅ</foreign> instead of <foreign>m</foreign> originates from the manner of interpreting <foreign>panyecek</foreign>? Cf. <foreign>oṅ</foreign> above, and <foreign>biṅba</foreign> (understood as <foreign>bimba</foreign>) in the inscription Kawali 5 (Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 187). The sounds /m/ and /ṅ/ are sometimes found to be interchangeable in MdS, for instance <foreign>bingbang</foreign> and <foreign>bimbang</foreign> ‘be in doubt’. The former is considered standard. </note> <supplied reason="subaudible">it exists</supplied> since the world exists.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.02">This is the “evidence” for it, that is the five spheres of activity (<foreign>pañca-byapara</foreign>): earth, water, fire, wind and ether. Words of the great holy man: “They are the substances of our <supplied reason="subaudible">bodies</supplied>; the skin is the earth, the blood <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the saliva are the water, the eyes are the light, the bones are the wind, the head is the ether. It (the skin) is called the earth in the body<note>While blood and saliva are called the water in the body, and so on</note>. The reason why they are compared to world authorities, is that they take shape<note> The word <foreign>maṅupati</foreign> is from Skt. <foreign>utpatti</foreign> ‘happening, appearing, taking place; proving right; demonstrated conclusion, proof, evidence, argument; fitness, suitability, possibility’. Cf. OJ <foreign>utpatti, utpətti, utpati, utpəti, upəti</foreign> ‘coming into existence; origin, birth, incarnation’. Also in OS texts, <foreign>upati</foreign> figures in meanings such as ‘manifestation, appearance’. Cf. CP 36r <foreign>disilihan ku saṅ rakeyan darmasiksa, paṅupatyan saṅ hyaṅ visnu, iña nu ñiən saṅ hyaṅ binayapanti</foreign> ‘being replaced by Honorable Darmasiksa, the manifestation of God Viṣṇu. He is the one who made the series of rules’. ASD translate <foreign>binayapanti</foreign> as ‘panti pendidikan’. I tend to associate <foreign>panti</foreign> with Skt. <foreign>paṅkti</foreign> ‘row, set, series, group, troop, company’ (MW, s.v.). If so, we are dealing with the local form of the Sanskrit compound <foreign>vinayapaṅkti</foreign>, which would mean ‘set of rules, series of training’. The pertinence of this interpretation is clearly seen in SC 493–496, which mentions the names of texts and teachings, in addition to mentioning <foreign>patikrama </foreign>(= OJ <foreign>paṅktikrama</foreign>): <foreign>cacanden dəṅ kararasen, tahampekan babahəman, paṅəsi binayapanti, patikrama mədaṅ kamulan</foreign> ‘The Cacanden and Kararasen, Tahampekan and Babahəman, contents of the set of rules, the order of Mədaṅ Kamulan’.</note> as the leader (<foreign>prabu</foreign>), the elder (<foreign>rama</foreign>), the hermit, the ritual expert (<foreign>disi</foreign>)<note> On <foreign>prabu</foreign>, <foreign>rama</foreign>, <foreign>rəsi</foreign> as triad elite in Sundanese, see Chapter 10. On the term <foreign>disi</foreign>, see Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 180.</note>, and the sailor”.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.03">These are the five sons (<foreign>pañca-putra</foreign>):<note> These five mythical figures are the sons of Kandyawan in the <foreign>Tantu Paṅgəlaran</foreign> and the <foreign>Carita Parahyaṅan</foreign>. The latter text adds that their mother was Kandyawati, and agrees precisely with SKK on the names of the sons. In the TP, by contrast, there are some minor variations of their names compared to the OS tradition. The OJ text has Katuṅ Malaras instead of Katuṅ Maralah and Saṇḍaṅ Garbha instead of Sandaṅ Grəba. (The latter is merely an orthographic variant.) The order in which these two sons appear is also inverted in TP. Cf. TP 61.7 <foreign>kahucapa ta sira hyaṅ kaṇḍyavan, manak ta sira limaṅ siki; saṅ Maṅukuhan anak panuha, saṅ saṇḍaṅ garbha paṅgulu, saṅ Katuṅ malaras panəṅah, saṅ karuṅ kalah kakaṅ riṅ pamuṅsu, saṅ vr̥tti kaṇḍayun pamuṅsu </foreign>“Let us tell of the holy Kandyawan, who had five sons. The eldest was Mangukuhan, Sandang Garbha the second, Katung Malaras the middle one, Karung Kalah the second youngest, and Wretti Kandayun the youngest”; CP 11a: <foreign>basa aṅkat sabumi jadi &lt;manik&gt; sakuruṅan nu misǝvǝkǝn pancaputra, saṅ apatiyan saṅ kusika, saṅ garga, saṅ mestri, saṅ purusa, saṅ patañjala, iña saṅ maṅukuhan, saṅ karuṅ kalah, saṅ katuṅ maralah, saṅ sandaṅ grǝba, saṅ vrǝti kandayun</foreign> “When he (Kandyawan) departs to become ‘a jewel in one cage’, he being the one who has the Five-Sons, those who are the reincarnation of Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusa, [and] Patanjala. They are Mangukuhan, Karung Kalah, Katung Maralah, Sandang Greba, [and] Wreti Kandayun”. For a comparison of these figures in both texts, see Hadi Sidomulyo 2021: 84–85, 111. The meanings of the names of the Five Sons are obscure. However, some of them can be guessed, such as <foreign>saṅ maṅukuhan</foreign> ‘the one who makes firm’ (from <foreign>kukuh</foreign>?), <foreign>saṅ karuṅ kalah</foreign> ‘the one whose boar is lost’, <foreign>saṅ sandaṅ grəba</foreign> ‘the one who carries a fetus’. The literal meaning of <foreign>saṅ katuṅ maralah</foreign> cannot even be guessed, but TP has <foreign>katuṅ malaras</foreign> ‘<foreign>katuṅ</foreign> with arrow’ (?). The last name, <foreign>saṅ vrəti kandayun</foreign>, might just possibly mean ‘the one whose occupation is the battlefield’ (<foreign>kaṇḍa</foreign> + <foreign>ayun</foreign>) (?).</note> <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Maṅukuhan is the earth, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Katuṅ Maralah is the water, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Karuṅ Kalah is the fire, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Sandaṅ Grәba is the wind, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Vrәti Kandayun is the ether.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.04">These are the five <foreign>kusika</foreign>s:<note>On <foreign>pañca-kusika,</foreign> see my commentary on the preceding paragraph, where the CP passage combines the <foreign>pañca-putra</foreign> with the <foreign>pañca-kusika</foreign>. Minor differences of reading also occur with regard to the names of the five <foreign>kusika</foreign>s in OS and OJ texts. In OS sources we regularly find <foreign>mestri</foreign> instead of <foreign>metri</foreign>, <foreign>purusa</foreign> instead of <foreign>kurusya</foreign>. Cf. NR 45.8 where the <foreign>kusika</foreign>s take shape in the body: <foreign>kusika riṅ kulit, garga riṅ dagiṅ, metri riṅ otot, kurusya riṅ tahulan, prətañjala riṅ sumsum</foreign>. On the history of the <foreign>pañca-kusika</foreign> in Java and Bali, see Acri 2014.</note> <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Kusika on the mountain, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Garga in the swamp, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Mestri on Mount Mahameru, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Purusa in Mandiri, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Patañjala in Panjulan.<note>Mandiri is an unidentified toponym. BM 45 mentions Tajur Mandiri which was apparently situated somewhere near present-day Bogor. Panjulan is not mentioned in BM, but a <foreign>kampung</foreign> of that name exists today in <foreign>kecamatan</foreign> Koroncong, <foreign>kabupaten</foreign> Pandeglang, Banten.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.05">If the holy five sections (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima</foreign>)* are taken into account altogether, the earth would be in harmony, all <supplied reason="subaudible">its</supplied> quarters of space. All quarters of space are east (<foreign>purba</foreign>), south (<foreign>daksina</foreign>), west (<foreign>pasirma</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>pasirma</foreign> is equivalent to Skt. <foreign>paścima. </foreign>In KaMah 120 we find <foreign>dataṅ kala ti pacirma</foreign> “Kala comes from west”. On the intrusive r, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> north (<foreign>utara</foreign>), center (<foreign>madya</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.06"><foreign>Purba</foreign>is the east, the abode of the god Iswara, whose color is white. <foreign>Daksina</foreign>is the south, the abode of the god Brahma, whose color is red. <foreign>Pasirma</foreign>is the west, the abode of the god Mahadéwa, whose color is yellow. <foreign>Utara</foreign>is the north, the abode of the god Wisnu, whose color is black. <foreign>Madya</foreign>is the center, the abode of the god Siwa, whose color is multifarious. <supplied reason="subaudible">That is</supplied> the reason why the five sacred sections (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima</foreign>) in the universe are like that.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.07">These are the five sections in <supplied reason="subaudible">the case of</supplied> the great scholar. The esoteric teaching is experienced by the one who is conscious (<foreign>si tutur</foreign>); asceticism is experienced by the one who is pure (<foreign>si liṅlaṅ</foreign>); posture is experienced by the one who is firm (<foreign>si pagəh</foreign>); perception is experienced by the one who is capable (<foreign>sy asəmbava</foreign>); liberation is experienced by the one who shares without receiving a share, who limits without being limited. The five sections in <supplied reason="subaudible">the case of</supplied> the great scholar are like that.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.08">As follows are the causes of accomplishment: they are the five gods, all embodying* your name, all watching your form. But if (the names and forms) are not guarded, as if crooked meets its crooked, straight meets its straight. This is how it is: it is by human actions that it becomes accomplished, by human actions that it becomes good.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_04">
<p corresp="#skk_04.01">These are the acts of the servant, every path taken by us as servants. The act means intellect <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> mode of conduct. Every path taken means: be fearful,<note>I take <foreign>maka</foreign> in this context as an equivalent to <foreign>mangka</foreign> in MdS ‘modal auxiliary word used in conjunction with immediately following adjective (occasionally verbs) by emphasizing how so. should act), e.g. <foreign>mangka iatna</foreign> be careful!; <foreign>mangka inget</foreign> be mindful of; <foreign>mangka sabar</foreign> be patient!’</note> be strong,<note>The word <foreign>jarot</foreign> ‘strong’ is not found in MdS, but MdJ has <foreign>jarot</foreign> ‘strong and handsome’ (Horne 1974, s.v.), which seems suitable in our context.</note> be respectful, be courteous, in behavior, in attitude,<note>Cf. <foreign>sapitvahən</foreign> in 10.3. In this case, the suffix -<foreign>ən</foreign> does not yield irrealis meaning. I presume that <foreign>pitvahən</foreign> is morphologically analogous to <foreign>pisabdaan</foreign> ‘speech’ = <foreign>sabda</foreign>. Cf. also the spelling <foreign>kaləpasən</foreign> for <foreign>kaləpasan</foreign> ‘liberation’. See Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> in action, in speech, especially when in front of His Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.02">We should be faithful in service, in order to wipe out the ten defilements (<foreign>dasa-kalesa</foreign>), so that the impurity leading to sin will be annihilated, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> heaven will be obtained.<note>All manuscripts have <foreign>kapaṅguh</foreign> ‘be obtained’; cf. OJ <foreign>paṅguh</foreign> ‘id’, not in MdS. ASD read it <foreign>kapaṅgih</foreign> as in MdS.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.03">If <supplied reason="subaudible">you are</supplied> excessive<note>On <foreign>tǝtǝiṅ</foreign>, cf. BM 623–627  <foreign>hantə paṅgərahan aiṅ, tətəiṅ oge tətəiṅ, na uraṅ anak pahatu, na uraṅ hantə dibapa, aya diinduṅ kasaruṅ</foreign> “I am not delighted, it is too much, really too much! I was an orphan, I had no father, I did have a mother, but she went astray”. Cf. MdS <foreign>teungteuingeun</foreign> ‘that’s a bit too much, that’s gone too far (of so.’s behaviour, actions, etc.), that’s gone beyond a joke (with ref. to treatment that so. suffers etc.); (as exclamation) too bad! it’s shameful! it’s disgraceful!’</note> in practicing the acts of the servant, that is worse than a monkey (<foreign>usyat</foreign>)<note>The emendation of <foreign>usyatitindih</foreign> as <foreign>usyat titindih</foreign> is based on the phenomenon of degemination which is common in scribing manuscripts. The word seems related to OJ <foreign>busyat </foreign>‘a kind of monkey’? Probably the phonological process involves the interchangeability of /b/, /v/, and /u/: <foreign>busyat</foreign> &gt; <foreign>vusyat</foreign> &gt; <foreign>usyat</foreign>. In OJ, <foreign>titindih ukir</foreign> is an expression meaning ‘mountain hermit’ (lit. ‘who lives the mountain’). Cf. ST 19 <foreign>sakveh iṅ aṅguguntuṅ maṅuyu, para poco maṅke / sakveh iṅ titiṇḍih vukir, kaṅ amuluṅ murunduṅ, ametiṅ / lavan puputut, iṅoṅ tədunakən kabeh, babaru ajana kantun, / padatisayatakena, sanjatane karepiṅvaṅ.</foreign></note> occupying a hill, performing penance on the top of the mountain, for it is forbidden to perform penance on an elephant mound<note>I translate <foreign>hunur</foreign>, not recorded in MdS dictionaries, as ‘hill, mound’; Cf. OJ <foreign>hunur</foreign> ‘id’. In MdS the form is <foreign>huñur</foreign>, but some dialects, for instance in Karawang, people recognize <foreign>unur</foreign> for the mound of earth where some archeological sites were found in Batujaya.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> a lion mound, near a great danger.<note>In this context, <foreign>bañcana</foreign> is probably equivalent with Mal. <foreign>bencana</foreign>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.04">These are the actions of man that will be of use to all people. We should not fail to follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! If<note>Cf. <foreign>jaka</foreign> in the Old Malay Tanjung Tanah manuscript in the sense ‘if’, cf. <foreign>jika</foreign> in Malay. In MdS <foreign>jaga</foreign> means ‘in the future, later; (dial.) far ahead (of a place)’. We find some examples of the change <foreign>k</foreign> &gt;<foreign> g</foreign> in Mal. and MdS, for instance, Mal. <foreign>gali</foreign> &gt; MdS <foreign>kali</foreign>, Mal. <foreign>gilir</foreign> &gt; MdS <foreign>kilir</foreign>. In SKK itself, we find both <foreign>cakal bakal</foreign> and <foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>. See also the representation of the toponym Kedah as <foreign>gədah</foreign> in 11.31. On the interchangeability of /k/ and /g/, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> we wish to be free from the five forms of reincarnation (<foreign>pañca-gati saṅsara</foreign>), we should not be deceitful (<foreign>carut</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>carut</foreign> is not recorded in MdS and OJ. The meaning of this word in Mal. is ‘ribald, vile, obscene’ (Wilkinson, s.v.). However, I sense that <foreign>carut</foreign> has a broader range of meanings in OS, like ‘deceitful, evil, filthy’, and this is the basis of my translations of the occurrences in this text (4.5, 8.6, 11.5, 13.6, 21.2).</note> should not have a habit of laziness,<note> I emend <foreign>sorereh</foreign> into <foreign>sok rereh</foreign> since the first is not attested in OS. In MdS <foreign>réréh</foreign> means ‘spread’, but seems too far from the context. I take the meaning from <foreign>rèrèh</foreign> in MdJ ‘langzaam, bedaard; traag; verwijlen, uitstellen, nalaten om iets op het oogenblik te doen’ (Gericke &amp; Roorda 1901: s.v.).</note> should not deceive ourselves. Deceiving ourselves means: what is present<note> It is clear that the scribe consistently writes <foreign>na</foreign> instead of <foreign>nu</foreign> as read by ASD in <foreign>na iña, na hantə, na lain</foreign>, so I take it as an article. Cf. JM.12.27–13.5 <foreign>sugan vaya nu milihan iña, dəṅ na iña, dəṅ na lain, dəṅ na juti, dəṅ na jati</foreign> “there may be someone who chooses that: between the truth and the opposite, delusion and reality”.</note> is considered absent, what is absent is considered present, what is true<note>The word <foreign>iña</foreign> here seems equivalent to <foreign>enya</foreign> in MdS, meaning ‘true, genuine, real’, as the antonym of <foreign>lain</foreign>, not as a demonstrative. This <foreign>əña</foreign> is only attested in a relatively more recent Old Sundanese text, namely CVG 213.</note> is considered not so, what is not so is considered true — so that<note>Cf. <foreign>karah</foreign> in MdS. It is also clearly related to OJ <foreign>harah</foreign>, <foreign>narah</foreign> ‘emphatic particle, stressing an announcement, question (<foreign>arah apa</foreign>), invitation, command, cause or reason (<foreign>arah de</foreign>, <foreign>arah wet</foreign>)’.</note> his mind is scheming, pretending, deceiving, hurting. That is the explanation of being deceitful to ourselves.<note> On <foreign>ta</foreign> in last sentence, cf. the use of <foreign>ya</foreign> in the last sentence of 4.5 — here <foreign>ta</foreign> is a short form of <foreign>eta</foreign>, so expressing a deictic meaning.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.05">Being deceitful to other people means: plucking without asking permission, taking without asking, picking without requesting, let alone looting, thieving, plundering, robbing, everything that counts as impudent and deceitful. Those are called being deceitful to other people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.06">And also infiltrating, grabbing, pilfering, seizing, groping, sneaking, let alone hanging around with a host, with a dignitary,<note>The term <foreign>paṅhulu tandaṅ</foreign> seems to be distinguished from <foreign>tohaan</foreign>. Rigg (1866, s.v. <foreign>panghulu tandang</foreign>) defines it as ‘a great man whom it is difficult to approach. A ringleader’, but Hardjadibrata notes that in <foreign>pantun</foreign> stories, it means ‘lord/lady!, master/mistress! (in addressing royal persons etc.). In RR, <foreign>paṅhulu tandaṅ</foreign> is the designation for king Manabaya. Assuming meanings like ‘dignitary’ or ‘local leader’ seems suitable in the present contexts.</note> let alone<note>The conjunction <foreign>saṅuni</foreign> ‘let alone, moreover, furthermore, and also’ is only occurred in SKK, the more common conjunction in this sense is <foreign>maṅkaṅuni</foreign>.</note> with one's own master. That should even less be done, be practiced by the servants.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.07">Do not fail to practice polite, respectful, and refined words,<note>The compound <foreign>gurubasa</foreign> is not attested in OJ. Cf. AG 4v <foreign>ṅalap kasor səmu guyu, teoh ambhək</foreign>,<foreign> gurubasa, di na uraṅ sakabeh, tuha kalavan anom</foreign> “[We should] be willing to give in, having a sweet temperament, a humble heart, refined words, all of us, young and old”. Cf. RD 45 where we find <foreign>ya sabda tata-basa, guru-basa ba- / … da suksila</foreign>. The phrase <foreign>sabda tatabasa</foreign> ‘words according to the rules’, occurring side by side with <foreign>guru-basa</foreign>, suggests that the word <foreign>guru</foreign> means ‘teacher’ in this context. Thus, the compound <foreign>guru-basa</foreign> seems to mean something like ‘words according to teaching, learned speech’.</note> to be humble and well-mannered to fellow humans, to family and relatives,<note>Pigeaud (1960–1963: vol. III, p. 175) translates <foreign>braya</foreign> in Selamandi Ib1 as ‘neighbours’; Arlo Griffiths (p.c.) prefers connecting this word, unrecorded in OJED, with Skt. <foreign>bhāryā</foreign>; <foreign>braya</foreign> in Balinese ‘family, relation’.</note> let alone to our master. We should use <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> feet to sit politely, <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> hands to pay respect.<note> See my comment on the word <foreign>umun</foreign> in  <ref target="#smg_20.04">SMG 20.4</ref>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.08">If we talk with a nobleman, with a gusti, with the lover of someone else, with a forbidden woman, let alone with our master; if we are employed <supplied reason="subaudible">by them</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not be angry<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006) note <foreign>surahan</foreign> with question mark ‘hot-tempered’, from SA 934        <foreign>ciciṅan hamo surahan</foreign> ‘firmly seated, never hot tempered’; not in OJ and MdS. However, the word <foreign>asurahan</foreign> is attested in OJ (not recorded in OJED), and its meaning seems to be something like ‘angry’, cf. SD 3.12: <foreign>vərniṅ ṣaḍpada vibhramāṅhrəṅ anaṅis humuṅ asurahan iṅ surālaya</foreign>.</note> in our minds, let alone answer wrongly, an expression of discontent visible to our master. Don’t! It is forbidden, lest the result of asceticism fail, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the result of the ancestors (<foreign>cakal bakal</foreign>)<note>This compound is not found in OJ or MdS, but attested in MdJ ‘first inhabitants of a new region, later on venerated as its tutelary spirits’. It seems equivalent with Mal. <foreign>cikal bakal</foreign>. In 10.2 it is spelled <foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>, showing variants <foreign>k</foreign> and <foreign>g</foreign>. On the sound interchangeability of /k/ and /g/, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> be lost! Lest the results<note>The word <foreign>batri</foreign> is equivalent to MdS <foreign>bati</foreign> ‘profit (gained from st.)’. Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw give the same meaning in the BM, based on the context in the text, without noticing the relation with MdS <foreign>bati</foreign>. Cf. OJ <foreign>wati</foreign> II? See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> of hard work be lost! <supplied reason="subaudible">We will</supplied> be met by the god of worldly misfortune, fined<note>The word <foreign>katigraha</foreign> is from Skt. nigraha (OJED nigraha), reanalyzed as containing a base <foreign>tigraha</foreign>, with meaning ‘to punish, to fine’. Kuñj 18 contains <foreign>vinigrahan</foreign>, apparently to be emended to <foreign>tinigrahan</foreign>: <foreign>tumiṅal ikaṅ pāpa vinigraha ḍeni saṅ yāmabalā, haṅrasa linu hatini saṅ kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> “Seeing the sinners who are punished by the troops of Yama, the heart of Kuñjarakarṇa is broken”. The word <foreign>nigraha</foreign> is common for monetary fines in inscriptions and <foreign>Śāsana</foreign> texts which use a language register similar to that of inscriptions. See for instance Cane: <foreign>knāna ya nigraha mā kā 1 su 5</foreign> (Brandes 1913: 120–125).</note> by His Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.09">If we are not faithful to our master, for instance if we are in a sick state, if we are tired, if we are careless, <supplied reason="subaudible">then</supplied> let’s honestly acknowledge that we have been very disgraceful,<note>The combination <foreign>tətəiṅ amat</foreign> is an expression with a meaning something like ‘it is a pity/how shameful’, addressed as a form of politeness in dialogue. See SKK 14.3, where such an expression is considered as <foreign>paṅvastu</foreign> ‘blessing’. More common is the expression <foreign>sumaṅər təiṅ</foreign>. On <foreign>sumaṅər</foreign>, see GNT  (s.v.  <foreign>sumanger</foreign>), where the word is related with Mal. <foreign>semangat</foreign>.</note> so that we are acknowledged to be faithful in service. But if we act, we should not be weak, we should not fall short,<note>Hardjadibrata records <foreign>kuciwa</foreign> as an archaic register ‘fault, defect, short-coming, blot, blemish; display some short-coming/blemish’. The more common meaning in MdS is ‘disappointed’ = Mal. <foreign>kecewa</foreign>.</note> should not refuse<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngontong</foreign> means ‘to say do not to someone’ (Hardjadibrata, s.v. <foreign>ontong</foreign>), but in this case it seems to have a more general meaning ‘to say no’ or in another word ‘to reject, to resist’.</note> when being ordered, should not be envious <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> malicious with those engaged in the same service, especially when seeing someone who gets praise <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> gets an audience (<foreign>parəkan</foreign>);<note>I take the meaning of <foreign>parəkan</foreign> ‘audience’ from OJ. In MdS, <foreign>parekan</foreign> means ‘concubine’ or ‘(with the Baduys) k.o. functionary (member of the village council)’.</note> seeing someone who is favored by the master, then our thoughts may become overheated.<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw translate <foreign>ñət</foreign> as ‘hot, shining’ in RR 44. Probably <foreign>ñətñot</foreign> is an intervocalic reduplication with the same meaning. Another possibility is to relate <foreign>ñot</foreign> with MdS <foreign>ñuat</foreign> (from <foreign>suat</foreign>), meaning ‘pierce (so.’s heart as it were by telling evil things about him, remind him of an insult experienced etc.)’.</note> They should not, it is forbidden!<note>See the quasi-synonymous expression <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign> in SKK 4.8.</note> Its being forbidden leads to tears,<note>Among other reasons, my emendation <foreign>dadi luh</foreign> is based on the occurrence of the equivalent OJ expression <foreign>dadi luh</foreign> in three important <foreign>kakavin</foreign>s: HV 13.6 <foreign>ndatan panamban lara mankin śīrṇa rəmək hatinya dadi luh tan pantaran her-tali</foreign>; BY 9.14 <foreign>yāvətu sukha dadi luh ndān avas harṣa hetu</foreign>; BK 2.27 <foreign>vineh səpah təñuh tvas ira śīrṇa rakva dadi luh drava ri mata niran parambəhan panampəta niran taṅis mara-marah nrəpasuta riy asih nirāṅrəsəp</foreign>. Probably the change is from <foreign>jadi na əluh</foreign> &gt; <foreign>jadi nəluh</foreign>.</note> the heart wounded without being able to be cured, mantras being ineffective, intentions not becoming reality, because the holy hermits’ precepts for society  are not adhered to.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.10">Likewise, if we are <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, do not reprimand <supplied reason="subaudible">us</supplied> discreetly. If we are reprimanded, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> must not fail to be devoted to the <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>,<note>On the word <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, see my commentary in SKK 2.1</note> because he is the agent (<foreign>tanda</foreign>) of His Majesty the king.<note>In Old Balinese Inscriptions such as Sembiran AI, we find that <foreign>taṇḍa haji</foreign> was translated as ‘<foreign>vorstelijk bewijs</foreign>’ (royal sign) by Goris (1954: 133). On the term <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> in OJ, see Jákl 2019 who concluded that it is associated with the court milieu and typically figures in a military context. According to him, between the ninth and thirteenth centuries CE, <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> were not ‘officers’, but rather active warriors in the service of the king or another lord, who stayed either at the court or were stationed in fortresses owned by the king or lesser lords in different parts of the realm. From the twelfth century CE onward, we encounter a category of royal notables denoted as <foreign>taṇḍa rakryān riṅ pakira-kiran</foreign>, rendered by Jákl as ‘lord’s men of [military] strategy’. These men formed the second highest echelon of state officials, preceded in rank only by the three highest dignitaries of the state. It seems that in the fourteenth century CE the importance of the category of <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> diminished, though at least some of the men were still active combatants. We see that in 15th-century Sunda, based on SKK 11.20, <foreign>tanda</foreign> seems to have a function related to the law (<foreign>darma</foreign>) or litigation.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.11">If we are under orders,<note>The word <foreign>pañuruhan</foreign> means ‘orders, commandments’. On the meaning of ‘<foreign>kumpulan, keseluruhan</foreign>’ of circumfix <foreign>pa- -an</foreign>, see Zoetmulder &amp; Poedjawijatna (1992/I: 84, §109b). See also my discussion in Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not fail to maintain the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society, so that we are faithful to the commandments.<note>On the word <foreign>pivaraṅan</foreign> ‘order, commandement’, cf. <foreign>Pantun</foreign> DK 36 <foreign>ayeuna engkang moal ngantos, piwarangan ti rayi</foreign> “Now I will not wait for the order from you”. In MdS, <foreign>piwarangan</foreign> means ‘the one who is given the order’.</note> But as regards the one who goes north, south, west, east, he must not<note>In the present context, <foreign>gəs ma</foreign> is a conjunction which precedes the list. Cf. SKK 11.2 and 14.3. See my discussion in Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <foreign>si vok cante</foreign>,<note>Terms with <foreign>cante</foreign> elements are difficult to understand. <foreign>Cante</foreign> is not listed in the dictionary. RR 56 contains <foreign>cantayan</foreign> which means ‘butcher’s beam’, probably derived from the base word <foreign>cantay</foreign> = <foreign>cante</foreign>; cf. Mal. <foreign>bantai</foreign>. The element <foreign>si</foreign> can form personifications. The word <foreign>vok</foreign> may be the same as OJ ‘hairy, beard’, but the relation with appetite is confusing. The word <foreign>mur</foreign> is not identified, while <foreign>mar</foreign> is listed in OJED with the meaning of ‘spreading, weak’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>mār</foreign>). For the time being, these four terms cannot be translated.</note> must not <foreign>si mur cante</foreign>, shall not become <foreign>si mar cante</foreign>, shall not <supplied reason="subaudible">become</supplied> <foreign>darma cante</foreign>. Those are called four efforts (<foreign>catur-yatna</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.12">This is the meaning. <foreign>Si vok cante</foreign> means easily tempted by food and drink. <foreign>Si mur cante</foreign> means guilty<note>The word <foreign>salimaha</foreign> is only recorded in Hardjadibrata, ‘excl. (dial.) it’s your own fault!’. However, in this context, the meaning ‘guilty’ seems more adequate.</note> of participating in making those who steal, who confiscate, who deceive, spread in all directions;<note>My emendation <foreign>ṅaramankən</foreign> is based on OJ <foreign>karaman</foreign> ‘(avs) to spread in all directions (fire, light, water)’ and MdS <foreign>karaman</foreign> which has the same meaning.</note> it is called the wrong destination. <foreign>Si mar cante</foreign> means to take merchandise, sheets of gold and silver, <supplied reason="subaudible">even if</supplied> it is not ordered by the commander; it is called wrong purpose. <foreign>Darma cante</foreign> means tolerant<note> The word <foreign>daranan</foreign> seems to be derived from <foreign>darana</foreign>. Hardjadibrata notes ‘Skr. (in archaic lit. lang.) tolerant, forbearing, patient; <foreign>kumaha darana tanah</foreign> (expr.) everything that the soil bears, i.e. it depends on the productive power of the soil’. The suffix -<foreign>an</foreign> seems to form adjectives in OS.</note> of what is detestable to our master. He is ordered to fetch <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, to go by foot <supplied reason="subaudible">to pick up someone</supplied>, and to kill those who are unfit for<note>If we emend <foreign>ka tohaan</foreign> into <foreign>ku tohaan</foreign>, then <foreign>tohaan </foreign>become the agent of <foreign>disuruh</foreign>. The alternative translation of <foreign>disuruh ñokot, ṅadarat, matyan nu tan yogya ku tohaan</foreign> would be “He is ordered to fetch [someone], to go by foot [to pick up someone], and to kill those who are unfit by [our] master”.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> master, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> instead he becomes more careful,<note><foreign>ṅisəsan</foreign> from <foreign>isəs</foreign> = MdS <foreign>iceus</foreign> ‘vi. know o.’s way around, able to do things that o. should do; (of animals) easily trained to do things, easy to break (in)’. Cf. AG <foreign>isəs-isəskən carekna pantikrama</foreign> “Be careful about the words of propriety (<foreign>pantikrama</foreign>)”.  See also <foreign>isəskən</foreign> in 4.14.</note> because they are friends,<note>The word <foreign>vagəy</foreign> means ‘friend, companion’. Cf. BM 607 <foreign>vagəyeṅ aməṅ sagala</foreign> ‘My companions would all be monk’. The word <foreign>wageuy</foreign>/<foreign>wagey</foreign> is not attested in MdS. However, the OS word it is clearly related to OJ <foreign>vage</foreign>. In the Wanua Tengah III and Śrī Kahulunan (= Tri Tepusan I) inscriptions, the word <foreign>vage</foreign> (one of the days in the five-day cycle, or <foreign>pañcavāra</foreign>) is translated in Sanskrit as <foreign>mitra</foreign>. On Tri Tepusan I, see De Casparis 1950: 74; n. 2 on p. 76 and Damais 1955: 103–104. For Wanua Tengah III, see Boechari 2012: 467–471 and Griffiths 2022: Appendix A. Another example of -<foreign>əy</foreign> in OS = -<foreign>ay</foreign>/-<foreign>e</foreign> in OJ is OS <foreign>təmbəy</foreign> = OJ <foreign>tambay</foreign>/<foreign>tambe</foreign>.</note> family, and relatives. That should not be done, for what is called the wrong <foreign>binarih</foreign> (?)<note>This word <foreign>binarih</foreign> is unknown in the dictionaries. Should it be emended to <foreign>birəṅəh</foreign>?</note> is forbidden; it is called <foreign>darma cante</foreign>. Those things should not be practiced by the servants: to love the detestable, to detest the lovable. They are improper to be practiced by the servants.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.13">This is so that we obey the master, so that we are long taken as servants, so that we are always controlled<note>The meaning of <foreign>diasa</foreign> is equivalent with <foreign>dipihulun</foreign> ‘to be in control of s.o., to be taken as a servant’. In RR.74 we found its active form <foreign>ṅasa</foreign> ‘to dominate, to control’. Cf. MdS <foreign>kawasa</foreign>, OJ <foreign>vaśa</foreign> (from Skt.) ‘power, force, dominion’. ASD translate it as ‘<foreign>diakui</foreign>’ (to be aknowledged).</note> by our master: follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! pay attention to the dignitary! If the master scolds <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, we too should participate in scolding with the master. If the master praises <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, we too should participate in praising with the master. If we cannot participate in praising <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> participate in criticizing<note>Based on the context it is clear that the meaning of <foreign>meda</foreign> is the opposite of <foreign>muji</foreign> ‘to praise’, so ‘to insult, to criticize’. In OJ, one of its meanings is ‘unrestrained feelings or conduct, passion, blindness’, with the base <foreign>meda</foreign>. Zoetmulder notes that in some occurrences, this word is also possible to be related to <foreign>peda</foreign> ‘hard-hearted, indifferent, unkind’.  It is probably also related to <foreign>pīḍā</foreign>, <foreign>pīḍāna, pedita</foreign>. Cf. SKK 9.2.</note> with the master, it is better that we keep quiet while devoting ourselves to the master.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.14">If we walk into the forest, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should wear</supplied> an upper garment, a lower garment,<note>The base word of <foreign>disimbut</foreign>, <foreign>simbut</foreign> in MdS means ‘blanket’. Its variant, <foreign>salimbut</foreign>, also occurs in OS. This word is clearly related to Mal. <foreign>selimut</foreign> and OJ <foreign>salimput</foreign>, perhaps also with Khmer <foreign>sampot</foreign> ‘lower garment’. However, its meaning in OS is not always clear, whether ‘blanket’ like MdS, or ‘lower garment’, which is more appropriate in this sentence. A meaning which is more likely close to ‘blanket’ occurs in RR 163–164  <foreign>saaṅgəsna dimandian, disimbutan tuaṅ tapih</foreign> “Having bathed the baby, he covered him with his mother’s skirt”. The meaning ‘lower garment’ is attested in KaPañ 813–816 <foreign>boeh laraṅ disarasah, pipiṅgir taluki jəṅgi, cavət vayaṅ simbut siñjaṅ, disabukan jamar tali</foreign> “sacred cloth is ornamented, on the edge is muslin from Jenggi, loincloth with a wayang motif and lower garments (<foreign>simbut siñjaṅ</foreign>), belted by the <foreign>jamar</foreign> rope”.</note> and a combination.<note>The meaning of <foreign>paṅadva</foreign>, both in OS and OJ, is problematic. Zoetmulder (1982, s.v. <foreign>paṅadva</foreign>) wonders whether the basic meaning is <foreign>adu</foreign> or <foreign>dwa</foreign>. I would be inclined towards the latter option, and take it as a ‘combination’ of both upper and lower garment. Here I revise my argument in Aditia Gunawan (2019), stating that <foreign>paṅadva</foreign> would point to an “upper garment”.</note> When coming to the <supplied reason="subaudible">sea</supplied>side,<note>I interpret <foreign>sisi</foreign> as an equivalent of OJ <foreign>pasisi</foreign> 'seaside, shore'. Cf. <ref target="#smg_16.02">SMG 16.2</ref> <foreign>pasu ma ṅaranya, savatək satva di dayəh, paksi ma ṅaranya, savatək satva di sisi</foreign>, <foreign>sarpa ma ṅaranya, savatək nu napak harəguna, mina ṅaranya, savatək satva di cai, pepelikan ṅaranya, savatək nu mava caṅkaṅ, nu kumarayap hantə kañahoan</foreign> “Domestic animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the settlements; birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>) are all kinds of animals on the seaside, snakes (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>) are all kinds of animals whose chest touch the ground; fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the water; creeping animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>) are all kinds of animals having a shell, who crawl without being discovered”. Cf. RY 5.21: <foreign>satəkanireṅ samudra suməpər ta sireṅ pasisi</foreign>. However, in MdS, <foreign>pasisian</foreign> means ‘countryside’, so the alternative translation would be “When coming to the countryside, [we] wear upper and lower garments as often as possible”.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should normally (<foreign>sakarajən</foreign>)<note>GNT records this term under <foreign>karajeun</foreign> “RR 748 let it be so, all right! Very well!’ MSd <foreign>kajeun</foreign> ‘id’.; sakarajeun ‘let it be according to…’; or from rajeun? Cf. <foreign>leumpang sakarajeun-rajeun</foreign> ‘to walk freely, entirely as [you] wish’”. They assume that the word is derived from base <foreign>kajeun</foreign> with infix -<foreign>ar</foreign>-, though the possibility of derivation from <foreign>rajeun</foreign> is mentioned. I favor the latter interpretation. In MdS <foreign>rajeun</foreign> means ‘every now and then, time and time again; <foreign>sok rajeun</foreign> fairly frequently; <foreign>rarajeunan</foreign> s.m. <foreign>rajeun</foreign>; <foreign>mirajeunan</foreign> do st. now and then, get used to st., try to do st’. Cf. AG 4r–v <foreign>muṅku kasoraṅ ja uraṅ hantǝ tapa, kena hantǝ dikabisa hantǝ dikarajǝnan</foreign> “it will not be achieved because we are not doing penance, because we are not skilled, because we are not used to it” and BM 1557–1560 <foreign>samapun saṅ hiaṅ atma, rakaki bujaṅga manik, lǝmpaṅ sakarajǝn-rajǝn, sia ka na kasorgaan</foreign> “My respects, sacred soul, honorable man Bujangga Manik, you should walk as it used to be, you may go to heaven”. In this context, I choose to interpret it as ‘normally’.</note> wear upper and lower garments. When not with the master, <supplied reason="subaudible">we must</supplied> be careful about the hermits’ holy precepts for society. Their precepts are: don’t go harvesting <supplied reason="subaudible">legumes</supplied> from other people’s small fields, from other people’s gardens, except by virtue of our having asked permission.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.15">A rope on a forest and on a garden,<note>I consider <foreign>kəboan</foreign> as a variant of <foreign>kəbon</foreign> ‘garden, plantation’, as in SKK 10.2. My emendation is based on the occurrences of <foreign>kəbon</foreign> and <foreign>alas</foreign> in OJ sources, among others RL 1.113 <foreign>kubon alas palaṅ-alaṅan eṅarit</foreign>; DS <foreign>riṅ kəbon, riṅ alas</foreign>; Pdg <foreign>inaryakən riṅ kubvan, riṅ alas</foreign>; Par 21.2 <foreign>vontən iṅ kubon alas... pinakaryakən gubug.</foreign> Bularut inscription <foreign>savaḥ ga[ga] kbvan· mvaḥ Alas</foreign>. My translation of <foreign>salaṅ iṅ kəboan iṅ alas</foreign> ‘A rope on a forest and on a garden’ is tentative. Another possibility is to emend to <foreign>salaṅ kəboan dəṅ alas</foreign> ‘the rope in the garden and the forest’.</note> wood that had been marked by a string, fruit that has been bunched together,<note>The basic form of <foreign>ṅararaṅgean, raṅge</foreign>, probably related to MdS <foreign>ranggeuy </foreign>‘ear (of corn), bunch (of fruit, flowers, grapes, bananas, etc.); <foreign>ranggeuyan</foreign> a. having ears, clusters or bunches of st., putting forth ears (of rice plants); b. forming ears or bunches, in a bunch’. Possibly also related to OJ <foreign>araṅgayan, araṅgeyan</foreign> ‘to stretch out and move the hands (forepaws) in order to seize, claw, clutch at’.</note> firewood that stands ready, a covering for mushrooms, hives or nests<note>Does the word <foreign>caṅrədan</foreign> mean ‘hive/nest’? But do <foreign>ulam</foreign> worms make nests? Or does <foreign>caṅrəd</foreign> just mean ‘a bunch’ (collected together for subsequent transport elsewhere)? According to Hady Prasetya, <foreign>caṅrǝdan</foreign> is very likely a bond on a tree near the nest, because these insects and caterpillars nest in trees.</note> of various bees (<foreign>təvvan</foreign>, <foreign>odeṅ</foreign>, <foreign>ñəruan</foreign>), of wasps (<foreign>eṅaṅ</foreign>), of woodworm (<foreign>ulam</foreign>),<note>In MdS, <foreign>ulam</foreign> is ‘a kind of woodworm (in trees and tree trunks)’. According to information from Dadan Sutisna and Mamat Sasmita, both <foreign>ulam</foreign> and <foreign>éngang</foreign> are still consumed by some Sundanese people, especially the larvae. <foreign>Ulam</foreign> in question may be the same as MdS <foreign>cangkilung</foreign>, a type of caterpillar on bamboo.</note> a fish trap (<foreign>parakan</foreign>) — all kinds of ownership marks (<foreign>babayan</foreign>): we should not take them carelessly, let alone bring down other people’s taps. That should not be done, for it is the origin of guilt, the source of suffering and misery.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.16">If we find a road, large or small, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> quickly<note>The word <foreign>baṅat</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but is found in Malay ‘haste, hurry, speed up’. Cf. OJ <foreign>baṅət</foreign> ‘speed, drive, vehemence’.</note> wear loin-cloth or a combination, <supplied reason="subaudible">as</supplied> we might be faced with <foreign>gusti</foreign>s or with <foreign>mantri</foreign>s. <supplied reason="subaudible">We</supplied> should not fail to move to the left and bend down.<note> On the word <foreign>paṅadoṅkoṅkən</foreign>, see my comment on <ref target="#smg_02.02">SMG 2.2</ref>.</note> If <supplied reason="subaudible">we meet with</supplied> <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>s, brahmans, royal ascetics, governors, princes, rich or poor, especially <foreign>guru loka</foreign>s,<note>OJED notes <foreign>guru loka</foreign> as ‘teacher or religious functionary at the court (cf. <foreign>paṇḍita nagara</foreign>, <foreign>viku nagara</foreign>, <foreign>viku haji</foreign>)’. Sum 42.15 concerns a <foreign>guru loka </foreign>who is a wandering ascetic accompanied by a female ascetic (<foreign>kili</foreign>). Cf. Vr̥h 50.1 which narrates Vr̥haspati as a <foreign>guru loka</foreign> in the heaven. In CA 122.27, guru loka belongs to the twice-born class (dvija) as distinguished from brahmin, bhujaṅga, and r̥si. SHKS 150–151 states that the guru loka is the leader of the vikus. The SKK should strengthen the assumption that the guru loka is related to the court, even though there are indications that they do not live in the palace but travel.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not fail to move to the left<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006: 39) note one example of <foreign>paṅ- -kən</foreign> which is an imperative: <foreign>paṅlumpatkən</foreign> ‘run away from’, based on RR 1512 <foreign>bat paṅlumpatkən aing</foreign> “Come on, run away from me!”. In this context, the imperative <foreign>paṅidalkən</foreign> can be preceded by a vetative <foreign>ulah mo</foreign>.</note> and sit, for those are the teachers of the king.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_05">
<p corresp="#skk_05.01">Keep in mind the Hermits’ Precepts for Society, and beware of adultery.<note>The word <foreign>haloan</foreign> corresponds to OJ <foreign>halvan</foreign>, not in MdS.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">We should not</supplied> go and whimper about<note>The verb <foreign>ṅərikən</foreign> probably related to OJ <foreign>kəri</foreign> ‘having a shivering or shuddering feeling (fear or horror), itching (to attack)’. Here I interpret it as ‘to whimper about, be lustful’.</note> the forbidden women of others, widowed maidens, lest we be guilty of ‘adultery of the road’; especially <supplied reason="subaudible">we should not go and</supplied> hold hands,<note>I interpret <foreign>ṅarovaṅ taṅan</foreign> as an idiom ‘holding hands’ = Mal. <foreign>bergandengan tangan </foreign>‘holding hands’. It seems that <foreign>arovaṅ</foreign> derived from <foreign>rovaṅ</foreign> ‘companion’ = OJ. Maybe it literally means ‘take (female)’s hand as his friend’, in other words ‘hold hands’. Cf. MdS idiom <foreign>murah tangan</foreign> ‘generous’.</note> sharing a seat on a tree trunk, on a couch, in a shelter (<foreign>təpas</foreign>), one with another.<note>I interpret <foreign>patutuṅgalan</foreign> as ‘one with another’, so not alone. It is interesting to compare with the equivalent expression <foreign>paduduaan</foreign> ‘(only) the two of them (do st.)’ in MdS.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">It</supplied> is called ‘adultery of the seating place’. Standing face to face<note>The word <foreign>patañjər-tañjər</foreign> may be compared with MdS <foreign>pahareup-hareup</foreign> ‘face to face’.</note> by the side of the house, in the yard, one with another. It is called ‘adultery of the yard’. Answering someone who coughs, who is clearing the throat, who is expectorating, especially someone else’s mother’s<note>The phrase <foreign>ambu iṅ kalih</foreign> means ‘someone else’s mother’, cf. <foreign>buhaya iṅ kalih</foreign> ‘someone else’s beloved’ in SKK 4.8.</note> song. It is called ‘the roaring cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgala</foreign>).<note>My emendation <foreign>aṅgala</foreign> is based on OJ <foreign>aṅgala</foreign> ‘to trumpet (of elephants), to roar (of a bull)’, which seems fit with the context. This word is not found in MdS. Cf. TK 84.2: <foreign>linūd i svaranyāṅgala saṅ nandaka</foreign> “The roaring sound of Nandaka is even more noisy”. MdS has <foreign>ngagalang</foreign> ‘run across (the road)’ which does not fit the context.</note> Resting on the place where the other one<note>In this passage, <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> probably does not mean other people in general, but other women. In <ref target="#smg_10.02">SMG 10.2</ref> <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> is clearly synonymous with <foreign>sakalih </foreign>‘other people’, reflecting a that the person thus designated is held in high esteem<foreign>. </foreign>In the <foreign>Udyogaparva</foreign> (ed. Zoetmulder, p. 73) <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> means both gods’ as one would expect: <foreign>kahiḍəp pva rasanikaṅ vara-varah de saṅ hyaṅ kalih, mojar ta saṅ hyaṅ viṣṇu ri saṅ hyaṅ indra</foreign> “After the gust of the information was understood by both gods, Viṣṇu spoke to Indra”. Another possibility is to emend it to <foreign>sakalih</foreign> or <foreign>saṅ kalih</foreign>.</note> has sat — on a post, on a tree, on a stone — <supplied reason="subaudible">after</supplied> seeing her having gotten up then replacing them to lean, that is called ‘the rubbing cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgasir</foreign>).<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngagasir</foreign> means ‘rub or graze against st., touch st. when passing (e.g. with the clothes); <foreign>ngagasirkeun</foreign> let st. graze or rub against st.; <foreign>pagasir</foreign> rub against each other, touch one another when passing’ which seems fit the context. In OJ <foreign>gaṅsir</foreign> ‘mole-cricket’.</note> Those should be remembered, if we want to free ourselves from hell.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_05.02">And also joining together in one lodging, one residence, one shelter, one couch, with someone else’s women,<note>The interpretation of <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> as ‘someone else’s women’ is not so convincing. Should it be emended to <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign>, since <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign> is often juxtaposed with <foreign>strī laraṅan</foreign> in OJ epigraphic passages? If this interpretation is correct, then the translation for <foreign>dəṅ dayaṅ kalih, dəṅ astri laraṅan sakalih</foreign> would be “with someone else’s concubine, with forbidden women of someone else”. For a discussion of the term <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign> in Austronesian languages, see Clavé &amp; Griffiths 2022: 185–186.</note> with forbidden women of someone else; it is called ‘the buffalo in one pen’ (<foreign>kəbo sapitunahan</foreign>).<note>The expression <foreign>kəbo sapitunahan</foreign> is probably equivalent with the Mal. idiom <foreign>kumpul kebo </foreign>‘cohabitation’?  On the circumfix <foreign>pi- -an</foreign> in <foreign>pitunahan</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> Those are the things to be kept in mind. They are called forbidden acts.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_05.03">In the same way, if we are going on a journey, we shouldn’t <supplied reason="subaudible">do that</supplied>, shouldn’t desire to be followed by the servants of someone else. If we desire to take them, we should ask their master. If they are trusted <supplied reason="subaudible">servants</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> make an oath* (as to our liability) for their sickness, for their death, for their loss, <supplied reason="subaudible">for their</supplied> passing  away and dying, in any way whatsoever, them you must take. There is no one who may be blamed*, for an oath is more eminent* than <supplied reason="subaudible">written</supplied> law (<foreign>agama</foreign>). If they are not trusted* <supplied reason="subaudible">servants</supplied>, then we should not! If we insist on taking them, we should help them when they are sick, we should redeem them individually (? <foreign>sakadǝgdǝgna</foreign>) if they are dead or lost. All of that should be taken into account.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_06">
<p corresp="#skk_06.01">Further, as follows: if we are visited by the <foreign>same</foreign>*, <foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>dasa</foreign>, <foreign>calagara</foreign>, <foreign>upəti paṅgərəs rəma</foreign>*, our thoughts should be cheerful, we should feel as though being visited by family, relatives, younger and elder siblings, children, friends, children of younger siblings (<foreign>suvan</foreign>)*, children of elder siblings (<foreign>kaponakan</foreign>). That is the metaphor for it. But if we have things to share, <supplied reason="subaudible">such as</supplied> food, drink, under garments, clothes <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> anything that we own*, we should feel as though making offerings and giving reception* to the ancestors and gods.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_06.02">Moreover, if we are employed <supplied reason="subaudible">to go</supplied> to the dry rice field, to the paddy field, to the great paddy field (<foreign>seraṅ agəṅ</foreign>)*; fencing, digging a trench, putting animals into the pen, making snares, dam fishing*, fishing with a casting net, fishing with a line (?, ṅadodoger)*, fishing with drag-net (mapayaṅ), fishing with a sieve (<foreign>ñair</foreign>)*, ensnaring animals by two people (? <foreign>biñcaṅ</foreign>)* — any kind of employment for the master, we should not be displeased, we should not be temperamental*, we should not be angry* or fuss*. We should enjoy it all. We should  mean our tasks.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_07">
<p corresp="#skk_07.01">However, if we are returning home, we should not defecate on the edge of the road, by the side of the house, on its bright end, lest it be smelled by a nobleman <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> by a <foreign>gusti</foreign>, not to mention by people who do not pay attention*; lest <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> be cursed <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> blamed* by <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> mother, father <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> teachers, be opposed* by the elders, because of our reckless deeds. But if <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> obey the holy precepts, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> defecate seven steps* from the road <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> urinate three steps from the road. May <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> not meet with criticism from other people, as we know <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign>*. The meaning is: <foreign>ulah</foreign> means sorrow, <foreign>pamali</foreign> means death.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.02">Furthermore, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> watch out for rope barriers (<foreign>gagavar</foreign>)*, the ends of snares (? <foreign>pucuk tambaluṅ</foreign>)*, as they could be court reservoirs*, forbidden enclosures, forbidden pavilions — all the more so for obstructing light*, for coming across <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> passing the king <supplied reason="subaudible">when he is</supplied> walking about, because those are the places where offense is liable to happen.  If we enter the court, we must often look <supplied reason="subaudible">in all directions</supplied>, as it may be that we are trampling, bumping, hitting* <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> cutting a line.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.03">If we sit down, we should not face the wrong way; we should cross our legs politely. And if we are invited to speak by the master, we should think about what we will say. Whatever is appropriate will please the master. And we should pay close attention to the ones who are to be followed: officer, <foreign>gusti</foreign>, military officer (<foreign>kasasa</foreign>)*, member of the <foreign>bayangkara</foreign> corps, confidant (<foreign>nu marək</foreign>)*, messenger, painter, coppersmith, goldsmith, bracelet smith, blacksmith, make up expert (? <foreign>juru vidaṅ</foreign>)*, actor, puppeteer, trumpeter*, gamelan musician, mask performer (<foreign>tapukan</foreign>)*, joker, dry rice field farmer, palm tapper, paddy farmer, sweeper, death-defier (<foreign>belamati</foreign>), magician (? <foreign>juru moha</foreign>), <foreign>barat katiga</foreign>*, soldier, blowpiper, archer, warrior, collector of <foreign>dasa</foreign> and <foreign>calagara</foreign> (penalties), young shepherds, boar farmers, chicken farmers, fishermen*, divers*, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> all those who are of use. If there are any ones who have the virtue of fidelity in service, it is they who are to be followed, for they dedicate themselves to the country.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_08">
<p corresp="#skk_08.01">If there is someone scolded by the master — such a one, his actions should not be followed, lest we also be scolded. This is an analogy for it: like a person going into the forest, who steps on a thorn, let’s step on it too*, it hurts in the same way. That is why, if there is someone who is praised as the agile, the nimble*, sensitive <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> generous (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>)*, frugal (emet)*, conscientious, diligent, painstaking, faithful to the service of the master — follow the acts and the qualities of such a one, so that we too may be praised!</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.02">If there is someone whose appearance is good, whose behavior is good <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> whose actions are good, we should follow as best as possible (<foreign>saagəṅna</foreign>)*, because he is considered a superior man.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.03">If there is someone whose appearance is beautiful <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> whose actions are bad <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> whose attitude is dumb, in that case (<foreign>itu</foreign>) we should not look at his appearance, we should not* follow his actions.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.04">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> whose actions are good, in that case we should not look at his attitude, we should not keep looking at his appearance, we should follow his actions.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.05">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb, whose actions are bad, in that case <supplied reason="subaudible">he</supplied> is what they call ‘the world’s offering (<foreign>caru</foreign>), the victim (<foreign>silih diri</foreign>) for the people of the whole world’*, the defect* of human beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.06">That is what should be remembered — the unmeritorious, the meritorious; the bad, the good* — take <supplied reason="subaudible">them as</supplied> teacher. This is the reminder of it: if anyone dies while stealing, dies while sneaking, dies while robbing, dies while infiltrating, any kind of impudent <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> deceitful <supplied reason="subaudible">behavior</supplied>, we should watch them for <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> are not to be followed. That is called the vile as a teacher.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.07">There is more: if we see people performing wayang, listen to people performing pantun, acquire teachings from the stories, that is called the stage as teacher. If we acquire good teachings from people reading, that is called the story as teacher. If we observe the products of handicraft: carvings, sculptures, planks, drawings, we should not* ask the craftsmen* — we should find out by our own feelings, as a result of paying attention to other people’s skill. It is called profession* as a teacher.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.08">Acquiring precepts from children, it is called children as teachers. Acquiring <foreign>dharma</foreign> from our grandfather, it is called the grandfather as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our elder brother (<foreign>lañcək</foreign>), it is called the elder brother (<foreign>kakaṅ</foreign>) as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from the elders, it is called our parents’ elder siblings (<foreign>uva</foreign>) as teachers. Acquiring rules of conduct from the places where we travel, (whether it is) in the village, in a place for staying overnight, in a place for breaking journey, in a place of lodging, it is called the road as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our parents, it is called the origins as teacher. Especially if (you find rules of conduct in) words (<foreign>hatur</foreign>)* from a great scholar, it is called the excellence as teacher, it is called honor as teacher, it is called authority as teacher, it is called doctrines as teacher: those are called the four excellences (<foreign>catur-utama</foreign>). Which is why*, when they are finished being done by those who do, being accomplished by those who accomplish, (then) all are finished being observed: the bad and the good, the evil and the just.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_09">
<p corresp="#skk_09.01">Likewise, if there is someone who praises us, our feelings should not be joyful, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> we should in turn cast back <supplied reason="subaudible">the praise</supplied> to those who praise, so that we will not be overshadowed by the other’s praise. If we are keen on being praised, it is like the ‘long pole with weak extensions (<foreign>galah dava sinambuṅan tuna</foreign>)’. <supplied reason="subaudible">If our</supplied> feelings are pleased with the praise, then it leads to vanity. Because we feel ourselves to be in our own house — by food, drink, pleasures, enjoyments, utensils (<foreign>pakaraṅ</foreign>)* — then they are used as something to be proud of (<foreign>aṅgəhan</foreign>). It is like the ‘long pole’ (as above); it is <supplied reason="subaudible">also</supplied> like the ‘empty paddy stalk’*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.02">Likewise, if there is someone who insults us, we should accept all the other’s insults, which is why it is comparable to the ‘pole cut short’. Suppose we have warts, it is like water for bathing; suppose we have dry skin*, it is like a person coming to smearing <supplied reason="subaudible">us</supplied> with oil; suppose we are hungry*, it is like a person coming to give rice*; suppose we are thirsty, it is like a person coming to give to drink; suppose we are dejected, it is like a person coming to give betel quid — they are called the five pure ones (<foreign>pañca-parisuda</foreign>). That is like the ‘pole cut short’.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.03">If <supplied reason="subaudible">the insult</supplied> makes us happy, <supplied reason="subaudible">we are</supplied> like paddy chock full <supplied reason="subaudible">with rice grains</supplied>*, that might keep the people alive*, because the origin of joy and pleasure has been obtained. Even if those who are slandering us are wrong, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> take <supplied reason="subaudible">their slander as</supplied> advice*. If we have the behavior (about which we are slandered), <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> stop <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied>. If we do not have <supplied reason="subaudible">such</supplied> behavior, we should consider (<foreign>uṅaṅ</foreign>)* <supplied reason="subaudible">the slander</supplied> (to merit attention), like mother, father <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> teachers. The meaning* of what is called a human being (<foreign>janma</foreign>): ‘It is considered the ultimate supreme; it is considered the deity becoming human; the one who has a perfect body*, who is the origin of goodness, and the source of the truth’.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_10">
<p corresp="#skk_10.01">These are the complementary practices*, so that no living beings* are ruined, so that <supplied reason="subaudible">we are</supplied> blessed* in our houses: careful <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> conscientious, scrupulous <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> diligent, sensitive <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> generous*, not falling down (? mo rogol-rogol)*, champions among experts, strong <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> unfatigued*, mobile <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> nimble.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_10.02">If we put dry rice-fields (<foreign>gaga</foreign>) and paddy fields under cultivation, it is only so that we do not suffer. If we make an orchard, it is only so that we do not pick in someone else’s small field, in someone else’s broad field — except by virtue of our having asked permission, politely requesting*. <supplied reason="subaudible">As for</supplied> domestic animals, we should not just buy, not just swap <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied>. <supplied reason="subaudible">As for</supplied> utensils, we should not just borrow <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied>. <supplied reason="subaudible">As for</supplied> blankets <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> loincloths, we should not have too many of them*. <supplied reason="subaudible">As for</supplied> food and drink, we should not have too little. Our children and wife should be given advice, to avoid <supplied reason="subaudible">their</supplied> being accused of being ‘disrespectful’ (<foreign>durbala siksa</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_10.03">Observe the hermits’ precepts for society: if we sleep, <supplied reason="subaudible">it is only</supplied> as a remedy for sleepiness*; <supplied reason="subaudible">if we</supplied> drink palm wine, <supplied reason="subaudible">it is only</supplied> as a remedy for thirst; <supplied reason="subaudible">if we</supplied> eat, <supplied reason="subaudible">it is only</supplied> a remedy for hunger. We should not be careless <supplied reason="subaudible">about them</supplied>. We should remember* their <supplied reason="subaudible">potential</supplied> absence. Even more so by children and by wife, we should not be shackled, for they may not behave in accordance <supplied reason="subaudible">with our advice</supplied>. If <supplied reason="subaudible">they are</supplied> good, by virtue of us giving advice, after which <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> follow the advice, those are called our children and our wife. If they do not follow <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> admonition, they are the same as outsiders. But if we insist on claiming our wife and child despite them being away without giving any news*, we will probably be burdened, we will probably be lost in hell together, lost <supplied reason="subaudible">will be</supplied> the results of our worship, ruined the results of the ancestors (<foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>)*.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_11">
<p corresp="#skk_11.01">This is the instruction of Darma Pitutur*, to avoid our not thinking of <supplied reason="subaudible">the instruction of Darma Pitutur</supplied>.</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.02">“<foreign>sriopeksah samutatah, paesanteh tan susuriyәm, jambaṅan esiniṅ bañu mahәniṅ, tah desanatah nora buksah</foreign>”*</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.03">The meaning is: sri means gold. Gold is like this: If it is not coated, its beauty is washed away*. If it is coated, <supplied reason="subaudible">it will be</supplied> beautifully bright* for it is well treated. Likewise is the analogy, for us humans here: if <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> follow the holy precepts, its essence will be well maintained by us, like the straight meeting its straight. Likewise, if we do not follow the holy precepts of the accomplished one (<foreign>krəta</foreign>)*, <supplied reason="subaudible">it is</supplied> like the crooked meeting its crooked.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.04"><foreign>Paesan</foreign> means mirror. The mirror is like this: If it is not regarded attentively*, our image is vague. If it is regarded attentively, our appearance is clear upon that mirror. Likewise are we humans here. If we can follow the customs* of others adequately, it may well be internalized* by our feelings. If we cannot follow the advice, it is called stupid.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.05"><foreign>Jambaṅan</foreign> means an object giving reflection*. The mind of the one who is accomplished is like clear water. That is the reason why we should regard <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> attentively, then the heart will be pleased*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.06"><foreign>Desa</foreign> means settlement. If the settlement is empty, there is nothing to be followed. Words are like that: if they are not substantial, they are considered deceitful. But if the residence is filled, that is to be followed. Likewise are words: they should be meaningful, so that they be considered truthful in character*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.07">Likewise are we humans here. If we wish to know the source of the joy and happiness, we should remember the word of the Darma Pitutur. This is the verse:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.08">‘The pond is the habitat of the goose; the forest is the elephant’s habitat; the sea is the habitat of fishes; flowers are the habitat of the bee’.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.09">The meaning is: if we are going to imitate behavior (<foreign>cəta</foreign>), we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about the clear pond, fresh water*, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the goose. The meaning is: if there is a person who is firm in steering*, whose mind is clear, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> whose heart is pleasant, that is indeed comparable to the goose on the clear pond.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.10">If we seek to know about the depth of the sea, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask a fish. The meaning is: like the man who knows about the mind of the divine king and about the mind of the great scholar.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.11">If we seek to know about the remoteness of  forests, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the elephant. This is its meaning: what is comparable to the remote* forest is knowing other people’s minds*; what is comparable to the elephant is the power* of Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.12">If we seek to know about the fragrance and sweetness of flowers, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the bee. The meaning is: what is comparable to the bee is the skillful man, who is wandering, roaming, <supplied reason="subaudible">so that he</supplied> knows other people’s habits. What is comparable to the fragrant flower is the person who has good conduct, sweet <foreign>baruṅusan</foreign>*, smiling expression, pleasing attitude*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.13">The meaning is: we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about every kind of story*, such as* <foreign>Darma Jati</foreign>*, <foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Hayu</foreign>, <foreign>Jayasena</foreign>*, <foreign>Sedamana</foreign>*, <foreign>Kuñjarakarna</foreign>, <foreign>Ramayana</foreign>, <foreign>Adiparva</foreign>, <foreign>Koravasrama</foreign>, <foreign>Bima Sorga</foreign>, <foreign>Raṅga Lave</foreign>, <foreign>Boma</foreign>, <foreign>Sumana</foreign>, <foreign>Kalapurbaka</foreign>, <foreign>Jarini</foreign>, <foreign>Tantri</foreign>, all types of stories, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the performer (<foreign>memen</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.14">If we seek to know about all kinds of songs (<foreign>kavih</foreign>)*: songs for the elderly*, long songs, amusement songs*, advice songs*, allusive songs*, <foreign>peṅpeledan</foreign> songs*, rafter hole (<foreign>boṅboṅ kaso</foreign>) <supplied reason="subaudible">songs</supplied>, <foreign>pore rane</foreign> <supplied reason="subaudible">songs</supplied>, sword-grass track (<foreign>porod әrih</foreign>) <supplied reason="subaudible">songs</supplied>, <foreign>babahanan</foreign> songs, bearish (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>) songs, <foreign>taṅtuṅ</foreign> songs, lament songs, dancing songs, all types of songs, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the virtuoso (<foreign>paraguna</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.15">If we seek to know about the jesters (<foreign>para macəh</foreign>)*: the performance of a jester (<foreign>cәta macәh</foreign>), the performance of a buffoon (<foreign>mirus</foreign>)*, the mask show (<foreign>tatapukan</foreign>), the bear show (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>), <foreign>bakutrak</foreign> show (<foreign>babakutrakan</foreign>)*, <foreign>abaṅ-abaṅan</foreign> (?)*, swallowing a pointed bamboo (<foreign>nәrәy pañcaṅ</foreign>)*, the sleight of hand (<foreign>munikәn ləbur</foreign>)*, the pounding block competition (<foreign>ṅadu ləsuṅ</foreign>)*, entering the <foreign>lantar</foreign> (?)*, the competition of elder women (<foreign>ṅadu nini</foreign>), all kinds of amusement, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the actor (<foreign>hәmpul</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.16">If we seek to know about <foreign>pantun</foreign>s* <supplied reason="subaudible">such as</supplied> <foreign>Laṅga Laraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>Bañak Catra</foreign>, <foreign>Sili Vaṅi</foreign>, <foreign>Hatur Vaṅi</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the pantun bard (<foreign>prəpantun</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.17">As for all kinds of* decorative patterns (<foreign>tulis</foreign>)* <supplied reason="subaudible">such as</supplied> the spiral motif (<foreign>pupuñjəṅan</foreign>), the writhing motif (<foreign>hihiṅgulan</foreign>), the flower motif (<foreign>kәkәmbaṅan</foreign>), the forest motif (<foreign>alas-alasan</foreign>), people motif (<foreign>uraṅ-uraṅa</foreign>n)*, picture motif (<foreign>mәmәtahan</foreign>), the diagonal motif (<foreign>sisiraṅan</foreign>), the climbing fern motif (<foreign>taruk hata</foreign>), lotus flower, any kind of decorative pattern, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the painter (<foreign>lukis</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.18">As for all kinds of forging, the three weapons are what differentiates them. As for the weapons for the king, they are sword, sickle (? <foreign>abət</foreign>)*, cleaver (<foreign>golok</foreign>), stabbing knife (<foreign>peso təndət</foreign>), kris. The Raksasas are their deities, for they are utensils to kill everything. As for the weapons of the peasants, they are machete (<foreign>kujaṅ</foreign>), hatchet (<foreign>baliuṅ</foreign>), big axe (<foreign>patik</foreign>), weeding hook (<foreign>kored</foreign>), tapping <supplied reason="subaudible">knife</supplied> (<foreign>sadap</foreign>)*. The Detyas are their deities, for they are utensils to obtain things to eat and things to drink. As for the weapons of the scholar (<foreign>pandita</foreign>), they are the <supplied reason="subaudible">betelnut</supplied> cutter (<foreign>kalakatri</foreign>)*, whittling knife (<foreign>peso raut</foreign>), <foreign>doṅdaṅ</foreign> knife, paṅot knife, spike (<foreign>pakisi</foreign>). The Danavas are their deities, for they are utensils to cut everything. That is, once again, why the three weapons are differentiated: for the king, for the peasant, for the scholar. Thus, if we wish to know all of that, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the blacksmith (panday).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.19">As for all kinds of carvings: made like snakes, made like bears, modeled after birds, modeled after monkeys*, modeled after lions — every kind of carving, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the scabbard carver (<foreign>maraṅguy</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.20">All kinds of preparations*: <foreign>ñupar-ñapir</foreign>*, <foreign>rara mandi</foreign>*, make <foreign>cobek</foreign> (<foreign>ñocobek</foreign>)*, <foreign>ñopoṅ koneṅ</foreign>*, <foreign>ñaṅlarkәn</foreign>*, <foreign>ñarəṅsәṅ</foreign>*, <foreign>ñәsәṅit</foreign>*, <foreign>ñayaṅ ku pədəs</foreign>*, roasting (<foreign>bәbәləman</foreign>), grilling (<foreign>papaṅgaṅan</foreign>), <foreign>kakasian</foreign>*, mincing (<foreign>hahañaṅan</foreign>)*, mixing (<foreign>raramәsan</foreign>)*, perfuming (<foreign>diruruum</foreign>)*, sweetening (<foreign>diamis-amis</foreign>)* — every kind of preparation, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask a <foreign>harəp catra</foreign>*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.21">All kinds of (woven) textile*: candlenut flower (<foreign>kәmbaṅ muñcaṅ</foreign>), <foreign>seṅgaṅ</foreign>’s stem (<foreign>gagaṅ seṅgaṅ</foreign>), moon-alike (<foreign>same leg</foreign>), group of səmat (<foreign>sәmat sahurun</foreign>), plaited cage (<foreign>añam cayut</foreign>), <foreign>sigәji</foreign> motif, stone motif (<foreign>pasi-pasi</foreign>), <foreign>kalaṅkaṅ ayakan</foreign>, <foreign>poleṅ raganis</foreign>, <foreign>jayanti</foreign>, <foreign>cәcәmpaan</foreign>, <foreign>paparanakan</foreign>, <foreign>maṅin haris</foreign>, <foreign>siliganti</foreign>, <foreign>boeh siaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>bәbәr natan</foreign>, <foreign>papakanan</foreign>, <foreign>surat avi</foreign>, <foreign>parigi ñeṅsoh</foreign>, <foreign>gagañjar</foreign>, <foreign>lusiyan bәsar</foreign>, <foreign>kampuh jayanti</foreign>, <foreign>hujan riris</foreign>, <foreign>laris</foreign>, <foreign>boeh alus</foreign>, <foreign>ragen paṅanten</foreign> — every kind of textile, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the weaver (<foreign>paṅәyәk</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.22">If we seek to know about all kinds of laws: established customs (<foreign>acara</foreign>) are under codified law (<foreign>adigama</foreign>)*, <foreign>adigama</foreign> is under teacher’s regulations (<foreign>gurugama</foreign>), teacher’s regulations are under elders’ regulations (<foreign>tuhagama</foreign>), elders’ regulations are under approval (<foreign>satmata</foreign>)*, approval is under public outcry (<foreign>surak loka</foreign>), public outcry is under court proceedings (<foreign>vicara</foreign>). High people* are outside of guilt, people outside* are of high guilt* — every kind of law, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the <foreign>tanda</foreign>s*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.23">If we seek to know about the strategies of war: <foreign>makara</foreign> formation*, chariot formation*, <foreign>linsang</foreign> formation*, lion formation*, garuda formation*, wheel formation*, needle point (<foreign>suci-muka</foreign>), iron cage (<foreign>bajra-pañjara</foreign>)*, surrounding dog (<foreign>asu maliput</foreign>), grazing peacock (<foreign>mərak simpir</foreign>)*, tailless crow (?, <foreign>gagak saṅkur</foreign>)*, descending civet (<foreign>luvak maturun</foreign>)*, climbing deer (<foreign>kidaṅ suməṅka</foreign>), crocodile hole (<foreign>babah buhaya</foreign>)*, taking the liṅga jewel form (<foreign>ṅaliṅga manik</foreign>)*, the victorious land (<foreign>ləmah mrəvasa</foreign>)*, ruling (<foreign>adipati</foreign>), dominating power (<foreign>prəbusakti</foreign>)*, the application of war and battle, the effort of <foreign>sapətrik</foreign> (?)* — <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the commander (<foreign>hulu jurit</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.24">If we seek to know about of all kinds formulas and mantras*:  mutterings and prayers (<foreign>jampa jampiya</foreign>)*, restoring consciousness (?, <foreign>gәgәiṅ</foreign>), diagrams (?, <foreign>susuratan</foreign>)*, protections (<foreign>sasaranaan</foreign>)*, distance vision (? <foreign>kaseraṅan</foreign>)*, <foreign>pavayagahan</foreign>*, (mantras) with flowers (? <foreign>pupuspaan</foreign>)*, purification mantras (<foreign>susudaan</foreign>)*, life giving mantras (?, <foreign>hurip-huripan</foreign>)*, tunduk iyәm (?), astrological formulas (<foreign>pararasen</foreign>)*, gnomon (<foreign>pasaṅkvan</foreign>)*, — every kind of sacred formula, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the <foreign>brahmana</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.25">If we seek to know about making offerings in the shrine (<foreign>saṅgar</foreign>): the drawings*, the leaf offering, <foreign>palajaṅ</foreign> offering*, flower offering, putting a cloth on <foreign>lingga</foreign>, maintenance of deities — every kind of offering, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the <foreign>jaṅgan</foreign>*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.26">If we seek to know about the descent of time, month of the quake*, year without neck, <supplied reason="subaudible">year</supplied> without head, walking world, immobile world, buried earth, earthquake* — every kind of knowledge of ancient accounts (<foreign>carek nu bəhəla</foreign>)*, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.27">If we seek to know about the precepts of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> (<foreign>darma-siksa</foreign>), the precepts of the community (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), becoming an ascetic (<foreign>pasuk tapa</foreign>)*, the meditation (?, <foreign>padonaan</foreign>)*, the very pure (act?) (<foreign>mahapavitra</foreign>), the precepts of the teacher, the ten virtues (<foreign>dasa-sila</foreign>), the five instructions (<foreign>pañca-siksa</foreign>), foot soles of the teacher (<foreign>guru-talapakan</foreign>), misfortune of the world (<foreign>jagat-upadrava</foreign>), four powers (<foreign>cadu-sakti</foreign>), the reality of the world (<foreign>tato buvana</foreign>), the reality of the body (<foreign>tato sarira</foreign>), the reality of knowledge (<foreign>tato ajñana</foreign>) — every kind of contents of the books, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the scholar*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.28">In the first place the blessings (<foreign>kasorgaan</foreign>) in the manifest world: the kingship, the nobility, the eminence, the authority, the supremacy, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.29">If we seek to know about the organization of land (<foreign>patitis bumi</foreign>)*: keeping the land apart*, consulting all people, ordering <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> discussing (<foreign>marin masini</foreign>), cutting* and trimming on a level*, measuring and making equal, fining and punishing*. If it is highland, it is made to be flat, headland is made to be equal* (with the shore?), all kinds of dependent villages (? <foreign>ampih-ampih</foreign>)*, we should ask the Maṅkubumi.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.30">If we seek to know about all sorts of anchorages, especially sandbanks (<foreign>gosoṅ</foreign>), channels (<foreign>goroṅ</foreign>)*, <foreign>kabua</foreign> (?)*, ripples from all directions (<foreign>ryak mokprok</foreign>), deceitful ripples (<foreign>ryak maliṅ</foreign>), big waves (<foreign>alun aguṅ</foreign>), headlands (<foreign>tañjuṅ</foreign>), promontories (<foreign>hujuṅ</foreign>), islands (<foreign>nusa</foreign>), islets (<foreign>pulo</foreign>)*, barrier reefs (<foreign>karaṅ nuṅgul</foreign>)*, south-easterly <supplied reason="subaudible">winds</supplied> (<foreign>tuṅgara</foreign>), south-westerly <supplied reason="subaudible">winds</supplied> (<foreign>barat daya</foreign>), all kinds of sea travel <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> sailing, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the sea captain (<foreign>puhavaṅ</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.31">If we seek to know about all kinds of prices: three million, three hundred thousand, thirty thousand, three thousand, six hundred, three hundred, thirty all the more so a half (<foreign>karo bəlah</foreign>), a third (<foreign>katәlu bәlah</foreign>), a quarter (<foreign>kapat bәlah</foreign>), a fifth (<foreign>kalima bәlah</foreign>), a sixth (<foreign>kanәm bәlah</foreign>), a seventh (<foreign>kapitu bәlah</foreign>), an eighth (<foreign>kavolu bәlah</foreign>), a ninth (<foreign>kasaṅa bәlah</foreign>) — every kind of price, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the <foreign>citrik byapari</foreign>*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.32">If we seek to know about the esoteric sciences, asceticism, posture, direct perception, detachment, epitome, liberation*, ancestor metaphysics, deity metaphysics*, elemental accounts, epochal accounts — every kind of deity metaphysics*, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the hermits of the people (<foreign>viku para loka</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.33">If we want to act, we should not ask the wrong person. If we seek to know about the languages of various countries* — the languages of China, South India (<foreign>kәliṅ</foreign>), Persia (<foreign>parasi</foreign>), Egypt (<foreign>mәsir</foreign>), Samudra*, Bengal (<foreign>baṅgala</foreign>), Makassar, Pahang, Palembang, Siam, Kelantan (<foreign>kalantәn</foreign>), Bangka, Buwun, Béten*, Tulang Bawang, Sela, Pasai (<foreign>pasay</foreign>), Pariaman (<foreign>parayaman</foreign>), <foreign>ṅara</foreign> Rokan (? ṅara dәkan)*, Dinah (?)*, Andalas (<foreign>andәləs</foreign>), Tego, Moluccas (<foreign>moloko</foreign>), Bandan (<foreign>badan</foreign>), Bago (<foreign>pego</foreign>), Minangkabau (<foreign>malaṅkabo</foreign>), Mecca, Buretet, Lawai (<foreign>lave</foreign>), Sasak (<foreign>saksak</foreign>), Sumbawa (<foreign>sәmbava</foreign>), Bali, Jenggi, Nusa Bini (<foreign>sabini</foreign>), Ogan (<foreign>ṅogan</foreign>), Kanangen, Komering (<foreign>kumәriṅ</foreign>), Sampang Tiga*, Gumantung, Manubi, Bubu, Nyiri, Sapari, Patukangan, Surabaya, Lampung, India (<foreign>jambudipa</foreign>), Seram (?, <foreign>seran</foreign>), Kedah (gәdah), Salaut (?, <foreign>solot</foreign>), Solodong, Indragiri, Tanjungpura*, Sakampung, Atas Angin, Campa (<foreign>cәmpa</foreign>), Baluk, Java — all kinds of countries, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the interpreter who is a reliable guide to dharma (<foreign>darma-murcaya</foreign>)*.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_12">
<p corresp="#skk_12.01">That is what should be known, as to their reliability and appropriateness. If there is one who says that he does not know, he is one who is not faithful to his own function, is very ignorant* as to the words of our Gods, does not fear misfortune (<foreign>upadrava</foreign>), the cycle of worlds (<foreign>jagat-ganti</foreign>)* <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the four powers (<foreign>cadu-sakti</foreign>) of the scholar. <supplied reason="subaudible">He</supplied> is certainly* awaited by the cauldron.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.02">Regarding the works, they should not be performed; regarding the actions, they should not be carried out — except (<foreign>sahiṅaniṅ</foreign>) virtuous works, for that is the thread of the ancestors <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the thread of the gods, the memorial of the Lord of the world, when He made the unmanifest world prosperous*. When Brahma, Wisnu, Isora, Mahadéwa, Siwa are devoted to the Lord; when Indra, Yama, Baruna, Kowéra, Bésawarna* are devoted to the Lord; when Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusa, Patanjala are devoted to the Lord — <supplied reason="subaudible">when</supplied> all of the gods together are devoted to Lord Séda Niskala, <supplied reason="subaudible">then</supplied> all of them find the one who is true with direct perception.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.03">This is what must be found in the manifest world, the thread of the Lord for the world, so that <supplied reason="subaudible">we are</supplied> firm in becoming ‘jewels in one cage’ (? <foreign>manik sakuruṅan</foreign>)*; so that we are shining <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> the whole world: the servant is devoted to his master, the wife is devoted to her husband, the child is devoted to his father, the pupil is devoted to his teacher, the <foreign>mantri</foreign> is devoted to the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign>, <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> is devoted to the king, the king is devoted to the Gods. They are ordered to stabilize their bodies, directing the breath, the speech <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the mind.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.04">If those <supplied reason="subaudible">actions</supplied> are not performed and <supplied reason="subaudible">not</supplied> carried out by the humans, of low, middle, and high class, each of them is thrown into the cauldron called ‘Bull Headed Copper <supplied reason="subaudible">Cauldron</supplied>’*. Because the human is overpowered by the Gods. <foreign>Pun</foreign>*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.05">Darma Pitutur spoke, reporting the words of the precursors: There is another comparison, like <supplied reason="subaudible">when</supplied> we went to Java, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> are unable to follow its language and its manners, we felt confused. After <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> returned home to Sunda, we were unable to speak Javanese. It felt as if we had not come <supplied reason="subaudible">back</supplied> from a journey, “what we bought as a result of visiting was worthless”*, because of inability to follow its language.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.06">That is how we are, as humans, continually* descending from the unmanifest, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> not finding the manners of the Gods, rushing to be incarnated as humans, because their appearance is silly, their behavior is ignorant, <supplied reason="subaudible">and they are</supplied> incapable of following the acts of the ones who know. There are acts committed that are unfaithful, that are improper. <supplied reason="subaudible">They</supplied> start to do evil, to trespass, to have affairs in secret (<foreign>bubunyan</foreign>) with younger and older relatives. That is why a woman enjoying a man who is not her husband is considered improper; a man enjoying a woman who is not his wife (? <foreign>əsi imahna</foreign>)* is <supplied reason="subaudible">likewise</supplied> considered improper. <supplied reason="subaudible">They</supplied> are liable to be thrown into the cauldron called ‘The Victorious Deer’ (Si Mrəga Vijaya)*, because humans prefer what is wrong.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_13">
<p corresp="#skk_13.01">These are the symbolic terms (<foreign>siloka</foreign>)* for the behavior of wrong people: lawless (<foreign>buraṅkak</foreign>)*, anxious (? <foreign>marende</foreign>)*, sulky (<foreign>mariris</foreign>)*, shameful (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>). They are called the four demons. The meaning is: <foreign>buraṅkak</foreign> means shuddering. What is horrifying*, as it were, is the behavior of the person who is envious, surly, staring, coarse (?, <foreign>gasoṅ</foreign>)*, rude in speech, ugly in behavior, hot of heart. <supplied reason="subaudible">Such behavior</supplied> is considered improper. That is what the behavior of such men is like, horrifying as it were. He becomes a demon, Durga, Durgi, the demon Kala. His place is in the dirt of the earth.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.02">The dirty soils are: hollows, clusters (? <foreign>saroṅge</foreign>)*, lime-stone cliffs (<foreign>cadas gantuṅ</foreign>), scattered stones*, gorges, swamps*, rhinoceros ponds, tree trunks upside down* and aslant (<foreign>cataṅ nuṅgaṅ cataṅ noṅgeṅ</foreign>), mine tunnels (<foreign>garuṅguṅan gareṅgeṅan</foreign>)*, dangerous lands (<foreign>saṅhar</foreign>)*, burning grounds*, <supplied reason="subaudible">lands of</supplied> crawling animals (<foreign>varian</foreign>), hillocks, male soils (<foreign>ləmah laki</foreign>), pigsties, gutters (<foreign>kalomberan</foreign>)*, rubbish dumps, cremation grounds (<foreign>səma</foreign>)* — every kind of soil avoided.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.03">What those who are obstinate in their ugly behaviors become is like that, because the behavior of men is what gives horror*. They become every sort of horrifying thing, because they do not follow the holy instruction of the accomplished one*, because they transgress the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society. That is why they become horrifying. That is the meaning of <foreign>buraṅkak</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.04"><foreign>Marende</foreign> means: being cooled down* and yet feeling hot; being given pity*, being given sympathy, being taken care of, being coddled, being given pleasures <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> enjoyments*, servants <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> slaves, and yet mistrusting <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied>. It is clear that he is affected by the misery of which the field <supplied reason="subaudible">called</supplied> Patana is full*. Its length is one <foreign>yojana</foreign>*. In the east is the Sword Tree*. One hundred thousand men are struck <supplied reason="subaudible">by its swords</supplied> there. In the south is the Stone Mountain. One hundred thousand evil men are suffering there together. In the west are the Fire-Headed ghosts*. Humans cannot fathom how much suffering is there. In the north, there are one hundred people suffering together there, like grass-hoppers on a skewer. In the middle is the crow of the Patana*, with the Dog ghosts. Thousands of evil people are suffering there. That is the misery of those called <foreign>marende</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.05"><foreign>Mariris</foreign> means defiled, disgusting like excrement, defiled like a reeking carcass. Such is the conduct of people who are kleptomaniac, who seize indiscriminately, or even take indiscriminately, without asking, stealing, plundering, deceiving, pilfering — all kinds of lying* to good persons. When he dies, his soul* will suffer, for one thousand <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> one hundred years afflicted by the curse of the gods. That is why birth as a human is not in sight. As for what he becomes: <foreign>koter</foreign>*, <foreign>jaṅgel</foreign>*, crop-worm*, horse-fly*, <foreign>titiṅgi</foreign>*, <foreign>jambəloṅ</foreign>*, leatherleaf slug*, <foreign>mear</foreign>*, <foreign>pacet</foreign>* (blood sucking haemadipsa), leech, <foreign>ləhəṅ</foreign>, <foreign>gərəṅ</foreign>* — everything that is despised by people in general, that is what is called <foreign>mariris</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.06">Disgrace (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>) means unwilling to be sincere, unwilling to truthful, unwilling to be proper, unwilling to be frank, unwilling to be polite. If his anxiety (?, <foreign>harən</foreign>)*, passion, love <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> astonishment is deceitful, <supplied reason="subaudible">then</supplied> when he dies, his soul will meet with suffering, <supplied reason="subaudible">i.e</supplied> a wobbly bridge, a slanting plank bridge, clashing stones. When they are made into being in the world, they become everything that is horrifying: rhinoceros, tiger, crocodile, great snake, everything that is horrifying. That is called disgrace (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>).  So much for the four demons.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_14">
<p corresp="#skk_14.01">This is like a man who travels to China, spends a long time in China. <supplied reason="subaudible">He</supplied> knows Chinese customs, Chinese habits, Chinese language, Chinese manners, Chinese etiquette. <supplied reason="subaudible">He</supplied> meets with three <supplied reason="subaudible">levels</supplied> of language, <supplied reason="subaudible">namely</supplied> low, middle, and high. <supplied reason="subaudible">He</supplied> knows all* about the speech of the king, the elder, and the hermit; is able to direct the breath, the speech, and the mind. That is the reason why <supplied reason="subaudible">he</supplied> knows about the consciousness (<foreign>gəiṅ</foreign>), the higher consciousness (<foreign>upagəiṅ</foreign>), the ultimate consciousness (<foreign>parigəiṅ</foreign>). They are called the three forms of consciousness.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.02">Consciousness is <supplied reason="subaudible">a person endowed with it</supplied> being able to taste, to drink, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> being able to have pleasure; that is called consciousness. What is called higher consciousness is <supplied reason="subaudible">a person endowed with it</supplied> being able to dress, able to wear clothes, able to wear a lower garment, able to wear festive attire; that is called higher consciousness. What is called ultimate consciousness is <supplied reason="subaudible">a person endowed with it</supplied> being able to instruct, able to command, because his speech is sweet <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> fragrant*, such that the one who is commanded does not become angry, because he is touched by the impact of applying expressions with a deeper meaning (<foreign>siloka</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.03">If his words (<foreign>basana</foreign>)* are <supplied reason="subaudible">addressed</supplied> to a youngster, <supplied reason="subaudible">he addresses him or her as</supplied> ‘boy’ (<foreign>utun</foreign>)*, ‘girl’ (<foreign>eten</foreign>)*, ‘baby’ (<foreign>orok</foreign>), ‘my child’, ‘my little sibling’. <supplied reason="subaudible">If they are addressed</supplied> to an elder, <supplied reason="subaudible">he addresses him or her as</supplied> ‘my elder brother’*, ‘my elder nephew or niece’, ‘my elder sister’, ‘my senior’, and ‘my grandfather’. His exclamations* are: are ‘be well!’ (<foreign>sumaṅər</foreign>), ‘what a pity!’ (<foreign>tətəiṅ amat</foreign>). As numerous are the ten pacifying acts*, namely: being virtuous*, reverent (<foreign>nama</foreign>)*, sympathetic*, forgiving*, loving, compassionate, generous*, gentle*, tranquil, ingratiating. That is why someone who is given an order is happy <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> joyful, bright <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> shining. That is called the ultimate consciousness.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.04">These are the metaphors for it*: gold, silver, jewel, diamond. They are called the four holy courtesies. This is its meaning: gold means the speech which is right, accurate, clear, <supplied reason="subaudible">applying</supplied> the formula of five syllables*. Silver means the mind which is accomplished, proper, good. Jewel means his consciousness is bright <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> shining, wide <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> broad*. Diamond means cheerfully laughing*, visibly smiling*, pleasant of heart. They are called the four courtesies.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.05">They are the people who originate from the pure ones among lands. The pure ones among lands are the offering place, the place of rolled offerings (? <foreign>pabuntəlan</foreign>)*, the worship place, the sturdy house (? <foreign>imah manəh</foreign>)*, the sanctuary, the temple tower, the <foreign>lingga</foreign>, the statue*, the <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> stone (<foreign>batu gaṅsa</foreign>)*, land with statues, where human figures are created <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> sweeping <supplied reason="subaudible">is performed</supplied>. So many are all lands which are maintained, waters that are strained <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> purified. It is indeed a good person, a kind person. He is an accomplished person. The one who is considered to originate from the pure ones among lands is aware of the holy precepts, heeding the advice of mother, father, grandfather and great-grandfather, knowing the teachings of the great scholars, upholding the words of the accomplished ones.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_15">
<p corresp="#skk_15.01">This is the account of the ancient ones who instated the holy instructions of the accomplished ones: the deified ancestor Déwaraja, the deified ancestor Rawung Langit, the deified ancestor at Medang, the deified ancestor at Menir*. They are called the four accomplished ones. That is why in the present, men who are aware of the holy supreme <foreign>dharma</foreign>, knowledgeable about the secret teachings of men, they are called esoteric men*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_15.02">If they die, their soul will find a beautiful heaven, finding daytime that does not turn into night, joy that does not turn into sorrow, heaven that does not turn into into <supplied reason="subaudible">the hell of</supplied> sinners, pleasure that does not turn into pain, good that does not turn into into bad, fortunate that does not turn into unfortunate, subtle that does not turn into gross, being gone that does not turn into being present, ancestors that do not turn into gods. That is what is called the supreme liberation*.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_16">
<p corresp="#skk_16.01">Likewise are the people in the present*. Compare us taking a bath, the choices of the water to be touched by us are only two: the one which is turbid and the one which is clear. Likewise are the behaviors of people, two (types) being put into practice: the bad and the good. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated badly is that bad behavior of theirs. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated well is that good behavior of theirs. That is why people are bad by their behavior, why they are good by their behavior*.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_16.02">Water is like that, insofar as the choices of it are said to be two. Water that is refreshing and clear is the holy supreme <foreign>dharma</foreign>, that is what is practiced by the great scholars. Water that is haunted and turbid is the emotional conduct (<foreign>rasa-carita</foreign>), which is practiced by all the <foreign>viku</foreign>s for whom the <foreign>nec plus ultra</foreign> is worldly*. That is why it (i.e., water) is comparable to consciousness* as well as unconsciousness. Consciousness is aware and mindful of memories without turning into forgetfulness. It is the root of a favorable rebirth, the cause of a prosperous earth*. Unconsciousness is forgetfulness <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> confusion, not endowed with memory. It is the cause of destruction, the starting point of the Kali era, the base of deviation, the root of falsehood*. It is the cause of people going to hell. That should not be taken as truth by those who wish to be sincere.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_17">
<p corresp="#skk_17.01">These are the words of the holy man, when he maintains his possessions*. These are the three threads in the world*. Our (<foreign>kita</foreign>) breath is the ruler, our speech is the elders, our mind is the hermits. Those are the three threads in the world, which are considered as the support of the world.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.02">These are the group of three in the distant <supplied reason="subaudible">world</supplied>*: Wisnu is considered as king, Brahma is considered as elder, Iswara is considered a hermit. It is the reason why the three threads are the support of the world, <supplied reason="subaudible">while</supplied> the group of three are the life of the world. They are considered as the three threads for all people. <supplied reason="subaudible">We</supplied> should hold <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied> up, hold <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied> fast until they are straight, true, evident, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> present*. The reason why the world is prosperous, why the earth is affluent, is because the actions of people are well maintained.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.03">Likewise, the scholars who are firm in their scholarship will prosper; the monk who are firm in their monkhood prosper; the <foreign>maṅuyu</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>maṅuyu</foreign>-ship will prosper; the <foreign>palikən</foreign>* who are firm in their <foreign>palikən</foreign>-ship will be prosper; the monks who are firm in their monkhood will be prosper; the wandering ascetics (<foreign>aməṅ</foreign>)* who are firm in their wanderership will be prosper; the <foreign>vasi</foreign>s* who are firm in their <foreign>vasi</foreign>-ship will be prosper; the nuns (<foreign>əbon</foreign>)* who are firm in their nunship will be prosper; the renouncers (<foreign>tiagi</foreign>) who are firm in their renunciation will be successful; even more so the aspirants (<foreign>valaka</foreign>) who are firm in their aspirantshipi will be successful; the peasants who are firm in their peasantship will be successful; the thieves (<foreign>əvah</foreign>)* firm in their thievery will be successful; the gusti firm in their <foreign>gusti</foreign>-ship will be successful; the minister firm in their ministership will be successful; the <foreign>masaṅs</foreign>* (?) who are firm in their <foreign>masaṅ</foreign>-ship will be successful; the <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>-ship will be successful; the seamen who are firm in their seamanship will be successful; the <foreign>disi</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>disi</foreign>-ship will be successful; the elders who are firm in their eldership will be successful; the hermits who are firm in their hermitship will be successful; the rulers who are firm in their rulership will be successful. Formerly, the scholars, together with the divine king who were firm in making the world prosperous, so that the north, south, west <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> east — everything which is held by the earth <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> covered by the sky — prospered, all beings are alive, all of them*.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_18">
<p corresp="#skk_18.01">All kinds of beings means: plant beings, animal beings, human beings, individual beings (<foreign>si voṅ</foreign>), the substance of the individual (<foreign>vastu si voṅ</foreign>)*. That is the reason that all of them are called all beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.02">Plant beings are grass, trees, creepers, shrubs, all that is alive, fresh green, wild. They are called plant beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.03">Animal beings are all kinds of animals, big or small, on land or in the water. They are called animal beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.04">Human beings are human <supplied reason="subaudible">only</supplied> in appearance, for their character is not good*. Individual beings (<foreign>si voṅ</foreign>) have good character, good family, for they do not know yet the holy <foreign>dharma</foreign>. The substance of the individual is the one who is firm in the impact of knowing, knowing the holy <foreign>dharma</foreign>, knowing the reality of holy knowledge. Those are called real human beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.05">May this be sought to be internalized by the inhabitants of the world*, four in number. These are <foreign>kurija</foreign>, <foreign>mataja</foreign>, <foreign>bagaja</foreign>, <foreign>payuja</foreign>. <foreign>Kurija</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the mouth*; <foreign>mataja</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the eyes; <foreign>bagaja</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the vulva; <foreign>payuja</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the anus. Those are called the holy four origins.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_19">
<p corresp="#skk_19.01">These are the 6 abilities of people in the world: to count (<foreign>ṅaṅka</foreign>), to chain yarns (<foreign>ñigi</foreign>), to tie (<foreign>ṅikət</foreign>), to touch (<foreign>ñigəṅ</foreign>), to bury (<foreign>ṅaruaṅ</foreign>), to heap up (<foreign>ṅaromboṅ</foreign>)*. To count means estimating; <foreign>ñigi</foreign>* means twisting*; <foreign>ṅikət</foreign> is various bindings; <foreign>ñigəṅ</foreign> is centering (? <foreign>məṅpəṅ</foreign>)*, splitting (<foreign>məlah</foreign>), using a wedge (<foreign>mañcir</foreign>/)*, halving, evaluating, calculating (<foreign>ṅaṅgit aṅka</foreign>)*, measuring, equating; to bury means all kinds of digging; <foreign>ṅaromboṅ</foreign> is all kinds of spaces (<foreign>hələt-hələt</foreign>). Those are called the six abilities (<foreign>sad-guna</foreign>)*, so many are all the abilities of the people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.02">These are the 4 desires of the people: the wish to be pure (<foreign>yun suda</foreign>), the wish to be happy (<foreign>yun suka</foreign>), the wish to ascend (<foreign>yun muṅgah</foreign>), the wish to be liberated (<foreign>yun luput</foreign>). This is what it means: <foreign>yun suda</foreign> is desiring to be healthy (<foreign>purna</foreign>)*, refusing to suffer from any disease; <foreign>yun suka</foreign> is desiring to be rich, refusing to be deprived of possessions; <foreign>yun muṅgah</foreign> is desiring heaven, refusing to obtain <supplied reason="subaudible">another rebirth in</supplied> the world; <foreign>yun luput</foreign> is desiring release, refusing to be taken by* all heavens*. That is why so many are all the desires of the people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.03">These are the 4 who bathe in the river, that is to say: male, female, effeminate man, unfeminine woman*. That is the number. How many are the <supplied reason="subaudible">types of</supplied> earmarked goods? <supplied reason="subaudible">There are</supplied> 2, that is to say: ripe and raw, bad and good, small and big. How many are the flavors? <supplied reason="subaudible">There are</supplied> 6, that is to say: salty (<foreign>lavaṇa</foreign>), hot (<foreign>kaṭuka</foreign>), bitter (<foreign>tikta</foreign>)*, sour (<foreign>amla</foreign>), astringent (<foreign>kaṣāya</foreign>)*, sweet (<foreign>madhura</foreign>). <foreign>Lavaṇa</foreign> means salty, <foreign>kaṭuka</foreign> means spicy*, <foreign>tikta</foreign> means bitter, <foreign>amla</foreign> means sour, <foreign>kaṣāya</foreign> means savory, <foreign>madhura</foreign> means sweet. So many are all the things tasted by the people.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_20">
<p corresp="#skk_20.01">These are for us to take into possession ourselves, in order that they descend continuously (<foreign>pativah-tivah</foreign>) to children <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> grandchildren, to great grandchildren, to great-great grandchildren, to <foreign>muniṅ</foreign>, to <foreign>aṅgasantana</foreign>, to <foreign>pratisantana</foreign>*; all ultimate descendants (<foreign>putu vəkas</foreign>)* of <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> family — those which are suitable be given in inheritance* as well as those which are not suitable.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_20.02">Gains from impudence are not suitable to be given inheritance: they are called “gifts of the demons”. Gains from gambling, from subletting (?, <foreign>babalañjaan</foreign>)* are not suitable to be given in inheritance: they are called “gifts of an egocentric mind”*. Nevertheless, gifts from the mother, gifts from the father, gifts from teachers, they can be given in inheritance: they are called “gods that protect us”. Profits from agriculture can be given in inheritance: they are called “jewels produced from the earth”. Profits from weaving <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> products of husbandry can be given in inheritance: they are called “rubies fallen from the sky”.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_21">
<p corresp="#skk_21.01">If there are rich people, then <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> redeem a woman, without knowing about her parents. <supplied reason="subaudible">Such a woman</supplied> should not be taken as purchased servant (<foreign>dipikaritakən</foreign>)*, lest we become involved in something wrong. </p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.02">There is more — when we do know about her parents, where the servant’s origin is —, if the behavior of her parents is good, the person (in question, <foreign>janma</foreign>) is still good. It is called “being defeated (kapapas) by <supplied reason="subaudible">ones</supplied> parents’ behavior”. <supplied reason="subaudible">She</supplied> can be taken as purchased servant. But if <supplied reason="subaudible">she is defeated</supplied> by their deceitful behavior, she should not be tolerated. It is called “a person wandering around in hell”.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.03">There is more, <supplied reason="subaudible">if</supplied> there is a person of good behavior, of good foundation*, of good origin, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> not fail to redeem <supplied reason="subaudible">her</supplied>, but <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not immediately (<foreign>tuluy</foreign>)* take <supplied reason="subaudible">her</supplied> as wife, lest the descendant be a servant. <supplied reason="subaudible">We</supplied> should not fail to tell <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> to our family. After that, we should propose <supplied reason="subaudible">to marry her</supplied>, bring a betel quid and serve it.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.04">Those are the powerful words (<foreign>jaṅjavokan</foreign>) so that <supplied reason="subaudible">her</supplied> family returns to its caste*, so that <supplied reason="subaudible">she</supplied> avoids, escapes from imprisonment*, so that <supplied reason="subaudible">she</supplied> mingles with our good family, so that <supplied reason="subaudible">she</supplied> avoids calamity.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_22">
<p corresp="#skk_22.01">This is for us to arrange our children’s marriage. They should not be matched* too early unless <supplied reason="subaudible">the other family</supplied> is as proper as ours, the majority of us. As for the venereal disease* of a father, it descends to the sons; as for the venereal disease of a mother, it descends to the daughters; if all die, they ascend from earth. It is called the demon entering into the Kali (epoch). It is improper to match infants (with each other), lest we become involved in something wrong, lest the <supplied reason="subaudible">parents</supplied> who made the arrangement get cornered*.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_23">
<p corresp="#skk_23.01">Thus far the instruction of the holy men, the words of the Darma Pitutur, who utters the words of the ancestors, which should be given due attention. Follow <supplied reason="subaudible">their</supplied> action, use <supplied reason="subaudible">these</supplied> words*: Homage to Siwa, homage to Buddha, homage to the fulfilled and perfect soul.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_23.02">Happy shall be the reader who intends that the good words be absorbed completely (<foreign>kasukma</foreign>)*, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> who is firm in his pure mind. Please be attentive O servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>. This is the completion of what are called ‘The Hermits’ Precepts for Society’, the title of the book. <foreign>Pun</foreign>.</p></div></body></text>
</TEI>