<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#sasanamahaguru">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI encoding</resp>
                    <!--TBM-->
                    <persName ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSasanaMahaguru_transEng01</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p/>
                        <p/>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <schemaRef type="guide" key="EGCv01"
                url="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15HFxHJTOzIU1UDyVrB2yQYJ5wI6JyEshEkYgg5qwj8M/edit#"
            />
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:axja" when="2022-11-24" status="draft">creation of the file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.01">Here is the name of the holy book: The Holy
                    Instruction of the Great Teacher (<foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</foreign>).
                        <foreign>Sasana</foreign> means the legacy of the ancestors,
                        <foreign>maha</foreign> means more superior than the superior of the world,
                        <foreign>guru</foreign> means the source of all the universe.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.02">There is your analogy: like the priceless jewel
                    and the most desirable gem, it is the source of the joy and sorrow, the bad and
                    the good. Its explanation is as follows: world
                        (<foreign>buh</foreign>),<note>MsA has <foreign>bvah</foreign>, but I render
                        it as <foreign>buh</foreign> since the context is quite clear. Cf.
                            <foreign>bvar</foreign> for <foreign>bur</foreign> in SMG 1.4.</note>
                        intention,<note> I interpret paksa as ‘intention’, see OJED, s.v. pakṣa
                        IV.</note> knowledge,<note>In OS we find that huniṅ is a verb ‘to know’, but
                        in this context it is clearly substantive.</note> determination,<note>Based
                        on the explanation that tǝmǝn is related to fire, maybe it means
                        determination. OJED does not record substantive meaning, but cf.
                            <foreign>anəməni</foreign> ‘to be serious about, set about doing st. in
                        real earnest (determinedly)’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>təmən</foreign>).</note>
                    total willingness.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.03">The meaning is: The world is the Holy Earth. When
                    it is beautified, degraded, upgraded, littered, mingled, it does not
                        fall<note>The meaning of fall is taken from MdS,
                            <foreign>nyusutkeun</foreign> ‘throw so. down forward on the ground’;
                            <foreign>tisusut</foreign> ‘fall forward’. Cf Mal
                            <foreign>susut</foreign> ‘to decrease; to shrink’. It is different from
                        OJ <foreign>susut</foreign> ‘entangled, confused.’</note> and it is not
                    indignant, it is not weak<note>I interpret <foreign>gərah</foreign> as ‘weak,
                        powerless’ as in OJ. In MdS, it has a positive nuance ‘cheerful, buoyant, in
                        high spirits; rejoice, glad, pleased, happy’.</note> and it is not
                        restless,<note>In MdS dictionaries, <foreign>mijah</foreign> is considered
                        as the base word. Clearly in OS we have the base word
                            <foreign>bijah</foreign>.</note> forcefull and firm in performing
                    earthiness (<foreign>kaprativian</foreign>). That is indeed the thing that the
                    servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should practice.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.04">Intention means the water. Its benefit is when
                    [it] emerges<note>The word <foreign>bvar</foreign> is not in the dictionaries,
                        but cf. MdS <foreign>bur</foreign>. ‘ant. for: hurry off, hasten away,
                        scamper off, fly away, strew (flowers), scatter, sow (seed), sprinkle
                        (sand), pour out, empty (contents of st.), etc’.</note> from its upstream.
                    It gushes clear, and it feels cool. Moreover, it also had no obstacles, reaching
                    the ocean. That is what the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> must
                    emulate.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.05">Knowledge means the wind. Its benefit is when it
                        blows<note> Like the word <foreign>bvar</foreign>, a single syllable word
                        hir is also, following Hardjadibrata’s terminology, an anticipator. However,
                        hir in this context is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but the present
                        context makes clear that it refers to ‘air motion, wind etc’. Cf. MdS
                            <foreign>hiliwir</foreign>, <foreign>ngahiliwir</foreign> ‘(come in)
                        blowing softly (of the breeze, of the scent of flowers filling the air);
                            <foreign>humiliwir</foreign> s.m. (in lit. lang.); (the root is used as
                        ant.)’.</note> from the west. It blows with coolness, [and] feels smooth on
                    our bodies. Moreover, it will not be obstructed when it appears at the right
                    moment in the world. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.06">Determination means fire and weapons. Because of
                    their natures (<foreign>ti iña</foreign>),<note> I take the conjunction ti in ti
                        iña as the reasoning. Cf. Skt. <foreign>tasmat</foreign>.</note> they are to
                    be used<note>The passive form <foreign>dipipakǝnakən</foreign> is from
                            <foreign>pakən</foreign> ‘for, so that’, cf. an equivalent construction
                        in Mal <foreign>diperuntukkan</foreign>.</note> by people whose minds are
                    determined.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.07">Willingness means the Holy Sun. When it rises
                    from the east, it is not impeded by clouds, rain, smoke, and fog until it
                    reaches the west, because of the concentration on one action [only]. That is
                    what the servant of the dharma must emulate. We should not fail to be mindful
                    toward the holy original cause. The following are called The Five Knowledges
                        (<foreign>pañca-vedani</foreign>).<note> The word <foreign>vedani</foreign>
                        ‘knowledge’ is probably being understood by the author as a neutral form of
                        Skt <foreign>veda</foreign>. Another possibility is that the author tends to
                        relate vedani with the OJ compound, <foreign>ve dani</foreign> ‘clear
                        water’, from OJ <foreign>ve</foreign> ‘water’, and <foreign>dani</foreign>
                        ‘(of the mind) to become clear, no longer darkened by emotions,
                        etc?’.</note>
                    <foreign>Panca</foreign> means <foreign>five</foreign>, <foreign>ve</foreign>
                    means water, <foreign>dani</foreign> means broomstick.</p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.01">This is called the precepts for society
                        (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), the precepts of religious groups
                        (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>), the root’s precepts (<foreign>siksa
                        dapur</foreign>). The meaning is: the precepts for society are around
                    yourself. To encounter<note>The initial reduplication form
                            <foreign>jǝṅjǝəṅ</foreign> means ‘to encounter’, from
                            <foreign>jəəṅ</foreign> ‘to see’. Cf. SKK 7.2.</note> the adultery, the
                    adultery of ‘The Journey’ [and] of ‘The Sitting Place’. That is what we should
                    keep in mind.<note>One would expect <foreign>ku uraṅ</foreign> instead of
                            <foreign>dəṅ uraṅ</foreign>. Cf. the attested use of conjunction
                            <foreign>mvaṅ</foreign> in OJ as a mark of agent. Cf. JS 19
                            <foreign>kapāśa mvaṅ triguṇa</foreign> ‘to be fettered by the
                        trigunas’.</note> Then let us be careful, in case we enter the yard,
                    entering the inner place, it is not comfortable [if we are] not their
                    inhabitants. That is called the precepts for society.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.02">When we are on a journey,<note>The word
                            <foreign>paparan</foreign> is from <foreign>paran</foreign>
                        ‘destination’, meaning ‘to go, in journey’, cf. OJ
                            <foreign>apara-paran</foreign> ‘to journey, wander abroad, roam’. This
                        form is not recorded in MdS, however, some dialects have
                            <foreign>maparan</foreign> ‘go to see so., going to look so. up’
                        (Hardjadibrata, s.v. <foreign>paran</foreign>). Cf. SKK 5.3.</note> it is
                    not proper to commit a deceitful act because of the commodity of someone else’s
                    farm, or someone else’s vegetable grove. Therefore,
                        “<foreign>hiris</foreign><note>In MdS, <foreign>hiris</foreign> refers to
                        various kinds of plant, ‘leguminous plant (s.m. kacang h., see
                            <foreign>kacang</foreign>); <foreign>ki hiris</foreign> I k.o. shrub,
                        Budleia asiatica Lour., member of the Loganiaceae (also called: <foreign>ki
                            kadal</foreign>, <foreign>ki kérését</foreign>, ki
                            <foreign>monyényén</foreign>); II (H.) k.o. shrub or small tree (wood
                        useful for charcoal; also called: <foreign>ki hurung</foreign>). Since it is
                        mentioned along with <foreign>kacaṅ</foreign>, I take hiris as a kind of
                        nut.</note> will smash the ear when the bean smashes the forehead”: to
                    collect what people put down temporarily (<foreign>tunda</foreign>),<note>In
                        MdS, <foreign>tunda</foreign>, <foreign>nunda</foreign> means ‘put st. down
                        temporarily (with the purpose of taking it up again later on the way); stop
                        st. (work, case, subject) temporarily (with the intention of picking it up
                        again at a later stage)’. In this case, I take tunda as a
                        substantive.</note> to take something clearly owned [by another],<note> In
                        MdS, <foreign>kantenan</foreign> is a high (<foreign>lemes</foreign>)
                        register of <foreign>puguh</foreign> ‘(adv) of course, certainly, sure,
                        positive’; or is it a <foreign>lemes</foreign> register of kari ‘remain,
                        residue’? If it is the case, then the translation of <foreign>ṅala
                            kantənan</foreign> would be ‘to collect the remains’.</note> [or] to
                    bring down someone else’s tap (<foreign>sadapan</foreign>). It is improper to
                    defecate on the side of the road, for it would be smelt by those who are
                        careless,<note>The reduplicated form <foreign>buṅah-baṅah</foreign> is not
                        in dictionaries. MdS has <foreign>balaṅah</foreign> ‘careless’, probably
                        from <foreign>baṅah</foreign> with infix -al-. The base word
                            <foreign>bangah</foreign>, however, is not recorded in dictionaries as a
                        base word.</note> for it is possible that you will be cursed and be
                        blamed<note> The passive word <foreign>kapadahkǝn</foreign> is not found in
                        MdS. Its occurrence is always with <foreign>kasumpah</foreign> ‘to be
                        cursed’ in OS texts. I render it as equivalent to OJ
                            <foreign>amāda</foreign> ‘to find fault with, judge harshly’, from the
                        base <foreign>vāda</foreign> (OJED, s.v.). It should be noted that MdS also
                        has <foreign>ngawada</foreign> ‘to criticize’.</note> [by] mother, father,
                    and teachers. We should not fail to wear loincloths and full attire; if we meet
                    a gusti or a minister, we should be on their left [and] bow.<note> The word
                            <foreign>paṅadoṅkoṅkən</foreign> is clearly related to OJ
                            <foreign>joṅkoṅ</foreign> 'squatting’. Cf. SKK 4.16. See the discussion
                        on <foreign>paN- -kən</foreign> in Chapter 3. Cf. also MdS
                            <foreign>dongko</foreign> vi. ‘bend the upper torso forward’, but MdS
                        also has <foreign>dongkong</foreign> ‘id.’ <foreign>mangdongkokeun</foreign>
                        ‘take a bent forward posture for so’.</note> Those are called the precepts
                    for society.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.03">The precepts of the religious group
                        (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>) are to be one action with the scholar.
                    After all,<note>Based on the context, <foreign>aṅgəs ma</foreign> here seems to
                        mean ‘after all’. See Glossary</note> it is not good to make trouble of
                    which has been deliberated, violating the holy precepts. If we are aware of the
                    sections (of the books) and their binding cords
                        (<foreign>lǝkǝr-lǝkǝr</foreign>),<note>The reduplication form
                            <foreign>ləkər-ləkər</foreign> is not attested in OS, but we find
                            <foreign>ləkər</foreign> in OJ ‘coil, encircling rope (etc) to provide
                        firmness’. I interpret it as an allusion to the binding cords on the palm
                        leaf manuscripts.</note> their <foreign>danda</foreign>s,<note> The word
                            <foreign>daṅda-daṅdi</foreign> probably refers to Sanskrit term
                            <foreign>daṇḍa</foreign> or punctuation mark in writing. It seems to be
                        a redundant compound. Cf. <foreign>trəpti-trəptva</foreign> on SMG
                        3.2.</note> lines (<foreign>sipat</foreign>), enclosures
                        (<foreign>galǝṅ</foreign>), their strokes, their compositions, their
                    boundary, their limits, all the imprints of the God Brahmā and Viṣṇu when they
                    delimited the world. That is called the precepts of the religious group. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.04">As for the precepts of the root is to reach the
                    core, to obtain the origin by one’s devoted and truthful mind toward the
                    scholar. That is called the precepts of the root. Those are called the precepts
                    for society,<note> One expected <foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>siksa
                            kuruṅ</foreign>, <foreign>siksa dapur ṅaranya</foreign> in this
                        sentence.</note> according to the great scholar.</p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.01">As follows is what the servant of the
                        <foreign>dharma</foreign> should be aware of, [that is] the original cause
                    of the holy scripture,<note>For the interpretation of this chapter, regarding
                        the writing supports and instruments in manuscript production, see Aditia
                        Gunawan 2015.</note> the form of stain<note>Maybe
                            <foreign>mala-murti</foreign> refers to the shape of the ink stains in
                        the book? But <foreign>mala</foreign> can also mean ‘curse’, which in this
                        connection probably displays the sacred nature of the book.</note> in the
                    past until present.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.02">Here is the beginning of the holy scripture. Its
                    form is as follows: after the sun<note> The sun with the personification
                        attribute is also found in SHH 24.6,
                        <foreign>śrīvikramāditya</foreign>.</note> had set, the night replaced [it].
                    Satisfaction and pleasure<note>I consider trǝpti-trǝptva as a redundant
                        compound, equivalent to OJ trǝpti and trǝpta, both mean ‘contentment,
                        gladness, well-being; content, glad, pleased’ (OJED, svv.).</note> are the
                    cause of the way of appearing, [thanks to] the reality of time of the Goddess
                    Durgi. The God Gana’s instrument (<foreign>jantra</foreign>) trumpeted, so that
                    it was sprayed towards humankind in the middle realm, and it turned into
                        <foreign>gebang</foreign> and <foreign>lontar</foreign>. [When] the time
                    came for the gebang and lontar to form young leaves, they followed precisely the
                    same pattern with respect to their width and length, [so that they could have]
                        <foreign>asta gaṅga vira tanu</foreign> applied.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.03">What is the <foreign>asta gaṅga vira
                        tanu</foreign>? <foreign>Asta</foreign> means hand, <foreign>gaṅga</foreign>
                    means water, <foreign>vira</foreign> means pen and brush,
                        <foreign>tanu</foreign> means ink. They are used for writing by the scholar,
                    for reading by one without knowledge to increase the range of the sounds, which
                    is constrained [according to the rules] by the poet.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.04">In the first place, the ten origins will be
                    narrated. <foreign>Oṅ</foreign> Saraswati the excellence mind<note>The
                        combination <foreign>tara-jñana</foreign> is unattested elsewhere. My
                        interpretation of <foreign>tara</foreign> as ‘excellent’ is based on the
                        meaning in OJ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>tara</foreign> 1).</note> and the
                    thought-gem. Let the eyes of God Bayu widely open. Let there be the embodiment
                    of Lord Guru, the accomplished ancient masters<note>The compound
                            <foreign>panditatita</foreign> is from <foreign>pandita</foreign> (Skt
                            <foreign>paṇḍita</foreign>) and <foreign>atita</foreign> (Skt
                            <foreign>atīta</foreign>) ‘the ancient master’. Not in MdS.</note> from
                    the earth, the accomplished ancien masters from the sky: Kusika, Garga, Méstri,
                    Purusya, Patañjala; also breath, sound, and mind; let alone The Witness,<note>On
                        the interpretation of The Witness (Saṅ Manon), see Chapter 9.</note> for He
                    is the one who counts.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.05">As follows are what are called the ten origins
                        (<foreign>dasa-purva</foreign>). <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten,
                        <foreign>purva</foreign> means the origin. Those should be taken notice by
                    the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, according to the scholar.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.06">Postphone! All that emerges from the narrative
                        (<foreign>carita</foreign>) should be followed; [yet] the essence of The One
                        (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ tuṅgal</foreign>) is inactive. For what purpose am I
                    uttering this mantra? Well, it is because I know that I wish to produce letters:
                    writing on gold, writing on silver, writing on copper, writing on knives (?,
                        <foreign>cudiga</foreign>),<note>In BM 1565–1569, <foreign>cudiga</foreign>
                        seems to refer to one of the metal materials, however, Noorduyn and Teeuw
                        translate cudiga as ‘spout’: <foreign>pañcuran tambaga sukla, caṅkorah
                            salaka pirak, dituṅtuṅ ku cudiga, pesek dipopokan omas, pañimbǝh undǝm
                            salaka</foreign> ‘The bathing place is of light copper, with a silver
                        basin, ending in a spout, a washing place coated with gold, its scoop a
                        silver vessel’. I rather consider that <foreign>cudiga</foreign> is derived
                        from Skt <foreign>churikā</foreign> ‘knife’, with the interchangeability of
                        /r/ with /d/ and /k/ with /g/, which is not extraordinary. I wonder if there
                        is a semantic shift from a knife into a general material of metal like
                        ‘steel’?</note> writing on iron, writing on stone, writing on wooden strips,
                    writing on bamboo (?, <foreign>pəjva</foreign>),<note>The word
                            <foreign>pəjva</foreign> could not be found in dictionaries. But this
                        word may be related with OJ <foreign>peñjor</foreign> ‘bamboo pole decorated
                        at the top’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>peñjor</foreign>), the changement of vowels
                        /e/ > /ə/, while the omission of a nasal and the addition of final /r/ are
                        imaginable. However, the connection with <foreign>ləpihan</foreign> which
                        means 'folded' is also confusing. I do not exclude the possibility that
                        pəjva may mean bark tree (<foreign>daluwang</foreign>), also used as a
                        writing support for manuscripts.</note> writing on
                        <foreign>lontar</foreign>,<note>Regarding the word <foreign>taal</foreign>,
                        we find several cases of the hiatus usage in OS which is comparable to long
                        vowels in OJ counterpart: OS <foreign>vaas</foreign> vs. OJ
                            <foreign>vās</foreign>, OS <foreign>duum</foreign> vs. OJ
                            <foreign>dūm</foreign>. See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> writing on
                        <foreign>gebang</foreign>.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.07">Writing on gold is called ‘transcendent ruby and
                    gold’; its form and its result is beautiful, for it may not be stored. Perhaps
                    many do not know this, so once again it is passed down: writing on silver is
                    called ‘silver’ (<foreign>kanaka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on
                    copper is called ‘thin plates of beaten gold’ (?,
                        <foreign>paripih</foreign>).<note>The word <foreign>paripid</foreign> seems
                        to be related to Skt <foreign>paripīḍ</foreign> ‘to press all round, press
                        together, squeeze’. However, I interpret this word from OJ paripih, meaning
                        ‘thin plates of beaten gold’. Should it be better to emend it to
                            <foreign>paripih</foreign>? However, the difference between OJ /h/ and
                        OS /d/ is difficult to understand. Cf. Mal <foreign>pipih</foreign> ‘thin
                        and flat’.</note> It is passed down again: writing on steel is called
                    ‘pressed’ (?, <foreign>prəka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on
                    iron is called ‘family’ (?, <foreign>gvatraka</foreign>). It is passed down
                    again: writing on stone is called ‘dead heirs’ (?, <foreign>tras
                        pati</foreign>).<note>The compound <foreign>tras pati</foreign> literally
                        means ‘dead heirs’; I wonder whether this contains an allusion to the more
                        durable nature of the inscription on stone and is intended for heirs?</note>
                    It is passed down again: writing on wooden boards is called ‘a bench’
                        (<foreign>salə</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on bamboo is
                    called ‘folded’ (?, <foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), which may not be kept for it
                    may cause danger. It is passed down again: writing on lontar is called incising
                        (<foreign>carik</foreign>), indeed it has its virtues for it is not to be
                    used for sacred texts (<foreign>kabuyutan</foreign>). Let’s go down again:
                    writing on gebang is called black (<foreign>cəməṅ</foreign>), and this is for
                    the sacred texts. For such texts referred to as manuscripts (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ
                        ripta</foreign>), [the means for attaining] emptiness
                        (<foreign>sunya</foreign>), folded books (<foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), the
                    weapons (?, <foreign>mastra</foreign>),<note> My interpretation of
                            <foreign>mastra</foreign> as ‘weapon’ is tentative, probably it should
                        be read <foreign>makastra</foreign>? Cf. PM 41b <foreign>makastra tanah
                            lǝpihan eñjiṅ mahas andon laṅu pañji</foreign></note> the smearing (of
                    ink ?, <foreign>lepa-karana</foreign> ),<note>The activity of smearing
                            (<foreign>lepa-karana</foreign>) probably refers to the smearing of palm
                        leaves manuscripts as we find its practice in Bali nowadays? This
                        combination is not found in OJ.</note> these are the [types of] books
                    enumerated one by one. Those are called ten advancements.</p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.01">The One said, “What is the purpose<note>The word
                        piǝnanana, which I interpret tentatively ‘purpose’, is not found in
                        dictionaries, but I wonder whether the semantic meaning is generated from
                        the morphological process of <foreign>pi- -ǝn</foreign> meaning ‘things to
                        be’ or ‘purpose’ and it becomes the base word <foreign>piən</foreign> with
                        suffix <foreign>-an</foreign> and the enclitic -<foreign>ana</foreign>; cf.
                            <foreign>pikavihən</foreign> ‘things to be sung’,
                            <foreign>pibudiən</foreign> ‘things to be thought’.</note> of this holy
                    book? Because I know that I will produce the composition, being the emergence of
                    The Teacher’s Precepts (<foreign>Siksa Guru</foreign>), from the holy
                    precepts.”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.02">Here, as follows, is the pure circle of three
                    bodily domains. This is what should be thrown out; the servant of the
                        <foreign>dharma</foreign> should not follow that (i.e.
                        <foreign>tri-mala</foreign>)<note>The allusion to the
                            <foreign>tri-mala</foreign> can only be understood in the light of the
                        source of this text, the <foreign>Śikṣā Guru</foreign> §8.3. Cf. also SMG
                        4.3 below.</note> — [for it is] the source of sadness, the origin of the
                    sins leading to misery, the beginning of the <foreign>kali</foreign>’s era, the
                    cause of the sins leading to hell — the three stains so it is called.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.03">[As far as the] categorizations [are concerned],
                    their comparisons are as follows: what is called the three defects is like
                    bronze and wax, copper and tin. What is comparable to copper and tin? The
                    meaning is the three evils: improper speeches, improper acts, improper minds.
                    Evil speeches, evil acts, and evil minds are performed.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.04">These are the manifestations of the evil acts:
                    flicking with the knuckle of finger, tapping, stabbing, punching, striking,
                    knocking, hitting, slapping, spanking, all kinds of hand’s actions, those are
                    called the evil acts.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.05">The evil speeches are: furious and angry without
                    reason, talking rudely, cursing, blaming, condemning, uttering black magic,
                    backbiting the teacher, all kinds of improper speeches, those are called the
                    evil speeches.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.06">The evil minds are: plotting, pretending,
                    slandering, using black magic, offending, bewitching, poisoning, being envious
                    of what is right, including plundering, stealing, trespassing, infiltrating, way
                    laying, anything that is improper is performed [and] intended, those are the
                    evil minds. That is called the three defects.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.07">As follows are three ultimate defects
                        (<foreign>tri-mala visesa</foreign>), possessed by the king, the elders, the
                    hermits, the ritual expert, the sailor. This is the explanation: there is
                    someone seen in sorrow, [then he] is sold, enslaved, robbed, and murdered. Those
                    are called the five sinful [men], all such things are considered the three
                    ultimate defects, according to the scholar, 3.</p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.01">Again, as follows is what should be carefully
                    noticed by the servant of the Truth. There are what are called the ten
                    defilements. What is the evidence? Here is the verse, the statement is as
                    follows:</p>

                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.02">“This [condition of] defilement and
                    sin having disappeared, and those who are afflicted having disappeared, they do
                    great meritorious conduct.”</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.03">The meaning is: you should be able to purify the
                    ten defilements. If comes to you, namely: vice (<foreign>doṣa</foreign>),
                    ignorance (<foreign>moha</foreign>), cupidity (<foreign>lobha</foreign>),
                    madness (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>), jealousy (<foreign>mātsarya</foreign>),
                    arrogance (<foreign>abhimāna</foreign>), stupidity (<foreign>mūrkha</foreign>),
                    cheat (<foreign>kuhaka</foreign>), idle talk
                        (<foreign>sambhinnapralāpa</foreign>), calumny (<foreign>peśuna</foreign>). </p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.04">The meaning is: the vice
                    (<foreign>doṣa</foreign>) is deeming oneself superior in happiness, deeming
                    oneself superior in knowledge, deeming oneself strong, that is called the vice.
                    Ignorance (<foreign>moha</foreign>) means not having affection toward fellow
                    human beings. Cupidity (<foreign>lobha</foreign>) means addicted to eating,
                    addicted to drinking, and continuously sleeping, [and] does not want to think of
                    goodness, that is called cupidity. Having a lot of things to think of, something
                    to carry out, something to act on, that is called cupidity. Madness
                        (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>) is being difficult by his wealth, being difficult
                    by his expertise, being difficult by his qualities, being difficult by his
                    knowledge, that is called madness (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>). Jealousy
                        (<foreign>matsārya</foreign>) is being jealous to see the welfare [of
                    others], jealous watching someone kind, jealous watching someone happy, that is
                    called jealousy. Arrogance (<foreign>abhimāna</foreign>) means not willing to
                    give lessons and advice, that is called arrogance. Stupidity
                        (<foreign>mūrkha</foreign>) means not willing to obey mother, father, [and]
                    teachers, that is called stupidity. Cheat (<foreign>kuhaka</foreign>) means to
                    claim the work of others. Idle talk (<foreign>sambhinnapralāpa</foreign>) means
                    constantly talking about the pleasure of those who have the pleasure, the wealth
                    of those who have wealth, that is called idle talk. Calumny
                        (<foreign>peśuna</foreign>) means easily to be jealous, easily to be
                    deceitful, to provoke [others]. Those are called ten defilements.</p>


            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.01">Furthermore, the following are called the ten
                    defects (<foreign>dasa-mala</foreign>). As follows is the verse: </p>

                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.02"><foreign>vigatah maladuhkhinaḥ,
                        kurvanti kuśalam mahat</foreign>| <foreign>gavayakən sutəm citəm, budi hiyəm
                        maguh narakəm</foreign> | </p>


                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.03">The meaning is: would you have the same
                    probability of misfortune (<foreign>marakarma</foreign>), if [it] comes to you?
                    Misfortune means sleep (<foreign>supta</foreign>), fear
                        (<foreign>bhaya</foreign>), laziness (<foreign>tandrī</foreign>),
                    irresolution (<foreign>kleda</foreign>), shame (<foreign>lajjā</foreign>), lust
                    for women (<foreign>rāgastrī</foreign>), adultery (<foreign>paradāra</foreign>),
                    eating of food (<foreign>bhakṣabhojana</foreign>), dishonest consideration
                        (<foreign>kuṭilaviveka</foreign>).</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.04">The meaning is: sleep (<foreign>supta</foreign>)
                    means continuously sleeping, forgetting to ask what is the good and the best for
                    oneself, forgetting to occupy oneself with the good mind, and speaking the
                    goodness to many people, those are called sleep. Fear (<foreign>bhaya</foreign>)
                    means being afraid to ask for oneself, being afraid to ask because he feels
                    senior, [and] being afraid to speak goodness, those are called fear. Laziness
                        (<foreign>tandrī</foreign>) means being lazy to ask because he feels
                    ignorant, being lazy to act with a joyful mind, and to speak of goodness to many
                    people, those are called laziness. Irresolution (<foreign>kleda</foreign>) means
                    being hesitant to act with good mind to the people, being hesitant to ask about
                    oneself, those are called irresolution. Shame (<foreign>lajjā</foreign>) means
                    he finds it difficult to to ask because he feels stupid, he finds it difficult
                    to render service because he feels senior, he finds it difficult to render
                    service because he feels rich. Lust of women (<foreign>rāgastrī</foreign>) means
                    being keen on desiring to have an intercourse and wish to be rich, [those] are
                    called lust of women. Adultery (<foreign>paradāra</foreign>) means desiring a
                    widowed girl, the forbidden woman of other people, those are called adultery.
                    Eating the food (<foreign>bhakṣabhojāna</foreign>) means he does not do the
                    goodness; that is bhakṣabhojāna, namely, always eating, always drinking,
                        †<foreign>dəṅ hjǝ</foreign>†, for his desire being fulfilled by the six
                    tastes (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>), those are called eating the food. Dishonest
                    consideration (<foreign>kuṭilaviveka</foreign>) means to postpone to act with
                    joyful mind and to speak the goodness to the people. Those are called the ten
                    stains, according to the learned master.</p>

            </div>


            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.01">Again, the following are called the ten hells
                        (<foreign>dasa-naraka</foreign>). This is its manifestations: ears, eyes,
                    nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hand, anus, genital, feet.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.02">The meaning is: the ears should not hear wrongly,
                    [and] quickly react when hearing [something]. The consequences are: having
                    imperfect hearing, purulent ear (<foreign>coṅe</foreign>), deafness,
                        <foreign>cadaṅ</foreign>, those would be the miseries of the ears.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.03">The eyes should not look wantonly, for instance
                    the widow of someone else, the forbidden woman of someone else, if they are not
                    ours. The consequences are: being blind in one eye (<foreign>pecak</foreign>),
                    poor eyesight (<foreign>bolor</foreign>), putikǝn, white spot in the eye
                        (<foreign>ceaṅ</foreign>), color-blindness (<foreign>buta
                    loroṅǝn</foreign>), night-blindness (<foreign>mata kotokǝn</foreign>),
                        <foreign>bilas susuhǝn</foreign>, those would be the miseries of the
                    eyes.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.04">The nose reacts quickly to all kinds of smell. If
                    [it] smells stink, mouldy smell, rancid, burning smell, those provoke him to
                    sneeze, to blow the nose (?, <foreign>ṅahubus</foreign>). The consequence is
                        <foreign>mekmek</foreign>, that would be the misery of the nose.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.05">The tongue reacts quickly to all kinds of tastes.
                    When [it tastes the flavor of] stale, cold, foul-smelling, acidic, spicy, salty,
                    it is used to taste everything (? <foreign>usuh-asahan</foreign>). The
                    consequences are: mute, tongue defect (?, <foreign>petal</foreign>), lisp, all
                    of those would be the miseries of the tongue.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.06">The mouth is used to gripe, only to be used to
                    talk and whine, and also to be used for cursing and scolding, inviting others to
                    do deceitful [acts]. The consequences are: harelips, wry lips, open mouth
                    disease (?, <foreign>dǝda</foreign>), those would be the miseries of the
                    mouth.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.07">The skin is used to touch wantonly. If it is
                    affected by hot, cold, itchy, tingling, [then] it is tossed and turned. The
                    consequences are: malignant boil (<foreign>tibar</foreign>), boil
                        (<foreign>bisul</foreign>), foot-sole skin disorder
                        (<foreign>boloṅǝn</foreign>), skin rash (<foreign>radaṅ</foreign>), smallpox
                        (<foreign>kuris</foreign>), reddish skin (<foreign>beaṅ</foreign>),
                    including cyste (<foreign>balas</foreign>) [and] itchy skin eruption
                        (<foreign>galigata</foreign>), those would be the miseries of the skin.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.08">The hand is used to grab wantonly, especially the
                    property of others, the plants of others. [It is] also used to clench the fist,
                    to stab, to knock, to clasp, to slap, to pull hair, to pinch, to lash (?,
                        <foreign>ṅagǝtil</foreign>). The consequences are bent fingers, arms that
                    are stiff, cut off, [and] difficult to move. Those would be the miseries of the
                    hand.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.09">The anus is used to fart wantonly, to defecate
                    wherever one wants, on the side yard of somebody else’s house, let alone let off
                    a fart against someone. The consequences are constipation (?,
                        <foreign>kabǝratan</foreign>), diarrhea (<foreign>tuju pañcar</foreign>),
                    bleeding anus (<foreign>kaliṅsir</foreign>), <foreign>uirǝn</foreign> (?). Those
                    would be the miseries of the anus.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.10">The genitals are used to pee wherever one wants.
                    They are also used to seek boys and girls, transgress with younger siblings,
                    elder siblings, children of younger siblings (<foreign>suan</foreign>), children
                    of elder siblings (<foreign>kaponakan</foreign>). The consequences are hernia
                        (<foreign>burut</foreign>), deformed [genitals] (<foreign>petot</foreign>),
                        <foreign>lañjo</foreign> (?), impaired sexual desire (<foreign>halaṅ
                        visaya</foreign>), impotence (<foreign>pǝluh</foreign>). Those would be the
                    miseries of the genitals.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.11">The feet are used to step wantonly, to walk
                    carelessly, for instance when you walk to the north, south, west, east; if the
                    feet happen to stumble, bump, or if they are used to kick. The consequences are
                    weak feet (?, <foreign>lisuh</foreign>), broken [feet], dog-like feet (?,
                        <foreign>añjiṅǝn</foreign>), feet with outgrowth (?,
                        <foreign>caniran</foreign>). Those would be the miseries of the feet.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.12">Thus are what are called the ten hells. The
                    servants of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention, those [actions]
                    should not be followed. </p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08">

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.01">As follows are the five objects of attention. How
                    so? The verse is as follows:</p>

                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.02">“Non-anger, obedience to the
                    teacher, purity, moderation in food, and non-inattentiveness are the five well
                    known as particular commandments.”</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.03">The meaning is: <foreign>akrodho</foreign> means
                    it does not happen to the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, that he
                    shows his anger in front of the elder (teacher), let alone in front of all
                    people. <foreign>Āhāralāghavam</foreign> means being unhurried in making
                    preparations for [the meal]; it is improper to eat and to drink in front of the
                    scholar. <foreign>Apramādas ca pañca vaite</foreign> means when there is
                    something needed by others, his attitude follows the one who is short-tempered
                    and surly: one doesn’t want to think about oneself, and does not want to seek
                    what will bring goodness [for oneself only]. Those are called the five objects
                    of attention. </p>

            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09">


                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.01">As follow are called the four means, as follows
                    is the meaning:</p>
                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.02">“Writing, laughing, singing,
                    yawning, and pure [from] the secret of fruit (?), shall not do in the front of
                    the teacher”</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.03">The meaning is: <foreign>ālekhyam</foreign> means
                    it is improper if we scratch the ground, to write the board [and] the couch in
                    front of the teacher. <foreign>Hasitam</foreign> means it is improper to laugh
                    when starting [activity] in front of the teacher, and also to play around in
                    front of the scholar [and] in front of all people. <foreign>Gītam</foreign>
                    means not singing <foreign>kiduṅ</foreign>, <foreign>kavih</foreign>, to sing
                    loudly, let alone to claim oneself skilled, expert, [and] wise in front of
                    people. <foreign>Jr̥mbhanam</foreign> means it is improper to declare oneself
                    thirsty and hungry, even though one is excessively full in front of the scholar,
                    let alone of all people. <foreign>Kaṇṭhāravāñ</foreign> means, it is improper if
                    we call [someone] out loud, and also to stretch oneself in front of the people.
                        <foreign>Śuddham</foreign> means it is improper if the mind and speech are
                    disturbing and false. <foreign>Phalarahasyam</foreign> means it is improper to
                    mention the genitals of others. <foreign>Na karotu gurumukhe</foreign> means, it
                    is improper if our mind and speech are careless (?,
                    <foreign>rumagodeh</foreign>) in front of the scholar. These are called the four
                    means. The servants of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention,
                    [those actions] should not be followed.</p>
            </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.01">The following are called the five explanations.
                    As follows is the verse: </p>
                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.02"><foreign>selajanəm suravile,
                        panatargasudya ceva, prayagamanəm, cevamasva cevamibuh, karmavidu, cevayude,
                        danakaləm ma suprəgrahaste</foreign>.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.03">The meaning is: <foreign>selajanəm</foreign>
                    means to be indifferent and denying when talking and deliberating in front of
                    the elder [teacher]. <foreign>Suravile</foreign> means to be indifferent:
                    especially when talking and deliberating, one does not apply good manners
                    towards the scholar. Also, it is improper to use powders that are smelled by a
                    lot of people, or [when one] welcomes (<foreign>asvagatah kunaṅ</foreign>)
                    [them]. <foreign>Panatarga</foreign> means it is improper to brush teeth and to
                    show teeth in front of people. <foreign>Sudyacava</foreign> means it is improper
                    to imitate the play of actors (<foreign>hǝmpul</foreign>) and buffoons
                        (<foreign>mirus</foreign>). <foreign>Prayāsamāgama</foreign> means, it is
                    improper if we stare at each other with other people, let alone to be face to
                    face, to be face to face with the elders staring at each other, also to claim
                    [to have been] eating and drinking in front of people. <foreign>Ceva
                        masvateh</foreign> means having wrong minds and intentions towards fellow
                    humans. <foreign>Ceva mibuh</foreign> means having bad appearance, bad
                    behaviors, [and] not following advice. <foreign>Karmavidu</foreign> means having
                    a wrinkled face, being surly, wry-faced, sullen, [or] frowning [when]
                    interacting with people. <foreign>Ceva yude</foreign> means having a bad
                    appearance, bad behaviors, bad results, those are called the lowest among
                    people. <foreign>Ceva yude</foreign> means beset with troubles by making a joke,
                    being fond of playing with pariambul words toward others.
                        <foreign>Danakalǝm</foreign> means not willingly helping, having compassion,
                    and love to fellow human beings. The mind is full of hate.
                        <foreign>Suprigrǝhasta</foreign> means having too much desire, talking about
                    our intention, bring it to the discussion wishing to realize it quickly,
                    although it will not be achieved. Those are called the five explanations
                        (<foreign>pañca-byakta</foreign>), those [actions] should not be followed,
                    5.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.01">As follows are called the four devotions
                        (<foreign>catur-paṅabakti</foreign>). The verses are as follows:</p>
                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.02">“[Through which] bad luck is left
                    behind, having bowed down to the Lord of the Universe, I will recite the foot
                    sole of the teacher.”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.03">The meaning is: <foreign>gurutalam</foreign>
                    means it is improper to speak and converse in haste in front of the scholar.
                        <foreign>Pravakṣyāmi</foreign> means it is improper to talk about
                    righteousness in front of the scholar, also in front of people, especially [in
                    front] of mother, father, and teachers. <foreign>Mahāyānam</foreign> means that
                    one forgets to think about oneself. <foreign>Hi tiṣṭhati</foreign> means it is
                    improper if we look at the elders with arrogance. <foreign>Durbhagahīne
                        sarveśaṁ</foreign> means that one forgets what is in front of him, does not
                    think of things which bring goodness. <foreign>Griyapa praṇamyāsīt</foreign>
                    means one wish to quickly get rich and have everything, i.e. to have servants,
                    subordinates, workers, and livestock, and yet this [wish] is not fulfilled.
                    Those are called the four devotions, as told by the scholar.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.01">As follows are called the five objects of
                    attention (<foreign>pañca-prayatna</foreign>). The verse is as follows:</p>
                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.02"><foreign>hīnavākyam siṅharupañ ca
                        grahaste</foreign> | <foreign>gurusaṅghāsanam prətanəm</foreign>,
                        <foreign>grəhaste nāmani mate</foreign>.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.03">The meaning is: <foreign>hīnavākyam</foreign>
                    means it is improper to speak of goodness, to teach in front of the elder
                    [teacher]. <foreign>Siṅharupañ ca grahaste</foreign> means it is improper that
                    we are seen angry by the elders and [showing] dislike. <foreign>Guru saṅgasanǝm
                        prītam</foreign> means it is improper if we [shot that we] are happy,
                    frolicking, joyful and pleased when we are on the street, [or] when we go to the
                    forest to take trees and leaves, [and] we sit there with legs wide, then we are
                    seen by the scholar. Also, it is unpleasant for us [to be] ahead in walking, and
                    to be in the shadow of the elders. <foreign>Prǝtanǝm</foreign> means it is
                    improper to smell the food of the teacher, let alone to use the utensils of the
                    scholar, to take marked properties (<foreign>savenan</foreign>), and to take
                    stored [properties]. <foreign>Grǝhaste namaniṅ mate</foreign> means it is
                    improper to mention the name of mother, father, as well as the teacher, and
                    especially the elders, not to mention the name of king, village elders, hermits,
                    ritual experts (<foreign>disi</foreign>), and sailors
                        (<foreign>tarahan</foreign>). Those are called the five objects of attention
                        (<foreign>pañca-prayatna</foreign>), according the scholar. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_13">
                
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_13.01">The following are called three elements
                        (<foreign>tri-buta</foreign>). These are the explanations: bad meets its
                    bad, crooked meets its crooked, misery meets its misery. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_13.02">The meaning is: <foreign>hala</foreign> means
                    bad; that the outcome is bad because what has been practiced is bad.
                        <foreign>Vilut</foreign> means crooked: that the outcome is crooked because
                    what has been practiced is crooked. <foreign>Duka</foreign> means terrified:
                    that the outcome is terrifying because what has been practiced is terrifying.
                    Those are called the three elements. The servants of the
                        <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention, those [actions] should not
                    be followed.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_14">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_14.01">As follows are called the four pacifiers
                        (<foreign>catur-pasanta</foreign>). The following are its explanations: the
                    formula of <foreign>jalakuna</foreign>, the formula of
                        <foreign>jalapaksa</foreign>, the formula of <foreign>sambarana</foreign>,
                    the formula of <foreign>taraṅgabahu</foreign>.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_14.02">The formula of <foreign>jalakuna</foreign> is the
                    sun. Things which cause miseries to the body are: weak vision, monocular
                    blindness, bilas, eye disease, color blindness, night blindness, dazzlement. The
                    formula of <foreign>jalapaksa</foreign> is the water. Things which cause
                    miseries to the body are shivering and chills. The formula of
                        <foreign>sambarana</foreign> is the wind. Things which cause miseries to the
                    body are reddish skin, skin eruptions, skin fungal disease (?,
                        <foreign>pipisisan</foreign>), every kind of skin disease. The formula of
                        <foreign>taraṅgabahu</foreign> is the mountain. Things which cause miseries
                    to the body are: headache, stomach ache, abdominal distention
                        (<foreign>mǝdu</foreign>), abscess of the liver
                    (<foreign>kavayaan</foreign>), every kind of disease in the stomach. Those are
                    called the four pacifiers, that should be made of attention by the servant of
                    the dharma, [and] should not be kept secret. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.01">As follows are called the five misfortunes. These
                    are the explanations: sorrow from the elements, sorrow from gods, sorrow from
                    three worlds.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.02">The sorrows from the elements are: died from
                    being bitten by the snake, being struck by lightning, bitten by the crocodile,
                    crushed by branches, devoured by the tiger, death in battle, intercepted,
                    attacked by many [enemies], died of falling [from above], [by] all kinds of
                    weapons in the battle. That is called the sorrow from the elements.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.03">The sorrows from the gods are: diarrhea
                        (<foreign>tajam bǝtǝṅ</foreign>), cold shivers, headache, sore eyes,
                        <foreign>jaroṅ</foreign>-like disease, <foreign>sumbilaṅ</foreign>-like
                    disease, madness, abdominal distention, fever. Those are called the sorrow from
                    the gods. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.04">The sorrows from the body are: monocular
                    blindness, cleft lip, crippled, blind, deaf, rash, cut (off ears?,
                        <foreign>rumpuṅ</foreign>), cut off [limbs]. Those are called the sorrow of
                    the body. As for what is called the sorrow of the three worlds are all kinds [of
                    persons] who are affected by misfortune in the world. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.05">These are the examples of those who are affected
                    by the miseries: kings, elders, hermits, ritualists, and sailors, for in the
                        <foreign>kali</foreign>’s era, they are the roots of the sins that lead to
                    suffering (i.e., hell), [they] become: the demon Kāla, the dogs called Jamproṅ
                    and Karavǝlaṅ; [they] become a pair of cauldrons, strips of iron lances and
                    spikes, in the village of destination, slanting plank bridge,
                        <foreign>vajra</foreign>’s coconut (i.e, sugar palm?), the dirty mud,
                    standing aslant branches, clutching rocks, the <foreign>rayang-rayang</foreign>
                    called Prǝca Kala and Prǝca Kali, — [also] the dissention and seduction (?,
                        <foreign>beda bañcana</foreign>), a creation expert, an iron expert, a
                    banner expert, an image expert, a child (play?) expert.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.06">The meaning is precisely as follows: the
                    balancing (?, <foreign>samya</foreign>) expert is the bracelet smith, the
                    creation (?, <foreign>sipta</foreign>) expert is the goldsmith, the iron expert
                    is the blacksmith, the banner expert is the cloth painter (?
                        <foreign>pamadǝk</foreign>), the plant expert is the cultivator
                        (<foreign>pahuma</foreign>), the creation expert is the carpenter, the
                    composition expert is the actor (<foreign>hǝmpul</foreign>), the childsplay (?
                        <foreign>kumara</foreign>) expert is the performer, the kala is the king’s
                    servant, [the dogs] called Jampoṅ and Karavǝlaṅ are the storm in the third month
                        (<foreign>barat katiga</foreign>); the female animals (or prostitutes ?
                        <foreign>rayang-rayang</foreign>) are those without a name, the dissention
                    and seduction [expert] is the merchant, the wide moor is the lǝbuh,
                        <foreign>salaksi loñana</foreign> is the hunter, the end of the moon is the
                        <foreign>prǝjala</foreign>, a sinful man is the gambler, a stained man is
                    the servant (<foreign>dasa</foreign>); the one who accepts in marriage is the
                        <foreign>calagara</foreign>, the one who extracts is the collector
                        (<foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>), the standing branch is the provider (?,
                        <foreign>parada</foreign>), the destination village is the helper (?,
                        <foreign>kasasa</foreign>), the slanting plank bridge is the
                        <foreign>pamǝǝṅ</foreign>, the sugar palm is the tapper
                        (<foreign>pañadap</foreign>), the dirty mud is the wet rice field farmer,
                    the strips of thorns are the foresters (<foreign>paṅalas</foreign>), the
                    clutching rocks are the matchmakers (<foreign>paṅavin</foreign>), the cauldron
                    is the <foreign>pamǝñǝp</foreign>, the rice (? <foreign>naseya</foreign>) is the
                    rice cooker, the wood-log is the pounder (<foreign>panutu</foreign>); the fire
                    is the kitchen guardian (<foreign>tuṅgu dapur</foreign>), the one who cooks is
                    the <foreign>harǝp catra</foreign>; the water is the one who usually takes water
                    for bathing; the cinder is the sweeper (<foreign>pañapu</foreign>); the
                    livestock is the chicken farmer, the boar farmer, the duck farmer; the one who
                    gives [food] is the herdsman; the one who guards the lake, the one who guards
                    the garden, anyone who guards domestic animals — [all of them] are being
                    enslaved by the god, [they are] obstructed, used as hands and feet [of the god],
                    do not have any power on their lives, on their destinies. That is called the
                    misfortune from the three worlds.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.07">These are called the sorrow from the three worlds
                        (<foreign>tri-bvana-loka</foreign>): the city is on fire, the harvest is
                    failed, destroyed by disease, a long dry-season in an anomalous period, all
                    kinds of fruit [trees] do not bear fruit, all animals are scattered around
                    [dead]. That is called the sorrow of the three worlds. <foreign>ma, ṅya buku, u,
                        sa, a</foreign>. Those are called the five misfortunes as said by the
                    scholar, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_16">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_16.01">Again, as follows is what should be remembered by
                    the servant of the dharma. There are what are called the five animals
                        (<foreign>pañca-triyak</foreign>). These are the explanations: domestic
                    animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>), birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>), snakes
                        (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>), fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>), [and] creeping
                    animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>).</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_16.02">Domestic animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>) are
                    all kinds of animals in the settlements; birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>) are
                    all kinds of animals on the side [of the settlement]; snakes
                        (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>) are all kinds of animals whose chest touch the
                    ground; fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the water;
                    creeping animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>) are all kinds of animals having
                    a shell, who crawl without being discovered. Their length of time from hell is
                    1100 years. Those are called the five animals.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_17">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_17.01">The following should also be remembered. There
                    are what are called the four roots. These are the explanations:
                        <foreign>mantaja</foreign>, <foreign>urija</foreign>,
                        <foreign>payuja</foreign>, <foreign>bagaja</foreign>.
                        <foreign>Mantaja</foreign> means all kinds [of things] born from the eye;
                        <foreign>urija</foreign> means all kinds [of things] born from the mouth;
                        <foreign>payuja</foreign> means all kinds [of things] born from the anus;
                        <foreign>bagaja</foreign> means all kinds [of things] born from sexual
                    organs. The length of time [before one who has sinned with those organs comes
                    back] from hell is 100 years. Those are called the four roots, as declared by
                    the scholar.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_18">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_18.01">As follows are called the four strengths
                        (<foreign>catur-virya</foreign>). The meaning is: what is called joy is used
                    to be hot tempered. The wealth is used to be rich. The hot temper is used to be
                    overcome […]. The strength is used to give [excessively] to those who are far,
                    to those who are near, to the family and relatives. Those are called the four
                    strengths. Those should be paid attention to, [they] should not be followed by
                    the servant of <foreign>dharma</foreign>. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_19">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_19.01">The following are called the release
                        (<foreign>kalǝpasǝn</foreign>). There are the holy immaculate four
                    practices. This is the explanation: the people who are farmers, who are full
                        (<foreign>purna</foreign>), who are very self-controlled
                        (<foreign>sudanta</foreign>), who turned out well
                        (<foreign>lastare</foreign>).</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_19.02">The farmer (<foreign>tani</foreign>) means:
                    [they] are made to harvest rice, tap, put the yoke, make quick ripening (?
                        <foreign>ñavara</foreign>), take care of the livestock, plant the crops.
                    That is called the farmer. The one who is full (<foreign>purna</foreign>) means
                    [the one who] does not have defects and diseases, [and who] does not act like
                    ordinary people. That is called <foreign>purna</foreign>.
                        <foreign>Sudanta</foreign> means [the one] who can not be redeemed [as a
                    slave], [or] be strongly obstructed by debt. <foreign>Lastare</foreign> are
                    people of the village who do not have illness, who do not have weakness. That is
                    called <foreign>lastare</foreign>. Those are called the four ordinances
                        (<foreign>catur-kalpa</foreign>), as declared by the scholar. All that
                    should be kept aside by the servant of <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.01">This is what should be prioritized, [namely] what
                    are called the three bodies (<foreign>trikaya</foreign>), which are claimed as
                    the source of beauty, the origin of splendor. There is what is called the pure
                    circle of three bodily domains, as declared by the great scholar.
                        <foreign>Tri</foreign> means three, <foreign>kaya</foreign> means what makes
                    firm, <foreign>mandala</foreign> means the body, and what is called
                        <foreign>suda</foreign> is already well known.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.02">Obey to the three bodily acts, as declared by the
                    teacher, the three bodily acts of the world and of the people. What would those
                    that are called the three bodily acts according to the teacher be? These are
                    their metaphors: “Like the priceless gem and the desired gem, and also the real
                    essence of gold.”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.03">As follows is the threefold good. These are their
                    kinds: pacifying thought, pacifying speech, pacifying intelect. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.04">That which is called good actions, the
                    explanations of good actions is: showing respect, being faithful, honoring,
                    being respectful, being afraid and fearful (i.e. being polite), agile, modest,
                    careful, thorough, diligent, persevering, charitable. Those are called good
                    actions. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.05">The good speeches are [the words which are]
                    friendly, soft, caring and loving, full of sympathy and compassion, persuasive,
                    cooling the heart, praising, polite, propitiating; all kinds of perfect
                    speeches. Those are called good speeches.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.06">The good mind means: [like] “a clean side yard, a
                    bright garden, a broad yard, a wide cultivated land”; it is put in action for
                    giving food, money, clothes, girls [in marriage], and so on. Those are the four
                    meritorious acts. Because of that [one gets] a stable intellect, a clear mind,
                    broad thinking, a good intellect which is like a polished jewel, like the water
                    on the <foreign>sulang</foreign> leaves, as a result of his good mind. That is
                    called the pure circle of three bodily domains, as declared by the scholar. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.01">These are called the four goodness. The verse is
                    as follows: “The gold, silver, luminous bezoar (<foreign>komala</foreign>),
                    diamond”. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.02">The meaning is: the gold is a truthful, sincere,
                    and correct word, the manifestation of the five sacred syllables. The silver
                    means the perfect, meritorious, and good mind. The luminous bezoar means that
                    his emotions are bright and shining, [and] his thoughts are clear and broad. The
                    diamond means to have a cheerful, smiley, agile, and joyful mind.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.03">This is the other meaning: what is called the
                    gold is the pure gold, what is called the silver is the most desirable jewel,
                    what is called luminous bezoar is the priceless jewel, what is called the
                    diamond is the glowing gold. Those are called the four types of goodness. </p>
            </div>
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_22">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_22.01">As for this one, it is the essence of goodness,
                    called the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>).
                        <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten, <foreign>sila</foreign> means quality.
                    These are the explanations: ear, eye, nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hand, sexual
                    organs, anus, foot. Those are called the ten holy virtues.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_23">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_23.01">These are called the ten paths
                        (<foreign>dasa-marga</foreign>). <foreign>Śrotra</foreign> means ears. What
                    is the sphere of ears? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you
                    should hear. <foreign>Cakṣuh</foreign> means eyes. What is the sphere of eyes?
                    What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should see.
                        <foreign>Ghrāṇa</foreign> means the nose. What is bad should be avoided;
                    goodness is what you should smell. <foreign>Jihvā</foreign> means the tongue.
                    What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should taste.
                        <foreign>Vāk</foreign> means the mouth. What is bad should be avoided;
                    goodness is what you should speak about. <foreign>Tvak</foreign> means the skin.
                    What is the sphere of the skin? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what
                    you should touch. <foreign>Pāṇi</foreign> means hands. What is the sphere of
                    hands? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should grasp.
                        <foreign>Pāyu</foreign> means anus. What is bad should be avoided; goodness
                    is what you should release. <foreign>Pastha</foreign> means penis. What is the
                    sphere of the penis? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should
                    discharge. <foreign>Pāda</foreign> means feet. What is the sphere of the feet?
                    What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should step on. Those are
                    called the ten paths.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24">
                
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.01">These are called the ten sense faculties. The
                    sense of hearing resides in the ears. It exists in you; it is the instrument of
                    the holy soul. [It is] the exit place of the mind. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.02">The sense of sight resides in the eyes. It exists
                    in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. It is the exit place of the mind.
                    Its function is to perceive form and color. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.03">The sense of smell resides in the nose. It exists
                    in you; [it is] the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to smell. [It
                    is] the exit place of the mind. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.04">The sense of taste resides in the tongue. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to taste
                    the six flavors. [It is] the exit place of the mind. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.05">The sense of speech resides in the mouth. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to speak.
                    [It is] the exit place of the mind. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.06">The sense of touch resides in the skin. It exists
                    in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to touch. [It is]
                    the exit place of the mind.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.07">The faculty of holding resides in the hands. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to seize.
                    [It is] the exit place of the mind.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.08">The faculty of relief resides in the anus. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to fart.
                    [It is] the exit place of the mind.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.09">The sexual faculty resides in the penis. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to have
                    sexual intercourse and to urinate. [It is] the exit place of the mind.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.10">The faculty of walking resides in the feet. It
                    exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to walk.
                    [It is] the exit place of the mind. Those are called the ten virtues.</p>

                <!--pasṭā Idriya haneṁ pəlat· sanika ri pananta, ya ta karana saṁ hyi Atma, Anada Aṅəyə pa 
<lb n="17r4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>saṁ hyi Atma, pamaṅətut lavan· maṁṅisiṁ pakən:anya, paməton·nikaṁ hidəp·, pada Idriya haneṁ<gap reason="lost" unit="character" quantity="2"/>-->

                <!--CB.174.I.26.17b.jpg-->
                <!--<pb n="17v" xml:id="pb024"/>
<lb n="17v1"/>ta sinaṁguḥ dasa Idriya, ṅa, //Ø Ini dasa paṁṅaku, ṅa, Inakunyi Ata ya paṁruṅunyi panvan·tvanya paṅabuṁnya pa<gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/>
<lb n="17v2" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>ya Ø hana saṅ maṅa<space type="binding-hole"/>buṁ, hana saṁ maṅR̥ṅə, hana saṁ hyi manikumaṁbaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṅ manon·tvan· ha
<lb n="17v3" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>mabuṁ, hana visesa<space type="binding-hole"/>ku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ mañabda hana saṅ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ ṅa
<lb n="17v4" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>məl· hana saṁ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ maṁrasa, hana saṁ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prə 
    -->
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_25">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_25.01">This is called the ten personalisations. What is
                    claimed by them is the hearing, the sight, the smelling, the speaking, the
                    releasing, the urinating, the walking. There is the one who claims for himself,
                    there is the one who hears, there is the holy floating jewel. It is called the
                    ten personalisations. </p>
            </div>
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_26">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_26.01">These are called the ten highest principles.
                    These are the explanations: there are ears, there is hearing, there is the
                    hearer, there is the highest principle. There are eyes, there is viewing, there
                    is the viewer, there is the highest principle. There is nose, there is smelling,
                    there is the smeller, there is the highest principle. There is tongue, there is
                    taste, there is the taster, there is the highest principle. There is the mouth,
                    there is the speech, there is the speaker, there is the highest principle. There
                    is the skin, there is the touch, there is the toucher, there is the highest
                    principle. There is the hand, there is the grasping, there is the grasper, there
                    is the highest principle. There is the anus, there is the releasing, there is
                    the releaser, there is the highest principle. There are the sexual organs, there
                    is the urinating, there is the one who urinates, there is the highest principle.
                    There are the feet, there is the walking, there is the walker, there is the
                    highest principle. Those are called the ten highest principles.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_27">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_27.01">These are called the ten pacifiers. This is their
                    explanation: donation (<foreign>dāna</foreign>), morality
                        (<foreign>śīla</foreign>), forbearance (<foreign>kṣānti</foreign>), strength
                        (<foreign>vīrya</foreign>), meditation (<foreign>dhyāna</foreign>), wisdom
                        (<foreign>prajñā</foreign>), compassion (<foreign>karuṇā</foreign>),
                    sympathy (<foreign>mudita</foreign>), friendship (<foreign>metrī</foreign>),
                    endurance (<foreign>upekṣā</foreign>). </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_27.02">The meaning is: donation
                    (<foreign>dāna</foreign>) means to give enjoyment to others. Morality
                        (<foreign>śīla</foreign>) means to know etiquette (<foreign>tvah</foreign>).
                    Strength (<foreign>vīrya</foreign>) means to strive to be continuously truthful,
                    to strive to do goodness. Meditation (<foreign>dhyāna</foreign>) means to
                    consider his own mind. Wisdom (<foreign>prajñā</foreign>) means to be quick to
                    get rid of the bad things of oneself. Compassion (<foreign>karuṇā</foreign>)
                    means his heart would be weak while thinking for himself and does not want to
                    make others sad. Sympathy (<foreign>mudita</foreign>) means not to forget the
                    others’ skill. Friendship (<foreign>metrī</foreign>) means to know the good
                    deed, to make the others feel at ease. Endurance (<foreign>upekṣā</foreign>)
                    means not being bothered by the good and the bad. Those are called the ten
                    pacifiers (<foreign>dasa-pasanta</foreign>).</p>
            </div>
            
        
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.01">This is what should be seriously done, what is
                    called the ten grounds. These are the verses:</p>
                <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.02"><foreign>agəm rahayəm
                        gunyam</foreign> | <foreign>tvah citane haləm</foreign> | <foreign>kurvanti
                        kuśalam mahat</foreign></p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.03">The excellent meritorious conduct should be
                    carried out. The excellent meritorious conduct means: love
                        (<foreign>asih</foreign>), devotion (<foreign>bhakti</foreign>), persevering
                    effort (<foreign>prayatna</foreign>), respectability
                    (<foreign>gorava</foreign>), honesty (<foreign>duga-duga</foreign>), calmness
                        (<foreign>śānta</foreign>), compassion (<foreign>karuṇa</foreign>), sympathy
                        (<foreign>anumoda</foreign>), consideration (<foreign>anumāna</foreign>),
                    respectful mutual dependence (<foreign>ālambana atəaṅ</foreign>). Those are
                    called ten grounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_29">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_29.01">These are called the ten superiorities
                        (<foreign>dasa-visesa</foreign>). As follows is the meaning: the Holy
                    hearing is not heard, because He is the one who hears, the Holy one who cannot
                    be used as hearing. The Holy sight is not seen, because He is the one who sees,
                    the Holy one who cannot be used as sight. The Holy smelling is not smelled,
                    because He is the one who smells, the Holy one who cannot be used as smelling.
                    The Holy taste is not tasted, because He is the one who tastes, the Holy one who
                    cannot be used as taste. The Holy speech is not spoken, because He is the one
                    who speaks, the Holy one who cannot be used as speech. The Holy touching is not
                    touched, because He is the one who touches, the Holy one who cannot be used as
                    touching. The Holy grasping is not grasped, because He is the one who grasps,
                    the Holy one who cannot be used as grasping. The Holy release is not released,
                    because He is the one who releases, The Holy one who cannot be used as
                    releasing. The Holy urinating is not urinated, because He is the one who
                    urinates, the Holy one who cannot be used as urinating. The Holy walking is not
                    moving, because He is the one who moves, the Holy one who cannot be used as
                    motion. Those are called the ten superiorities.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_30">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_30.01">These are the ten supreme superiorities
                        (<foreign>dasa-mahavisesa</foreign>). The Holy organ of hearing is
                    materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy
                    organ of sight is materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the
                    Supreme One. The Holy organ of taste is materialized in your body, it is supreme
                    because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of speech is materialized in your
                    body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of touch is
                    materialized in your body; it is supreme because of the Supreme One, [for the
                    organ of touch itself] is not superior. The Holy organ of grasping is
                    materialized in your body; it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy
                    organ of release is materialized in your body; it is supreme because the Supreme
                    One, [for the organ of release itself] is not superior. The Holy organ of
                    urinating is materialized in your body; it is supreme because the Supreme One,
                    [for the organ of urinating itself] is not superior. Those are called the ten
                    supreme superiorities. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_31">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_31.01">These are called the ten non-superiorities
                        (<foreign>dasa-tan-kavisesa</foreign>). The meaning is as follows: There is
                    no hearing, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning
                    in yourself. There is no sight, nothing is materialized in your body, there is
                    no means for sinning and vice in yourself. There is no smelling, nothing is
                    materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is
                    no taste, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in
                    yourself. There is no speech, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no
                    means for sinning and vice in yourself. There is no touch, nothing is
                    materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is
                    no grasping, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning
                    in yourself. There is no release, nothing is materialized in your body, there is
                    no means for sinning in yourself. There is no urinating, nothing is materialized
                    in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no walking,
                    nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself,
                    none of them. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_31.02">The meaning is: there is no one who hears, no one
                    with form, no one who smells, no one who speaks, no one who touches, no one who
                    grasps, no one who eats, no one no one who drinks, no one who tastes, there are
                    no divine [embodiments] for them. Those are called the ten
                    non-superiorities.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_32">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_32.01">Furthermore, my lesson for the servant of the
                    dharma is as follows: There is what is called the four splendours; it is [also]
                    called the four principles. This is the meaning: [they] serve as the boat,
                    [they] serve as the ship, [they] serve as the ark, [they] serve as the junk.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_32.02">What is compared to the boat is the pacified act,
                    what is compared to the ship is the pacified speech, what is compared to the ark
                    is the pacified thought, what is compared to the junk is the stable [and]
                    pacified awareness. They are called the one of Siddha-nature
                        (<foreign>sidajati</foreign>), the lord among yogins
                        (<foreign>yogisvara</foreign>), the scholar (<foreign>pandita</foreign>),
                    the men of religion (<foreign>viku</foreign>). Those are called the four
                    splendours, those are called the four principles.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33">
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.01">These are called the four purities. The pure and
                    transparent jewel is still, the pure jewel is clear, the pure jewel is white,
                    those are the pure seat of thought (<foreign>cita</foreign>).</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.02">The following is also to be taken into account
                    carefully. There is what is called the origin of goodness. It is that which is
                    extraordinary and very secret. It is the holy virtue. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.03">This is called the release, the holy purity. It
                    is called the four final liberations (<foreign>catur-mokta</foreign>): release,
                    disappearance, vanishing, dissolution. That is called the four final
                    liberations. That should be kept in secret by the servant of the
                        <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_34">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_34.01">This is the six of two. The meaning [is in the
                    words] <foreign>ndah saṅ hyaṅ hayu</foreign>. The meaning is:
                        <foreign>nən</foreign> is like the king who thinks, who reflects carefully
                    when he is on the sacred throne, emerges from the condition of stability. That
                    is called <foreign>nən</foreign>. The <foreign>dah</foreign> is the willingness
                    to present the possessions to the king, elders, hermits, ritualists, and
                    sailors. The <foreign>saṅ</foreign> means, it is said, single; there is
                    certainly no second, and also no third. What is called <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign>
                    is the relic of the past. What is called <foreign>hayu</foreign> means
                    lightweight, it is said, the body is like a flower-bud and a kapok fiber. Those
                    are the truths. That is the one who <foreign>aroṅe</foreign>?</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_34.02">This is the meaning of two: that is one man [and]
                    one woman, it is called two. Three means the king, the elder, [and] the hermit,
                    3. Five means Brahmā, Viṣṇu, Iśvāra, Mahādeva, Śiva Śaṅkara; Kusika, Garga,
                    Méstri, Purusya, Patañjala; Indra, Yama, Baruṇa, Kuvera, Besavarna. That is
                    called the five gods. Seven means: the seven underworlds, the seven middle
                    worlds, the seven upperworlds, the seven voids, the Absolute. That is called the
                    account of the creation (<foreign>kalpa-carita</foreign>). </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.01">These are called the three in number: three
                    opinions (3), three inconclusive [propositions] (3), the means of knowledge (4),
                    the artificial knowledge (4). These are the breath, the speech, and the people’s
                    mind, which surround (<foreign>narivrəta</foreign>) the world, which sink (?
                        <foreign>ñəluman</foreign>) into the trees, into the rock, into the earth,
                    into the water, into every kind of plant, into the animals (3).</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.02">These are the three [existing] in the scholar. It
                    is called the <foreign>tiga sadana</foreign>: <foreign>tiga</foreign> means
                    three, <foreign>sadana</foreign> means element. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.03">These are called the three truths. This is [the
                    syllables] <foreign>a</foreign>, <foreign>ña</foreign>, [and]
                        <foreign>na</foreign>. That is called the three true words. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.04">[The pupil]: “Where can the three be found in the
                    scholar? Show your favour to your son [by revealing] about the location where
                    the <foreign>a</foreign>, the <foreign>ña</foreign>, and the
                        <foreign>na</foreign> can be found!”</p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.05">[The teacher:] “So be it. As follows. First I
                    will explain the equality and the difference, your means to know the truth of
                    the three. What is the meaning of the <foreign>vari</foreign>,
                        <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign>, [and] <foreign>asoka</foreign> flowers? You
                    should explain! Are they identical?”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.06">[The pupil:] “So be it. They are different, my
                    lord. The <foreign>vari</foreign> flower is still the <foreign>vari</foreign>
                    flower. The <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign> is still the
                    <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign>, the <foreign>asoka</foreign> is still the
                        <foreign>asoka</foreign>, my lord. Please tell [me] your words.” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.07">[The teacher:] “The three are like that, the
                    means to evaluate the equality and the difference in a sincere, truthful,
                    rightful, and clearly perceived manner.” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.08">[The teacher:] “First of all, here is the
                    instrument to evaluate the equality and the difference of the
                        <foreign>a</foreign>. What is entering and exiting by means of the nose and
                    of your mouth, <foreign>upamāna praveśanam</foreign>, [and] its use in your
                    body?” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.09">[The pupil:] “The wind as breath, my lord. That
                    is what is called <foreign>a</foreign>, according to the scholars.” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.10">[The teacher:] “As follows is what could also be
                    asked regarding that [issue]. What is the name that is heard, as the thunder and
                    thunderous noise of all beings? What are the[ir] names, according to you?” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.11">[The pupil:] “The sound, my lord!”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.12">[The teacher:] “That is called the
                        <foreign>ña</foreign>, according to the scholars.” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.13">[The teacher:] “As follows is what could also be
                    asked, there is nobody who knows about it. What is the meaning of that which is
                    caused by you to reach the limit of the world: north, south, west, east, [and]
                    in a wink it crosses the ocean, disappears and comes back again in an instant?
                    What is your opinion, my son?” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.14">[The pupil:] “The mind, my lord!” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.15">[The teacher:] “That is called the na, according
                    to the scholars. That is the reason why they are called breath, speech, and
                    mind, which are spread through the world. Those are called the three
                    instruments. They are the means to reach the world; [they] are used as a support
                    for all beings.” </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.16">[The teacher:] These are the activities in the
                    body. <foreign>Bayu</foreign> serves as the vital principle, entering and
                    exiting your nose; it serves as your breath. It is considered right, correct,
                    and clearly perceived. It is called the truth in the body.
                        <foreign>Sabda</foreign> means the speech. It is used to define the bad and
                    the good, to name vowels and consonants. It serves as your speech.
                        <foreign>Hǝdap</foreign> means the mind, your thoughts directed towards the
                    near and the far. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.17"> [The teacher:] The <foreign>a</foreign> is the
                    breath, the <foreign>ña</foreign> is the speech, the <foreign>na</foreign> is
                    the mind. [They are] the content of the three knowledges (<foreign>tiga
                        ajñana</foreign>), which are the first argument of the scholars. They should
                    be taught [as follows:] <foreign>tiga</foreign> means three,
                        <foreign>ajñana</foreign> means the place to be reached
                        (<foreign>kasampəran</foreign>). It is the Great Supreme (4). </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.01">Furthermore, this is called the innate knowledge.
                    It can not be given to the pupil, it can not be faked. The knowledge and the
                    real are the origin of the Supreme One. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.02">This is the excellent [principle], the origin of
                    joy and sorrow, what is pleasant [and unpleasant?]. That is the reason why [it
                    is] the origin of power and strength, the origin of being respected, the origin
                    of being endowed, the origin of being venerated in the case of the scholar. As
                    for the existence of the breath, speech, and mind in your body: if the breath,
                    speech, and mind vanish in your body, [it means that one] ceases to be
                    venerated, [and] ceases to be worshiped.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.03">The mind is used as the mind by wisdom. The mind
                    is manifold. It is the truth and correct. It is truly perceivable in the body.
                    It is called the three truths. <foreign>Tri</foreign> means three,
                        <foreign>tǝpǝt</foreign> means superior. </p>
            </div>
          
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.01">[The teacher:] This is their union. The
                    “straight” is the thought, far and near. Its entire life and its targets are not
                    hindered by the difficulties. It reaches the edges of the world-egg, [including]
                    heaven and the underworlds, unseen during day and night. It is called “to
                    achieve the ultimate” (<foreign>boṅboṅ botos</foreign>) and “to completely
                    dissolve” (<foreign>buṅbaṅ lǝpas</foreign>). Those whose desires, all [of them],
                    are true and <foreign>rasti</foreign> (?) are leaving without being noticed.
                    What is the meaning of such [teaching]? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.02">[The pupil:] [This is] the thought indeed, my
                    lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.03">[The teacher:] That is the holy knowledge,
                    according to the scholar. It is the union of the three truths. When the beauty
                    [of knowledge] is thrown away, it is called the carcass. That is the reason why
                    supreme knowledge is the origin of ultimate excellence. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.04">What is the form of what is called the truly
                    priceless? This is your metaphor: like the court filled with the gold, jewel,
                    [and] priceless clothes of the worthy king. All of that is truly priceless. Thus
                    [far] about the existence of the holy breath, sound and mind. Thus is the
                    supreme knowledge in your body. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.05">Indeed, the holy knowledge regarding the living
                    as a householder (<foreign>momah</foreign>), of breathing, of speaking, of
                    thinking is no other than the holy supreme knowledge. Its meaning is to be kept
                    as a secret by the pupil of the scholar. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.06">[Disciple:] So be it. This is fortunate.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.01">[Teacher:] This is my word, the endless wisdom.
                    Is there any breath, speech, and mind in you, my child?</p>
                
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.02">[Pupil:] Yes, they exist, my lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.03">[Teacher:] Is it seen by you? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.04">[Pupil:] No, my lord. It is proper to regard it
                    as existing. Anything that is felt and touched, it exists in the world and in
                    the body, my lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.05">[Teacher:] Such [answer] is true. Does the speech
                    exist? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.06">[Pupil:] It exists, my lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.07">[Teacher:] Such [answer] is true. Is the speech
                    seen by you? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.08">[Pupil:] No, it is not seen, my lord. It is
                    proper to regard it as existing. All that is heard, it exists in the world and
                    in the body, my lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.09">[Teacher:] Does the mind exist in you? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.10">[Pupil:] It exists, my lord. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.11">[Teacher:] Is it seen by you? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.12">[Pupil:] No, it is not seen, my lord. It is
                    proper to regard it as existing. All that is thought, far and near, exists in
                    the world and in the body.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.13">[Master:] You are right to know in this way. That
                    is the reason why what is called the Holy Invisible [essence] is clearly
                    perceptible; it exists perpetually in the body and [in] the world, there is
                    nothing else. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.14">This is the activity of the breath, the speech,
                    and the mind: the appellation of the breath, speech, and mind (3), the
                    demonstration of the breath (6). This is the five tasks ordered by the king (5),
                    the five organs (5), the teaching about the way to vanish (3), the highest truth
                        (<foreign>paramarta</foreign>) (4), the ultimate isolation (4), the eight
                    supernatural powers (8), the section of knowledge (3),
                        <foreign>kisiñan</foreign>;(?) (8), unperceived by faculties
                        (<foreign>anendriya</foreign>) (3), the gross and subtle elements (4). These
                    are the numbers of the section of knowledge; the servant of the
                        <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention to them. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.01">This is called the addition (2), the state of the
                        <foreign>viku</foreign>s (4), the naming [and] the personalisation [of] the
                    reverend teacher. This is what should be made an object of attention by the one
                    who searches for the truth. [It is] the holy knowledge: the reason that [it is]
                    the possession of one who possesses, the reason that it is not used as a
                    possession, like the enjoyment [of consumption] (<foreign>boga</foreign>),
                    enjoyment [of living properties] (<foreign>pariboga</foreign>), enjoyments of
                    appearance (<foreign>rupaboga</foreign>). What is that which is called
                        <foreign>boga</foreign>, <foreign>pariboga</foreign>, [and]
                        <foreign>rupaboga</foreign>? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.02">As follows: what is called
                        <foreign>boga</foreign> is food and drink; <foreign>pariboga</foreign> is
                    the slave, servant, buffalo, cow, any kind of livestock;
                        <foreign>rupaboga</foreign> is gold, jewel, fine lower cloths for a worthy
                    king, that is, the ornaments of a divine king. The possession is the supreme
                    knowledge, to be used as the embellishment [and] as the ornament of any worthy
                    person (<foreign>vastu siṅ vvaṅ</foreign>).</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.03">In addition, O child of the scholar, what will be
                    thought should be absorbed, about what is called any worthy person. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.04">Let it be so! [I] teach you as follows: what is
                    called a worthy person is the one of true being (<foreign>saṅ
                    sat-hana</foreign>), [which is] not created. It is the source. It is called the
                    root of the origin and the end. It is called pure nature. It is called the
                    source of the mother and father. It is regarded as the secret. It is called the
                    paramount <foreign>dharma</foreign>, who carries out all the actions in the
                    world. He creates without joining [all the other beings in] being created. That
                    is why what is called “Someone” (<foreign>si anu</foreign>) does not come from
                    the treatises, does not come from the teacher, [but] it is from oneself
                        (<foreign>na śāstrataḥ na gurutaḥ svataḥ</foreign>). </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.05">The meaning is: <foreign>na śāstrataḥ</foreign>
                    [means] cannot be found by the means of scriptures and wisdom; <foreign>na
                        gurutaḥ</foreign> is <foreign>kaimariṅun</foreign> (?). What is sought [by
                    him] is penetrated and filled. It cannot be used as a means, it cannot be
                    instructed, by (<foreign>ri</foreign>) the teacher. It is only from oneself. It
                    exists without being made into existence: no wife, no son, no relatives, no
                    mother, no father: [it is] from oneself. The meaning is: <foreign>na
                        bhārya</foreign> is not having a wife, na <foreign>putraḥ</foreign> is not
                    having child and grandchild, <foreign>na mātā</foreign>, <foreign>na pitam
                        svataḥ</foreign> is not having a father, not having a mother.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.06"><foreign>Avismṛtidṛṣṭi</foreign> (the sight of
                    one who is not forgetful). He sees without being seen, knows without being
                    known, embodies without being embodied, blows the vital air [into other beings]
                    without being blown the vital air into [by any other beings], speaks without
                    being spoken, thinks without being thought. He appears just at the same time
                    with his body, his breath, his speech, and his mind, in the embryo-abode in the
                    past. When he appears in the external [world], he is called “Someone”. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.07">That is the reason why the Someone else is called
                    the one having difficulty, namely, its ignorance about the world and the
                    universe is extraordinary, is not knowing the father and the mother of the whole
                    world, and the child of the world. Who is the one who is knowledgeable? It is
                    only the scholar, no one else. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.08">O, child of the learned master, “Someone” will
                    emerge from what are called parents. </p>
            </div>            
            
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.01">Indeed, the following is my love for you (5).
                    These are the <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers. The meaning is as follows:
                        <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers means cotton, the color means a thread, the
                    cognition (<foreign>vri</foreign>) means fabric.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.02">The meaning is: what is called
                        <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers is the body, what is called the thread is
                    the mind, what is called fabric is the individualized divine emanation
                        (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ pramana</foreign>). </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.03">The meaning is: he uses his mind as the sight, he
                    uses his two eyes as the gate, he uses his breath as the vital principle, he
                    uses his speech as the means of realizing, he uses his body as the abode, he
                    uses the world as the gate.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.04">The ‘red’ is a color, the meaning is that [he]
                    knows what he sees. The gate to see the varis flowers is the two eyeballs. The
                    instrument to see the varis flowers is the mind. It means that he knows his
                    sight. Who is the one who sees the <foreign>varis</foreign> flowers?</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.05">It is you, son. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.06">The skill (3), the truth (1), its
                        <foreign>panatab</foreign> (?) (3), the liberated soul (9), inconceivable,
                        <foreign>icaluṅ</foreign> (?), <foreign>i</foreign> (?), to carry over the
                    shoulder, <foreign>ba</foreign> (?), the big trees (<foreign>kayu
                        magəṅ</foreign>). </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.07">This is the five gross elements (5), the five
                    forms [of suffering], (5), the five paths (5). All of that should be made the
                    object of the attention of the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.01">As follows is the esoteric teaching, the
                    beginning of the scholar telling about the [five] sections. The esoteric
                    teaching (<foreign>sandi</foreign>) means the consciousness. It serves as the
                    direction of the world and all beings. That is the reason why the whole world is
                    not evolving in the wrong manner and with the wrong essences. They are following
                    in the right direction their father and their mother, and the origin and
                    particular nature of all the beings: humans give birth to humans, animals give
                    birth to animals. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.02">The following is called the penance
                        (<foreign>tapa</foreign>). What is the essential meaning of it? The purity
                        (<foreign>si lilaṅ</foreign>). What is the reason it is called purity? As
                    follows its explanation: it is aware to have the world and the body as
                    properties.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.03">Likewise, the posture
                    (<foreign>luṅguh</foreign>), what is its essential meaning? The firmness. It is
                    true indeed that The Witness is firm in his knowledge of the manifest and
                    unmanifest world. What is the firmness of The Witness in the manifest world? He
                    does not follow along [others] in prioritizing sacred formulas, mantras, the
                    mantra <foreign>huṅ</foreign>, a lotus-like hand (<foreign>padmakara</foreign>),
                    especially performing worship, healing spells (<foreign>jampa-jampya</foreign>).
                    He does not follow those in prioritizing the way of penance, observances, yoga,
                    and concentration. He is not obstructed by any kind of magic
                        (<foreign>guna</foreign>). Thus is the firmness of the witness in the
                    manifest world. What is the firmness of the one who sees the unmanifest world?
                    He should not be involved in demonic [activities]. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.04">Likewise, the direct perception
                        (<foreign>pratyaksa</foreign>), what is its essential meaning? The ability.
                    What is the meaning of the ability? This is its nature: He knows the union of
                    the ability of the whole world to serve as his world. The Witness does not know
                    that the body serves as his body. The holy dharma does not know that the smell
                    serves as his smell. The holy virtue does not know that the color serves as his
                    color. The highest principle does not know that breath, the speech, and the mind
                    serves as his life principle. The holy supreme does not know that the speech
                    serves as his means of realizing. The concealed one does not know that the mind
                    serves as the means of thought. That is called the ability. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.05">Where does the capacity and the application of
                    the capacity come from? As follows: consciousness in the mind. There is the most
                    desired jewel, that is known as ‘the fulfiller’. The Witness is the most desired
                    jewel and the great unconceivable one. It [manik sarvesta] is used as a
                    plaything by the holy <foreign>dharma</foreign>. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.06">What is that which is called the most desired
                    jewel [and] what is known as ‘the fulfiller’? It is the mind. What is the jewel
                    known as ‘the creator (anuṅ vidi)’? It is consciousness. What is the jewel known
                    as ‘the inconceivable one’? It is the witness. Those are called the three secret
                    words. The secret of the scholar is not found by the servant of the truth. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.01">What are called the three secrets, that is the
                    breath, the speech, and the mind? Those which are called the three secrets are
                    not the three means. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.02">The meaning is: what is called the three secrets
                    according to the great teacher?</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.03">Indeed, as follows is its form: that is the mind,
                    the consciousness, the witness. Those are called the origin of existence. What
                    is the explanation of the origin of existence, my lord? The illustration about
                    that is as follows: like the lamp, the flame, and the light.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.04">Are the flame and the light identical, my lord? </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.05">No, they are not like that. The flame, the light,
                    and the fire are different. The flame and the light are coming out from the
                    fire. Their outcome dies with the fire, going back to their origin; their
                    original condition dies.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.06">What is its explanation? Prepare the torch
                    already! Its nature is to suddenly flame firmly, and at the same time, is to be
                    extinguished. The appearance of the flame is [also] the appearance of the light.
                    In a similar way they are extinguished. The swallow of the flame and the light,
                    they are swallowed and vanished simultaneously. The mind and the consciousness,
                    as well as the witness are likewise. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.07">What is considered the fire? The individualized
                    divine emanation. What is the flame? The mind. What is the heat and the light?
                    The esoteric [consciousness]. The meaning is: the mind, the consciousness, [and]
                    the witness. Those are called the origin of existence (3). </p>
                
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.08">This is the means of individualization, like the
                    painter, the action [of painting], and the brush; like the bronze and the wax,
                    along with the silver. The meaning is: the mind, the consciousness, the witness.
                    Those are called the means of individualization of existence. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.09">This is the meaning that the fire is different.
                    What is the explanation? Prepare the lamp, that is, its wick is set ablaze. [The
                    fire] that stands and flames, quickly shines. Its measure stands in the same
                    direction (satuduhan). That is called the flame. What is spreading out [and]
                    filling the house, it is called the light. What is shining as small as a
                    fire-fly, and the red on the top of the wick, that is called the fire. This is
                    the proof that the fire is different from the flame and the light. Where to the
                    destination of the flame and the light? Does it go to void and non-existence?
                    No, it is not like that.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.10">What is the meaning of all of this, [about the
                    fire] going to the void and non-existence? No, it is not like that. What is the
                    meaning of all this, [namely] the flame, along with the light and its fire,
                    going to the void and non-existence, according to another viku? No, it is not
                    according to the scholar. You should not [say] like that.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.11">Where would be the destination of the torch and
                    its light? They go to the state that exists. The meaning is: like the egg, like
                    the seed of mango, like the rice-straw, like planting in the rice field, like
                    the flowers and the yarn, sa, a. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.12">That is called the work of the Lord. This is the
                    power of the Great One. This is the power of the Supreme One. Me means I, the
                    one who truly exists, which is not created, the holy one who exists by itself,
                    who creates which does not follow [others] in being created. Because I am the
                    life-giving power which is not the embodiment of the living power (kapramanaan).
                    I am the Supreme which is not the embodiment of the Supreme. That is called the
                    three supreme secrets. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.13">This is its means of tatab (? panatabna). The
                    world has ceased to support, the body has ceased to serve as the abiding place,
                    the breath has ceased to be the vital principle, the speech has ceased to be
                    used as a means to put into effect, the mind has ceased to be produced, the
                    consciousness has ceased to be the instrument of action, the witness has ceased
                    to act upon. This is the explanation according to the noble master. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.14">This is the means of their union
                        (<foreign>pamupul</foreign>). The mind has ceased to be created, the
                    consciousness has ceased to be used as an instrument to create, the Witness has
                    ceased to create. That is called the means of the union.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.15">This is the means of coloring (?
                        <foreign>pamulas</foreign>). The mind acknowledges (?
                        <foreign>maṅku</foreign>) that it has ceased to be made upon by that
                        (<foreign>tutur</foreign>); the consciousness acknowledges (?
                        <foreign>maṅku</foreign>) has ceased to create by way of that
                        (<foreign>hədap</foreign>); the Witness, consequently, has ceased to act by
                    way of people. It is called its means of coloring. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.16">This is called its fixation. It is not seen. What
                    is made and the instrument of action, let alone the one who acts are visualized.
                    For the mind is subtle. It has ceased to be created. The consciousness is
                    invisible. It has ceased to be created. The Witness is inconceivable. Those are
                    called the process of fixation, of what is called the three secrets.</p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.01">Likewise is the release. What serves as the
                    secret by him to act? That is called the process of fixation. The creation
                        (<foreign>krataka</foreign>) and the sharing task (<foreign>si
                    dum</foreign>). The meaning is: The Witness will know the means to the act, [He]
                    will know to arrange his acts in the material [and] immaterial world. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.02">What is your analogy? Like the goldsmith. The one
                    who gave the order comes. [He says:] “Please make for me a bracelet and a ring”.
                    The smith says “I already abandoned my work. It was already given by me to the
                    assistant. The occupation is abandoned by me. Already a long time that the skill
                    was left by me.” The one who gave the order then left, he was looking for
                    another smith.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.03">Likewise also the individualized divine
                    emanation. “The painter” has ceased to create. The Witness has ceased to cause
                    the consciousness. All of them have ceased to be constitutive elements [of the
                    human being]. That is why that is called being apportioned [according to their
                    original prerogatives]: have limit without being limited with regard to their
                    manifest and unmanifest activities. The meaning is: that is called the release
                    according to the scholar. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.01">What is called the epitome is like that. Seek the
                    essence of the truth, without being turned into untruth! What is your analogy?
                    Like the fibres of the palm rib broom. Their number being great, they are held
                    together (?, <foreign>kasigənan</foreign>) by the single tie. All the teachings
                    are like that. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.02">The Holy Supreme, He creates what serves as the
                    essence with respect to the direct perception (<foreign>pratyaksa</foreign>). It
                    is true that the Witness knows about the demonic substance, which serves as the
                    sin of the posture (<foreign>luṅguh</foreign>). It is true that the Witness will
                    know about the one who has attachment which serves as its sin. The one without
                    attachment serves as the supreme power in the penance (<foreign>tapa</foreign>).
                    It is true that the Witness will know the unconsciousness which serves as its
                    sin. The consciousness serves as its supreme power with regard to the esoteric
                    [teaching] (<foreign>sandi</foreign>). Do not let the Witness join them, insofar
                    that such [involvement] is sinful. Those should be considered cautiously by the
                    servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, according to the great scholar. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.03">The following is called the beginning of writing.
                    What is pointed out by the scholar about the beginning of writing, absolutely
                    without any doubt whatsoever? What serves as the essence of it? As follows: the
                    muscle of the right and left hands, the writing on the palms of the hands. Those
                    are called the hands. There is nothing lacking in them, there is nothing that is
                    slipping away from the moving hands. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.04">The following is the second [part] of writing.
                    Its form is as follows: the manifestation is the riddle words. It serves as the
                    challenge of the scholar. What does it refer to? As follows: both pupils. The
                    meaning is: the conduct of life is the conduct of speech; the meaning is: the
                    conduct of intellect is the conduct of knowledge, the conduct of esoteric
                    [knowledge] is the conduct of mind. Likewise, the individualized divine
                    emanation and the supreme are united with the secret, their nature is to
                    disappear simultaneously all together. There is not [even] the knowledge that
                    they have already been released. They are the content of the second part of
                    writing, according to the foremost master, which is paid full attention by the
                    servant of dharma. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.05">The following is the third part of writing, the
                    beginning of the master discussing the secret, that is the origin of the self
                    divine emanation. If one realizes its own self, that is the Supreme Dharma. It
                    releases from the world, it departs from the body. The breath, the speech, and
                    the mind are not embodied. Moreover, [they are] the ultimate void and emptiness,
                    free from disturbance, pure, unobstructed. That is the perpetual dharma that
                    exists in the body. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.06">It continuously flames and shines, not being
                    extinguished by day and night, also in the manifest and unmanifest [worlds]. It
                    has been shown based on the true nature (vastu) by the master. You should not
                    have any doubt! They are the content of the third part of writing, which is paid
                    full attention by the servant of dharma, it is the word of the lord of yogins. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.07">The following is called the fixed number of four.
                    The meaning is: life, death, sleep, and unconsciousness. Those serve as the
                    place of the Witness in material and immaterial reality. They are shown by the
                    scholar to the servant of the dharma.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.08">The gross body is death. You see the body, small
                    and little. It is seen for an instant only. As for the subtle body, that is
                    regarded as sleep, it serves as your body while dreaming. As for the pure body,
                    that is called the unconsciousness which is void, absence, and the ultimate
                    reality. These are called the fixed number of four. The Witness, the life and
                    the Soul does not manifest: clear, silent, unhindered; perpetual, steadfast,
                    independent. All beings are like that. Those [i.e. kalakar pat] are called the
                    king of sins. The King Witness does not manifest in material and immaterial
                    world, meaning that it serves as the essence of the fixed number of four. It
                    should be thought carefully by my child, the servant of the dharma, according to
                    the lord of yogins.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- mari saṁsaya ta kita denya, mari meliḥ na<space type="binding-hole"/> ta kita, saṁ hya pramana, manilvalita saṁ hya visesa, ka, tan· na svaga, tar nahala, tar na hayu, tar na su<lb 
  n="35v4" break="no"/>ka, tar na duka, Iya ta rasaniṁ pati ṅaranya, katəmvan ikaṁ manivan·, ri sala niskala, Apa ta maryikən·n ika hala, hala hayu, suka duka, ṅəkeri bvana sarira, ṅaniveḥ Ikaṁ sarvvajan·ma kabeḥ

<!-\-SSMG_L621_36r.JPG-\->
<pb n="36r"/>
<lb n="36r1"/>Ana saṁ hyaṁ pramana, juga tan· hana vaneḥ nihan· sinaṁguḥ rahasye pandi ṅaranya, -->
<div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.01">The following is called the secret of the
                    scholar. What is the detailed explanation of it? As follows, there is your
                    analogy: like the Witness, after the individualized divine emanation is blissful
                        (<foreign>hayu</foreign>), when it is released from the world, freed from
                    the body, [it] being only the everlasting consciousness and the deepest point of
                    esoteric knowledge. What is the everlasting consciousness and the deepest point
                    of esoteric knowledge?</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.02">Their meanings are as follows: “As the fire
                    [which is] in every piece of wood is not perceived because of [its] subtlety.”
                    The meaning is: it is not found. You have ceased to be doubtful about it, you,
                    the individualized divine emanation, have ceased to be hesitant, the holy
                    supreme has ceased to be tremulous. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.03">The meaning is: it is not heaven, nor the bad,
                    nor the goodness, nor the joy, nor the sorrow. That is called the essence of
                    death. The experience of The Witness in the material and immaterial [worlds].
                    What causes one to give up the bad and the good, the joy and the sorrow, here in
                    the world and the body, and in all beings? It is only the individualized divine
                    emanation, nothing else. Those are called the secrets of the scholar; they
                    should be clearly understood by the servant of the dharma, according to the
                    noble scholar, 4. </p>
            </div>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.01">As follows are the instruction words, the climax
                    of the scholar who ceases to teach the servant of the dharma, the climax of the
                    teacher who ceases to teach the pupil, the climax of the pupil who ceases to ask
                    the teacher. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.02">How is it so? As follows: like the jewel with the
                    crystal, likewise are the scholar and the servant of the dharma. If they have
                    understood about all holy dharmas, each of them, the servant of the dharma and
                    the teacher are one, the one who teaches and the one who asks are united. The
                    scholar has ceased to teach the servant of the dharma, the lord of yogin has
                    ceased to ask. </p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.03">The meaning is: if all of them already know,
                    also, their individualized divine emanations are equally priceless, meaning that
                    they equally return to their original nature. That is called the instruction
                    words. It should be paid attention to by the servant of the dharma, according to
                    the noble great scholar. </p>
            </div>
            <!--Ø, tləs· sinurat· riṁ vulan· kapat·, manibakən· sasṭā, ri de<space type="binding-hole"/>sa mahapaviṭā, riṁ gunuṁ jədaṁ pun·, Uliḥ sabian· ṅeca pun·, saṁṅ anurat· bvacaḥ nu ṅaheraṁ nibaṁ kaca<lb 
  n="36v3" break="no"/>na pun·, // // Ø malapaḥh iṅapura, ku na sasṭā 2cek· kadi tapak· yuyu riṁ tacaṁ pun·, Ø L̥viḥ<space type="binding-hole"/> lvaṅan· kuraṁ tinabəhan· kena bənaṁ nu IR̥g· pun // , //,,,,,,,,,, -->
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_47">
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_47.01">This is what should be paid attention to, the
                    holy book called Sasana Mahaguru. It has been completely written in the fourth
                    month. Accomplishing the writing at the region Mahapavitra on Mount Jedang. The
                    product of an ugly side job. The one who writes is an amateur boy who weighs the
                    gold. Apologize for the ugly writing like the trace of a crab in the sand. If
                    something is missing, please add it, if it is too much, please reduce it,
                    because it is the work of a stupid one. </p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
