<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#skk">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Translation of the Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian_transEng01</idno>
                <!-- Replace by filename following FNC -->
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!-- <notesStmt><note><bibl>Digital translation of <bibl><ptr target="bib:"></ptr></bibl>.<relatedItem target=""></relatedItem></bibl></note></notesStmt>-->
            <!-- provide a notesStmt if you need to add some precision regarding the establishement of the translation -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull> <!-- Copy and paste the titleStmt and publicationStmt of the edition file -->           <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
                    <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                    <editor ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </editor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                        <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian</idno>
                        <availability>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                                <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                                <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                            </licence>
                        </availability>
                        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <!-- if your translation is a copy of already published one: fill a biblStruct -->
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Part mandatory -->
                <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
                <p></p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
            <!-- replace this by a line that has you as @who, that has the @date on which you finished the first basic encoding of the file, and that has the following description of what was finished on that date: "Initial encoding of the file." Then add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div corresp="#skk_01">
    <p n="1" corresp="#skk_01.01">Here, as follows, is what will be taught by the holy man: the way (<foreign>de</foreign>) of one who searches weal. As regards what are called the hermits’ holy precepts for society (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</foreign>), all people should exert themselves [to follow them]. These are the words of the holy man, revealing the hermits’ holy precepts for society. 
</p>
     <p n="2" corresp="#skk_01.02">These are the ten holy accomplishments (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-krəta</foreign>), which must be adhered to by all people. Anyone who starts to uphold the holy instructions of accomplishments (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ sasana krəta</foreign>), is destined to be long-lived, to be of long youth, to have success in paddy fields (kuras), to have success in cultivation, to stand firm, to win in battle — all people [who do so] will be youthful.
</p>
      <p n="3" corresp="#skk_01.03">This is the explanation of the ‘Ten Holy Accomplishments’: [their are] the shadows of the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>), the reflections of the ten holy paths (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-marga</foreign>), the manifestations of the ten sense faculties (<foreign>dasa-indriya</foreign>), what is needed to make the spacious world and the near world prosperous. 
</p> 
      <p n="4" corresp="#skk_01.04">This is what we need to make the wide world prosperous: roads being well-lit, plantations being large, [the country is] well developed and productive (paka pradana), [but also] the side [yard] being clean, the front yard being well-lit. Moreover, the house being full, the rice barn is full, the chicken coop being full, the dry rice-field being cultivated, the tap [of palm trees] being protected. The result is a life full of vitality, a long-lasting health, youthfulness of the ruler (<foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign>). Even in the spacious [world], grasses, trees, climbing plants, bushes — all grown with fresh green leaves (<foreign>hejo lembok</foreign>), all trees bearing fruit, falling fertile rains, growing seasonal crops; [those] will bring life for people in general. That is what is called the holy instructions of accomplishments in the wide world. 
</p>
       <p n="5" corresp="#skk_01.05">These are the ten accomplishments, considered as the shadow of the ten holy virtues. It is the reflection of the ten paths, the manifestation of the ten sense faculties. 
</p> 
       <p n="6" corresp="#skk_01.06">This is its explanation. 
Ears should not listen randomly [to a discussion], if it is not fit to be listened to. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune (<foreign>mala</foreign>), the payment (<foreign>lunas</foreign>) is punishment [in] hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result, (obtained) from the ears, is considered optimal. </p> 
       <p n="7" corresp="#skk_01.07">Eyes should not watch randomly [any event], if it is not fit to be watched. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result of watching is considered optimal. </p> 
    <p n="8" corresp="#skk_01.08">The skin should not be used jerkingly, due to hot and cold. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the skin is considered optimal.</p> 
      <p n="9" corresp="#skk_01.09">The tongue should not be wrong [in] what is tasted. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the tongue is considered optimal.</p> 
        <p n="10" corresp="#skk_01.10">The nose should not smell wrongly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the nose is considered optimal. </p> 
        <p n="11" corresp="#skk_01.11">The mouth should not speak randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the mouth is considered optimal.</p> 
        <p n="12" corresp="#skk_01.12">The hands should not grasp randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the hands is considered optimal.</p>
        <p n="13" corresp="#skk_01.13">The feet should not step randomly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the feet is considered optimal. </p> 
        <p n="14" corresp="#skk_01.14">The anus should not be used rumblingly. For [this] is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the anus is considered optimal. </p> 
        <p n="15" corresp="#skk_01.15">The vulva and the penis should not be used for seducing, for [this] is the gate of misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the vulva and the penis is considered best. This is what is called the ten accomplishments. If the ten gates are completely used appropriately, the behavior of all people will be good, let alone the behavior of His Majesty the king. </p>
</div>

<div corresp="#skk_02">
    <p n="1" corresp="#skk_02.01">The following are called the ten devotions (<foreign>dasa-prəbakti</foreign>): first, a child devoted to the father; 2, a wife devoted to [her] husband; 3, a servant devoted to the officers (<foreign>pacandaan</foreign>); 4, a pupil devoted to [his] master; 5, a farmer devoted to the soldier; 6, a soldier devoted to the minister; 7, a minister is devoted to the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>; 8, the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign> devoted to the governor; 9, the governor devoted to the king; 10, the king devoted to the gods; the gods devoted to the ancestors. They are called the ten devotions. 10.</p>
</div>
          
          <div corresp="#skk_03">
             <p n="1" corresp="#skk_03.01">This is what should be practised, the message from the true sage. ‘<foreign>Oṅ</foreign>, [I give] homage to Śiva! My veneration [goes] to the Holy Five tathagatas!’ <foreign>Pañca</foreign> means five, <foreign>tata</foreign> means speech, <foreign>gata</foreign> means passion. Those are which will become a virtue, all of them. The five syllables (<foreign>pañcaksara</foreign>) are the masters of men. The meaning is: the five syllables are manifest, being  seen, experienced, observed, [and] perceived by the senses. The master is the one to be asked by the people. That is why they are called the masters of men. As for ignorance, [it exists] since the world exists. </p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#skk_03.02">This is the “evidence” for it, that is the five spheres of activity (<foreign>pañca-byapara</foreign>): earth, water, fire, wind and ether. Words of the great holy man: “They are the substances of our [bodies]; the skin is the earth, the blood [and] the saliva are the water, the eyes are the light, the bones are the wind, the head is the ether. It (the skin) is called the earth in the body. The reason why they are compared to world authorities, is that they take shape as the leader (<foreign>prabu</foreign>), the elder (<foreign>rama</foreign>), the hermit, the ritual expert (<foreign>disi</foreign>), and the sailor”.</p>
             <p n="3" corresp="#skk_03.03">These are the five sons (pañca-putra): saṅ Maṅukuhan is the earth, saṅ Katuṅ Maralah is the water, saṅ Karuṅ Kalah is the fire, saṅ Sandaṅ Grәba is the wind, saṅ Vrәti Kandayun is the ether.</p>
             <p n="4" corresp="#skk_03.04">These are the five kusikas: saṅ Kusika on the mountain, saṅ Garga in the swamp, saṅ Mestri on Mount Mahameru, saṅ Purusa in Mandiri, saṅ Patañjala in Pañjulan.</p>
              <p n="5" corresp="#skk_03.05">If the holy five sections (saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima) are taken into account altogether, the earth would be in harmony, all [its] quarters of space. All quarters of space are east (<foreign>purba</foreign>), south (<foreign>daksina</foreign>), west (<foreign>pasirma</foreign>), north (<foreign>utara</foreign>), center (<foreign>madya</foreign>).</p>
              <p n="6" corresp="#skk_03.06"><foreign>Purba</foreign> is the east, the abode of the god Iswara, whose color is white. Daksina is the south, the abode of the god Brahma, whose color is red. <foreign>Pasirma</foreign> is the west, the abode of the god Mahadéwa, whose color is yellow. <foreign>Utara</foreign> is the north, the abode of the god Wisnu, whose color is black. <foreign>Madya</foreign> is the center, the abode of the god Siwa, whose color is multifarious. [That is] the reason why the five sacred section (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima</foreign>) in the universe are like that.</p>
              <p n="7" corresp="#skk_03.07">These are the five sections in [the case of] the great scholar. The esoteric teaching is experienced by the one who is conscious (<foreign>si tutur</foreign>); asceticism is experienced by the one who is pure (<foreign>si liṅlaṅ</foreign>); posture is experienced by the one who is firm (<foreign>si pagəh</foreign>); direct perception is experienced by the one who is extraordinary (<foreign>sy asəmbava</foreign>); liberation is experienced by the one who shares without receiving a share, who limits without being limited. The five sections in [the case of] the great scholar are like that.</p>
              <p n="8" corresp="#skk_03.08">As follows are the causes of accomplishment: they are the five gods, all embodying your name, all watching your form. But if (the names and forms) are not guarded, as if crooked meets its crooked, straight meets its straight. This is how it is: it is by human actions that it becomes accomplished, by human actions that it becomes good.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div corresp="#skk_04">
              <p n="1" corresp="#skk_04.01">These are the acts of the servant, every path taken by servants. The act means intellect [and] mode of conduct. Every path taken means: be fearful, be strong, be respectful, be courteous, in behavior, in attitude, in action, in speech, especially when in front of His Majesty the king.</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#skk_04.02">We should be faithful in service, in order to wipe out the ten defilements (<foreign>dasa-kalesa</foreign>), so that the impurity leading to sin will be annihilated, [and] heaven will be obtained.</p>
              <p n="3" corresp="#skk_04.03">If [you are] excessive in practicing the acts of the servant, that is worse than a monkey (<foreign>usyat</foreign>) occupying a hill, performing penance on the top of the mountain, for it is forbidden to perform penance on an elephant mound [or] a lion mound, near a great danger.</p>
              <p n="4" corresp="#skk_04.04">These are the actions of man that will be of use to all people. We should not fail to follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! If we wish to be free from the five forms of reincarnation (<foreign>pañca-gati saṅsara</foreign>), we should not be deceitful, should not have a habit of laziness, should not deceive ourselves. Deceiving ourselves means: what is present is considered absent, what is absent is considered present, what is true is considered not so, what is not so is considered true — so that his mind is scheming, pretending, deceiving, hurting. That is the explanation of being deceitful to ourselves.</p> 
             <p n="5" corresp="#skk_04.05">Being deceitful to other people means: plucking without asking permission, taking without asking, picking without requesting, let alone looting, thieving, plundering, robbing, everything that counts as impudent and deceitful. Those are called being deceitful to other people.</p>
             <p n="6" corresp="#skk_04.06">And also infiltrating, grabbing, pilfering, seizing, groping, sneaking, let alone hanging around with a host, with a dignitary, let alone with one's own master. That should even less be done, be practiced by the servants.</p>  
              <p n="7" corresp="#skk_04.07">Do not fail to practice polite, respectful, and refined words, to be humble and well-mannered to fellow humans, to family and relatives, let alone to our master. We should use [our] feet to sit politely, [our] hands to pay respect.</p> 
              <p n="8" corresp="#skk_04.08">If we talk with a nobleman, with a gusti, with the lover of someone else, with a forbidden woman, let alone with our master; if we are employed [by them], [we] should not be angry in our minds, let alone answer wrongly, an expression of discontent visible to our master. Don’t! It is forbidden! The result of asceticism may fail! The result of the ancestors (cakal bakal) [may] be lost! The results of hard work may be lost! [We will] be met by the god of worldly misfortune, fined by His Majesty the king.</p>
              <p n="9" corresp="#skk_04.09">If we are not faithful to our master, for instance if we are in a sick state, if we are tired, if we are careless, [then] let’s honestly acknowledge that we have been very disgraceful, so that we are acknowledged to be faithful in service. But if we act, we should not be weak, we should not fall short, should not refuse when being ordered, should not be envious [or] malicious with those engaged in the same service, especially when seeing someone who gets praise [or] gets an audience (<foreign>parəkan</foreign>); seeing someone who is favored by the master, then our thoughts may become overheated. They should not, it is forbidden! Its being forbidden leads to tears, the heart wounded without being able to be cured, mantras being ineffective, intentions not becoming reality, because the holy hermits’ precepts for society  are not adhered to. </p>
              <p n="10" corresp="#skk_04.10">Likewise, if we are <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, do not reprimand [us] discreetly. If we are reprimanded, [we] must not fail to be devoted to the naṅganan, because he is the agent (<foreign>tanda</foreign>) of His Majesty the king.</p>
              <p n="11" corresp="#skk_04.11">If we are under orders, [we] should not fail to maintain the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society, so that we are faithful to the commandments. But as regards the one who goes north, south, west, east, he must not si vok cante, must not si mur cante, shall not become si mar cante, shall not [become] darma cante. Those are called four considerations (<foreign>catur-yatna</foreign>).</p>
              <p n="12" corresp="#skk_04.12">This is the meaning. <foreign>Si vok cante</foreign> means easily tempted by food and drink. <foreign>Si mur cante</foreign> means guilty of participating in making those who steal, who confiscate, who deceive, spread in all directions; it is called the wrong destination. <foreign>Si mar cante</foreign> means to take merchandise, sheets of gold and silver, [even if] it is not ordered by the commander; it is called wrong purpose. <foreign>Darma cante</foreign> means tolerant of what is detestable to our master. He is ordered to fetch [someone], to go by foot [to pick up someone], and to kill those who are unfit for [our] master, [but] instead he becomes more careful, because they are friends, family, and relatives. That should not be done, for what is called the wrong <foreign>binarih</foreign> (?) is forbidden; it is called <foreign>darma cante</foreign>. Those things should not be practiced by the servants: to love the detestable, to detest the lovable. They are improper to be practiced by the servants.</p>    
              <p n="13" corresp="#skk_04.13">This is so that we obey the master, so that we are long taken as servants, so that we are always controlled by our master: follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! Pay attention to the dignitary! If the master scolds [someone], we too should participate in scolding with the master. If the master praises [someone], we too should participate in praising with the master. If we cannot participate in praising [or] participate in criticizing with the master, it is better that we keep quiet while devoting ourselves to the master.</p> 
              <p n="14" corresp="#skk_04.14">If we walk into the forest, [we should wear] an upper garment, a lower garment, and a combination. When coming to the [sea]side, [we] wear upper and lower garments as often as possible (<foreign>sakarajən</foreign>). When not with the master, [we must] be careful about the hermits’ holy precepts for society. Their precepts are: don’t go harvesting [legumes] from other people’s small fields, from other people’s gardens, except by virtue of our having asked permission.</p>
              <p n="15" corresp="#skk_04.15">A rope on a forest and on a garden, wood that had been marked by a string, fruit that has been bunched together, firewood that stands ready, a covering for mushrooms, hives or nests of various bees (<foreign>təvvan</foreign>, <foreign>odeṅ</foreign>, <foreign>ñəruan</foreign>), of wasps (<foreign>eṅaṅ</foreign>), of woodworm (<foreign>ulam</foreign>), a fishing dam (parakan) — all kinds of ownership marks (<foreign>babayan</foreign>): we should not take them carelessly, let alone bring down other people’s taps. That should not be done, for it is the origin of guilt, the source of suffering and misery.</p>
              <p n="16" corresp="#skk_04.16">If we find a road, large or small, [we should] quickly wear loin-cloth or a combination, [as] we might be faced with gustis or with mantris. [We] should not fail to move to the left and bend down. If [we meet with] <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>s, brahmans, royal ascetics, governors, princes, rich or poor, especially <foreign>guru loka</foreign>s, [we] should not fail to move to the left and sit, for those are the teachers of the king.</p>
          </div>
          <div corresp="#skk_05">
              <p n="1" corresp="#skk_05.01">Keep in mind the Hermits’ Precepts for Society, and beware of adultery. Do not go and whimper about the forbidden women of others, widowed maidens, for [you] might be guilty of ‘adultery of the road’; especially [do not go and] hold hands, sharing a seat on a tree trunk, on a couch, in a shelter (<foreign>təpas</foreign>), one with another. [It] is called ‘adultery of the seating place’. Standing face to face by the side of the house, in the yard, one with another. It is called ‘adultery of the yard’. Answering someone who coughs, who is clearing the throat, who is expectorating, especially someone else’s mother’s song. It is called ‘the roaring cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgala</foreign>). Resting on the place where the other one has sat — on a post, on a tree, on a stone — [after] seeing her having gotten up then replacing them to lean, that is called ‘the rubbing cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgasir</foreign>). Those should be remembered, if we want to free ourselves from hell. </p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#skk_05.02">And also joining together in one lodging, one residence, one shelter, one couch, with someone else’s women, with forbidden women of someone else; it is called ‘the buffalo in one pen’ (<foreign>kəbo sapitunahan</foreign>). Those are the things to be kept in mind. They are called forbidden acts.</p>
              <p n="3" corresp="#skk_05.03">In the same way, if we are going on a journey, we shouldn’t [do that], shouldn’t desire to be followed by the servants of someone else. If we desire to take them, we should ask their master. If they are trusted [servants], [we should] make an oath (as to our liability) for their sickness, for their death, for their loss, [for their] passing  away and dying, in any way whatsoever. If that [be the case], we should take [them]. There is no one who may be blamed, for an oath is more eminent than [written] law (<foreign>agama</foreign>). If they are not trusted [servants], then we should not! If we insist on taking them, we should help them when they are sick, we should redeem them individually (? <foreign>sakadǝgdǝgna</foreign>) if they are dead or lost. All of that should be taken into account. </p>
          </div>
          
          <div corresp="#skk_06">
              <p n="1" corresp="#skk_06.01">Further, as follows: if we are visited by the <foreign>same</foreign>, <foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>dasa</foreign>, <foreign>calagara</foreign>, <foreign>upəti</foreign> <foreign>paṅgərəs rəma</foreign>, our thoughts should be cheerful, we should feel as though being visited by family, relatives, younger and elder siblings, children, friends, children of younger siblings (<foreign>suvan</foreign>), children of elder siblings (<foreign>kaponakan</foreign>). That is the metaphor for it. But if we have things to share, [such as] food, drink, blankets, clothes [or] anything that we own, we should feel as though making offerings and giving reception to the ancestors and gods.</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#skk_06.02">Moreover, if we are employed [to go] to the dry rice field, to the paddy field, to the great paddy field (<foreign>seraṅ agəṅ</foreign>); fencing, digging a trench, putting animals into the pen, making snares, dam fishing, fishing with a casting net, fishing with a line (?, <foreign>ṅadodoger</foreign>), fishing with drag-net (<foreign>mapayaṅ</foreign>), fishing with a sieve (<foreign>ñair</foreign>), ensnaring animals by two people (? <foreign>biñcaṅ</foreign>) — any kind of employment for the master, we should not be displeased, we should not be temperamental, we should not be angry or fuss. We should enjoy it all. We should mean our tasks. </p> 
          </div>
          
          <div corresp="#skk_07">
              <p n="1" corresp="#skk_07.01">However, if we are returning home, we should not defecate on the edge of the road, by the side of the house, on its bright end, as it may be smelled by a nobleman [or] by a gusti, not to mention by people who do not pay attention; as it may be that [we] are cursed [and] blamed by [our] mother, father [and] teachers, be opposed by the elders, because of our reckless deeds. But if [we] obey the holy precepts, [we] defecate seven steps from the road [and] urinate three steps from the road. May [we] not meet with criticism from other people, as we know <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign>. The meaning is: <foreign>ulah</foreign> means sorrow, <foreign>pamali</foreign> means death.</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#skk_07.02">Furthermore, [we should] watch out for rope barriers (<foreign>gagavar</foreign>), the ends of snares (? <foreign>pucuk tambaluṅ</foreign>), as they could be court reservoirs, forbidden enclosures, forbidden pavilions — all the more so for obstructing light, for coming across [or] passing the king [when he is] walking about, because those are the places where offense is liable to happen.  If we enter the court, we must often look [in all directions], as it may be that we are trampling, bumping, hitting [or] cutting a line.</p> 
              <p n="3" corresp="#skk_07.03">If we sit down, we should not face the wrong way; we should cross our legs politely. And if we are invited to speak by the master, we should think about what we will say. Whatever is appropriate will please the master. And we should pay close attention to the ones who are to be followed: officer, gusti, military officer (<foreign>kasasa</foreign>), member of the <foreign>bayangkara</foreign> corps, confidant (<foreign>nu marək</foreign>), messenger, painter, coppersmith, goldsmith, bracelet smith, blacksmith, make up expert (? <foreign>juru vidaṅ</foreign>), actor, puppeteer, trumpeter, gamelan musician, mask performer (<foreign>tapukan</foreign>), joker, dry rice field farmer, palm tapper, paddy farmer, sweeper, death-defier (<foreign>belamati</foreign>), magician (? <foreign>juru moha</foreign>), barat katiga, soldier, blowpiper, archer, warrior, collector of <foreign>dasa</foreign> and <foreign>calagara</foreign> (penalties), young shepherds, boar farmers, chicken farmers, fishermen, divers, [and] all those who are of use. If there are any ones who have the virtue of fidelity in service, it is they who are to be followed, for they dedicate themselves to the country.</p>
          </div>
          
           <div corresp="#skk_08">
                                <p corresp="#skk_08.01">If there is someone scolded by the master — such a one, his actions should not be followed, as we might also be scolded. This is an analogy for it: like a person going into the forest, who steps on a thorn, let’s step on it too, it hurts in the same way. That is why, if there is someone who is praised as the agile, the nimble, the sensitive and generous, frugal, conscientious, diligent, painstaking, faithful to the service of the master — follow the acts and the qualities of such a one, so that we too may be praised!</p>
                 <p corresp="#skk_08.02">If there is someone whose appearance is good, whose behavior is good [and] whose actions are good, we should follow as best as possible (<foreign>saagəṅna</foreign>), because he is considered a superior man.</p>
                  <p corresp="#skk_08.03">If there is someone whose appearance is beautiful [but] whose actions are bad [and] whose attitude is dumb, in that case (<foreign>itu</foreign>) we should not look at his appearance, we should not follow his actions.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_08.04">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb [but] whose actions are good, in that case we should not look at his attitude, we should not keep looking at his appearance, we should follow his actions.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_08.05">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb, whose actions are bad, in that case [he] is what they call ‘the sacrifice of the world, the substitute for the people of the whole world’, the defect of human beings.</p>
                  <p corresp="#skk_08.06">That is what should be remembered — the unmeritorious, the meritorious; the bad, the good — take [them as] teacher. This is the reminder of it: if anyone dies while stealing, dies while sneaking, dies while robbing, dies while infiltrating, any kind of impudent [or] deceptive [behavior], we should watch them for [they] are not to be followed. That is called the vile as teacher.</p>
                 <p corresp="#skk_08.07">There is more: if we see people performing <foreign>wayang</foreign>, listen to people performing <foreign>pantun</foreign>, acquire teachings from the stories, that is called the stage as teacher. If we acquire good teachings from people reading, that is called the story as teacher. If we observe the products of handicraft: carvings, sculptures, planks, drawings, we should not ask the craftsmen — we should find out by our own feelings, as a result of paying attention to other people’s skill. It is called profession as teacher.</p>
                  <p corresp="#skk_08.08">Acquiring precepts from children, it is called children as teachers. Acquiring dharma from our grandfather, it is called the grandfather as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our elder brother (<foreign>lañcək</foreign>), it is called the elder brother (<foreign>kakaṅ</foreign>) as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from the elders, it is called our parents’ elder siblings (<foreign>uva</foreign>) as teachers. Acquiring rules of conduct from the places where we travel, (whether it is) in the village, in a place for staying overnight, in a place for breaking journey, in a place of lodging, it is called the road as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our parents, it is called the origins as teacher. Especially if (you find rules of conduct in) words (<foreign>hatur</foreign>) from a great scholar, it is called the excellence as teacher, it is called honor as teacher, it is called authority as teacher, it is called doctrines as teacher: those are called the four excellences (<foreign>catur-utama</foreign>). Which is why, when they are finished being done by those who do, being accomplished by those who accomplish, (then) all are finished being observed: the bad and the good, the evil and the just.</p>
               </div>
          
                        <div corresp="#skk_09">
                        
                    <p corresp="#skk_09.01">Likewise, if there is someone who praises us, our feelings should not be joyful, [but] we should in turn cast back [the praise] to those who praise, so that we will not be overshadowed by the other’s praise. If we are keen on being praised, it is like the ‘long pole with weak extensions (<foreign>galah dava sinambuṅan tuna</foreign>)’. [If our] feelings are pleased with the praise, then it leads to vanity. Because we feel ourselves to be in our own house — by food, drink, pleasures, enjoyments, utensils (<foreign>pakaraṅ</foreign>) — then they are used as something to be proud of (<foreign>aṅgəhan</foreign>). It is like the ‘long pole’ (as above); it is [also] like the ‘empty paddy stalk’.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_09.02">Likewise, if there is someone who insults us, we should accept all the other’s insults, which is why it is comparable to the ‘pole cut short’. Suppose we have warts, it is like water for bathing; suppose we have dry skin, it is like a person coming to smearing [us] with oil; suppose we are hungry, it is like a person coming to give rice; suppose we are thirsty, it is like a person coming to give to drink; suppose we are dejected, it is like a person coming to give betel quid — they are called the five pure ones (<foreign>pañca-parisuda</foreign>). That is like the ‘pole cut short’.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_09.03">If [the insult] makes us happy, [we are] like paddy chock full [with rice grains], that might keep the people alive, because the origin of joy and pleasure has been obtained. Even if those who are slandering us are wrong, [we should] take [their slander as] advice. If we have the behavior (about which we are slandered), [we should] stop [it]. If we do not have [such] behavior, we should consider (<foreign>uṅaṅ</foreign>) [the slander] (to merit attention), like mother, father [and] teachers. The meaning of what is called a human being (<foreign>janma</foreign>): ‘It is considered the ultimate supreme; it is considered the deity becoming human; the one who has a perfect body, who is the origin of goodness, and the source of the truth.’
</p>
          </div>
        <div>
        
                  <p corresp="#skk_10.01">This is the enhancement of action, so that no living beings are ruined, so that [we are] blessed in our houses: generous [and] conscientious, scrupulous [and] diligent, sensitive (*<foreign>paka</foreign>) [and] generous (*<foreign>prədana</foreign>), not falling down (? <foreign>mo rogol-rogol</foreign>), champions among experts, strong [and] unfatigued, mobile [and] nimble.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_10.02">If we put dry rice-fields (<foreign>gaga</foreign>) and paddy fields under cultivation, it is only so that we do not suffer. If we make an orchard, it is only so that we do not pick in someone else’s small field, in someone else’s broad field — except by virtue of our having asked permission, politely requesting. [As for] domestic animals, we should not just buy, not just swap [them]. [As for] utensils, we should not just borrow [them]. [As for] blankets [and] loincloths, we should not have too many of them. [As for] food and drink, we should not have too little. Our children and wife should be given advice, to avoid [their] being accused of being ‘disrespectful’ (<foreign>durbala siksa</foreign>).</p>
                <p corresp="#skk_10.03">Observe the hermits’ precepts for society: if we sleep, [it is only] as a remedy for sleepiness; [if we] drink palm wine, [it is only] as a remedy for thirst; [if we] eat, [it is only] a remedy for hunger. We should not be careless [about them]. We should remember their [potential] absence. Even more so by children and by wife, we should not be shackled, for they may not behave in accordance [with our advice]. If [they are] good, by virtue of us giving advice, after which [they] follow the advice, those are called our children and our wife. If they do not follow [our] admonition, they are the same as outsiders. But if we insist on claiming our wife and child despite them being away without giving any news, we will probably be burdened, we will probably be lost in hell together, lost [will be] the results of our worship, ruined the results of the ancestors (<foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>).</p>
            </div>
          
                    <div corresp="#skk_11">
                    
                            <p corresp="#skk_11.01">This is the instruction of Darma Pitutur, to avoid our not thinking of [the law and admonitions]. </p>


                    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.02"/>  
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.03">The meaning is: <foreign>sri</foreign> means gold. Gold is like this: If it is not coated, its beauty is washed away. If it is coated, [it will be] beautifully bright for it is well treated. Likewise is the analogy, for us humans here: if [we] follow the holy precepts, its essence will be well maintained by us, like the straight meeting its straight. Likewise, if we do not follow the holy precepts of the accomplished one, [it is] like the crooked meeting its crooked. </p>
                      <p corresp="#skk_11.04"><foreign>Paesan</foreign> means mirror. The mirror is like this: If it is not regarded attentively, our image is vague. If it is regarded attentively, our appearance is clear upon that mirror. Likewise are we humans here. If we can follow the customs of others adequately, it may well be internalized by our feelings. If we cannot follow the advice, it is called stupid.</p>
                      <p corresp="#skk_11.05"><foreign>Jambaṅan</foreign> means an object giving reflection. The mind of the one who is accomplished is like clear water. That is the reason why we should regard [it] attentively, then the heart will be pleased.</p>
                      <p corresp="#skk_11.06">Desa means settlement. If the settlement  is empty, there is nothing to be followed. Words are like that: if they are not substantial, they are considered obscene. But if the residence is filled, <foreign>that</foreign> is to be followed. Likewise are words: they should be meaningful, so that they be considered truthful in character.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.07">Likewise are we humans here. If we wish to know the source of the joy and happiness, we should remember the word of the Darma Pitutur. This is the verse:</p>

                    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.08">‘The pond is the habitat of the goose; the forest is the elephant’s habitat; the sea is the habitat of fishes; flowers are the habitat of the bee.’</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_11.09">The meaning is: if we are going to imitate behavior (<foreign>cəta</foreign>), we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about the clear pond, fresh water, [we should] ask the goose. The meaning is: if there is a person who is firm in steering, whose mind is clear, [and] whose heart is pleasant, that is indeed comparable to the goose on the clear pond. </p>
                        <p corresp="#skk_11.10">If we seek to know about the depth of the sea, [we should] ask a fish. The meaning is: like the man who knows about the mind of the divine king and about the mind of the great scholar. </p>
                        <p corresp="#skk_11.11">If we seek to know about the remoteness of  forests, [we should] ask the elephant. This is its meaning: what is comparable to the remote forest is knowing other people’s minds; what is comparable to the elephant is the power of Majesty the king. </p>
                      <p corresp="#skk_11.12">If we seek to know about the fragrance and sweetness of flowers, [we should] ask the bee. The meaning is: what is comparable to the bee is the skillful man, who is wandering, roaming, [so that he] knows other people’s habits. What is comparable to the fragrant flower is the person who has good conduct, sweet baruṅusan, smiling expression, pleasing attitude.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.13">The meaning is: we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about every kind of story, such as Darma Jati, Saṅ Hyaṅ Hayu, Jayasena, Sedamana, Kuñjarakarna, Ramayana, Adiparva, Koravasrama, Bima Sorga, Raṅga Lave, Boma, Sumana, Kala-Purbaka, Jarini, Tantri, all types of stories, [we should] ask the performer (memen).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.14">If we seek to know about all kinds of songs (<foreign>kavih</foreign>): songs for the elderly, long songs, amusement songs, advice songs, allusive songs, <foreign>peṅpeledan</foreign> songs, rafter hole (<foreign>boṅboṅ kaso</foreign>) [songs], pore rane [songs], sword-grass track (<foreign>porod әrih</foreign>) [songs], <foreign>babahanan</foreign> songs, bearish (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>) songs, <foreign>taṅtuṅ</foreign> songs, lament songs, dancing songs, all types of songs, [we should] ask the virtuoso (<foreign>para guna</foreign>).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.15">If we seek to know about the jesters (<foreign>para macəh</foreign>): the performance of a jester (<foreign>cәta macәh</foreign>), the performance of a buffoon (<foreign>mirus</foreign>), the mask show (<foreign>tatapukan</foreign>), the bear show (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>), <foreign>bakutrak</foreign> show (<foreign>babakutrakan</foreign>), <foreign>abaṅ-abaṅan</foreign> (?), swallowing a pointed bamboo (<foreign>nәrәy pañcaṅ</foreign>), hiding [something and causing it to] disappear (<foreign>munikәn ləbur</foreign>), the pounding block competition (<foreign>ṅadu ləsuṅ</foreign>), entering the <foreign>lantar</foreign> (?), the competition of elder women (<foreign>ṅadu nini</foreign>), all kinds of amusement, [we should] ask the actor (<foreign>hәmpul</foreign>). </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.16">If we seek to know about pantuns [such as] Laṅga Laraṅ, Bañak Catra, Sili Vaṅi, Hatur Vaṅi, [we should] ask the <foreign>pantun</foreign> bard.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.17">As for all kinds of decorative patterns (<foreign>tulis</foreign>) [such as] <foreign>pupuñjəṅan</foreign>, <foreign>hihiṅgulan</foreign>, flowers motifs, the forest motif, the shrimp motif (<foreign>uraṅ-uraṅan</foreign>), <foreign>mәmәtahan</foreign>, <foreign>sisiraṅan</foreign>, <foreign>taruk hata</foreign>, lotus flower, any kind of decorative pattern, [we should] ask the painter (<foreign>lukis</foreign>). </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.18">As for all kinds of forging, the three weapons are what differentiates them. As for the weapons for the king, they are sword, whip (? <foreign>abət</foreign>), cleaver (<foreign>golok</foreign>), stabbing knife (<foreign>peso təndət</foreign>), kris. The Raksasas are their deities, for they are utensils to kill everything. As for the weapons of the peasants, they are machete (<foreign>kujaṅ</foreign>), hatchet (<foreign>baliuṅ</foreign>), big axe (<foreign>patik</foreign>), weeding hook (<foreign>kored</foreign>), tapping [knife] (<foreign>sadap</foreign>). The Detyas are their deities, for they are utensils to obtain things to eat and things to drink. As for the weapons of the scholar (<foreign>pandita</foreign>), they are the [betelnut] cutter (<foreign>kalakatri</foreign>), whittling knife (<foreign>peso raut</foreign>), <foreign>doṅdaṅ</foreign> knife, <foreign>paṅot</foreign> knife, spike (<foreign>pakisi</foreign>). The Danavas are their deities, for they are utensils to cut everything. That is, once again, why the three weapons are differentiated: for the king, for the peasant, for the scholar. Thus, if we wish to know all of that, [we should] ask the blacksmith (<foreign>panday</foreign>).</p>
                            
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.19">As for all kinds of carvings: made like snakes, made like bears, modeled after birds, modeled after monkeys, modeled after lions — every kind of carving, [we should] ask the scabbard carver (<foreign>maraṅguy</foreign>).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.20">All kinds of preparations: <foreign>ñupar-ñapir</foreign>, rara mandi, make cobek (<foreign>ñocobek</foreign>), <foreign>ñopoṅ koneṅ</foreign>, ñaṅlarkәn, ñarəṅsәṅ, ñәsәṅit, ñayaṅ ku pədəs, roasting (<foreign>bәbәləman</foreign>), grilling (<foreign>papaṅgaṅan</foreign>), <foreign>kakasian</foreign> (?), mincing (<foreign>hahañaṅan</foreign>), mixing (<foreign>raramәsan</foreign>), perfuming (<foreign>diruruum</foreign>), sweetening (<foreign>diamis-amis</foreign>) — every kind of preparation, [we should] ask a <foreign>harəp catra</foreign>.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.21">All kinds of (woven) textile: candlenut flower (<foreign>kәmbaṅ muñcaṅ</foreign>), <foreign>seṅgaṅ</foreign>’s stem (gagaṅ seṅgaṅ), moon-alike (same leg), group of səmat (sәmat sahurun), añam cayut, sigәji, pasi-pasi, kalaṅkaṅ ayakan, poleṅ raganis, jayanti, cәcәmpaan, paparanakan, maṅin haris, siliganti, boeh siaṅ, bәbәr natan, papakanan, surat avi, parigi ñeṅsoh, gagañjar, lusiyan bәsar, kampuh jayanti, hujan riris, laris, boeh alus, ragen paṅanten — every kind of textile, [we should] ask the weaver (paṅәyәk).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.22">If we seek to know about all kinds of laws: <foreign>acara</foreign> is under <foreign>adigama</foreign>, <foreign>adigama</foreign> is under teacher’s doctrines (<foreign>gurugama</foreign>), teacher’s doctrines are under elders’ doctrines (tuhagama), elders’ doctrines are under approval (<foreign>satmata</foreign>), approval is under public outcry (<foreign>surak loka</foreign>), public outcry is under court proceedings (<foreign>vicara</foreign>). High people, external guilt, external people, high guilt — every kind of law, [we should] ask the <foreign>tanda</foreign>s. </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.23">If we seek to know about the strategies of war: makara formation, chariot formation, linsang formation, lion formation, garuda formation, wheel formation, needle point (<foreign>suci-muka</foreign>), diamond-cage (<foreign>bajra-pañjara</foreign>), surrounding dog (<foreign>asu maliput</foreign>), grazing peacock (<foreign>mərak simpir</foreign>), tailless crow (?, <foreign>gagak saṅkur</foreign>), descending civet (<foreign>luvak maturun</foreign>), climbing deer (<foreign>kidaṅ suməṅka</foreign>), crocodile hole (<foreign>babah buhaya</foreign>), taking the liṅga jewel form (<foreign>ṅaliṅga manik</foreign>), the encompassed land (<foreign>ləmah mrəvasa</foreign>), ruling (<foreign>adipati</foreign>), dominating power (<foreign>prabu-sakti</foreign>), the application of war and battle, the effort of <foreign>sapətrik</foreign> (?) — [we should] ask the commander (hulu jurit).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.24">If we seek to know about of all kinds formulas and mantras:  remedies (<foreign>jampa-jampiya</foreign>), restoring consciousness (?, <foreign>gәgәiṅ</foreign>), diagrams (?, <foreign>susuratan</foreign>), protections (<foreign>sasaranaan</foreign>), distance vision (? <foreign>kaseraṅan</foreign>), <foreign>pavayagahan</foreign>, (mantras) with flowers (? <foreign>pupuspaan</foreign>), purification mantras (<foreign>susudaan</foreign>), life giving mantras (?, <foreign>hurip-huripan</foreign>), <foreign>tunduk iyәm</foreign>, astrological formulas (<foreign>pararasen</foreign>), gnomon (<foreign>pasaṅkvan</foreign>), — every kind of sacred formula, [we should] ask the brahmana. </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.25">If we seek to know about making offerings in the shrine (<foreign>saṅgar</foreign>): the arrangement, the leaf offering, <foreign>palajaṅ</foreign> offering, flower offering, putting a cloth on liṅga, maintenance of deities — every kind of offering, [we should] ask the <foreign>jaṅgan</foreign>.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.26">If we seek to know about the descent of time, month of the quake, year without neck, [year] without head, walking world, immobile world, buried earth, earth quake — every kind of knowledge of ancient accounts (<foreign>carek bəhəla</foreign>), [we should] ask the <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.27">If we seek to know about the precepts of the dharma (<foreign>darma-siksa</foreign>), the precepts of the community (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), becoming an ascetic (<foreign>pasuk tapa</foreign>), the meditation (?, <foreign>padonaan</foreign>), the very pure (act?) (mahapavitra), the precepts of the teacher, the ten virtues (<foreign>dasa-sila</foreign>), the five teachings (<foreign>pañca-siksa</foreign>), foot sole of the teacher (<foreign>guru-talapakan</foreign>), misfortune of the world (jagat-upadrava), four powers (cadu-sakti), the reality of the world (<foreign>tato buvana</foreign>), the reality of the body (<foreign>tato sarira</foreign>), the reality of knowledge (<foreign>tato ajñana</foreign>) — every kind of contents of the books, [we should] ask the scholar. </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.28">In the first place the blessings (kasorgaan) in the manifest world: the kingship, the nobility, the eminence, the authority, the supremacy, [we should] ask the king. </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.29">If we seek to know about the organization of land: protecting the land, consulting all people, ordering [or] discussing, cutting and trimming on a level, measuring and making equal, fining and punishing. If it is highland, it is made to be flat, headland is made to be equal (with the shore?), all kinds of dependent villages (? <foreign>ampih-ampih</foreign>), we should ask the Maṅkubumi.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.30">If we seek to know about all sorts of anchorages, especially sandbanks (<foreign>gosoṅ</foreign>), channels (<foreign>goroṅ</foreign>), <foreign>kabua</foreign> (?), ripples from all directions (<foreign>ryak mokprok</foreign>), deceitful ripples (<foreign>ryak maliṅ</foreign>), big waves (<foreign>alun aguṅ</foreign>), headlands (<foreign>tañjuṅ</foreign>), promontories (<foreign>hujuṅ</foreign>), islands (<foreign>nusa</foreign>), islets (<foreign>pulo</foreign>), barrier reefs (<foreign>karaṅ nuṅgul</foreign>), south-easterly [winds] (<foreign>tuṅgara</foreign>), south-westerly [winds] (<foreign>barat daya</foreign>), all kinds of sea travel [and] sailing, [we should] ask the sea captain (<foreign>puhavaṅ</foreign>).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.31">If we seek to know about all kinds of prices: three million, three hundred thousand, thirty thousand, three thousand, six hundred, three hundred, thirty all the more so a half (<foreign>karo bəlah</foreign>), a third (<foreign>katәlu bәlah</foreign>), a quarter (<foreign>kapat bәlah</foreign>), a fifth (<foreign>kalima bәlah</foreign>), a sixth (kanәm bәlah), a seventh (<foreign>kapitu bәlah</foreign>), an eighth (<foreign>kavolu bәlah</foreign>), a ninth (<foreign>kasaṅa bәlah</foreign>) — every kind of price, [we should] ask the citrik byapari.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.32">If we seek to know about the esoteric sciences (sandhi), asceticism, posture, direct perception, detachment, epitome, liberation, ancestor metaphysics, deity metaphysics, elemental accounts, epochal accounts — every kind of deity metaphysics, [we should] ask the hermits of the people (<foreign>viku para loka</foreign>).</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_11.33">If one wants to act, we should not ask the wrong person. If we seek to know about the languages of various countries — the languages of China (cina), South India (kәliṅ), Persia (parasi), Egypt (mәsir), Samudra, Bengal (baṅgala), Makassar, Pahang, Palembang, Siam, Kelantan (kalatәn), Bangka, Buvun, Betәn, Tulang Bawang, Sela, Pasai (pasay), Pariaman (parayaman), Deccan Canyon (? ṅara dәkan), Dinah (?), Andalas (andәləs), Tego, Moluccas (moloko), Bandan (badan), Bago (pego), Minangkabau (malaṅkabo), Mecca, Buretet, Lawai (lave), Sasak (saksak), Sumbawa (sәmbava), Bali, Jәṅgi, Nusa Bini (sabini), Ogan (ṅogan), Kanaṅәn, Komering (kumәriṅ), Sampaṅ Tiga, Gumantuṅ, Manubi, Bubu, Ñiri, Sapari, Patukangan, Surabaya, Lampung, India (jambudipa), Seram (?, seran), Kedah (gәdah), Salaut (?, solot), Solodoṅ, Indragiri, Tanjuṅpura, Sakampuṅ, Atas Aṅin, Campa (cәmpa), Baluk, Java — all kinds of countries, [we should] ask the interpreter darma-murcaya.</p>
                    </div>

<div corresp="#skk_12">

                            <p corresp="#skk_12.01">That is what should be known, as to their reliability and appropriateness. If there is one who says that he does not know, he is one who is not faithful to his own function, is very ignorant as to the words of our Gods, does not fear misfortune (upadrava), the cycle of world (jagat-ganti) [and] the four powers (cadu-sakti) of the scholar. [He] is certainly awaited by the cauldron.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_12.02">Regarding the works, they should not be performed; regarding the actions, they should not be carried out — except (sahiṅaniṅ) virtuous works, for that is the thread of the ancestors [and] the thread of the gods, the memorial of the Lord of the world, when He made the unmanifest world prosperous. When Brahma, Visnu, Isora, Mahadeva, Siva are devoted to the Lord; when Indra, Yama, Baruna, Kovera, Besavarna are devoted to the Lord; when Kusika, Garga, Mestri, Purusa, Patanjala are devoted to the Lord — [when] all of the gods together are devoted to Lord Seda Niskala, [then] all of them find the one who is true with direct perception.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_12.03">This is what must be found in the manifest world, the thread of the Lord for the world, so that [we are] firm in becoming ‘jewels in one cage’ (? manik sakuruṅan); so that the whole world is shining: the servant is devoted to his master, the wife is devoted to her husband, the child is devoted to his father, the pupil is devoted to his teacher, the mantri is devoted to the maṅkubumi, maṅkubumi is devoted to the king, the king is devoted to the Gods. They are ordered to stabilize their bodies, directing the breath, the speech [and] the mind. </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_12.04">If those [actions] are not performed and [not] carried out by the humans, of low, middle, and high class, each of them is thrown into the cauldron called ‘Bull Headed Copper [Cauldron]’. Because the human is overpowered by the Gods. Pun.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_12.05">Darma Pitutur spoke, reporting the words of the precursors: There is another comparison, like [when] we went to Java, [we] are unable to follow its language and its manners, we felt confused. After [we] returned home to Sunda, we were unable to speak Javanese. It felt as if we had not come [back] from a journey, what we bought as a result of visiting was worthless, because of inability to follow its language.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_12.06">That is how we are, as humans, continually descending from the unmanifest, [but] not finding the manners of the Gods, rushing to be incarnated as humans, because their appearance is silly, their behavior is ignorant, [and they are] incapable of following the acts of the ones who know. There are acts committed that are unfaithful, that are improper. [They] start to do evil, to trespass, to have affairs in secret (bubunyan) with younger and older relatives. That is why a woman enjoying a man who is not her husband is considered improper; a man enjoying a woman who is not his wife (? əsi imahna) is [likewise] considered improper. [They] are liable to be thrown into the cauldron called ‘The Victorious Deer’ (Si Mrəga Vijaya), because humans prefer what is wrong.</p>
</div>

<div corresp="#skk_13">

        <p corresp="#skk_13.01">These are the symbolic terms (siloka) for the behavior of wrong people: lawless (buraṅkak), anxious (? marende), sulky (mariris), shameful (viraṅ). They are called the four demons. The meaning is: buraṅkak means shuddering. What is horrifying, as it were, is the behavior of the person who is envious, surly, staring, coarse (?, gasoṅ), rude in speech, ugly in behavior, hot of heart. [Such behavior] is considered improper. That is what the behavior of such men is like, horrifying as it were. He becomes a demon, Durga, Durgi, the demon Kala. His place is in the dirt of the earth. </p>

        <p corresp="#skk_13.02">The dirty soils are: hollows, clusters (? saroṅge), lime-stone cliffs (cadas gantuṅ), scattered stones, gorges, swamps, rhinoceros ponds, tree trunks upside down and aslant (cataṅ nuṅgaṅ cataṅ noṅgeṅ), mine tunnels (garuṅguṅan gareṅgeṅan), dangerous lands (saṅhar), burning grounds, watery lands (varian), hillocks, ‘male’ soils, pigsties, gutters, rubbish dumps, cremation grounds (səma) — every kind of avoided soil. </p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_13.03">What those who are obstinate in their ugly behaviors become is like that, because the behavior of men is what gives horror. They become every sort of horrifying thing, because they do not follow the holy instruction of accomplishment, because they transgress the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society. That is why they become horrifying. That is the meaning of buraṅkak.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_13.04">Marende means: being cooled down and yet feeling hot; being given pity, being given sympathy, being taken care of, being coddled, being given pleasures [and] enjoyments, servants [and] slaves, and yet mistrusting [them]. It is clear that he is affected by the misery of which the field [called] the Patana is full. Its length is one yojana. In the east is the Sword Tree. One hundred thousand men are struck [by its swords] there. In the south is the Stone Mountain. One hundred thousand evil men are suffering there together. In the west are the Fire-Headed ghosts. Humans cannot fathom how much suffering is there. In the north, there are one hundred people suffering together there, like grass-hoppers on a skewer. In the middle is the crow of the Patana, with the Dog ghosts. Thousands of evil people are suffering there. That is the misery of those called marende.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_13.05">Mariris means defiled, disgusting like excrement, defiled like a reeking carcass. Such is the conduct of people who are kleptomaniac, who seize indiscriminately, or even take indiscriminately, without asking, stealing, plundering, deceiving, pilfering — all kinds of lying to good persons. When he dies, his soul will suffer, for one thousand [and] one hundred years afflicted by the curse of the gods. That’s why birth as a human is not in sight. As for what he becomes: koter, jaṅgel, crop-worm, horse-fly, titiṅgi, jambəloṅ, leatherleaf slug, mear, pacet (blood sucking haemadipsa), leech, ləhəṅ, gərəṅ — everything that is despised by people in general, that is what is called mariris.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_13.06">Disgrace (viraṅ) means unwilling to be sincere, unwilling to truthful, unwilling to be proper, unwilling to be frank, unwilling to be polite. If his harən, passion, love [or] astonishment or obscene, [then] when he dies, his soul will meet with suffering, [i.e] a wobbly bridge, a slanting plank bridge, clashing stones. When they are made into being in the world, they become everything that is horrifying: rhinoceros, tiger, crocodile, great snake, everything that is horrifying. That is called disgrace (viraṅ).  So much for the four demons. </p>

</div>
          
<div corresp="#skk_14">

        <p corresp="#skk_14.01">This is like a man who travels to China, spends a long time in China. [He] knows Chinese customs, Chinese habits, Chinese language, Chinese manners, Chinese etiquette. [He] meets with three [levels] of language, [namely] low, middle, and high. [He] knows all about the speech of the king, the elder, and the hermit; is able to direct the breath, the speech, and the mind. That is the reason why [he] knows about the consciousness (gəiṅ), the higher consciousness (upagəiṅ), the ultimate consciousness (parigəiṅ). They are called the three forms of consciousness. </p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_14.02">Consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to taste, to drink, [and] being able to have pleasure; that is called consciousness. What is called higher consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to dress, able to wear clothes, able to wear a lower garment, able to wear festive attire; that is called higher consciousness. What is called ultimate consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to instruct, able to command, because his speech is sweet [and] fragrant, such that the one who is commanded does not become angry, because he is touched by the impact of one who applies suitable words (siloka).</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_14.03">If his words (basana) are [addressed] to a youngster, [he addresses him or her as] ‘boy’ (utun), ‘girl’ (eten), ‘baby’ (orok), ‘my child’, ‘my little sibling’. [If they are addressed] to an elder, [he addresses him or her as] ‘my elder brother’, ‘my elder nephew or niece’, ‘my elder sister’, ‘my senior’, and ‘my grandfather’. His exclamations are: are ‘be well!’ (sumaṅər), ‘what a pity!’ (tətəiṅ amat). As numerous are the ten pacifying acts, namely: being virtuous, reverent (nama), sympathetic, forgiving, loving, compassionate, generous, gentle, tranquil, ingratiating. That is why someone who is given an order is happy [and] joyful, bright [and] shining. That is called the ultimate consciousness.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_14.04">These are the metaphors for it: gold, silver, jewel, diamond. They are called the four holy courtesies. This is its meaning: gold means the speech which is right, accurate, clear, the formula of five syllables. Silver means the mind which is accomplished, proper, good. Jewel means his consciousness is bright [and] shining, wide [and] broad. Diamond means cheerfully laughing, visibly smiling, pleasant of heart. They are called the four courtesies. </p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_14.05">They are the people who originate from the pure ones among lands. The pure ones among lands are the offering place, the wrapping place (? pabuntəlan), the worship place, the sturdy house (? imah manəh), the sanctuary, the temple tower, the liṅga, the statue, the gong-like stone (batu gaṅsa), land with statues, where human figures are created [and] sweeping [is performed]. So many are all lands which are maintained, waters that are strained [and] purified. It is indeed a good person, a kind person. He is an accomplished person. The one who is considered to originate from the pure ones among lands is aware of the holy precepts, heeding the advice of mother, father, grandfather and great-grandfather, knowing the teachings of the great scholars, upholding the words of the accomplished ones.</p>

</div>

<div corresp="#skk_15">
             
                <p corresp="#skk_15.01">This is the account of the ancient ones who instated the holy instructions of the accomplished ones: the deified ancestor Déwaraja, the deified ancestor Rawung Langit, the deified ancestor at Medang, the deified ancestor at Menir. They are called the four accomplished ones. That is why in the present, men who are aware of the holy supreme dharma, knowledgeable about the secret teachings of men, they are called the esoteric men.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_15.02">If they die, their soul will find a beautiful heaven, finding daytime that does not turn into night, joy that does not turn into sorrow, heaven that does not turn into into hell, pleasure that does not turn into pain, good that does not turn into into bad, fortunate that does not turn into unfortunate, subtle that does not turn into gross, being gone that does not turn into being present, ancestors that do not turn into gods. That is what is called the supreme liberation.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_16">
             
                    <p corresp="#skk_16.01">Likewise are the people in the present. Compare us taking a bath, the choices of the water to be touched by us are only two: the one which is turbid and the one which is clear. Likewise are the behaviors of people, two (types) being put into practice: the bad and the good. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated badly is that bad behavior of theirs. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated well is that good behavior of theirs. That is why people are bad by their behavior, why they are good by their behavior.</p>

                    <p corresp="#skk_16.02">Water is like that, insofar as the choices of it are said to be two. Water that is refreshing and clear is the holy supreme dharma, that is what is practiced by the great scholars. Water that is haunted and turbid is the emotional conduct (rasa-carita), which is practiced by all the vikus for whom the highest truth is worldly. That is why it (i.e., water) is comparable to consciousness as well as unconsciousness. Consciousness is aware and mindful of memories without turning into forgetfulness. It is the root of a favorable rebirth, the cause of a prosperous earth. Unconsciousness is forgetfulness [and] confusion, not endowed with memory. It is the cause of destruction, the starting point of the Kali era, the base of deviation, the root of falsehood. It is the cause of people going to hell. That should not be taken as truth by those who wish to be sincere.</p>
</div>

<div corresp="#skk_17">
             
                <p corresp="#skk_17.01">These are the words of the holy man, when he beautified his substance. These are the three threads in the world. Your breath is the ruler, your speech is the elders, your mind is the hermit. Those are the three causes of continuity in the world, which is claimed as the support of the world. 
</p>
                <p corresp="#skk_17.02">This is the three classes in the world: Viṣṇu is comparable with the king, Brahmā is comparable to the elder, Iśvara is comparable to the hermit. The reason why the three causes of continuity as a support of the world, the three classes as the life of the world, [for] those are considered as the three continuity for all people. Hold it up, straighten [them] until they become straight, true, evident, present. The reason why the world is prosperous, why the earth is preserved, is because the actions of men are truthful.</p>
    
                 <p corresp="#skk_17.03">Like that: the scholars firm in their scholarship will be successful; the ascetic firm in their ascetic values will be successful; the manguyus firm in their manguyu-ship will be successful; the paliken firm in their paliken-ship will be successful; male monks firm in their male-monaster-ship will be successful; the wanderers firm in their wanderership will be successful; the vasi ascetic firm in their vasi-ship will be successful; the nun firm in their nunship will be successful; the tiagi ascetic firm in their tiagi-ship will be successful; let alone the ascetic disciple (?, valaka) firm in their valaka-ship will be successful; the peasant firm in their peasantship will be successful; the thief firm in their thiefship will be successful; the noble gusti firm in their gusti-ship will be successful; the minister firm in their ministership will be successful; the gambler (?, saṅ masaṅ) firm in their gamblership will be successful; the disciples firm in their discipleship will be successful; seamen firm in their seamanship will be successful; disis firm in their disi-ship will be successful; the elders firm in their eldership will be successful; the hermits firm in their hermitship will be successful; the king firm in their kingship will be successful, especially the scholars and the divine king are firm to make the world prosperous, so that it is prosper on the north, south, west, east, everything which is hold by the earth, covered by the sky, all of that grant life to all beings. </p>
 </div>

<div corresp="#skk_18">

         <p corresp="#skk_18.01">All kinds of beings means: plant beings, animal beings, human beings, human beings with name (si voṅ), real (vastu) human beings. Thus, that is all what is called all beings.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_18.02">Grower beings are grass, trees, creeping trees, shrubs, all make the yard dangkura lives green and fresh. Those are called grower beings.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_18.03">Animal beings are all kinds of animals, great and small, on the land and the water, those are called animal beings.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_18.04">Human beings are whose [only] human in appearance, for their character is not good. Human beings bearing name (si voṅ) are only good character and lineage, for they do not know yet the holy Righteousness. The real human beings are those who are firm to the acquired knowledge, know the holy Righteousness, understand the reality of knowledge. Those are called real human beings.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_18.05">This is if [you] probably wish to be aware of the world content. Its number is four. Those are, kurija, mataja, bagaja, payuja.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_18.06">Kurija means all kinds which appear from the mouth; mataja means all kinds which appear from the eyes; bagaja means all kinds which appear from the vulva; payuja means all kinds which appear from the anus. Those are called the holy four origins.</p>

</div>
<div corresp="#skk_19">

                        <p corresp="#skk_19.01">This is the use of the people in the world: to count, to do sigi, to tie, to touch (ñigəṅ), to bury (ṅaruaṅ), ṅaromboṅ. To count means to think; ñigi means to chaining yarns; ṅiket is the acts of tying; ñigəṅ is to use at the right moment (? məṅpəṅ), making wedge (to split wood) (mañcir), splitting, halving, qualifying, ṅagitaka (?), measuring, equating; to bury means all kinds of digging; ṅaromboṅ is all kinds of exchange. Those are called six uses, as such is all the use of all people.</p>
</div>

 <div corresp="#skk_20">

                        <p corresp="#skk_20.01">These are the men desires, 4: wish to be pure (yun suda), wish to be happy (yun suka), wish to ascend (yun muṅgah), wish to be free (yun luput). This is the meaning: yun suda is desiring to be accomplished, doesn’t want to be suffer from disease; yun suka is desiring to be rich, doesn’t want to be ceased by the wealth; yun muṅgah is desiring the heaven, doesn’t want to find the world; yun luput is desiring liberation, doesn’t want to be taken by all heavens. All of that is the desire of all men.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_20.02">These are those who take baths in the toilet, 4. The meaning is: male, female, eunuch, hermaphrodite. That is the number. How much earmarked merchandise? [There are] two, namely ripe and raw, bad and good, small and big. How many flavors? [It is] six: lavana, kaduka, tritka, amla, kasaya, madura. Lavana means salty, kaduka means spicy, tritka means bitter, amla means sour, kasaya means tasty, madura means sweet. Like that is what is tasted by all people.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_21">
        
                    <p corresp="#skk_21.01">This is the requisite for with regard to the ownership, in order that it can descend continuously (pativah-tivah) to the child, grandchild, great grandchild, great-great grandchild, all offspring etc. (muniṅ, aṅgasantana, pratisantana, putu vəkas). Those which are merit to be made as heirloom and those which are not merit.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_21.02">Property as a result of an impudent act is not merit to be made as heirloom, it is called squeezed by the demons. Properties as an outcome of gambling, as an outcome of shopping (daily necessities?) doesn’t merit to be made as heirloom, these are called the given things that of the atmosphere-thought. However, the gifts from mother, the gifts from father, the gifts from the teachers, they merit to be made as an heirloom. These are called the gods that protect people. The results of agriculture can be made into an heirloom. These are called jewels that come from the earth. The products of weaving and livestock can be made into an heirloom. These are called rubies that fall from the sky.</p>
</div>

                    <div corresp="#skk_22">
          
                    <p corresp="#skk_22.01">Rich people redeem a woman without knowing her father and her mother, [she] should not be hired to work, for it may be that we are involved in the wrong [act].</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_22.02">Furthermore, [if] we know her father and her mother, seek [her] for service. If the behavior of her mother and father is of good people, it is called as being affected (kapapanas) by the parent's behavior. [She] can be taken as a servant. But if [her parent behavior is full] of stain, do not accept [her] service. It is called the man who goes around the hell.</p>
                            
                    <p corresp="#skk_22.03">Again, if there are women that are good in behavior, good in foundation, good in origin, redeem her, but should not then take them as a wife, for that is possible that the descendant will be a servant. Should not take our family as a servant (mapajikən). Instead, ask them to take the betel quid [as a] service to us.</p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_22.04">That is all the sacred formulas (jaṅjavokan) so that their families return to their original state, in order to avoid yourself (or: we get off soon) from the prison, to mix up the family in good manner, to avoid yourself from being hit by calamity.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div corresp="#skk_23">
                            
                    <p corresp="#skk_23.01">These are ways we are matchmaking childrens. [They] should not be matchmaking too early if [their family] is not as proper as ours, [or] the people in general. If the venereal disease of a father is inherited to the sons, then the venereal disease of a mother descends to the daughters. If all die and ascend from earth called the demon entering to the kali (yuga?), [then] it is improper to matchmaking the child, for it may be joint to be wrong, for the matchmaker may get flanked.</p>
                            </div>

<!--<lb n="5r1"/><gap reason="lost" unit="chars" quantity="3"/>bisi kaparisidәk· nu ṅajajadikәn·, samaṁkana kayatnaya<gap reason="lost" unit="chars" quantity="1"/>na<gap reason="lost" unit="chars" quantity="4"/>, mujarrakәn·na sabda saṁ rumuhun·, nama
<lb n="5r2"/><gap reason="lost" unit="chars" quantity="2"/>ya, namo budaya, namo sidam·, sor jiva saṅ anurat· palipur<space type="binding-hole"/>na saṅ amaca, mo<gap reason="lost" unit="chars" quantity="3"/>saṅ ahaṚp·, kasukma ujar raḥhayu, ṅaṚgәp· ci
<lb n="5r3"/>p·ta nirmala, Iyatna saṁ sevaka darma, Ini kahuvusan· sisa kadaṁ ka<space type="binding-hole"/>Ṛsyi ṅaranya, ṅana saṁ pus·taka pun·, təlas sinurat· bulan kasapuluḥ
<lb n="5r4"/>bijilna, poEna Aṅgara manis·, tulis·na tә Acan· ras·ti, masa di nusakrata, panəpen hada-hade pun· //o// malapaḥhiṅ parakana sa
-->
                    <div corresp="#skk_24">
          
                    <p corresp="#skk_24.01">Thus, the message of the holy man, the words of the holy message of dharma speaking the word of the ancestors, should be taken into account. Follow the action, use [it] as a sound. Homage to Siwa, homage to Buddha, homage to the fulfilled and perfect soul. </p>
                    </div>
          
          <div corresp="#skk_25">
                    <p corresp="#skk_25.01">The one who reads will be happy, the one who follows the good speech [and] keeps firm the pure mind, he is truly the servant of the Truth. This is the word called The hermits’ holy precepts for society, the book of the listener. The beginning of undertaking the writing during the day was bright, finished in the third month. This is the composition of the writing: zero-four-sea-moon (1440 Ś). </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_25.02"> </p>
                    <p corresp="#skk_25.03"> </p>
               </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
