<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#siksaguru">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Translation of the Śikṣā Guru</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaGuru_transEng01</idno>
                <!-- Replace by filename following FNC -->
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!-- <notesStmt><note><bibl>Digital translation of <bibl><ptr target="bib:"></ptr></bibl>.<relatedItem target=""></relatedItem></bibl></note></notesStmt>-->
            <!-- provide a notesStmt if you need to add some precision regarding the establishement of the translation -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull> <!-- Copy and paste the titleStmt and publicationStmt of the edition file -->           <titleStmt>
                    <title type="main">Śikṣā Guru</title>
                    <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                    <editor ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </editor>
                    <respStmt>
                        <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                        <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                    </respStmt>
                </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                        <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaGuru</idno>
                        <availability>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                                <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                                <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                            </licence>
                        </availability>
                        <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                <!-- if your translation is a copy of already published one: fill a biblStruct -->
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Part mandatory -->
                <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
                <p></p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
            <!-- replace this by a line that has you as @who, that has the @date on which you finished the first basic encoding of the file, and that has the following description of what was finished on that date: "Initial encoding of the file." Then add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div>
    <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_01.01">As follows I will teach first to the servant of the law. You will succeed in listening to the discussion of the holy law and the determined state of the holy gnosis. There is what is called the pure circle of three bodily domains, uttered by the teacher to the servant of law. That is probably the action, speech, and mind. If so, there is a feeling of loss in your heart, that is the practice that should be restrained. You should just guard them and fix them, for it is the cause of finding joy and sorrow, and good and bad.</p>
             <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_01.02">If your action, your speech and your mind are unrighteous, in that case you surely obtain the wrong. If your action, your speech, your heart are righteous, in that case it is clear that you obtain the virtue. That is why there is a proverb “Thus one repeatedly baths, the water is touched by the original nature of the human: bad meets its bad, good meets its good”. Likewise is human nature.</p>
             <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_01.03">What are the illustrations with regard to the consequence of this, [namely]: bad from its bad, good from its good? As follows that will be used as the special condition by you: there are what are called priceless jewels, its value can not be known, incomparable in terms of beauty. The meaning is: the priceless jewel and the most coveted jewel. It is fitting to be bound to bell-metal, copper and tin. What is the appropriateness? It is evident that its splendour and its shine come out, if your binding for the priceless jewel and your tieing for the most coveted gem are appropriate according to that manner.</p>
             <p n="4" corresp="#siksaguru_01.04">As follows is the word of the holy treatise: <q><foreign>lpas ca vuṅkunuṅ ceva, aḍika udika tatte tatur tathya tuṅgəṁ, ta deva nigaḍyate</foreign></q>. Because what is considered the loose hair is the square hair; there is the <foreign>uḍika</foreign>, the <foreign>tater</foreign>, and the lice. All of them are appropriate to be bound to the priceless jewel and chained to the most coveted jewel. No, it is not like that, they should be bound to the bell-metal, copper and tin. Why is that appropriate? The binding to the priceless jewel, the chaining to the most coveted jewel, such is the word of the holy treatise <q><foreign>lpəs ca vuṅkunuṅ cova, aḍi ikaṅ, uḍi ikā, tater tatur tatya tuṅgəṅ nu yvagyanika</foreign></q>.</p>
             <p n="5" corresp="#siksaguru_01.05">There is what is called the glowing gold, beautiful gold, its value is one <foreign>kati</foreign>. The course of action will be [as follows]: it is layered seven times seven, transformed into weighing one <foreign>tahil</foreign> of stone. How can it be strong, not undulating, unwavering, when it is set ablaze again? For only in this way is the outcome of all the gold, and then the binding of priceless jewels and the tying of the most coveted jewel are appropriate and good.</p>
             <p n="6" corresp="#siksaguru_01.06">It is [i.e. gold] bound with bell-metal, copper and tin, its splendour and its shine do not come out. What are the reasons they are not appropriate? Wrong inner nature, wrong action, wrong nature. Just so is the holy supreme dharma, it is a priceless gem; and also your body: that is the most coveted gem. Then what is considered bell-metal, copper, and tin, are not appropriate to be bound to the priceless jewel, [and as] the tying of the most coveted jewel.</p>
             <p n="7" corresp="#siksaguru_01.07">As follows are the bad actions, improper speech, dirty heart towards all humans, especially toward the learned teacher. The meaning is: bad actions, improper speech, and a dirty heart are not appropriate; the holy dharma shall be reflected upon. Furthermore, your body should be protected, especially for the learned teacher. No! Love is not proper, the repetition of your human condition, one ceases to love having children, having a wife, building a family, having relatives and a mother in law. He is unable to protect [himself] from bad actions, improper speech, a dirty heart towards all humans, and especially towards ascetics. How would your protection of your body be appropriate? That is the glowing <foreign><supplied reason="explanation">santaṅva</supplied></foreign> as said by the master. What is called a glowing gold is the good action, the good speech, the good heart. Those should be protected by the holy dharma.</p>
             <p n="8" corresp="#siksaguru_01.08">This is the reason why it is called the pure circle of three bodily domains, as said by the master: <foreign>tri</foreign> means three. The circle of three bodily domains is pure. So it is said. Thus are the three bodily domains, as said by the master.</p> 
             <p n="9" corresp="#siksaguru_01.09">As follows is the beginning of the love of a learned teacher toward the servant of the dharma. It is pure in the good thought. Do it quickly! Do not be obsessed with dirty thoughts.  The heart and mind are pure. Then, purify the mind and the set of your emotions! You should be aware when thinking; you should practice the activity of begging for alms (<foreign>bhikṣālakṣanam</foreign>) with full attention.</p>
             <p n="10" corresp="#siksaguru_01.10">Here are your characteristics, O holy man. Do not be attached to the servants. It is evident that the hair has been cut by it. Cut it [so that] there is no obstruction or hindrance. That is purity, you should cut it before and you should control it. It is what is called … made flower offering with water. In this manner you serve the learned teacher. Do not commit the sin of violating the guru’s bed, [which is] a misfortune for the world; [the pupil] should fear him. You should be devoted and submit to the teacher, you should carry out [acts of] extreme respect toward the teacher, including to the learned masters. You should arrive to its goal.</p>
             <p n="11" corresp="#siksaguru_01.11">In this manner you are the servant of the learned master, even more so of the king. Do not be unfaithful toward the king. [You] will be punished, hated, you will be afraid of him, so that you will be sold and horribly die. You should be loyal to the king, so that [you] will be affected by its result. Thus you, the elder (<foreign>rāma</foreign>), the <foreign>kalaṅ</foreign>, the <foreign>gusti</foreign>, the chief of the village (<foreign>patih banva</foreign>), and also the quality (<foreign>dharma</foreign>) of a balanced mind in people like you. You should not have a biased voice in the legal proceeding, do not lean left and right with respect to good and bad qualities. It is not appropriate [as the] behaviour of experienced men, says the holy scriptures. That should not be followed by you. That is the reason why [if you follow them] the three domains of body and mind (<foreign>trikāya maṇḍalam cittam</foreign>) are not achieved. Then the servants of the dharma should devote their full attention to what is called the sacred circle of the three pure bodily domains. It is the beginning of love of the learned teacher towards the servants of the dharma.</p>
         </div>
          <div>
              <p n="1" corresp="#siksaguru_02.01">There is a second love of the learned teacher towards the servant of the dharma, which is called the ten rules (<foreign>daśaśīla</foreign>); they are the following: ears, eyes, nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hands, genitals, anus, legs. These are what the servant of the dharma should hear.</p>
              <p n="2" corresp="#siksaguru_02.02"><foreign>Śrotra</foreign> means ears. What is the sphere of the ears? They serve as a gate to hear bad and good words. When you hear sweet and fragrant words, your heart becomes comfortable. When you hear a bad word, oppression is what is experienced, that is its fault. Do not treat good duty towards the teacher as a second priority. That is what the servants of the dharma should pay attention to, who are deaf in hearing the scriptures of the holy man.</p>
              <p n="3" corresp="#siksaguru_02.03"><foreign>Cakṣuh</foreign> means eyes. What is the sphere of the eyes? To see good and bad, that causes joy and sorrow. How can they cause the joy? They serve as your instrument to see the good deeds, [that] come down from there. How can that bring sorrow? Because of that you should see ‘the gold’ from other fellow human beings. You walk to the public place, you see people with disabilities, leprosy, invalidity, goitre, starvation (?, <foreign>buḍaya</foreign>), deformities, epilepsy, rheumatism, all kinds of abnormalities that exist in humans, let alone those who are blind and deaf of the eyes and ears. Do not hurt somebody who has a disabled bodies. You should not be like that. It is called avoiding strong emotion (<foreign>caṇḍaparihāra</foreign>), for the innate reaction is not seen, let alone people hurt because of it. That is what the servant of the dharma should pay attention to.</p>
              <p n="4" corresp="#siksaguru_02.04"><foreign>Ghrāṇa</foreign> means nose. What is the sphere of the nose? It serves as an instrument to smell fragrant scents (<foreign>surabhi</foreign>), stinking smells (<foreign>asurabhi</foreign>), extraordinary smells (<foreign>asādhāraṇa</foreign>). <foreign>Surabhi</foreign> means fragrant, <foreign>asurabhi</foreign> means stinking and musty, <foreign>asadhāraṇa</foreign> means singed smell (<foreign>aṅit</foreign>). Therefore three are the kinds of smells. When you smell the fragrance, your heart is happy, when you smell stink and must, your heart is not happy, then your anger appears, that is the cause for the inappropriate speech to arise. The three bodily domains of ultimate truth (<foreign>trikāya paramārtha</foreign>) are not experienced. That is the reason why the sphere of the nose must be properly paid attention to and seriously cared for by the servant of the dharma.</p>
              <p n="5" corresp="#siksaguru_02.05"><foreign>Jihva</foreign> means tongue. What is the sphere of the tongue? It serves as an instrument of six flavours, namely: salty (<foreign>lavaṇa</foreign>), spicy (<foreign>kaṭuka</foreign>), bitter (<foreign>tikta</foreign>), sour (<foreign>amla</foreign>), savory / astringent (<foreign>kaṣāya</foreign>), sweet (<foreign>madhura</foreign>). These are called the six flavours (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>).</p> 
               <p n="6" corresp="#siksaguru_02.06"><foreign>Lavaṇa</foreign> means salty, <foreign>kaṭuka</foreign> is spicy, <foreign>tikta</foreign> bitter, <foreign>amla</foreign> sour, <foreign>kaṣāya</foreign> savory, <foreign>madhura</foreign> sweet. Those are called the six flavours (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>). If they are all enjoyed by you, you will be addicted to becoming sick because of them. You should not do so. Its object [of the tongue] becomes a goal to be realized. That is a sign that you will abandon the good works toward the teacher. If so then the pure circle of three bodily domains are not experienced.</p>
              <p n="7" corresp="#siksaguru_02.07"><foreign>Vak</foreign> means sound. What is the sphere of the sound? All your words should not have to be followed: harsh words, aggressive behaviour, in the situation of powerless and in trouble, it will not make the other human beings feel at ease. However what you should say is the words that are sweet, gentle, and stealing hearts in appearance. All kinds of things that make them indifferent to the world, and which are heard by the other human beings. That is how you guard your words.</p>
              <p n="8" corresp="#siksaguru_02.08"><foreign>Tvak</foreign> means skin. What is the sphere of the skin? To feel and experience heat and cold. The point of this is the effort to restrain the passions that emerge from the skin.</p>
              <p n="9" corresp="#siksaguru_02.09"><foreign>Pāṇi</foreign> means hand. What is the sphere of the hand? To join fingers, join [hands] when talking to the teacher, also not join the hands together with the teacher, especially not point the hand toward the face of the teacher; what is to be touched and received by the teacher should not be touched with the mouth. Or, do not take the teacher’s property, let alone of all people. This means do not be disloyal if he has a request. There are rules in the sacred texts of the ascetics. Such is what you should do to guard your hands.</p>
             <p n="10" corresp="#siksaguru_02.10"> <foreign>Pāyu</foreign> means anus. What is the sphere of the anus? It is eddy and joint. To defecate, to fart are the ways you guard the anus. You shall not fart in the front of the teacher, shall not be in front of people when you defecate. [These behaviours] are not ordered by the teacher, and by all the religious wanderers. Such is what you should do to guard your anus.</p>
              <p n="11" corresp="#siksaguru_02.11"><foreign>Upastha</foreign> means sexual organ. What is the sphere of the sexual organ? To feel a sexual pleasure, to urinate are its functions. To urinate, it should not be done in front of the people, especially those of high birth: male, female, servant, noble man, low, medium and high. For great is its <foreign>maruruca</foreign> (?), the misery of becoming a human being comes out.  What is considered as its misery? You see a man that is sold, his sins are: the seizing of women, misbehaving toward friends, misbehaving toward the teachers, taking by force women who are forbidden. The body is violent. It is not good if it is as such.</p>
              <p n="12" corresp="#siksaguru_02.12"><foreign>Pāda</foreign> means the feet. What is the sphere of the feet? To walk wherever is your destination, whether you go to the north, south, west, east, or to sit in <foreign>sila</foreign> position. Then the way to guard the foot is: not kicking, not assuming an impolite posture, not being in unstable posture, not to lean sideways, not to lie stretched out, not swinging the leg in front of the teacher, [or] to any religious wanderer. This [is the way] to guard the foot, [that] should be made the object of the full attention of the servant of the law.</p> 
<div>
            <p n="01" corresp="#siksaguru_03.01">As follows is the third love of the learned master towards the servant of law. Here are the five instructions as they are called, namely:</p>
            <p n="02" corresp="#siksaguru_03.02">Non-anger (<foreign>akrodho</foreign>) means it is forbidden that a servant of the law shows his anger in front of the teacher, let alone to all good men. Obedience to the teacher (<foreign>guruśuśruṣā</foreign>) means that you are devoted and obedient to the teacher, never far from the feet of the elders. [It should be] really that way if there is an order from the teacher. [You should be] completely pure: The  highest reality of three bodily domains should be made the object of your attention, that is good act, good speech, good thought. The pure circle of three bodily domains, together with ten good conduct and five instructions  should be made object of your efforts whether [you are] far or near. Thus is what is called the obedience when having a master. Purity (<foreign>śauca</foreign>) is to clean your hand when there is something to be grasped and eaten by the teacher, let alone the offerings of the teacher. Moderation in food (<foreign>āhāralāghava</foreign>) [means] you are swift [while] eating; [however, if] the balls of rice are big, and [your] eating quickly is uncontrolled, don’t [act] like that! That is called the belly palace (<foreign>kukṣi pura</foreign>). How could be the way of eating? That is the vital breath with control (<foreign>prāṇa sadhāraṇa</foreign>), the subsistence of thinking about the Holy Good. This is what is called the five instructions that should be made the object of attention by the servant of the law.</p> 
</div>
              <div>
                  <p n="01" corresp="#siksaguru_04.01">As follows is the fourth love of the learned master towards the servant of the law. This is what is called the instruction about the law, here it is—the <foreign>śloka</foreign> about it is as follows:</p> 
                  <p n="02" corresp="#siksaguru_04.02">The meaning is: <foreign>ālekhyam</foreign> means, do not write on the ground, do not write on the board, let alone your body, when you serve the teacher, for those who are considered men with good characteristics never tire to write on their thighs when talking with the teacher; <foreign>hasitam</foreign>: not to laugh in the front of the teacher, let alone to make a joke; <foreign>gītam</foreign>: not to sing—by that, you do not to claim expertise, if it is not ordered by the teacher; <foreign>jr̥mbhanam</foreign>: not to express hunger [and] satiety in the front of the teacher; <foreign>kaṇṭhāravam</foreign>: not to yawn; †<foreign>akadanǝm</foreign>† do not stretch [and emit sounds]  in front of the teacher;  <foreign>sudәm phalarahasyam</foreign>: not to speak presumptuously in front of the teacher, let alone to pronounce the name “penis”, as such it is forbidden. What is called <foreign>na karotu gurumukhe</foreign>, its meaning is as follows: the servant of the law should not do [that].</p>
                  <p n="03" corresp="#siksaguru_04.03">As follows is what is called the instruction of the law (\textit{dharmaśikṣā}).</p>
                  <p n="04" corresp="#siksaguru_04.04">The meaning is, \textit{śalākāñjanam}: not to use eye-paint in front of the tea\-cher, [or] in front of the forbidden women. \textit{Suravile}: not to open wide the mouth when one talks, let alone when one sits in sila position, not to use unguents, not to use powder, whether [in] a place for the service to the teacher, let alone [where] his water stream springs forth, or [in] the pavilion for welcoming [guests]. \textit{Dantagharsā}: not to chew a quid (\textit{susur}) when you speak to the teacher. \textit{Adhyasta}: without the ornaments of the performers, [of those] who play music instruments, and [of] the \textit{kecaka} dancers. \textit{Hārahataḥ}: not taking a pointed lance [measuring] one \textit{vilah}. \textit{Prayāsamāgama}: not to stare at each other with the forbidden woman, let alone the wife of the teacher, to carry a civet-cat (\textit{luvak}) along with prey, not to occupy oneself constantly with eating and drinking in front of the teacher. That is called the instruction of the law (\textit{dharmaśikṣā}); [it] should be made the object of the attention of the servant of the law.</p>
              </div>
              <div>
                  
              </div>
          </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
