<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#skk">
   <teiHeader xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of the Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
            <editor ref="part:adgu">
               <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>DHARMA</authority>
            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
            <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian_transEng01</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                  <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</title>
                  <title type="sub" subtype="editorial">Digital Critical Edition and Translation</title>
                  <editor ref="part:adgu">
                     <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                  </editor>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>structuring of the TEI file</resp>
                     <persName>Aditia Gunawan</persName>
                  </respStmt>
               </titleStmt>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                  <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                  <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSiksaKandangKaresian</idno>
                  <availability>
                     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
                        <p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Aditia Gunawan.</p>
                     </licence>
                  </availability>
                  <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
               </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="part:adgu" when="2021-12-15" status="draft">Creating the file for the translation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
         <div corresp="#skk_01">
<p corresp="#skk_01.01">Here, as follows, is what will be taught by the holy man: the way (de) of one who searches weal.<note>The meaning of <foreign>de</foreign> is ambiguous. Another possibility is to take the third meaning recorded in OJED, viz. ‘in relation to, with regard to, toward, to’, in which case the alternative translation would be ‘what will be taught by the holy man to the one who searches weal’. See Oglobin 2000: 184.</note> As regards what are called the hermits’ holy precepts for society (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian</foreign>),<note> See the discussion of the title in the Chapter 6, §The Title.</note> all people should exert themselves <supplied reason="subaudible">to follow them</supplied>. These are the words of the holy man, revealing the hermits’ holy precepts for society.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.02">These are the ten holy accomplishments (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-krəta</foreign>), which must be adhered to by all people. Anyone who starts to uphold the holy instructions of the accomplishments (<foreign>sasana krəta</foreign>), is destined to be long-lived, to be of long youth,<note> The word <foreign>ñovana</foreign>, which seems to be derived from Skt. <foreign>yauvana</foreign> ‘youth, youthfulness, adolescence, puberty, manhood’, here probably has one of the meanings ‘ageless, long youth, youthful’ (MW, s.v.) that are also inherent in the Skt. word.</note> to have success in paddy fields (<foreign>kuras</foreign>),<note> ASD translate <foreign>kuras</foreign> as ‘<foreign>ternak</foreign>’ (livestock), which seems unlikely. In MdS, <foreign>kuras</foreign> is a verbal base meaning ‘to rince, clean up’. One occurrence in KaPani 737 seems to furnish a clue: <foreign>upamana ṅuṅkuṅ añjiṅ, hayaṅ aya kadaekna, sandigana ṅuruṅ hayam, hayaṅ rampes pamuluna, upamana dina kəbo, hayaṅ nimu pakən ṅuras </foreign>“just as we raise dogs, wishing they are obedient; just as we cage the chickens, wishing their feathers are good; just as, regarding the buffalo, we wish to find them for <foreign>ṅuras</foreign>”. Seeing the relationship <foreign>ṅuras</foreign> with the buffalo, perhaps this word means ‘to plow’)? If so, then the base <foreign>kuras </foreign>most likely means ‘rice-field’.</note> to have success in cultivation,<note> The word <foreign>tahun</foreign> means ‘seasonal plant, i.e. agriculture’ = OJ (OJED: s.v. <foreign>tahun</foreign> 2). Cf. also RS 2.2 <foreign>ṅuniveh kahayvakənaniṅ rāt kabeh, dadyaniṅ tahun, laṇḍuṅaniṅ udan, karuhun kadīrghāyuṣakəna śrī mahārāja </foreign>“and especially he should foster the well-being of the whole world, the success of the crops, the long duration of rains, and in the first place bring about the longevity of the great king”<foreign>.</foreign> Among parallels in OS texts, I may cite PNJ 129 <foreign>jadyan kuras jadyan tahun </foreign>“The paddy fields and crops are successfully growing” and TB 35v  <foreign>pada ñovana, dadian kuras, dadian tahun, dadian kaneneh </foreign>“All people are youthful, the paddy fields, crops, and livestocks are successfully growing”. Note that <foreign>dadian</foreign> and <foreign>jadyan</foreign> are equivalent, the former a loanword from OJ, the latter its proper OS form <foreign>jadyan</foreign> (&lt; <foreign>jadi</foreign>).</note> to stand firm,<note>I interpret <foreign>dəgdəg tañjər</foreign> as ‘stand firm’. The word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> is probably related to <foreign>adəg</foreign>, so in this case, <foreign>dǝgdəg tañjər</foreign> is a twin form (see Chapter 3, §Morphology). In some texts, we find <foreign>dǝdǝg</foreign> instead of <foreign>dǝgdǝg</foreign> (e.g. in PNJ 150 <foreign>dǝdǝg tañjǝr jaya ñovana</foreign>) so the word <foreign>dəgdǝg</foreign> seems to be a reduplication of <foreign>dǝg</foreign>. The word <foreign>dədǝg</foreign> in MdS means ‘well-built, strongly-built, square built, a fine body’, so it is synonymous with tañjǝr (MdS tanjeur ‘standing upright’). Cf. <foreign>sakadəgdəgna</foreign> ‘according to the individual’ in SKK 5.3. However, it is noteworthy that Hardjadibrata (based on Eringa) notes the idiom <foreign>deugdeug tanjeuran</foreign> ‘where people come from all corners to see’. If this meaning was also prevalent in OS, then an alternative translation might be ‘crammed by visitors’.</note> to win in battle — all people <supplied reason="subaudible">who do so</supplied> will be youthful.<note> The construction <foreign>ñovana na uraṅ reya</foreign> is rather unusual. Hardjadibrata designates this case in MdS as an unsyntactical compound. Maybe emend <foreign>ñovana na</foreign> &gt; <foreign>ñovana</foreign>? </note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.03">This is the explanation<note> Based on OJED, <foreign>byakta</foreign> = <foreign>vyakti</foreign> (Skt visible appearance, becoming evident or known) evidence, proof, clarification, explanation; in later texts, esp. <foreign>kidung</foreign>s = <foreign>byakta</foreign>, q.v.</note> of the ‘Ten Holy Accomplishments’: <supplied reason="subaudible">their are</supplied> the shadows of the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>), the reflections of the ten holy paths (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-marga</foreign>), the manifestations of the ten sense faculties (<foreign>dasa-indriya</foreign>), what is needed to make<note> <foreign>di</foreign> here is marking the direct object, like <foreign>ri</foreign> in OJ. On the function of the preposition <foreign>di</foreign>in OS, see Chapter 3, §Note on <foreign>di</foreign>.</note> the distant world and the near world<note> In MdS, <foreign>lamba</foreign> means ‘singular, uncomplicated; simple, (just very) common’, like OJ <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘single (not double), incomplete, halfhearted’. However, in the present context it seems that it is an OS translation of the OJ compound <foreign>bhuvana ləmbana</foreign>, attested in SHH 40.1: <foreign>manon vijñana ṅaranya panonta ri madoh ri bhuvana lǝmbana</foreign>, <foreign>jñānendriya ṅaranya panonta ri maparǝk maṅke pratyakṣa ṅaranya</foreign> “Seeing with discernment (<foreign>manon vijñāna</foreign>) is your means to see what is far in the ‘distant world’, the faculty of knowledge is your means to see what is near, here, which is called the direct perception”. The word <foreign>ləmbana</foreign> or <foreign>lamba</foreign> can be traced to Skt. <foreign>lamba</foreign> ‘hanging down’, but also ‘long, large, spacious’ (MW, s.v. <foreign>lamba</foreign>). Another way to analyze bhuvana ləmbana might be as deriving from bhuv-anālambana, which should be <foreign>bhv-anālambana</foreign> in correct Skt. (see OJED <foreign>anālambana</foreign>, meaning ‘without relation to an object’), perhaps a suitable way of saying 'distant'. What is clear is that <foreign>bumi lamba</foreign> must mean ‘distant world’, the opposite of <foreign>bumi parək</foreign>. I don’t understand what considerations led ASD to emend <foreign>bumi parək</foreign> to <foreign>bumi tan parək</foreign>. Cf. SC 536 <foreign>bumi lamba bumi parǝk</foreign>.</note> prosperous.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.04">This is what we need to make the wide world prosperous: having well-lit roads, plantations being large, well developed and productive (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>),<note>The expression <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> is problematic both in terms of its meaning and of its function in the sentence. This combination occurs more than once in SKK (1.4, 8.1, 10.1) and once in <ref target="#smg_19.02">SMG 19.2</ref>. I have the impression that paka and pradana are two separate words, and that paka should not in this context be understood as a prefix. The word paka, without pradana, appears in AG 5r <foreign>si caṅciṅan</foreign>, <foreign>si laṅsitan</foreign>, <foreign>si paka, si rajǝn-lǝkǝn, si mva surahan</foreign>, <foreign>si preña</foreign>. The combination <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> only appears in lists of good characteristics applying to a servant or to a country. However, the meanings of both words are still unknown. Let us try to determine which meaning might be suitable to the context. As for <foreign>pradana</foreign>, the first derivation that comes to mind is from Skt. <foreign>pradhāna</foreign> ‘(Skt) chief thing or person, the most important or essential part; chiefly, in the first place’, in other words ‘virtuous’. The second, which I find more plausible, is from the Skt. <foreign>pradāna</foreign> ‘giving, presentation; gift’. As for paka, I suppose that it is to be explained as reflecting Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign> ‘ripening, becoming ripe, ripeness; maturity, perfect development (e.g. dhiyas, of the intellect), development of consequences (as of an act done in a former life or of any act); completion, perfection’. In this case, the word <foreign>paka</foreign> could mean ‘mature’. We may then ask whether the word Mal. <foreign>peka</foreign> ‘caring, sensitive’ is also etymologically derived from Skt. <foreign>pāka</foreign>. The Sundanese and Malay words could alternatively be related to the Hindi word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> (which is traced back to Skt. pakva, another derivative of the root pac). The word <foreign>pakkā</foreign> has gone worldwide in the form of the English word <foreign>pukkah/pucka</foreign> (Hobson-Jobson 1903, s.v.). According to the Hindi dictionary by McGregor (1993), the meaning of <foreign>pakkā</foreign> is ‘1. cooked, boiled …; 2. transfer. ripe, mature, experienced, knowing, astute; …; 8. genuine, real, thoroughgoing, solid, reliable, fixed, standard; …’ and many other positive qualities. If OS <foreign>paka</foreign> and Mal. peka were derived from Skt. pāka, it would be surprising that no such word appears in OJ, and this may be a reason to prefer the derivation from a more recent layer of Indo-Aryan vocabulary such as Hindi <foreign>pakkā</foreign>. In sum, I interpret paka pradana rather loosely as meaning ‘well developed and productive’ if it is said of a country or ‘sensitive and generous’ in the case of human qualities. If we look at the paired series such as emet and imət, rajən and lǝkən, it appears that the meaning of <foreign>paka</foreign> may be almost synonymous with pradana, in other words, that <foreign>paka pradana</foreign> may be a ‘twin form’. On this concept of ‘twin form’, see Chapter 3.</note> having clean yards, having well-lit front yards,<note>In the Baduy dialect, <foreign>pipir</foreign> refers to parts of the open land on the back, left, and right of the house, while <foreign>buruan</foreign> refers only to the front side (Judistira K. Garna 1987: 77).</note> also having filled houses, filled rice barns, filled chicken coops, cultivated dry rice-fields, protected taps <supplied reason="subaudible">of palm trees</supplied>. The result is a life full of vitality: having a long-lasting health, having youthful rulers (<foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign>).<note><foreign>saṅ mavaṅ rat</foreign> literary means ‘one who carry the world’, i.e. ‘the ruler’. Cf. RY 24.124 <foreign>tūs ny ambək saṅ mavaṅ rat ya ta dumulurakən sattvāsiṅ atukar.</foreign></note> Even<note> In MdS, <foreign>saṅkilaṅ</foreign> is a conjunction meaning ‘(al)though, in spite of, notwithstanding; <foreign>sangkilangan</foreign> ‘although’, but in OS it also means ‘and yet, even’. Cf. RR 1696–1599 <foreign>saṅkilaṅ na tuaṅ ais, na pərəbu puspalava, eleh-alah tan pamənaṅ</foreign> “even your younger brother, Prince Puspa Lawa, has been utterly defeated“.</note> in the wide <supplied reason="subaudible">world</supplied>: having grasses, trees, climbing plants, bushes; having fresh green (<foreign>hejo lembok</foreign>) plants,<note>For a similar expression, see SKK 18.1.</note> having all trees bearing fruit, having fertile rains,<note> Cf. OJ <foreign>laṇḍuh</foreign> ‘uninterrupted, prosperous’ (OJED, s.v.). ASD choose to emend it as <foreign>landuṅ</foreign>, which also means ‘long’ in MdS.</note> having grown seasonal crops; <supplied reason="subaudible">those</supplied> will bring life for people in general. That is what is called the holy instructions of the accomplished one (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ sasana krəta</foreign>) in the wide world.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.05">These are the ten accomplishments, considered as the shadow of the ten holy virtues. It is the reflection of the ten paths, the manifestation of the ten sense faculties.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.06">This is its explanation. Ears should not listen randomly <supplied reason="subaudible">to a discussion</supplied>*, if it is not fit to be listened to. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune (<foreign>mala</foreign>), the payment (<foreign>lunas</foreign>)* is punishment <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result, (obtained) from the ears, is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.07">Eyes should not watch randomly <supplied reason="subaudible">any event</supplied>, if it is not fit to be watched. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, then the result of watching is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.08">The skin should not be used jerkingly,<note>Cf. <ref target="#smg_07.07">SMG 7.7</ref> <foreign>kulit ma ṅaranna, bogoh saprasa-prasana, lamun ku panas ku tiis, ku meraṅ ku atəl, dipake gulaṅ-gasehan</foreign> “What is called skin, loves to touch whatever it likes. If due to hot and cold, to itching and irritation, the skin is exposed to discomfort”. The word <foreign>gulang-gaséhan</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but cf. MdS <foreign>guling-gasah</foreign> vi. <foreign>guling-gasahan</foreign> ‘toss and turn, toss round and round (so. who is troubled by pain or problems)’. There is also a semantic connection with MdS <foreign>gulang-gapér</foreign>, <foreign>ngagulang-gapér </foreign>‘physically spoil so. (a sick person, lover) (by stroking, massaging, etc.), (molly-)coddle so.; keep on touching and stroking st. (e.g. an ornament o. is attached to)’<foreign>.</foreign></note> due to hot and cold. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the skin is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.09">The tongue should not be wrong <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> what is tasted. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the tongue is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.10">The nose should not smell wrongly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the reason we encounter misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the nose is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.11">The mouth should not speak randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the mouth is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.12">The hands should not grasp randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the hands is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.13">The feet should not step randomly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if they are used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the feet is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.14">The anus should not be used rumblingly. For <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of calamity, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the anus is considered optimal.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_01.15">The vulva and the penis should not be used for seducing,<note>In MdS, the word <foreign>kañcolah</foreign> means ‘want to draw attention through busy behavior’. ASD read <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> and translate it as ‘<foreign>mesum</foreign>’ (perversion), although <foreign>kañcoleh</foreign> is unattested in MdS.</note> for <supplied reason="subaudible">this</supplied> is the gate of misfortune, the payment is punishment in hell. But if it is used appropriately, the result (obtained) from the vulva and the penis is considered best. This is what is called the ten accomplishments. If the ten gates are completely used appropriately, the behavior of all people will be good, let alone the behavior of His Majesty the king.<note>It seems that <foreign>saṅ deva</foreign> in <foreign>saṅ deva ratu</foreign> is equivalent with <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ</foreign>, that is used to refer to the king in general. Cf. <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ haji</foreign> as a honorific name of  Kertanagara in RPG: <foreign>liṅ saṅ hyaṅ haji kr̥tthanagarā.</foreign> Cf. <ref target="#smg_39.03">SMG 39.3</ref>.</note></p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_02">
<p corresp="#skk_02.01">The following are called the ten devotions (<foreign>dasa-prəbakti</foreign>):<note>Cf. OJ <foreign>prabhakti</foreign> (= <foreign>bhakti</foreign>) ‘devotion, attachment, worship, love’.  No sauch word has survived in MdS. It is important to note that the list in this section contains eleven levels, not ten. Is the item of the gods devoted to ancestors an interpolation? Or is God excluded from the list of <foreign>dasa-prəbakti</foreign>? We have the correspondent hierarchy in the RPG 17a: <foreign>kunaṅ dr̥vya muleha riṅ gusti, gusti muleha riṅ taṇḍa, taṇḍa muleha riṅ mantri, mantri muleha riṅ ratu, ratu muleha riṅ vikū, vikū muleha riṅ deva, deva muleha riṅ hyaṅ, hyaṅ muleha riṅ śūnya</foreign> “As to property, it should honour its <foreign>gusti</foreign> (master), the <foreign>gusti</foreign> should honour the <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> (headman), the <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> should honour the <foreign>mantri</foreign> (mandarin), the <foreign>mantri</foreign> should honour the <foreign>ratu</foreign> (prince), the <foreign>ratu</foreign> should honour the <foreign>viku</foreign> (priest), the <foreign>viku</foreign> should honour the <foreign>deva</foreign> (god), the <foreign>deva</foreign> should honour the <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign> (Holy Spirit), the <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign> should honour <foreign>śūnya</foreign> (Supreme Non-Entity)” (Pigeaud 1960, I: 190; III: 135).</note> first, a child devoted to the father; 2, a wife devoted to <supplied reason="subaudible">her</supplied> husband; 3, a servant devoted to the officers (<foreign>pacandaan</foreign>);<note>The word <foreign>pacandaan</foreign> seems to be the group of officers. Cf. OJ <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> ‘a group of officers (= <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign>, q.v. ?) (OJED, s.v. <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> 2). It is important to note that the examples in OJED are cited from the <foreign>Raṅga Lave</foreign>, i.e. a text known to author of SKK, RL 5.12: <foreign>rahadyan pacuh amuvus, iya ujarira voṅ, agra-pāvakāraneki, iku atut, caṇḍa kaṅ muṅgu iṅ untat</foreign> “The venerable smile and speaks, and his word to the people of Agra-Pāvakārana, the <foreign>caṇḍa</foreign> who is in the back  should be followed”; see also  <foreign>caṇḍamantri</foreign>, an entry that only cites data from <foreign>Tantri Kədiri</foreign> 4.3b <foreign>hiṅan iṅ parimaṇḍala dudug iṅ lor vetan kidul pascima ry uṅgvan ikaṅ satus caṇḍamantri, ndatan pinucap dohnira sakiṅ balamantrinira kapat</foreign>; 4.4a: <foreign>lila tumandiri punpunan sovaṅ-sovaṅ nimittaniṅ krəteṅ puri mevəh ry ananiṅ catus canḍamantri</foreign>. Is there any connection with <foreign>parvaṇḍan</foreign> in Old Malay? See Cœdès 1930.</note> 4, a pupil devoted to <supplied reason="subaudible">his</supplied> master; 5, a farmer devoted to the soldier;<note>The word <foreign>vado</foreign> ‘soldier, troop’ is not recorded in MdS. Cf. OJ <foreign>vadva</foreign> or <foreign>vado</foreign> from Skt <foreign>badva</foreign> ‘large number, multitude subject, follower, (the lesser) troops’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>vadvā</foreign>).</note> 6, a soldier devoted to the minister; 7, a minister is devoted to the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>;<note><foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> is problematic. The most possible base word is <foreign>taṅgan</foreign>, but it is not found in OJ and OS. Should it be understood as <foreign>taṅan</foreign> ‘hand’. If it is so, then the literal meaning of <foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> would be ‘who are giving hand, the helper’. Cf. CRP 173–175 which depicts <foreign>nu naṅganan</foreign> who accompany the princesses: <foreign>saha nu aṅkat ti həla, tan liyan giraṅ naṅganan, nu naṅganan para putri nu gəlis</foreign> “Who is the one who walks in front? None other than the one who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, who <foreign>naṅganan</foreign> the beautiful princesses”.</note> 8, the one who naṅganan devoted to the governor;<note>In OJ texts such as the <foreign>Pararaton</foreign> and <foreign>kiduṅ</foreign>s, the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> occupy the highest position in the palace after the king, who appeared during the Mahapahit period. Maṅkubumi's position as second in command after the king is also confirmed in Sundanese sources. Apart from this paragraph, in the RR, Sombali is the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> of king Bibisana, and occupies the highest function after the king. See SKK 11.8 regarding the duties of maṅkubumi in the Sundanese context of the 15th century.</note> 9, the governor devoted to the king; 10, the king devoted to the gods; the gods devoted to the ancestors. They are called the ten devotions. 10.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_03">
<p corresp="#skk_03.01">This is what should be practiced, the message from the true sage. ‘<foreign>Oṅ</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">I give</supplied> homage to Śiva! My veneration <supplied reason="subaudible">goes</supplied> to the Holy Five <foreign>tathagatas</foreign>!’ <foreign>Pañca</foreign> means five, <foreign>tata</foreign> means speech, <foreign>gata</foreign> means passion.<note>The relation between <foreign>gata</foreign> and <foreign>raga</foreign> ‘body’ is obscure. We could interpret <foreign>gata</foreign> as ‘those that are left’, and <foreign>raga</foreign> as ‘passion’. In this case, the translation would be “those that are left are passions”. But it seems more persuasive to take <foreign>gata</foreign> as intended to stand for Skt./OJ <foreign>gātra</foreign> ‘body’ (MW, s.v.; OJED, s.v.). The word <foreign>gātra</foreign> is attested in Kuñj 28: <foreign>ikaṅ cetana, ya ta ikaṅ gave tr̥ṣṇa, ya ta misanakən ikaṅ ātma pat, ya ta dadi kinimpəlakən, ya matəmahan ri śarīra gātra</foreign> “The consciousness, it is the product of craving, it has as relatives the four souls, it becomes a solid object, it becomes the body and the limbs”. It is important to note that the one of the mss. of the <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> comes from West Java.</note> Those ones should be well maintained, all of them. The five syllables (<foreign>pañcaksara</foreign>) are the masters of men. The meaning is: the five syllables are manifest, being  seen, experienced,<note>The word <foreign>kavrətan</foreign> is derived from <foreign>vrətta</foreign> Skt. ‘Set in motion; occurred, happened; past; matter, affair; action, conduct’. However, the manuscript has <foreign>-on</foreign> instead of <foreign>-an</foreign>, probably intended to make a correspondent sound with <foreign>katoṅton</foreign>. Cf. JM 18.22 <foreign>diucap tan kaucap, tan katoṅton, tan kavrətan, tan karagap, tan kasikəp, tan kagaməl, tan karasa</foreign> “it is said without being spoken, not being seen, not being experienced, not being touched, not being catched, not being grasped”.</note> observed, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> perceived by the senses. The master is the one to be asked by the people. That is why they are called the masters of men. As for ignorance,<note>I take <foreign>saṅmoha</foreign> as a Sanskrit derivative <foreign>sammoha</foreign> ‘stupefaction, bewilderment, confusion, insensibility, unconsciousness, ignorance, folly, illusion of mind’, not as a person <foreign>saṅ moha</foreign> ‘the one who is ignorant’. Cf. OJ <foreign>samoha</foreign> ‘id’. Could it be that the phenomenon of <foreign>ṅ</foreign> instead of <foreign>m</foreign> originates from the manner of interpreting <foreign>panyecek</foreign>? Cf. <foreign>oṅ</foreign> above, and <foreign>biṅba</foreign> (understood as <foreign>bimba</foreign>) in the inscription Kawali 5 (Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 187). The sounds /m/ and /ṅ/ are sometimes found to be interchangeable in MdS, for instance <foreign>bingbang</foreign> and <foreign>bimbang</foreign> ‘be in doubt’. The former is considered standard. </note> <supplied reason="subaudible">it exists</supplied> since the world exists.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.02">This is the “evidence” for it, that is the five spheres of activity (<foreign>pañca-byapara</foreign>): earth, water, fire, wind and ether. Words of the great holy man: “They are the substances of our <supplied reason="subaudible">bodies</supplied>; the skin is the earth, the blood <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the saliva are the water, the eyes are the light, the bones are the wind, the head is the ether. It (the skin) is called the earth in the body<note>While blood and saliva are called the water in the body, and so on</note>. The reason why they are compared to world authorities, is that they take shape<note> The word <foreign>maṅupati</foreign> is from Skt. <foreign>utpatti</foreign> ‘happening, appearing, taking place; proving right; demonstrated conclusion, proof, evidence, argument; fitness, suitability, possibility’. Cf. OJ <foreign>utpatti, utpətti, utpati, utpəti, upəti</foreign> ‘coming into existence; origin, birth, incarnation’. Also in OS texts, <foreign>upati</foreign> figures in meanings such as ‘manifestation, appearance’. Cf. CP 36r <foreign>disilihan ku saṅ rakeyan darmasiksa, paṅupatyan saṅ hyaṅ visnu, iña nu ñiən saṅ hyaṅ binayapanti</foreign> ‘being replaced by Honorable Darmasiksa, the manifestation of God Viṣṇu. He is the one who made the series of rules’. ASD translate <foreign>binayapanti</foreign> as ‘panti pendidikan’. I tend to associate <foreign>panti</foreign> with Skt. <foreign>paṅkti</foreign> ‘row, set, series, group, troop, company’ (MW, s.v.). If so, we are dealing with the local form of the Sanskrit compound <foreign>vinayapaṅkti</foreign>, which would mean ‘set of rules, series of training’. The pertinence of this interpretation is clearly seen in SC 493–496, which mentions the names of texts and teachings, in addition to mentioning <foreign>patikrama </foreign>(= OJ <foreign>paṅktikrama</foreign>): <foreign>cacanden dəṅ kararasen, tahampekan babahəman, paṅəsi binayapanti, patikrama mədaṅ kamulan</foreign> ‘The Cacanden and Kararasen, Tahampekan and Babahəman, contents of the set of rules, the order of Mədaṅ Kamulan’.</note> as the leader (<foreign>prabu</foreign>), the elder (<foreign>rama</foreign>), the hermit, the ritual expert (<foreign>disi</foreign>)<note> On <foreign>prabu</foreign>, <foreign>rama</foreign>, <foreign>rəsi</foreign> as triad elite in Sundanese, see Chapter 10. On the term <foreign>disi</foreign>, see Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 180.</note>, and the sailor”.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.03">These are the five sons (<foreign>pañca-putra</foreign>):<note> These five mythical figures are the sons of Kandyawan in the <foreign>Tantu Paṅgəlaran</foreign> and the <foreign>Carita Parahyaṅan</foreign>. The latter text adds that their mother was Kandyawati, and agrees precisely with SKK on the names of the sons. In the TP, by contrast, there are some minor variations of their names compared to the OS tradition. The OJ text has Katuṅ Malaras instead of Katuṅ Maralah and Saṇḍaṅ Garbha instead of Sandaṅ Grəba. (The latter is merely an orthographic variant.) The order in which these two sons appear is also inverted in TP. Cf. TP 61.7 <foreign>kahucapa ta sira hyaṅ kaṇḍyavan, manak ta sira limaṅ siki; saṅ Maṅukuhan anak panuha, saṅ saṇḍaṅ garbha paṅgulu, saṅ Katuṅ malaras panəṅah, saṅ karuṅ kalah kakaṅ riṅ pamuṅsu, saṅ vr̥tti kaṇḍayun pamuṅsu </foreign>“Let us tell of the holy Kandyawan, who had five sons. The eldest was Mangukuhan, Sandang Garbha the second, Katung Malaras the middle one, Karung Kalah the second youngest, and Wretti Kandayun the youngest”; CP 11a: <foreign>basa aṅkat sabumi jadi &lt;manik&gt; sakuruṅan nu misǝvǝkǝn pancaputra, saṅ apatiyan saṅ kusika, saṅ garga, saṅ mestri, saṅ purusa, saṅ patañjala, iña saṅ maṅukuhan, saṅ karuṅ kalah, saṅ katuṅ maralah, saṅ sandaṅ grǝba, saṅ vrǝti kandayun</foreign> “When he (Kandyawan) departs to become ‘a jewel in one cage’, he being the one who has the Five-Sons, those who are the reincarnation of Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusa, [and] Patanjala. They are Mangukuhan, Karung Kalah, Katung Maralah, Sandang Greba, [and] Wreti Kandayun”. For a comparison of these figures in both texts, see Hadi Sidomulyo 2021: 84–85, 111. The meanings of the names of the Five Sons are obscure. However, some of them can be guessed, such as <foreign>saṅ maṅukuhan</foreign> ‘the one who makes firm’ (from <foreign>kukuh</foreign>?), <foreign>saṅ karuṅ kalah</foreign> ‘the one whose boar is lost’, <foreign>saṅ sandaṅ grəba</foreign> ‘the one who carries a fetus’. The literal meaning of <foreign>saṅ katuṅ maralah</foreign> cannot even be guessed, but TP has <foreign>katuṅ malaras</foreign> ‘<foreign>katuṅ</foreign> with arrow’ (?). The last name, <foreign>saṅ vrəti kandayun</foreign>, might just possibly mean ‘the one whose occupation is the battlefield’ (<foreign>kaṇḍa</foreign> + <foreign>ayun</foreign>) (?).</note> <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Maṅukuhan is the earth, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Katuṅ Maralah is the water, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Karuṅ Kalah is the fire, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Sandaṅ Grəba is the wind, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Vrəti Kandayun is the ether.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.04">These are the five <foreign>kusika</foreign>s:<note>On <foreign>pañca-kusika,</foreign> see my commentary on the preceding paragraph, where the CP passage combines the <foreign>pañca-putra</foreign> with the <foreign>pañca-kusika</foreign>. Minor differences of reading also occur with regard to the names of the five <foreign>kusika</foreign>s in OS and OJ texts. In OS sources we regularly find <foreign>mestri</foreign> instead of <foreign>metri</foreign>, <foreign>purusa</foreign> instead of <foreign>kurusya</foreign>. Cf. NR 45.8 where the <foreign>kusika</foreign>s take shape in the body: <foreign>kusika riṅ kulit, garga riṅ dagiṅ, metri riṅ otot, kurusya riṅ tahulan, prətañjala riṅ sumsum</foreign>. On the history of the <foreign>pañca-kusika</foreign> in Java and Bali, see Acri 2014.</note> <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Kusika on the mountain, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Garga in the swamp, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Mestri on Mount Mahameru, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Purusa in Mandiri, <foreign>saṅ</foreign> Patañjala in Panjulan.<note>Mandiri is an unidentified toponym. BM 45 mentions Tajur Mandiri which was apparently situated somewhere near present-day Bogor. Panjulan is not mentioned in BM, but a <foreign>kampung</foreign> of that name exists today in <foreign>kecamatan</foreign> Koroncong, <foreign>kabupaten</foreign> Pandeglang, Banten.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.05">If the holy five sections (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima</foreign>)* are taken into account altogether, the earth would be in harmony, all <supplied reason="subaudible">its</supplied> quarters of space. All quarters of space are east (<foreign>purba</foreign>), south (<foreign>daksina</foreign>), west (<foreign>pasirma</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>pasirma</foreign> is equivalent to Skt. <foreign>paścima. </foreign>In KaMah 120 we find <foreign>dataṅ kala ti pacirma</foreign> “Kala comes from west”. On the intrusive r, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> north (<foreign>utara</foreign>), center (<foreign>madya</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.06"><foreign>Purba</foreign>is the east, the abode of the god Iswara, whose color is white. <foreign>Daksina</foreign>is the south, the abode of the god Brahma, whose color is red. <foreign>Pasirma</foreign>is the west, the abode of the god Mahadéwa, whose color is yellow. <foreign>Utara</foreign>is the north, the abode of the god Wisnu, whose color is black. <foreign>Madya</foreign>is the center, the abode of the god Siwa, whose color is multifarious. <supplied reason="subaudible">That is</supplied> the reason why the five sacred sections (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ vuku lima</foreign>) in the universe are like that.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.07">These are the five sections in <supplied reason="subaudible">the case of</supplied> the great scholar. The esoteric teaching is experienced by the one who is conscious (<foreign>si tutur</foreign>); asceticism is experienced by the one who is pure (<foreign>si liṅlaṅ</foreign>); posture is experienced by the one who is firm (<foreign>si pagəh</foreign>); perception is experienced by the one who is capable (<foreign>sy asəmbava</foreign>); liberation is experienced by the one who shares without receiving a share, who limits without being limited. The five sections in <supplied reason="subaudible">the case of</supplied> the great scholar are like that.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_03.08">As follows are the causes of accomplishment: they are the five gods, all embodying* your name, all watching your form. But if (the names and forms) are not guarded, as if crooked meets its crooked, straight meets its straight. This is how it is: it is by human actions that it becomes accomplished, by human actions that it becomes good.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_04">
<p corresp="#skk_04.01">These are the acts of the servant, every path taken by us as servants. The act means intellect <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> mode of conduct. Every path taken means: be fearful,<note>I take <foreign>maka</foreign> in this context as an equivalent to <foreign>mangka</foreign> in MdS ‘modal auxiliary word used in conjunction with immediately following adjective (occasionally verbs) by emphasizing how so. should act), e.g. <foreign>mangka iatna</foreign> be careful!; <foreign>mangka inget</foreign> be mindful of; <foreign>mangka sabar</foreign> be patient!’</note> be strong,<note>The word <foreign>jarot</foreign> ‘strong’ is not found in MdS, but MdJ has <foreign>jarot</foreign> ‘strong and handsome’ (Horne 1974, s.v.), which seems suitable in our context.</note> be respectful, be courteous, in behavior, in attitude,<note>Cf. <foreign>sapitvahən</foreign> in 10.3. In this case, the suffix -<foreign>ən</foreign> does not yield irrealis meaning. I presume that <foreign>pitvahən</foreign> is morphologically analogous to <foreign>pisabdaan</foreign> ‘speech’ = <foreign>sabda</foreign>. Cf. also the spelling <foreign>kaləpasən</foreign> for <foreign>kaləpasan</foreign> ‘liberation’. See Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> in action, in speech, especially when in front of His Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.02">We should be faithful in service, in order to wipe out the ten defilements (<foreign>dasa-kalesa</foreign>), so that the impurity leading to sin will be annihilated, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> heaven will be obtained.<note>All manuscripts have <foreign>kapaṅguh</foreign> ‘be obtained’; cf. OJ <foreign>paṅguh</foreign> ‘id’, not in MdS. ASD read it <foreign>kapaṅgih</foreign> as in MdS.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.03">If <supplied reason="subaudible">you are</supplied> excessive<note>On <foreign>tǝtǝiṅ</foreign>, cf. BM 623–627  <foreign>hantə paṅgərahan aiṅ, tətəiṅ oge tətəiṅ, na uraṅ anak pahatu, na uraṅ hantə dibapa, aya diinduṅ kasaruṅ</foreign> “I am not delighted, it is too much, really too much! I was an orphan, I had no father, I did have a mother, but she went astray”. Cf. MdS <foreign>teungteuingeun</foreign> ‘that’s a bit too much, that’s gone too far (of so.’s behaviour, actions, etc.), that’s gone beyond a joke (with ref. to treatment that so. suffers etc.); (as exclamation) too bad! it’s shameful! it’s disgraceful!’</note> in practicing the acts of the servant, that is worse than a monkey (<foreign>usyat</foreign>)<note>The emendation of <foreign>usyatitindih</foreign> as <foreign>usyat titindih</foreign> is based on the phenomenon of degemination which is common in scribing manuscripts. The word seems related to OJ <foreign>busyat </foreign>‘a kind of monkey’? Probably the phonological process involves the interchangeability of /b/, /v/, and /u/: <foreign>busyat</foreign> &gt; <foreign>vusyat</foreign> &gt; <foreign>usyat</foreign>. In OJ, <foreign>titindih ukir</foreign> is an expression meaning ‘mountain hermit’ (lit. ‘who lives the mountain’). Cf. ST 19 <foreign>sakveh iṅ aṅguguntuṅ maṅuyu, para poco maṅke / sakveh iṅ titiṇḍih vukir, kaṅ amuluṅ murunduṅ, ametiṅ / lavan puputut, iṅoṅ tədunakən kabeh, babaru ajana kantun, / padatisayatakena, sanjatane karepiṅvaṅ.</foreign></note> occupying a hill, performing penance on the top of the mountain, for it is forbidden to perform penance on an elephant mound<note>I translate <foreign>hunur</foreign>, not recorded in MdS dictionaries, as ‘hill, mound’; Cf. OJ <foreign>hunur</foreign> ‘id’. In MdS the form is <foreign>huñur</foreign>, but some dialects, for instance in Karawang, people recognize <foreign>unur</foreign> for the mound of earth where some archeological sites were found in Batujaya.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> a lion mound, near a great danger.<note>In this context, <foreign>bañcana</foreign> is probably equivalent with Mal. <foreign>bencana</foreign>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.04">These are the actions of man that will be of use to all people. We should not fail to follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! If<note>Cf. <foreign>jaka</foreign> in the Old Malay Tanjung Tanah manuscript in the sense ‘if’, cf. <foreign>jika</foreign> in Malay. In MdS <foreign>jaga</foreign> means ‘in the future, later; (dial.) far ahead (of a place)’. We find some examples of the change <foreign>k</foreign> &gt;<foreign> g</foreign> in Mal. and MdS, for instance, Mal. <foreign>gali</foreign> &gt; MdS <foreign>kali</foreign>, Mal. <foreign>gilir</foreign> &gt; MdS <foreign>kilir</foreign>. In SKK itself, we find both <foreign>cakal bakal</foreign> and <foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>. See also the representation of the toponym Kedah as <foreign>gədah</foreign> in 11.31. On the interchangeability of /k/ and /g/, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> we wish to be free from the five forms of reincarnation (<foreign>pañca-gati saṅsara</foreign>), we should not be deceitful (<foreign>carut</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>carut</foreign> is not recorded in MdS and OJ. The meaning of this word in Mal. is ‘ribald, vile, obscene’ (Wilkinson, s.v.). However, I sense that <foreign>carut</foreign> has a broader range of meanings in OS, like ‘deceitful, evil, filthy’, and this is the basis of my translations of the occurrences in this text (4.5, 8.6, 11.5, 13.6, 21.2).</note> should not have a habit of laziness,<note> I emend <foreign>sorereh</foreign> into <foreign>sok rereh</foreign> since the first is not attested in OS. In MdS <foreign>réréh</foreign> means ‘spread’, but seems too far from the context. I take the meaning from <foreign>rèrèh</foreign> in MdJ ‘langzaam, bedaard; traag; verwijlen, uitstellen, nalaten om iets op het oogenblik te doen’ (Gericke &amp; Roorda 1901: s.v.).</note> should not deceive ourselves. Deceiving ourselves means: what is present<note> It is clear that the scribe consistently writes <foreign>na</foreign> instead of <foreign>nu</foreign> as read by ASD in <foreign>na iña, na hantə, na lain</foreign>, so I take it as an article. Cf. JM.12.27–13.5 <foreign>sugan vaya nu milihan iña, dəṅ na iña, dəṅ na lain, dəṅ na juti, dəṅ na jati</foreign> “there may be someone who chooses that: between the truth and the opposite, delusion and reality”.</note> is considered absent, what is absent is considered present, what is true<note>The word <foreign>iña</foreign> here seems equivalent to <foreign>enya</foreign> in MdS, meaning ‘true, genuine, real’, as the antonym of <foreign>lain</foreign>, not as a demonstrative. This <foreign>əña</foreign> is only attested in a relatively more recent Old Sundanese text, namely CVG 213.</note> is considered not so, what is not so is considered true — so that<note>Cf. <foreign>karah</foreign> in MdS. It is also clearly related to OJ <foreign>harah</foreign>, <foreign>narah</foreign> ‘emphatic particle, stressing an announcement, question (<foreign>arah apa</foreign>), invitation, command, cause or reason (<foreign>arah de</foreign>, <foreign>arah wet</foreign>)’.</note> his mind is scheming, pretending, deceiving, hurting. That is the explanation of being deceitful to ourselves.<note> On <foreign>ta</foreign> in last sentence, cf. the use of <foreign>ya</foreign> in the last sentence of 4.5 — here <foreign>ta</foreign> is a short form of <foreign>eta</foreign>, so expressing a deictic meaning.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.05">Being deceitful to other people means: plucking without asking permission, taking without asking, picking without requesting, let alone looting, thieving, plundering, robbing, everything that counts as impudent and deceitful. Those are called being deceitful to other people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.06">And also infiltrating, grabbing, pilfering, seizing, groping, sneaking, let alone hanging around with a host, with a dignitary,<note>The term <foreign>paṅhulu tandaṅ</foreign> seems to be distinguished from <foreign>tohaan</foreign>. Rigg (1866, s.v. <foreign>panghulu tandang</foreign>) defines it as ‘a great man whom it is difficult to approach. A ringleader’, but Hardjadibrata notes that in <foreign>pantun</foreign> stories, it means ‘lord/lady!, master/mistress! (in addressing royal persons etc.). In RR, <foreign>paṅhulu tandaṅ</foreign> is the designation for king Manabaya. Assuming meanings like ‘dignitary’ or ‘local leader’ seems suitable in the present contexts.</note> let alone<note>The conjunction <foreign>saṅuni</foreign> ‘let alone, moreover, furthermore, and also’ is only occurred in SKK, the more common conjunction in this sense is <foreign>maṅkaṅuni</foreign>.</note> with one's own master. That should even less be done, be practiced by the servants.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.07">Do not fail to practice polite, respectful, and refined words,<note>The compound <foreign>gurubasa</foreign> is not attested in OJ. Cf. AG 4v <foreign>ṅalap kasor səmu guyu, teoh ambhək</foreign>,<foreign> gurubasa, di na uraṅ sakabeh, tuha kalavan anom</foreign> “[We should] be willing to give in, having a sweet temperament, a humble heart, refined words, all of us, young and old”. Cf. RD 45 where we find <foreign>ya sabda tata-basa, guru-basa ba- / … da suksila</foreign>. The phrase <foreign>sabda tatabasa</foreign> ‘words according to the rules’, occurring side by side with <foreign>guru-basa</foreign>, suggests that the word <foreign>guru</foreign> means ‘teacher’ in this context. Thus, the compound <foreign>guru-basa</foreign> seems to mean something like ‘words according to teaching, learned speech’.</note> to be humble and well-mannered to fellow humans, to family and relatives,<note>Pigeaud (1960–1963: vol. III, p. 175) translates <foreign>braya</foreign> in Selamandi Ib1 as ‘neighbours’; Arlo Griffiths (p.c.) prefers connecting this word, unrecorded in OJED, with Skt. <foreign>bhāryā</foreign>; <foreign>braya</foreign> in Balinese ‘family, relation’.</note> let alone to our master. We should use <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> feet to sit politely, <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> hands to pay respect.<note> See my comment on the word <foreign>umun</foreign> in  <ref target="#smg_20.04">SMG 20.4</ref>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.08">If we talk with a nobleman, with a gusti, with the lover of someone else, with a forbidden woman, let alone with our master; if we are employed <supplied reason="subaudible">by them</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not be angry<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006) note <foreign>surahan</foreign> with question mark ‘hot-tempered’, from SA 934        <foreign>ciciṅan hamo surahan</foreign> ‘firmly seated, never hot tempered’; not in OJ and MdS. However, the word <foreign>asurahan</foreign> is attested in OJ (not recorded in OJED), and its meaning seems to be something like ‘angry’, cf. SD 3.12: <foreign>vərniṅ ṣaḍpada vibhramāṅhrəṅ anaṅis humuṅ asurahan iṅ surālaya</foreign>.</note> in our minds, let alone answer wrongly, an expression of discontent visible to our master. Don’t! It is forbidden, lest the result of asceticism fail, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the result of the ancestors (<foreign>cakal bakal</foreign>)<note>This compound is not found in OJ or MdS, but attested in MdJ ‘first inhabitants of a new region, later on venerated as its tutelary spirits’. It seems equivalent with Mal. <foreign>cikal bakal</foreign>. In 10.2 it is spelled <foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>, showing variants <foreign>k</foreign> and <foreign>g</foreign>. On the sound interchangeability of /k/ and /g/, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> be lost! Lest the results<note>The word <foreign>batri</foreign> is equivalent to MdS <foreign>bati</foreign> ‘profit (gained from st.)’. Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw give the same meaning in the BM, based on the context in the text, without noticing the relation with MdS <foreign>bati</foreign>. Cf. OJ <foreign>wati</foreign> II? See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> of hard work be lost! <supplied reason="subaudible">We will</supplied> be met by the god of worldly misfortune, fined<note>The word <foreign>katigraha</foreign> is from Skt. nigraha (OJED nigraha), reanalyzed as containing a base <foreign>tigraha</foreign>, with meaning ‘to punish, to fine’. Kuñj 18 contains <foreign>vinigrahan</foreign>, apparently to be emended to <foreign>tinigrahan</foreign>: <foreign>tumiṅal ikaṅ pāpa vinigraha ḍeni saṅ yāmabalā, haṅrasa linu hatini saṅ kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> “Seeing the sinners who are punished by the troops of Yama, the heart of Kuñjarakarṇa is broken”. The word <foreign>nigraha</foreign> is common for monetary fines in inscriptions and <foreign>Śāsana</foreign> texts which use a language register similar to that of inscriptions. See for instance Cane: <foreign>knāna ya nigraha mā kā 1 su 5</foreign> (Brandes 1913: 120–125).</note> by His Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.09">If we are not faithful to our master, for instance if we are in a sick state, if we are tired, if we are careless, <supplied reason="subaudible">then</supplied> let’s honestly acknowledge that we have been very disgraceful,<note>The combination <foreign>tətəiṅ amat</foreign> is an expression with a meaning something like ‘it is a pity/how shameful’, addressed as a form of politeness in dialogue. See SKK 14.3, where such an expression is considered as <foreign>paṅvastu</foreign> ‘blessing’. More common is the expression <foreign>sumaṅər təiṅ</foreign>. On <foreign>sumaṅər</foreign>, see GNT  (s.v.  <foreign>sumanger</foreign>), where the word is related with Mal. <foreign>semangat</foreign>.</note> so that we are acknowledged to be faithful in service. But if we act, we should not be weak, we should not fall short,<note>Hardjadibrata records <foreign>kuciwa</foreign> as an archaic register ‘fault, defect, short-coming, blot, blemish; display some short-coming/blemish’. The more common meaning in MdS is ‘disappointed’ = Mal. <foreign>kecewa</foreign>.</note> should not refuse<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngontong</foreign> means ‘to say do not to someone’ (Hardjadibrata, s.v. <foreign>ontong</foreign>), but in this case it seems to have a more general meaning ‘to say no’ or in another word ‘to reject, to resist’.</note> when being ordered, should not be envious <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> malicious with those engaged in the same service, especially when seeing someone who gets praise <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> gets an audience (<foreign>parəkan</foreign>);<note>I take the meaning of <foreign>parəkan</foreign> ‘audience’ from OJ. In MdS, <foreign>parekan</foreign> means ‘concubine’ or ‘(with the Baduys) k.o. functionary (member of the village council)’.</note> seeing someone who is favored by the master, then our thoughts may become overheated.<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw translate <foreign>ñət</foreign> as ‘hot, shining’ in RR 44. Probably <foreign>ñətñot</foreign> is an intervocalic reduplication with the same meaning. Another possibility is to relate <foreign>ñot</foreign> with MdS <foreign>ñuat</foreign> (from <foreign>suat</foreign>), meaning ‘pierce (so.’s heart as it were by telling evil things about him, remind him of an insult experienced etc.)’.</note> They should not, it is forbidden!<note>See the quasi-synonymous expression <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign> in SKK 4.8.</note> Its being forbidden leads to tears,<note>Among other reasons, my emendation <foreign>dadi luh</foreign> is based on the occurrence of the equivalent OJ expression <foreign>dadi luh</foreign> in three important <foreign>kakavin</foreign>s: HV 13.6 <foreign>ndatan panamban lara mankin śīrṇa rəmək hatinya dadi luh tan pantaran her-tali</foreign>; BY 9.14 <foreign>yāvətu sukha dadi luh ndān avas harṣa hetu</foreign>; BK 2.27 <foreign>vineh səpah təñuh tvas ira śīrṇa rakva dadi luh drava ri mata niran parambəhan panampəta niran taṅis mara-marah nrəpasuta riy asih nirāṅrəsəp</foreign>. Probably the change is from <foreign>jadi na əluh</foreign> &gt; <foreign>jadi nəluh</foreign>.</note> the heart wounded without being able to be cured, mantras being ineffective, intentions not becoming reality, because the holy hermits’ precepts for society  are not adhered to.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.10">Likewise, if we are <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, do not reprimand <supplied reason="subaudible">us</supplied> discreetly. If we are reprimanded, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> must not fail to be devoted to the <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>,<note>On the word <foreign>naṅganan</foreign>, see my commentary in SKK 2.1</note> because he is the agent (<foreign>tanda</foreign>) of His Majesty the king.<note>In Old Balinese Inscriptions such as Sembiran AI, we find that <foreign>taṇḍa haji</foreign> was translated as ‘<foreign>vorstelijk bewijs</foreign>’ (royal sign) by Goris (1954: 133). On the term <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> in OJ, see Jákl 2019 who concluded that it is associated with the court milieu and typically figures in a military context. According to him, between the ninth and thirteenth centuries CE, <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> were not ‘officers’, but rather active warriors in the service of the king or another lord, who stayed either at the court or were stationed in fortresses owned by the king or lesser lords in different parts of the realm. From the twelfth century CE onward, we encounter a category of royal notables denoted as <foreign>taṇḍa rakryān riṅ pakira-kiran</foreign>, rendered by Jákl as ‘lord’s men of [military] strategy’. These men formed the second highest echelon of state officials, preceded in rank only by the three highest dignitaries of the state. It seems that in the fourteenth century CE the importance of the category of <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> diminished, though at least some of the men were still active combatants. We see that in 15th-century Sunda, based on SKK 11.20, <foreign>tanda</foreign> seems to have a function related to the law (<foreign>darma</foreign>) or litigation.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.11">If we are under orders,<note>The word <foreign>pañuruhan</foreign> means ‘orders, commandments’. On the meaning of ‘<foreign>kumpulan, keseluruhan</foreign>’ of circumfix <foreign>pa- -an</foreign>, see Zoetmulder &amp; Poedjawijatna (1992/I: 84, §109b). See also my discussion in Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not fail to maintain the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society, so that we are faithful to the commandments.<note>On the word <foreign>pivaraṅan</foreign> ‘order, commandement’, cf. <foreign>Pantun</foreign> DK 36 <foreign>ayeuna engkang moal ngantos, piwarangan ti rayi</foreign> “Now I will not wait for the order from you”. In MdS, <foreign>piwarangan</foreign> means ‘the one who is given the order’.</note> But as regards the one who goes north, south, west, east, he must not<note>In the present context, <foreign>gəs ma</foreign> is a conjunction which precedes the list. Cf. SKK 11.2 and 14.3. See my discussion in Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <foreign>si vok cante</foreign>,<note>Terms with <foreign>cante</foreign> elements are difficult to understand. <foreign>Cante</foreign> is not listed in the dictionary. RR 56 contains <foreign>cantayan</foreign> which means ‘butcher’s beam’, probably derived from the base word <foreign>cantay</foreign> = <foreign>cante</foreign>; cf. Mal. <foreign>bantai</foreign>. The element <foreign>si</foreign> can form personifications. The word <foreign>vok</foreign> may be the same as OJ ‘hairy, beard’, but the relation with appetite is confusing. The word <foreign>mur</foreign> is not identified, while <foreign>mar</foreign> is listed in OJED with the meaning of ‘spreading, weak’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>mār</foreign>). For the time being, these four terms cannot be translated.</note> must not <foreign>si mur cante</foreign>, shall not become <foreign>si mar cante</foreign>, shall not <supplied reason="subaudible">become</supplied> <foreign>darma cante</foreign>. Those are called four efforts (<foreign>catur-yatna</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.12">This is the meaning. <foreign>Si vok cante</foreign> means easily tempted by food and drink. <foreign>Si mur cante</foreign> means guilty<note>The word <foreign>salimaha</foreign> is only recorded in Hardjadibrata, ‘excl. (dial.) it’s your own fault!’. However, in this context, the meaning ‘guilty’ seems more adequate.</note> of participating in making those who steal, who confiscate, who deceive, spread in all directions;<note>My emendation <foreign>ṅaramankən</foreign> is based on OJ <foreign>karaman</foreign> ‘(avs) to spread in all directions (fire, light, water)’ and MdS <foreign>karaman</foreign> which has the same meaning.</note> it is called the wrong destination. <foreign>Si mar cante</foreign> means to take merchandise, sheets of gold and silver, <supplied reason="subaudible">even if</supplied> it is not ordered by the commander; it is called wrong purpose. <foreign>Darma cante</foreign> means tolerant<note> The word <foreign>daranan</foreign> seems to be derived from <foreign>darana</foreign>. Hardjadibrata notes ‘Skr. (in archaic lit. lang.) tolerant, forbearing, patient; <foreign>kumaha darana tanah</foreign> (expr.) everything that the soil bears, i.e. it depends on the productive power of the soil’. The suffix -<foreign>an</foreign> seems to form adjectives in OS.</note> of what is detestable to our master. He is ordered to fetch <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, to go by foot <supplied reason="subaudible">to pick up someone</supplied>, and to kill those who are unfit for<note>If we emend <foreign>ka tohaan</foreign> into <foreign>ku tohaan</foreign>, then <foreign>tohaan </foreign>become the agent of <foreign>disuruh</foreign>. The alternative translation of <foreign>disuruh ñokot, ṅadarat, matyan nu tan yogya ku tohaan</foreign> would be “He is ordered to fetch [someone], to go by foot [to pick up someone], and to kill those who are unfit by [our] master”.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> master, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> instead he becomes more careful,<note><foreign>ṅisəsan</foreign> from <foreign>isəs</foreign> = MdS <foreign>iceus</foreign> ‘vi. know o.’s way around, able to do things that o. should do; (of animals) easily trained to do things, easy to break (in)’. Cf. AG <foreign>isəs-isəskən carekna pantikrama</foreign> “Be careful about the words of propriety (<foreign>pantikrama</foreign>)”.  See also <foreign>isəskən</foreign> in 4.14.</note> because they are friends,<note>The word <foreign>vagəy</foreign> means ‘friend, companion’. Cf. BM 607 <foreign>vagəyeṅ aməṅ sagala</foreign> ‘My companions would all be monk’. The word <foreign>wageuy</foreign>/<foreign>wagey</foreign> is not attested in MdS. However, the OS word it is clearly related to OJ <foreign>vage</foreign>. In the Wanua Tengah III and Śrī Kahulunan (= Tri Tepusan I) inscriptions, the word <foreign>vage</foreign> (one of the days in the five-day cycle, or <foreign>pañcavāra</foreign>) is translated in Sanskrit as <foreign>mitra</foreign>. On Tri Tepusan I, see De Casparis 1950: 74; n. 2 on p. 76 and Damais 1955: 103–104. For Wanua Tengah III, see Boechari 2012: 467–471 and Griffiths 2022: Appendix A. Another example of -<foreign>əy</foreign> in OS = -<foreign>ay</foreign>/-<foreign>e</foreign> in OJ is OS <foreign>təmbəy</foreign> = OJ <foreign>tambay</foreign>/<foreign>tambe</foreign>.</note> family, and relatives. That should not be done, for what is called the wrong <foreign>binarih</foreign> (?)<note>This word <foreign>binarih</foreign> is unknown in the dictionaries. Should it be emended to <foreign>birəṅəh</foreign>?</note> is forbidden; it is called <foreign>darma cante</foreign>. Those things should not be practiced by the servants: to love the detestable, to detest the lovable. They are improper to be practiced by the servants.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.13">This is so that we obey the master, so that we are long taken as servants, so that we are always controlled<note>The meaning of <foreign>diasa</foreign> is equivalent with <foreign>dipihulun</foreign> ‘to be in control of s.o., to be taken as a servant’. In RR.74 we found its active form <foreign>ṅasa</foreign> ‘to dominate, to control’. Cf. MdS <foreign>kawasa</foreign>, OJ <foreign>vaśa</foreign> (from Skt.) ‘power, force, dominion’. ASD translate it as ‘<foreign>diakui</foreign>’ (to be aknowledged).</note> by our master: follow the hermits’ holy precepts for society! pay attention to the dignitary! If the master scolds <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, we too should participate in scolding with the master. If the master praises <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied>, we too should participate in praising with the master. If we cannot participate in praising <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> participate in criticizing<note>Based on the context it is clear that the meaning of <foreign>meda</foreign> is the opposite of <foreign>muji</foreign> ‘to praise’, so ‘to insult, to criticize’. In OJ, one of its meanings is ‘unrestrained feelings or conduct, passion, blindness’, with the base <foreign>meda</foreign>. Zoetmulder notes that in some occurrences, this word is also possible to be related to <foreign>peda</foreign> ‘hard-hearted, indifferent, unkind’.  It is probably also related to <foreign>pīḍā</foreign>, <foreign>pīḍāna, pedita</foreign>. Cf. SKK 9.2.</note> with the master, it is better that we keep quiet while devoting ourselves to the master.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.14">If we walk into the forest, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should wear</supplied> an upper garment, a lower garment,<note>The base word of <foreign>disimbut</foreign>, <foreign>simbut</foreign> in MdS means ‘blanket’. Its variant, <foreign>salimbut</foreign>, also occurs in OS. This word is clearly related to Mal. <foreign>selimut</foreign> and OJ <foreign>salimput</foreign>, perhaps also with Khmer <foreign>sampot</foreign> ‘lower garment’. However, its meaning in OS is not always clear, whether ‘blanket’ like MdS, or ‘lower garment’, which is more appropriate in this sentence. A meaning which is more likely close to ‘blanket’ occurs in RR 163–164  <foreign>saaṅgəsna dimandian, disimbutan tuaṅ tapih</foreign> “Having bathed the baby, he covered him with his mother’s skirt”. The meaning ‘lower garment’ is attested in KaPañ 813–816 <foreign>boeh laraṅ disarasah, pipiṅgir taluki jəṅgi, cavət vayaṅ simbut siñjaṅ, disabukan jamar tali</foreign> “sacred cloth is ornamented, on the edge is muslin from Jenggi, loincloth with a wayang motif and lower garments (<foreign>simbut siñjaṅ</foreign>), belted by the <foreign>jamar</foreign> rope”.</note> and a combination.<note>The meaning of <foreign>paṅadva</foreign>, both in OS and OJ, is problematic. Zoetmulder (1982, s.v. <foreign>paṅadva</foreign>) wonders whether the basic meaning is <foreign>adu</foreign> or <foreign>dwa</foreign>. I would be inclined towards the latter option, and take it as a ‘combination’ of both upper and lower garment. Here I revise my argument in Aditia Gunawan (2019), stating that <foreign>paṅadva</foreign> would point to an “upper garment”.</note> When coming to the <supplied reason="subaudible">sea</supplied>side,<note>I interpret <foreign>sisi</foreign> as an equivalent of OJ <foreign>pasisi</foreign> 'seaside, shore'. Cf. <ref target="#smg_16.02">SMG 16.2</ref> <foreign>pasu ma ṅaranya, savatək satva di dayəh, paksi ma ṅaranya, savatək satva di sisi</foreign>, <foreign>sarpa ma ṅaranya, savatək nu napak harəguna, mina ṅaranya, savatək satva di cai, pepelikan ṅaranya, savatək nu mava caṅkaṅ, nu kumarayap hantə kañahoan</foreign> “Domestic animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the settlements; birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>) are all kinds of animals on the seaside, snakes (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>) are all kinds of animals whose chest touch the ground; fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the water; creeping animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>) are all kinds of animals having a shell, who crawl without being discovered”. Cf. RY 5.21: <foreign>satəkanireṅ samudra suməpər ta sireṅ pasisi</foreign>. However, in MdS, <foreign>pasisian</foreign> means ‘countryside’, so the alternative translation would be “When coming to the countryside, [we] wear upper and lower garments as often as possible”.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should normally (<foreign>sakarajən</foreign>)<note>GNT records this term under <foreign>karajeun</foreign> “RR 748 let it be so, all right! Very well!’ MSd <foreign>kajeun</foreign> ‘id’.; sakarajeun ‘let it be according to…’; or from rajeun? Cf. <foreign>leumpang sakarajeun-rajeun</foreign> ‘to walk freely, entirely as [you] wish’”. They assume that the word is derived from base <foreign>kajeun</foreign> with infix -<foreign>ar</foreign>-, though the possibility of derivation from <foreign>rajeun</foreign> is mentioned. I favor the latter interpretation. In MdS <foreign>rajeun</foreign> means ‘every now and then, time and time again; <foreign>sok rajeun</foreign> fairly frequently; <foreign>rarajeunan</foreign> s.m. <foreign>rajeun</foreign>; <foreign>mirajeunan</foreign> do st. now and then, get used to st., try to do st’. Cf. AG 4r–v <foreign>muṅku kasoraṅ ja uraṅ hantǝ tapa, kena hantǝ dikabisa hantǝ dikarajǝnan</foreign> “it will not be achieved because we are not doing penance, because we are not skilled, because we are not used to it” and BM 1557–1560 <foreign>samapun saṅ hiaṅ atma, rakaki bujaṅga manik, lǝmpaṅ sakarajǝn-rajǝn, sia ka na kasorgaan</foreign> “My respects, sacred soul, honorable man Bujangga Manik, you should walk as it used to be, you may go to heaven”. In this context, I choose to interpret it as ‘normally’.</note> wear upper and lower garments. When not with the master, <supplied reason="subaudible">we must</supplied> be careful about the hermits’ holy precepts for society. Their precepts are: don’t go harvesting <supplied reason="subaudible">legumes</supplied> from other people’s small fields, from other people’s gardens, except by virtue of our having asked permission.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.15">A rope on a forest and on a garden,<note>I consider <foreign>kəboan</foreign> as a variant of <foreign>kəbon</foreign> ‘garden, plantation’, as in SKK 10.2. My emendation is based on the occurrences of <foreign>kəbon</foreign> and <foreign>alas</foreign> in OJ sources, among others RL 1.113 <foreign>kubon alas palaṅ-alaṅan eṅarit</foreign>; DS <foreign>riṅ kəbon, riṅ alas</foreign>; Pdg <foreign>inaryakən riṅ kubvan, riṅ alas</foreign>; Par 21.2 <foreign>vontən iṅ kubon alas... pinakaryakən gubug.</foreign> Bularut inscription <foreign>savaḥ ga[ga] kbvan· mvaḥ Alas</foreign>. My translation of <foreign>salaṅ iṅ kəboan iṅ alas</foreign> ‘A rope on a forest and on a garden’ is tentative. Another possibility is to emend to <foreign>salaṅ kəboan dəṅ alas</foreign> ‘the rope in the garden and the forest’.</note> wood that had been marked by a string, fruit that has been bunched together,<note>The basic form of <foreign>ṅararaṅgean, raṅge</foreign>, probably related to MdS <foreign>ranggeuy </foreign>‘ear (of corn), bunch (of fruit, flowers, grapes, bananas, etc.); <foreign>ranggeuyan</foreign> a. having ears, clusters or bunches of st., putting forth ears (of rice plants); b. forming ears or bunches, in a bunch’. Possibly also related to OJ <foreign>araṅgayan, araṅgeyan</foreign> ‘to stretch out and move the hands (forepaws) in order to seize, claw, clutch at’.</note> firewood that stands ready, a covering for mushrooms, hives or nests<note>Does the word <foreign>caṅrədan</foreign> mean ‘hive/nest’? But do <foreign>ulam</foreign> worms make nests? Or does <foreign>caṅrəd</foreign> just mean ‘a bunch’ (collected together for subsequent transport elsewhere)? According to Hady Prasetya, <foreign>caṅrǝdan</foreign> is very likely a bond on a tree near the nest, because these insects and caterpillars nest in trees.</note> of various bees (<foreign>təvvan</foreign>, <foreign>odeṅ</foreign>, <foreign>ñəruan</foreign>), of wasps (<foreign>eṅaṅ</foreign>), of woodworm (<foreign>ulam</foreign>),<note>In MdS, <foreign>ulam</foreign> is ‘a kind of woodworm (in trees and tree trunks)’. According to information from Dadan Sutisna and Mamat Sasmita, both <foreign>ulam</foreign> and <foreign>éngang</foreign> are still consumed by some Sundanese people, especially the larvae. <foreign>Ulam</foreign> in question may be the same as MdS <foreign>cangkilung</foreign>, a type of caterpillar on bamboo.</note> a fish trap (<foreign>parakan</foreign>) — all kinds of ownership marks (<foreign>babayan</foreign>): we should not take them carelessly, let alone bring down other people’s taps. That should not be done, for it is the origin of guilt, the source of suffering and misery.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_04.16">If we find a road, large or small, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> quickly<note>The word <foreign>baṅat</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but is found in Malay ‘haste, hurry, speed up’. Cf. OJ <foreign>baṅət</foreign> ‘speed, drive, vehemence’.</note> wear loin-cloth or a combination, <supplied reason="subaudible">as</supplied> we might be faced with <foreign>gusti</foreign>s or with <foreign>mantri</foreign>s. <supplied reason="subaudible">We</supplied> should not fail to move to the left and bend down.<note> On the word <foreign>paṅadoṅkoṅkən</foreign>, see my comment on <ref target="#smg_02.02">SMG 2.2</ref>.</note> If <supplied reason="subaudible">we meet with</supplied> <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>s, brahmans, royal ascetics, governors, princes, rich or poor, especially <foreign>guru loka</foreign>s,<note>OJED notes <foreign>guru loka</foreign> as ‘teacher or religious functionary at the court (cf. <foreign>paṇḍita nagara</foreign>, <foreign>viku nagara</foreign>, <foreign>viku haji</foreign>)’. Sum 42.15 concerns a <foreign>guru loka </foreign>who is a wandering ascetic accompanied by a female ascetic (<foreign>kili</foreign>). Cf. Vr̥h 50.1 which narrates Vr̥haspati as a <foreign>guru loka</foreign> in the heaven. In CA 122.27, guru loka belongs to the twice-born class (dvija) as distinguished from brahmin, bhujaṅga, and r̥si. SHKS 150–151 states that the guru loka is the leader of the vikus. The SKK should strengthen the assumption that the guru loka is related to the court, even though there are indications that they do not live in the palace but travel.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> should not fail to move to the left<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006: 39) note one example of <foreign>paṅ- -kən</foreign> which is an imperative: <foreign>paṅlumpatkən</foreign> ‘run away from’, based on RR 1512 <foreign>bat paṅlumpatkən aing</foreign> “Come on, run away from me!”. In this context, the imperative <foreign>paṅidalkən</foreign> can be preceded by a vetative <foreign>ulah mo</foreign>.</note> and sit, for those are the teachers of the king.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_05">
<p corresp="#skk_05.01">Keep in mind the Hermits’ Precepts for Society, and beware of adultery.<note>The word <foreign>haloan</foreign> corresponds to OJ <foreign>halvan</foreign>, not in MdS.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">We should not</supplied> go and whimper about<note>The verb <foreign>ṅərikən</foreign> probably related to OJ <foreign>kəri</foreign> ‘having a shivering or shuddering feeling (fear or horror), itching (to attack)’. Here I interpret it as ‘to whimper about, be lustful’.</note> the forbidden women of others, widowed maidens, lest we be guilty of ‘adultery of the road’; especially <supplied reason="subaudible">we should not go and</supplied> hold hands,<note>I interpret <foreign>ṅarovaṅ taṅan</foreign> as an idiom ‘holding hands’ = Mal. <foreign>bergandengan tangan </foreign>‘holding hands’. It seems that <foreign>arovaṅ</foreign> derived from <foreign>rovaṅ</foreign> ‘companion’ = OJ. Maybe it literally means ‘take (female)’s hand as his friend’, in other words ‘hold hands’. Cf. MdS idiom <foreign>murah tangan</foreign> ‘generous’.</note> sharing a seat on a tree trunk, on a couch, in a shelter (<foreign>təpas</foreign>), one with another.<note>I interpret <foreign>patutuṅgalan</foreign> as ‘one with another’, so not alone. It is interesting to compare with the equivalent expression <foreign>paduduaan</foreign> ‘(only) the two of them (do st.)’ in MdS.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">It</supplied> is called ‘adultery of the seating place’. Standing face to face<note>The word <foreign>patañjər-tañjər</foreign> may be compared with MdS <foreign>pahareup-hareup</foreign> ‘face to face’.</note> by the side of the house, in the yard, one with another. It is called ‘adultery of the yard’. Answering someone who coughs, who is clearing the throat, who is expectorating, especially someone else’s mother’s<note>The phrase <foreign>ambu iṅ kalih</foreign> means ‘someone else’s mother’, cf. <foreign>buhaya iṅ kalih</foreign> ‘someone else’s beloved’ in SKK 4.8.</note> song. It is called ‘the roaring cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgala</foreign>).<note>My emendation <foreign>aṅgala</foreign> is based on OJ <foreign>aṅgala</foreign> ‘to trumpet (of elephants), to roar (of a bull)’, which seems fit with the context. This word is not found in MdS. Cf. TK 84.2: <foreign>linūd i svaranyāṅgala saṅ nandaka</foreign> “The roaring sound of Nandaka is even more noisy”. MdS has <foreign>ngagalang</foreign> ‘run across (the road)’ which does not fit the context.</note> Resting on the place where the other one<note>In this passage, <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> probably does not mean other people in general, but other women. In <ref target="#smg_10.02">SMG 10.2</ref> <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> is clearly synonymous with <foreign>sakalih </foreign>‘other people’, reflecting a that the person thus designated is held in high esteem<foreign>. </foreign>In the <foreign>Udyogaparva</foreign> (ed. Zoetmulder, p. 73) <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> means both gods’ as one would expect: <foreign>kahiḍəp pva rasanikaṅ vara-varah de saṅ hyaṅ kalih, mojar ta saṅ hyaṅ viṣṇu ri saṅ hyaṅ indra</foreign> “After the gust of the information was understood by both gods, Viṣṇu spoke to Indra”. Another possibility is to emend it to <foreign>sakalih</foreign> or <foreign>saṅ kalih</foreign>.</note> has sat — on a post, on a tree, on a stone — <supplied reason="subaudible">after</supplied> seeing her having gotten up then replacing them to lean, that is called ‘the rubbing cow’ (<foreign>ləmbu aṅgasir</foreign>).<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngagasir</foreign> means ‘rub or graze against st., touch st. when passing (e.g. with the clothes); <foreign>ngagasirkeun</foreign> let st. graze or rub against st.; <foreign>pagasir</foreign> rub against each other, touch one another when passing’ which seems fit the context. In OJ <foreign>gaṅsir</foreign> ‘mole-cricket’.</note> Those should be remembered, if we want to free ourselves from hell.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_05.02">And also joining together in one lodging, one residence, one shelter, one couch, with someone else’s women,<note>The interpretation of <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ kalih</foreign> as ‘someone else’s women’ is not so convincing. Should it be emended to <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign>, since <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign> is often juxtaposed with <foreign>strī laraṅan</foreign> in OJ epigraphic passages? If this interpretation is correct, then the translation for <foreign>dəṅ dayaṅ kalih, dəṅ astri laraṅan sakalih</foreign> would be “with someone else’s concubine, with forbidden women of someone else”. For a discussion of the term <foreign>dayaṅ</foreign> in Austronesian languages, see Clavé &amp; Griffiths 2022: 185–186.</note> with forbidden women of someone else; it is called ‘the buffalo in one pen’ (<foreign>kəbo sapitunahan</foreign>).<note>The expression <foreign>kəbo sapitunahan</foreign> is probably equivalent with the Mal. idiom <foreign>kumpul kebo </foreign>‘cohabitation’?  On the circumfix <foreign>pi- -an</foreign> in <foreign>pitunahan</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> Those are the things to be kept in mind. They are called forbidden acts.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_05.03">In the same way, if we are going on a journey, we shouldn’t <supplied reason="subaudible">do that</supplied>, shouldn’t desire to be followed by the servants of someone else. If we desire to take them, we should ask their master. If they are trusted <supplied reason="subaudible">servants</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> make an oath<note>See OJED (s.v. <foreign>samaya</foreign>), <foreign>sinamayākən</foreign> (pf) ‘to make an arrangement about, predestine, foreordain, make so. the object of an oath determining what will happen to him in a certain case’, not in MdS.</note> (as to our liability) for their sickness, for their death, for their loss, <supplied reason="subaudible">for their</supplied> passing  away and dying, in any way whatsoever, them you must take. There is no one who may be blamed,<note>I consider <foreign>pidosaən</foreign> as the irrealis of <foreign>pidosa</foreign>. Cf. OJ <foreign>amidoṣa</foreign>, <foreign>pinidoṣa</foreign> ‘to consider guilty (of an offence or a crime)’.</note> for an oath is more eminent<note>In this context, I interpret <foreign>kolot</foreign> as ‘eminent, sacred’, not in the literal meaning ‘old, elder’. See my comments on the word <foreign>dipikakolotan</foreign> in SKK 20.1.</note> than <supplied reason="subaudible">written</supplied> law (<foreign>agama</foreign>). If they are not trusted<note>Cf. OJED <foreign>picaya = parcaya/pracaya kaparcaya, kapracaya</foreign> ‘trusted (servant, companion, etc.)’. Cf. Mal. expression <foreign>orang kepercayaan </foreign>‘confidant’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">servants</supplied>, then we should not! If we insist on taking them, we should help them when they are sick, we should redeem them individually (? <foreign>sakadǝgdǝgna</foreign>) if they are dead or lost. All of that should be taken into account.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_06">
<p corresp="#skk_06.01">Further, as follows: if we are visited by the <foreign>same</foreign>,<note>The word <foreign>same</foreign> seems to correspond to <foreign>sāmya</foreign> in OJ. Zoetmulder (OJED, s.v. <foreign>sāmya</foreign>) notes: “It seems to be a person (group of persons, <foreign>para sāmya</foreign>) with some authority on a lower (village?) level, subaltern official or chief. They are mentioned with <foreign>kuwu</foreign> and <foreign>juru</foreign>. Cf. OJO 61 (distinguished from <foreign>tanayan thāni</foreign>)”.</note> <foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>dasa</foreign>, <foreign>calagara</foreign>, <foreign>upəti paṅgərəs rəma</foreign>,<note>On the interpretation of <foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>,<foreign> dasa</foreign>,<foreign> calagara</foreign>,<foreign> upəti paṅgərəs rəma</foreign>, see Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths (2021).</note> our thoughts should be cheerful, we should feel as though being visited by family, relatives, younger and elder siblings, children, friends, children of younger siblings (<foreign>suvan</foreign>),<note>In MdS, <foreign>suvan</foreign> (spelled <foreign>suan</foreign>) is the son/daughter of our younger brother or sister, from <foreign>uva</foreign> with circumfix <foreign>sa</foreign>- -<foreign>an</foreign>?</note> children of elder siblings (<foreign>kaponakan</foreign>). That is the metaphor for it. But if we have things to share, <supplied reason="subaudible">such as</supplied> food, drink, under garments, clothes <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> anything that we own,<note>The form <foreign>sakadrəbya</foreign> ‘anything that we own’ is rarely attested in OJ. In the corpus at my disposal, it only occurs in one manuscript containing Saṅ Hyaṅ Hayu (Mal. Pol. 161) and ms. E of the <foreign>Tantu Paṅgəlaran </foreign>(Pigeaud 1924).</note> we should feel as though making offerings and giving reception<note>On the occurrences of the word <foreign>puja </foreign>and <foreign>saṅgraha </foreign>in the same context in OJ, see AsP 114  <foreign>masaṅgraha ta devī Gāndhārī, lāvan bhaṭārī Kuntī, mamūjā ya va (l. thā)śakti, sahana-hana riṅ āśram</foreign>; Udy 89.2 <foreign>maṅarpaṇākən pūjālaṅkārasaṅgraha ri mahārāja Kr̥ṣṇa.</foreign></note> to the ancestors and gods.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_06.02">Moreover, if we are employed <supplied reason="subaudible">to go</supplied> to the dry rice field, to the paddy field, to the great paddy field (<foreign>seraṅ agəṅ</foreign>);<note>The word <foreign>seraṅ agəṅ</foreign> literally means ‘great paddy field’. The attribution of the word <foreign>agəṅ</foreign> indicates a special function of the place. Cf. <foreign>ləbuh agǝṅ</foreign> in BM 35, which refers to the main square. Probably <foreign>seraṅ agǝṅ</foreign> refers to a kind of court or main paddy field? Cf. the idiom <foreign>pada agəṅ</foreign> in Baduy, most sacred place in Baduy.</note> fencing, digging a trench, putting animals into the pen, making snares, dam fishing,<note>Cf. <foreign>parakan </foreign>in SKK 4.15.</note> fishing with a casting net, fishing with a line (?, ṅadodoger),<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngadogér</foreign> means ‘to perform <foreign>dogér</foreign> dance’ or ‘brace o.self, exert o.self to the utmost, do st. with great exertion, put everything to work for st.’ Neither meaning fits the context. However, Satjadibrata notes ‘<foreign>narik at[awa] ngajungjungkeun naon-naon sataker tanaga</foreign>’ (to pull or to lift anything with maximum force). Cf. MdS  <foreign>dogéng, ngadogéng</foreign> ‘with great exertion pull on st./push against st. If the idea of full and push is correct then it can mean fishing as we know today. Hardjadibrata also mentions <foreign>sair dogé</foreign> ‘[a kind of sieve] with a 10 to 15 foot pole, used to fish in the deep’.</note> fishing with drag-net (mapayaṅ), fishing with a sieve (<foreign>ñair</foreign>),<note>As in MdS, <foreign>sair</foreign> means a ‘sieve’, cf. OJ <foreign>ser</foreign> which Zoetmulder defines as ‘a kind of net (= <foreign>seser</foreign>)’ and its verb <foreign>aner</foreign> ‘to fish with a net’.</note> ensnaring animals by two people (? <foreign>biñcaṅ</foreign>)<note>I wonder whether <foreign>biñcaṅ</foreign> should be emended to <foreign>ṅabiñcaṅ</foreign>? However, in MdS it means ‘tie st. up on either sides; lead (a horse) with two people so that it walks in between (tied to ropes on either ends of the bit); catch (a horse that has broken loose) by two people with the aid of a rope slung around its neck’  <foreign>. </foreign>Cf. Mal.  <foreign>bincang.</foreign></note> — any kind of employment for the master, we should not be displeased, we should not be temperamental,<note>See my comment on <foreign>surah</foreign> in SKK 4.8</note> we should not be angry<note>I render the meaning from OJ <foreign>purik</foreign> ‘bad temper, crossness’, not in MdS.</note> or fuss.<note>There are two occurrences of <foreign>gariṅsiṅ</foreign> in SA, which translated differently by Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw: first, SA 385 <foreign>tiagi bogoh gariṅsiṅ</foreign>, <foreign>əbon-əbon bogoh toroṅ</foreign> 'ascetics who practice quackery [rather: never stop fussing], nuns who enjoy quarrelling', and second, SA 934–935 <foreign>ciciṅan hamo surahan, hamo purik mo gariṅsiṅ</foreign> ‘firmly seated, never hot-tempered, never angry, never out of humor’. The last passage, with the words <foreign>surahan</foreign>, <foreign>purik</foreign> and <foreign>gariṅsiṅ</foreign>, shows the same series as the one we have here in SKK. Cf. MdS <foreign>rungsing </foreign>'whining, in a bad mood, dissatisfied’, not in OJ. The meaning in MdS seems to fit in all OS contexts.</note> We should enjoy it all. We should  mean our tasks.</p>
</div>
<div corresp="#skk_07">
<p corresp="#skk_07.01">However, if we are returning home, we should not defecate on the edge of the road, by the side of the house, on its bright end, lest it be smelled by a nobleman <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> by a <foreign>gusti</foreign>, not to mention by people who do not pay attention;<note>The reduplication form <foreign>buṅah-baṅah</foreign> is an emendation based on SMG. Cf. MdS <foreign>balaṅah</foreign> ‘careless’. This word seems to have the same meaning as MdS <foreign>rungah-ringeuh</foreign> ‘look around sheepishly (when o. doesn’t know what to think, drops a brick, etc.)’.</note> lest <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> be cursed <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> blamed<note>On the word <foreign>kapadahkən, </foreign>see my comment on <ref target="#smg_02.02">SMG 2.2</ref>.</note> by <supplied reason="subaudible">our</supplied> mother, father <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> teachers, be opposed<note>My translation is based on the meaning of <foreign>papas</foreign> in OJ. Cf. BM 1523 <foreign>kilaṅ devata kapapas </foreign>‘even the gods are attacked (by them)’. In MdS, <foreign>kapapas</foreign> means ‘accidentally cut by an adze (e.g. so.’s leg)’.</note> by the elders, because of our reckless deeds. But if <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> obey the holy precepts, <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> defecate seven steps<note>ASD read it <foreign>leṅkah</foreign> as in MdS. However, it is worth to note that the Baduy’s dialect has <foreign>leungkah</foreign>, but not recorded in Meijer. E.g., it appears in their idiom <foreign>teu meunang pajauh-jauh leungkah</foreign> ‘it should be far from each other in walking’.</note> from the road <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> urinate three steps from the road. May <supplied reason="subaudible">we</supplied> not meet with criticism from other people, as we know <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign>.<note>Actually the meaning of <foreign>ulah pamali</foreign> is quite clear, namely ‘taboo acts’, but our author interprets the expression in an idiosyncratic way, which imposes the choice to leave the words untranslated.</note> The meaning is: <foreign>ulah</foreign> means sorrow, <foreign>pamali</foreign> means death.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.02">Furthermore, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> watch out for rope barriers (<foreign>gagavar</foreign>),<note><foreign>gagavar</foreign> ‘rope barrier’ is not recorded in MdS and OJ. Cf. MdJ <foreign>gawar</foreign> ‘cord strung between posts to mark off a forbidden area’ (Horne 1974, s.v. <foreign>gawar</foreign>).</note> the ends of snares (? <foreign>pucuk tambaluṅ</foreign>),<note>In OJ, <foreign>tambaluṅ</foreign> means ‘snare’, but in MdS it means ‘(appliance consisting of) a piece of wood with two holes through which arms are stuck (in former times employed to prevent the use of the prisoner’s hands), wooden handcuffs’. In this context it seems to mean ‘snare’ as in OJ.</note> as they could be court reservoirs,<note>Cf. CP  24b <foreign>prəbu ratu devata, iña nu surup ka savah tampian daləm</foreign>.</note> forbidden enclosures, forbidden pavilions — all the more so for obstructing light,<note>The combination <foreign>ṅalaṅ sinaṅ</foreign> is probably from <foreign>alaṅ</foreign> ‘to obstruct’ and OJ <foreign>sinaṅ</foreign> ‘radiance’ (OJED, s.v.). The context is not clear, but it seems that it refers to obstructing the sunlight. However, the prohibition of obstructing sunlight can be found in Baduy, where people are not allowed to build a house that covers the light to the other houses.</note> for coming across <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> passing the king <supplied reason="subaudible">when he is</supplied> walking about, because those are the places where offense is liable to happen.  If we enter the court, we must often look <supplied reason="subaudible">in all directions</supplied>, as it may be that we are trampling, bumping, hitting<note>My translation is taken from OJ <foreign>təmbuṅ </foreign>‘to deal a blow to, to hit’. In MdS it means ‘address so. about st.’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> cutting a line.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_07.03">If we sit down, we should not face the wrong way; we should cross our legs politely. And if we are invited to speak by the master, we should think about what we will say. Whatever is appropriate will please the master. And we should pay close attention to the ones who are to be followed: officer, <foreign>gusti</foreign>, military officer (<foreign>kasasa</foreign>),<note>See my comment on <foreign>kasasa</foreign> in <ref target="#smg_15.06">SMG 15.6</ref>.</note> member of the <foreign>bayangkara</foreign> corps, confidant (<foreign>nu marək</foreign>),<note>Instead of <foreign>nu marǝk</foreign>, ms B has <foreign>marək giraṅ</foreign>, literally means ‘confidant to the upstream?’ seems to be inadequate. The word <foreign>giraṅ</foreign> is one of an honorific prefix in Baduy, e.g. <foreign>girang puun </foreign>‘principal chief’ (in inner Baduy) and <foreign>girang seurat</foreign> ‘sub-ordinate headmen’.</note> messenger, painter, coppersmith, goldsmith, bracelet smith, blacksmith, make up expert (? <foreign>juru vidaṅ</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>vidaṅ</foreign> is obscure. I tentatively assume that <foreign>vidaṅ</foreign> is related to OJ <foreign>vida </foreign>‘make-up, powder, rouge’. Alternatives are to connect it with MdS <foreign>pidang</foreign> ‘wear beautiful clothes, dress up beautifully, deck out beautifully’, or to emend it to <foreign>vidu </foreign>since the word <foreign>vidu</foreign> often occurs in lists of professionals in OJ inscriptions. In the latter case, then the <foreign>juru vidu</foreign> would be a ‘musician’.</note> actor, puppeteer, trumpeter,<note>In MdS, <foreign>kumbang</foreign> denotes a kind of bamboo flute (Hardjadibrata, s.v. <foreign>kumbang</foreign> 2), here it clearly refers to the professional who plays it.</note> gamelan musician, mask performer (<foreign>tapukan</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>tapukan</foreign> presumably has the same meaning as <foreign>atapukan</foreign> or <foreign>anapukan</foreign> in the list of workers in OJ inscriptions. However, its meaning remains obscure. Pigeaud (1938: 125) states that the <foreign>tapukan</foreign> is a mask dancer, while Zoetmulder (OJED, s.v. tapuk) interprets <foreign>tapukan</foreign> as a performance involving percussion beats. The latter interpretation was already proposed by Kunst (1968: 4). The Old Balinese inscription of Gurun Pai, Banjar Lahing, Pandak village, Bandung (Tabanan), suggests that Pigeaud’s hypothesis may be more suitable in our context: <foreign>yan amukul anuliṅ atapukan abañval pirus menmen</foreign>. This list seems to correspond with SKK as follows: <foreign>anuliṅ– kumbaṅ, amukul–gəndiṅ, atapukan–tapukan</foreign>, and <foreign>abañol–bañolan</foreign>. Cf. MdJ <foreign>tapuk</foreign> ‘mask’.</note> joker, dry rice field farmer, palm tapper, paddy farmer, sweeper, death-defier (<foreign>belamati</foreign>), magician (? <foreign>juru moha</foreign>), <foreign>barat katiga</foreign>,<note>See my comment on <foreign>barat katiga</foreign> in <ref target="#smg_15.06">SMG 15.6</ref>.</note> soldier, blowpiper, archer, warrior, collector of <foreign>dasa</foreign> and <foreign>calagara</foreign> (penalties), young shepherds, boar farmers, chicken farmers, fishermen,<note>In MdS, <foreign>palika</foreign> means ‘diver’, but Coolsma denotes it as ‘fisherman fishing with nets in big Waters’ (Coolsma 1913, s.v.). The interpretation of<foreign> palika</foreign> as a diver is unlikely since we have <foreign>prətəlem</foreign>. Cf. CaPur 496.</note> divers,<note>On the prefix <foreign>prə-</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> all those who are of use. If there are any ones who have the virtue of fidelity in service, it is they who are to be followed, for they dedicate themselves to the country.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_08">
<p corresp="#skk_08.01">If there is someone scolded by the master — such a one,<note>The word <foreign>uraṅ</foreign> in the first sentence seems to mean people in general.</note> his actions should not be followed, lest we also be scolded. This is an analogy for it: like a person going into the forest, who steps on a thorn, let’s step on it too,<note>See the explanation of <foreign>keh</foreign> in Chapter 3, §Syntax.</note> it hurts<note>The adjective <foreign>sakitan</foreign> is not attested in OJ, but probably has the same meaning as OJ <foreign>kasakitan </foreign>‘to feel hurt’. In MdS <foreign>sakitan</foreign> refers to the people that have undergone the sickness, and the meaning is ‘convict (in lock-up or forced labour), prisoner’.</note> in the same way. That is why, if there is someone who is praised as the agile, the nimble,<note>In MdS, <foreign>langsit</foreign> is a <foreign>lemes</foreign> register for <foreign>kuru</foreign> ‘thin, slim’, but it does not fit the context. In Malay and MdS the word for <foreign>thin</foreign> is <foreign>ramping</foreign>. It is interesting to compare that in OJ <foreign>rampiṅ</foreign> means ‘effortless, adroit, deft, nimble, skilful, correct, adjusting os. to all circumstances’. So probably this word has changed its meaning from OS ‘<foreign>deft, nimble</foreign>’ to MdS ‘<foreign>thin</foreign>’. Cf. Mal. <foreign>langsing.</foreign></note> sensitive <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> generous (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>),<note>See my comment on SKK 1.4.</note> frugal (<foreign>emet</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>emet</foreign> is probably related to <foreign>emét</foreign> n. <foreign>saemét</foreign> a little bit; <foreign>ngemét-ngemét</foreign> do or use st. in little quantities, use st. frugally. It seems to function as a quasi-synonym of <foreign>imeut</foreign> ‘diligent’ (= MdS). The occurrence of this word in OS is limited to the fixed expression <foreign>emet imət rajǝn lǝkǝn</foreign>. </note> conscientious, diligent, painstaking, faithful to the service of the master — follow the acts and the qualities of such a one, so that we too may be praised!</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.02">If there is someone whose appearance is good, whose behavior is good <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> whose actions are good, we should follow as best as possible (<foreign>saagəṅna</foreign>),<note>See Chapter 3, §Morphology on prefix <foreign>sa- </foreign>with adjective base. Manuscript B has <foreign>sakagəiṅna</foreign> on which basis we might alternatively emend to <foreign>sakaagəṅna</foreign>.</note> because he is considered a superior man.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.03">If there is someone whose appearance is beautiful <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> whose actions are bad <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> whose attitude is dumb, in that case (<foreign>itu</foreign>) we should not look at his appearance, we should not<note>The word <foreign>dara</foreign> ‘do not’ is not in dictionaries. See Noorduyn’s explanation to this word in <foreign>Carita Parahyaṅan</foreign> (Noorduyn 1966: 371–372).</note> follow his actions.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.04">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> whose actions are good, in that case we should not look at his attitude, we should not keep looking at his appearance, we should follow his actions.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.05">If there is someone whose appearance is bad, whose attitude is dumb, whose actions are bad, in that case <supplied reason="subaudible">he</supplied> is what they call ‘the world’s offering (<foreign>caru</foreign>), the victim (<foreign>silih diri</foreign>) for the people of the whole world’,<note>The combination <foreign>silih diri</foreign> does not exist in MdS. In OJ, it means ‘substitute (for another person), esp. offering or victim’. It goes parallel with <foreign>caru </foreign>in several passages in OJ, e.g. Sut 141.3: <foreign>maṅgəh ṅvaṅ siliḍirya saṅ prabhu gumantya carva taḍahən</foreign> “I am willing to take your place to be sacrificed and devoured [by god Kāla]”. ASD read <foreign>carut</foreign> without marking it as an emendation.</note> the defect<note>I prefer the B reading <foreign>cala </foreign>instead of <foreign>calaṅ</foreign> in A and EdASD, and take its meaning to be ‘defect, lack, shortcoming, fault, blemish, spot’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>cala</foreign> 3). The meaning of <foreign>calaṅ</foreign> would be uncertain, though in MdS we find <foreign>kacingcalang</foreign> ‘adj. (of an egg) bad (laid but did not hatch); (also said of a person that is) no good for anything, good-for-nothing’ which seems to be related. <foreign>Pūrvādhigama</foreign> (§5.5) has <foreign>calaṅ caṅkriṅan</foreign>. Taking it from this text, Zoetmulder relates <foreign>calaṅ</foreign> to a ‘certain tax or contribution given to the <foreign>maṅilala dr̥vya haji</foreign>’.</note> of human beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.06">That is what should be remembered — the unmeritorious, the meritorious; the bad, the good<note>See the end of SKK 8.8, where the order is reversed: nu gopel nu rampes, nu hala nu hayu.</note> — take <supplied reason="subaudible">them as</supplied> teacher. This is the reminder of it: if anyone dies while stealing, dies while sneaking, dies while robbing, dies while infiltrating, any kind of impudent <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> deceitful <supplied reason="subaudible">behavior</supplied>, we should watch them for <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> are not to be followed. That is called the vile as a teacher.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.07">There is more: if we see people performing wayang, listen to people performing pantun, acquire teachings from the stories, that is called the stage as teacher. If we acquire good teachings from people reading, that is called the story<note>In this context, <foreign>taṅtu</foreign> seems to mean ‘thread (contents) of a story’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>tantu</foreign> III), not in MdS. </note> as teacher. If we observe the products of handicraft: carvings, sculptures, planks, drawings, we should not<note>The prohibition <foreign>sui</foreign> means ‘do not, we should not’, not in MdS, while <foreign>svī</foreign> in OJ has a different meaning ‘insisting, urging, pressing’. Cf. SA 746 <foreign>samapun sui pamali</foreign> ‘Pardon, you should not [do that], it is forbidden’; BM 890 <foreign>sui dipavalaṅati</foreign> ‘don’t be anxious about it’.</note> ask the craftsmen<note>I favor the B reading and edit <foreign>dikuryak</foreign> because of its correspondence with the previous use of <foreign>dikuryak</foreign>, and because <foreign>guna</foreign> is used in a different sense in both A and B in a following sentence. In the A reading <foreign>diguna</foreign>, it seems somewhat unusual that <foreign>guna</foreign> is used in the meaning ‘to work, to act, to perform’, although this usages is not entirely unknown in OS. See e.g. RD <foreign>ja aiṅ nu digave tan kapigave, ja aiṅ nu diguna tan kapiguna</foreign> “Because I who create without being created, who act without being affected by the acts [of others]”.</note> — we should find out by our own feelings, as a result of paying attention to other people’s skill. It is called profession<note>In Skt., one of the meanings of <foreign>vr̥tti</foreign> is ‘profession, maintenance, subsistence, livelihood’ (MW, s.v.). This meaning is not acknowledged explicitly in OJED, but it appears likely from this context that it was known in Java/Sunda.</note> as a teacher.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_08.08">Acquiring precepts from children, it is called children as teachers. Acquiring <foreign>dharma</foreign> from our grandfather, it is called the grandfather as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our elder brother (<foreign>lañcək</foreign>), it is called the elder brother (<foreign>kakaṅ</foreign>) as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from the elders, it is called our parents’ elder siblings (<foreign>uva</foreign>) as teachers. Acquiring rules of conduct from the places where we travel, (whether it is) in the village, in a place for staying overnight, in a place for breaking journey, in a place of lodging, it is called the road as teacher. Acquiring rules of conduct from our parents, it is called the origins as teacher. Especially if (you find rules of conduct in) words (<foreign>hatur</foreign>)<note>In this context, I take <foreign>hatur</foreign> as a noun, indicating the teaching given by the teacher. See OJED (s.v. <foreign>hatur</foreign> 4) ‘that which is respectfully told (reported), when appearing before a person of high rank’. In this case, the reading <foreign>ti</foreign> of ms. B instead of <foreign>ka</foreign> in ms. A is more plausible.</note> from a great scholar, it is called the excellence as teacher, it is called honor as teacher, it is called authority as teacher, it is called doctrines as teacher: those are called the four excellences (<foreign>catur-utama</foreign>). Which is why,<note>There is a mark indicating the end of the topic in the manuscripts. On the limited reliability of section marking in the mss., see Chapter 5, §Manuscripts.</note> when they are finished being done by those who do, being accomplished by those who accomplish, (then) all are finished being observed: the bad and the good, the evil and the just.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_09">
<p corresp="#skk_09.01">Likewise, if there is someone who praises us, our feelings should not be joyful, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> we should in turn cast back <supplied reason="subaudible">the praise</supplied> to those who praise, so that we will not be overshadowed by the other’s praise. If we are keen on being praised, it is like the ‘long pole with weak extensions (<foreign>galah dava sinambuṅan tuna</foreign>)’. <supplied reason="subaudible">If our</supplied> feelings are pleased with the praise, then it leads to vanity. Because we feel ourselves to be in our own house — by food, drink, pleasures, enjoyments, utensils (<foreign>pakaraṅ</foreign>)<note>In MdS <foreign>pakarang</foreign> means ‘weapon’, but it seems ‘utensil’ is more suitable based on the context. Cf. SKK 10.2 <foreign>pakaraṅ ulah tihap ṅiñjəm</foreign> ‘utensils are not just to borrow’. Cf. also <ref target="#smg_12.02">SMG 12.2</ref> where <foreign>papakaraṅan</foreign> is used to translate OJ <foreign>agəm-agəman</foreign> in the corresponding passage <ref target="#siksaguru_05.03">SiGu 5.3</ref>: <foreign>prətanəm ṅaranya, hantə ṅənah ṅambəan tadahən saṅ guru, maṅkaṅuni make papakaraṅan saṅ pandita</foreign> “<foreign>Prǝtanǝm</foreign> means it is improper to smell the food of the teacher, let alone to use the utensils of the scholar” (The corresponding OJ words in <ref target="#siksaguru_05.03">SiGu 5.3</ref> are: <foreign>saṅ guru saṅghāsanam pr̥tatəm [...] tan paṅambvan taḍahən saṅ guru, tar paṅaṅgva agəm-agəman saṅ guru</foreign>). The word <foreign>agəm-agəman</foreign> is not recorded in OJED, but it clearly derived from <foreign>agəm</foreign> ‘grasp’ so <foreign>agəm-agəman</foreign> means ‘items that are grasped’, i.e. ‘utensils’. It must be close in meaning to OJ and OS <foreign>gagaman</foreign> ‘arms, weapon’. However, <foreign>pakaraṅ</foreign> also occurs in the sense ‘weapon’, especially in TB 14.4 <foreign>maṅkaṅuni sañjatana pahi divayakǝn, pakaraṅ pañcamahabuta, saṅ hyaṅ pǝpǝt pǝtǝṅ adikara</foreign> “and also all of his weapons are prepared, the weapon called ‘five gross elements’, [and] ‘the holy supreme envelope’”.</note> — then they are used as something to be proud of (<foreign>aṅgəhan</foreign>).<note>I interpret <foreign>aṅgəhan</foreign> as ‘something to be proud of’. In OS <foreign>aṅg̵əh</foreign> occurs in RR 1433 <foreign>ulah aṅgəh-aṅgəh təiṅ </foreign>‘don’t be overconfidence’. In OJ <foreign>aṅgəh</foreign> means ‘fixed place, position, location; proper place, proper function (condition, way of being); personal relationship (esp. within the family)’. It seems that the word <foreign>aṅgəh</foreign> is somehow related to MdS <foreign>angkeuh </foreign>‘image (in the mind), notion, imagination, fancy, delusion’, whose derived form <foreign>angkeuhan</foreign> means ‘what o. imagines/ fancy, what o. believes, notion (that o. has); st. of which o. imagines a lot of o.self, st. upon which o. fancies to be able to trust/ call upon’. Glossary NT note <foreign>aṅgəh</foreign> ‘to feel sure’.  KUBS notes <foreign>angkeuh, angkeuhan</foreign>, ‘<foreign>kamegahan</foreign>’ (luxury) and <foreign>umangkeuh</foreign> as ‘<foreign>ieu aing</foreign>’ (arrogant). Cf. Mal. <foreign>angkuh </foreign>‘arrogant’. Here <foreign>aṅgəhan</foreign> is a nominal form means ‘something to be arrogant about, something to be proud of’.</note> It is like the ‘long pole’ (as above); it is <supplied reason="subaudible">also</supplied> like the ‘empty paddy stalk’.<note>On the expression of pare hapa, cf. AG 6r: <foreign>Uməsi t</foreign>a<foreign> karaḥ lagu tu⟨ṅ⟩kul·, haray·⟨⟨hay·⟩⟩ Asśak ta ⟨⟨ka⟩⟩raḥ cadukur, ṅarasa maneḥ kaqəsi, Aya si nu hayaṁ, daEk tu maka hurip· na Uraṁ reya, Agamaniṁ pare pun·, lamun uməsi taṁgaḥ, harayhay· taṁgaḥ, Asak taṁgaḥ, hapa ṅarana</foreign>. “[When the paddy] is filled, it lowers his head instead, when it's time to ripen, it ducks down instead, because it feels itself to be full. There will be the one who wants it. The custom of paddy is that it will make the people alive. If [the paddy] lifts the head when filled, lifts the head when it begins to have a yellow tinge, lifts its head when ripe, it means it is empty”.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.02">Likewise, if there is someone who insults us, we should accept all the other’s insults, which is why it is comparable to the ‘pole cut short’. Suppose we have warts,<note>In the present context, <foreign>kudil</foreign> seems to refer to some kind of skin disease. Is it related to OJ <foreign>kuḍis</foreign> ‘scurvy, scabby’ or to MdS <foreign>kutil</foreign> ‘wart’? The latter is more similar phonologically.</note> it is like water for bathing; suppose we have dry skin,<note>The word <foreign>kurit</foreign> is probably the same as Mal. <foreign>kurik</foreign> ‘freckle, speckle [on skin]’. Cf. MdS <foreign>hurik</foreign> ‘have a blackish colour (of hens, also over-ripe bananas etc.)’. In my understanding, <foreign>hurik</foreign> also refers to ‘dry skin’.  The sound change from /t/ to /k/ is unusual, but that does not mean it is inconceivable. I may cite these changes in the Baduy dialect: <foreign>atma</foreign> &gt; <foreign>akma</foreign> and <foreign>teja</foreign> &gt; <foreign>keja</foreign>. Another possibility is to emend it to <foreign>kurik</foreign>.</note> it is like a person coming to smearing <supplied reason="subaudible">us</supplied> with oil; suppose we are hungry,<note>The meaning ‘hungry’ for <foreign>poño</foreign> only occurs in OS; its meaning in MdS is slightly different, viz. ‘nice and full (eat, sleep), do o. self well, eat heartily’. Cf. SMG 9.2 <foreign>jr̥mbhanam ṅaranya, hantə ṅənah mikonokən maneh hanaaṅ poño, aṅgəs ma vərə səbəh, di harəpən saṅ pandita</foreign> ‘<foreign>jr̥mbhanam</foreign> means it is improper to declare oneself thirsty and hungry, even though one is excessively full in front of the learned teacher’; also in SKK 10.2.</note> it is like a person coming to give rice;<note>It is quite remarkable that the word <foreign>kejo</foreign> ‘rice’ (= MdS) is not found in OJ and Mal. However, it seems that the word <foreign>kijo</foreign>, which is very likely the predecessor to <foreign>kejo</foreign>, is found only in SHH, an OJ text from the Sundanese region: <foreign>kady aṅganiṅ səkul an makveh ṅaranya, ya səkul, ya me, ya baikṣa, ya nasi, ya kijo, ya praṇik, ya campagi, ya mandura, ya gərul, səkul katuṅgalan ika, iva maṅkana tekaṅ hədap an makveh ṅaranya</foreign> “Like the rice in having many names: <foreign>səkul, me, baikṣa, nasi,  kijo, praṇik, campagi, mandura, gərul</foreign>. Rice is only one. So is the mind, its names are many”.</note> suppose we are thirsty, it is like a person coming to give to drink; suppose we are dejected, it is like a person coming to give betel quid — they are called the five pure ones (<foreign>pañca-parisuda</foreign>). That is like the ‘pole cut short’.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_09.03">If <supplied reason="subaudible">the insult</supplied> makes us happy, <supplied reason="subaudible">we are</supplied> like paddy chock full <supplied reason="subaudible">with rice grains</supplied>,<note>The expression <foreign>pare bərat saṅga</foreign> literarily means ‘paddy with heavy to hold’. Cf. the similar expression in Malay <foreign>padi berisi kian merunduk</foreign> ‘the more paddy stalk is filled, the more it is stoop’, referring to a humble intelligent person.</note> that might keep the people alive,<note>Regarding <foreign>maka suka</foreign> in the present context, cf. another meaning of <foreign>mangka</foreign> in MdS ‘s.m.  <foreign>matak</foreign>, <foreign>nu mangka</foreign>; <foreign>taya mangkana</foreign> s.m. <foreign>taya matakna</foreign> (it) doesn’t seem to matter, (it) doesn’t make a difference’ (Hardjadibrata, s.v.  <foreign>mangka b</foreign>)‘. The word <foreign>matak</foreign> means ‘be the cause of, leading towards, with the consequence that, causing (st. to happen, a situation to occur, etc.)’. See the discussion of <foreign>maka</foreign> in Chapter 3, §Morphology. See KaPaṅ 1073–1075 <foreign>nu makaiṅ ṅarəṅəhən, nu makaiṅ jəjəəṅən, teka rumaṅ brənaṅ siaṅ, parapat kunaṅ-kunaṅan, na ku imah maṅəniṅ, na imah sarba kañcana</foreign> ‘what made me watch intensely, what made me astonishing, then it seen vaguely before it is bright clearly, blinking like fireflies, is by the lucent house, the house with gold ornament everywhere’. Cf. <foreign>maka</foreign> in Old Malay and Mal. <foreign>makanya.</foreign></note> because the origin of joy and pleasure has been obtained. Even if those who are slandering us are wrong, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> take <supplied reason="subaudible">their slander as</supplied> advice.<note>ASD take <foreign>saṅkilaṅ nu ṅupat uraṅ salah, ala pañaraman</foreign> differently and translate this clause as ‘<foreign>(yaitu) tahan celaan dan mengambil (memperhatikan) nasihat orang lain</foreign>’.</note> If we have the behavior (about which we are slandered), <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> stop <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied>. If we do not have <supplied reason="subaudible">such</supplied> behavior, we should consider (<foreign>uṅaṅ</foreign>)<note>In KUBS, <foreign>diungang </foreign>means ‘ditimbang-timbang’ (to consider). In OJ it means ‘to look down on or in, overlook, look into’. Ms B contains <foreign>ala</foreign>, it means that one should take [the accusation] as the mother, father, and teachers, so I render <foreign>uṅaṅ ambu bapa paṅguruan</foreign> as having the same construction as <foreign>ala pañaraman</foreign>. Cf. <foreign>Carita Pantun Nyi Sumur Bandung</foreign>: <foreign>nyabdana tara diungang</foreign> “his speech is thoughtless”.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">the slander</supplied> (to merit attention), like mother, father <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> teachers. The meaning<note>The word <foreign>kaliṅane</foreign> with enclitic <foreign>-e</foreign> only occurs in this paragraph, but <foreign>kaliṅanya</foreign> or <foreign>kaliṅanna</foreign>, <foreign>passim</foreign> in this text.</note> of what is called a human being (<foreign>janma</foreign>): ‘It is considered the ultimate supreme; it is considered the deity becoming human; the one who has a perfect body,<note>Rather than to split the words as <foreign>saṅ purna sarira</foreign>, I read <foreign>saṅpurnasarira</foreign> as local spelling of the Sanskrit compound <foreign>sampūrṇaśārīra</foreign> ‘one who has a perfect body’, attested in the Daśa-bāyu mantra used on Bali during the ritual of taking scarf: <foreign>idəp jaya sampūrṇaśarīraniṅsun</foreign> (Hooykaas 1973: 66). Cf. the <foreign>śloka</foreign> in Gaṇ 57 <foreign>bhaktaṁ tu jagati loke śuddhapūrṇaśarīraṇam</foreign>; Tjñ 46 <foreign>yeka nimittani rāsana paripūrṇa śarīranira</foreign>.</note> who is the origin of goodness, and the source of the truth’.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_10"><p n="1" corresp="#skk_10.01">These are the complementary practices,<note>The word <foreign>paṅimbuh</foreign> (OJED, s.v. <foreign>imbuh</foreign> “addition, a means to increase (the beauty of st.)”, with reference to Sri Tañjuṅ 1.62 <foreign>kəmbaṅ priyaka paṅimbuh gəluṅ</foreign> “the <foreign>priyaka</foreign>’s flower is a beauty enhancer of [her] chignon”) is attested in the OJ Talan inscription <foreign>kunaṁ rasani paṅimbuḥ śrī mahārāja Irikaṁ vargga ri talan· ri vnaṅanyāvarugā Inantun·</foreign> “As for the substance of the additional [grant] (paṅimbuh) of the Great King to the inhabitants in Talan”; <foreign>maṅkana rasani paṅimbuḥ śrī mahārāja Irikaṁ vargga ri talan·</foreign> “Such was the substance of the additional [grant] of the Great King to the inhabitants of Talan, to stand permanently on a stone stele” (text and translation Eko Bastiawan <foreign>et al</foreign>., forthcoming). In the present context, ‘complementary’ seems to be a suitable meaning.</note> so that no living beings<note>I take <foreign>sakala</foreign> in the sense of ‘all, whole’ (see OJED s.v. 2). Cf. FCP 26a.3 where <foreign>maṅhurip</foreign> is preceded by a synonym word <foreign>sarva</foreign>: <foreign>kita tuturkǝnǝn voṅ sakabeh, pinaka dǝdǝlan bvana, pinaka dasarniṅ prǝtivi, andǝlan sarvoṅ maṅhurip</foreign>.</note> are ruined, so that [we are] blessed<note>I consider <foreign>vastu</foreign> (cf. Malay <foreign>restu</foreign>, from Sanskrit <foreign>siddhir astu</foreign>) as a substantive verb in this context, with meaning ‘achieved, succeed, blessed’. The same construction, this time after the word <foreign>palana</foreign> (parallel to <foreign>pakən</foreign>), is found in KaMah 70: <foreign>palana vastu di tutur</foreign> ‘its result: the consciousness is achieved’; KavPani: 495–197: <foreign>aiṅ mana yukti, mana vastu bayu sabda hdap, sya nu purah ṅavǝkaskǝn</foreign> “[As for] me, the reason that [my] breath, speech [and] mind are proper, the reason [that they are] blessed, it is the One whose task it is to give instructions”. Cf. SC 1039 <foreign>vastu bənaṅ nu mahayu</foreign> “achieved as a result of arranging”. Cf. OJ vastu and its derivations <foreign>amastvani, (u)mastvi, vinastvan, kavastvan</foreign> (more or less = <foreign>amastu</foreign>) ‘to know or perceive st. in its concrete form; to form a picture of, define’. Cf. also MdS <foreign>éstu</foreign> ‘really, true; in truth, in reality; faithfully (carried out, observed); to have a sincere intention (<foreign>ka</foreign>) towards so.’.</note> in our houses: careful [and] conscientious, scrupulous [and] diligent, sensitive [and] generous (<foreign>paka pradana</foreign>),<note>See my comment on SKK 1.4.</note> not falling down (? <foreign>mo rogol-rogol</foreign>),<note>ASD take it as <foreign>morogol-rogol</foreign> and translate it ‘bersemangat’. In MdS it means ‘fall down (one after the other, of rice kernels off the ear)’. With this basis, I tend to interpret <foreign>mo rogol-rogol</foreign> as  ‘not falling down, steadfast, upright’.</note> champions among experts, strong [and] unfatigued,<note>For the expression of <foreign>hapitan karavaleya</foreign> ‘strong and unfatigued’; see Aditia Gunawan 2019: 18.</note> mobile [and] nimble.</p>
<p n="2" corresp="#skk_10.02">If we put dry rice-fields (<foreign>gaga</foreign>) and paddy fields under cultivation, it is only so that we do not suffer. If we make an orchard, it is only so that we do not pick in someone else’s small field, in someone else’s broad field — except by virtue of our having asked permission, politely requesting.<note>The word <foreign>bema</foreign> is not found in Dictionaries, but MdS records <foreign>bémakrama</foreign> ‘good etiquette’. Sundanese dictionaries note the “Kawi” derivation of <foreign>bemakrama</foreign>. Cf. SKK 4.14 for a parallel expression.</note> [As for] domestic animals, we should not just buy, not just swap [them]. [As for] utensils, we should not just borrow [them]. [As for] blankets [and] loincloths, we should not have too many of them.<note>The base word <foreign>kasaratan</foreign> is <foreign>sarat</foreign> meaning ‘heavily loaded, overloaded (esp. of a boat)’ = MdS; Cf. OJ ‘heavily laden; to run aground’. Cf. RR 1324–1325 in which <foreign>sarat</foreign> seems to be synonymous with <foreign>pənuh</foreign> ‘full’ and occurs outside of the context of transport: <foreign>pənuh di na suruṅ maṅguṅ, sarat di na pada handap</foreign> ‘It was full in the upper dais, crammed in the lower platform’. ASD translate it as ‘kekurangan’ (<foreign>lacking</foreign>), which is quite the opposite of its real meaning. Cf. <foreign>kasaratan</foreign> in PYñ 22.7: <foreign>kayu hanan kasaratan vatunya kasəlap ri paṅ iṅ kayu</foreign> “the trees are heavily laden, [for] the rocks are crammed inside the branch of trees”. In the Malay syair <foreign>Siti Zubaidah</foreign> (ca. 1800), we find the word <foreign>sarat</foreign> being used in relation to clothes: <foreign>saratnya pakaian Ahmad Paduka, intan permata berjenis neka, lengkaplah dengan geleng paduka, sekalian pakaian tiada terhingga</foreign> “In abundance are the clothes of His Majesty Ahmad: diamonds and jewels of various kinds, complete with His Majesty’s bracelet, while his clothes are innumerable”.</note> [As for] food and drink, we should not have too little. Our children and wife should be given advice, to avoid [their] being accused of being ‘disrespectful’ (<foreign>durbala siksa</foreign>).<note>The expression <foreign>durbala siksa</foreign> literally means ‘weak with regard to the instruction’. It is important to note that this compound is made up from Sanskrit loanwords but is not found in the OJ corpus. So probably this is a Sanskritization of local idiom. In MdS we find the similar expression <foreign>atah warah</foreign> ‘too little admonished, uneducated, unmannered’ (litt. immature in teaching). Cf. the Mal. idiom <foreign>kurang ajar</foreign> ‘disrespectful’. However, <foreign>bālaśikṣā</foreign> exists in some Skt. texts, so the expression could also mean ‘poor pedagogy’. In that case, an alternative translation would be: ‘to avoid [us] being accused of poor pedagogy (<foreign>durbalasiksa</foreign>)’.</note> </p>
<p n="3" corresp="#skk_10.03">Observe the hermits’ precepts for society: if we sleep, [it is only] as a remedy for sleepiness;<note>In this context, I consider that the conditional sense of <foreign>jaga raṅ</foreign> is not very strong in the sentence, presumably more equivalent to Mal. <foreign>kalau</foreign>. Thus I translate it ‘that we sleep only as a remedy for sleepiness’.</note> [if we] drink palm wine, [it is only] as a remedy for thirst; [if we] eat, [it is only] a remedy for hunger. We should not be careless [about them]. We should remember<note>I take the meaning of <foreign>mariṅ</foreign> from OJ ‘to, toward, in the direction of’ (OJED, s.v. I).</note> their [potential] absence. Even more so by children and by wife, we should not be shackled, for they may not behave in accordance [with our advice]. If [they are] good, by virtue of us giving advice, after which [they] follow the advice, those are called our children and our wife. If they do not follow [our] admonition, they are the same as outsiders. But if we insist on claiming our wife and child despite them being away without giving any news,<note>Cf. MdS <foreign>medeng</foreign> ‘be away without giving any news, do not let o.self be heard’.</note> we will probably be burdened, we will probably be lost in hell together, lost [will be] the results of our worship, ruined the results of the ancestors (<foreign>cakal bagal</foreign>).<note>See my comment on <foreign>cakal bakal </foreign>under 4.8.</note></p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_11"><p n="1" corresp="#skk_11.01">This is the instruction of Darma Pitutur,<note>This combination occurs in some other Old Sundanese texts as well, e.g., KaPaṅ 151 <foreign>muṅkur ti darma pitutur</foreign> ‘turning away from the law and the admonitions’. SA 865–880 narrates that true <foreign>viku</foreign>s who have understood the <foreign>darma pitutur</foreign> deserve liberation. In OJ, the compound <foreign>dharma pitutur</foreign> occurs in a list in BK 108.9d, and Teeuw &amp; Robson translate as ‘moral law and teaching’: <foreign>pūjā dhyāna samādhi dharma pitutur panalimur ira riṅ kapaṇḍitan</foreign> “Praise, meditation, concentration, the moral law and teaching are a distraction for him in his pursuit of spiritual learning”. In BM 330–331 we encounter an indication that <foreign>darma pitutur</foreign> might be differentiated from <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ darma</foreign>: <foreign>vǝruh di na darma pitutur, bisa di saṅ hiaṅ darma</foreign> ‘knows the law and the admonitions, is acquainted with the Sacred Law’. In the present text, the combination <foreign>darma pitutur</foreign> is systematically preceded by the personal article <foreign>saṅ</foreign> (cf. SKK 11.6, 12.5, 23.1), suggesting that the intended meaning is the personification of such <foreign>darma pitutur</foreign>. Also in the mantra <foreign>Dharma Paṅulih</foreign> recorded by Hooykaas (1993: 180), we find a line of mantra: <foreign>aja tan paṅandəl i pitutur saṅ hyaṅ dharma, oṁ saṁ baṁ taṁ aṁ iṁ, naṁ maṁ śiṁ vāṁ yaṁ</foreign>.</note> to avoid our not thinking of [the instruction of Darma Pitutur].</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.02">“<foreign>sriopeksah samutatah, paesanteh tan susuriyəm, jambaṅan esiniṅ bañu mahəniṅ, tah desanatah nora buksah</foreign>”<note>This paragraph seems to be intended as a quote in verse. However, this śloka is composed in a language that mixes “Sanskrit” and “Old Javanese”. Only lines 1 and 4 consist of eight syllables, while the second line has one extra syllable, and the third line has an excess of three syllables. Of these four lines, only the third is easy to understand, meaning ‘a pot filled with clear water’. The meaning of <foreign>sri opeksah samutatah</foreign> is obscure. The word <foreign>sri</foreign> means ‘beautiful, amazing, splendor’, but the OS paraphrase refers to it as ‘gold’. The word <foreign>opeksah</foreign> can be traced from Skt. <foreign>apekṣa</foreign> &gt; OJ <foreign>opekṣa, mopekṣa</foreign> ‘to pay attention to, take account of; notice, observe’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>opekṣa</foreign>). The meaning of <foreign>samutatah</foreign> is not understood. The word <foreign>paesanteh</foreign> (not to be read <foreign>paesan teh</foreign>) is presumably a style of expression in order to give a Sanskrit impression to the OJ word <foreign>paesan</foreign> ‘mirror’. However, it seems that the element <foreign>teh</foreign> is not an Old Sundanese particle, since it is totally absent in OS corpus. The word <foreign>susuriyəm</foreign> is meant to give the same impression. This word is probably derived from <foreign>suruy</foreign> or <foreign>suri</foreign> ‘a comb’, and its reduplicated derivation <foreign>asusuri</foreign> is attested (OJED, s.v. suruy). The meaning of <foreign>paesanteh tan susuriyəm</foreign> may be ‘not using a quid in front of the mirror’, but the expected meaning is ‘the mirror is the place to comb’. The sentence <foreign>tah desanatah nora buksah</foreign> is even more obscure. The expected meaning would be ‘the region if it is not empty’, as we learn from its explanation. If we expect such a meaning, then maybe we need to take <foreign>nora buksah</foreign> as a mistake for a hybrid form <foreign>norābhūka</foreign> ‘not empty’? The problem is that the Skt. word <foreign>ābhūka</foreign> is not attested nor in OJ and in OS. However, the ms. B reading <foreign>tah desana tah nobusah</foreign> is metrical.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.03">The meaning is: <foreign>sri</foreign> means gold. Gold is like this: If it is not coated, its beauty is washed away.<note>I take the meaning of <foreign>pǝlǝk</foreign> from OJ ‘drowned, swallowed up, washed away’ (OJED, s.v.)</note> If it is coated, [it will be] beautifully bright<note>In MdS <foreign>cénang</foreign> means ‘k.o. small ulcer on the skin’. But in OS, it always means ‘shine, bright’. Cf. LJ 9.14–32 <foreign>bray bitan kilat mijil sǝmbava, heraṅ, cenaṅ, lumeṅgaṅ, tərus paratnikaṅ bvana</foreign> ‘the existence (<foreign>səmbava</foreign>) is shining like the coming of thunder, clear, bright, translucent, penetrating through the world’. On variant readings in B involving the <foreign>aksara mp</foreign> in A, see Chapter 5, §Siksa Kandaṅ Karəsian.</note> for it is well treated. Likewise is the analogy, for us humans here: if [we] follow the holy precepts, its essence will be well maintained by us, like the straight meeting its straight. Likewise, if we do not follow the holy precepts of the accomplished one (<foreign>krəta</foreign>),<note>I interpret <foreign>krəta</foreign> as referring to a person. In prescriptive OJ texts such as the unpublished <foreign>Pūrvādhigama</foreign>, the expression <foreign>saṅ krəta</foreign> refers to ‘the consecrated priest’. It is probably derived from <foreign>saṅakr̥ta </foreign>‘one who has been initiated’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>askr̥ta</foreign>) which itself reflects Skt. <foreign>saṁskr̥ta</foreign>. In our context, it seems that <foreign>kr̥ta</foreign> has taken on a more general meaning, ‘the perfected ones, the accomplished one’, referring to ancient figures who are considered to have promulgated basic precepts. Can it be the figure Darma Pitutur? Cf. <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ sasana krəta</foreign> in SKK 13.3 and 15.1 which seems to be an equivalent expression.</note> [it is] like the crooked meeting its crooked.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.04"><foreign>Paesan </foreign>means mirror. The mirror is like this: If it is not regarded attentively,<note><foreign>kavaas</foreign> ‘to be observed, to be regarded attentively’. In MdS <foreign>waas</foreign> means ‘moving, stirring of satisfying happy feelings (because of seeing an enchanting landscape, listening to a sweet melody, thinking about pleasant experiences, etc.)’. Such a nuance also occurs in OS: SA 42–44 <foreign>sia ləmpaṅ sumoreaṅ, təhər rəmbay na cimata, vaas di na kasorgaan </foreign>‘While going he looked back, and burst into tears, sadly remembering the heavenly abode’. However, in this context, the meaning is more related to MdS <foreign>awas </foreign>‘be able to see well; look properly with o.’s eyes, pay attention closely’ and OJ <foreign>avās </foreign>‘clear (clearly visible or audible), (of persons:) clear, having clear insight; to be clear (evident) that; bright, becoming light’.</note> our image is vague. If it is regarded attentively, our appearance is clear upon that mirror. Likewise are we humans here. If we can follow the customs<note>The word <foreign>upacara</foreign> means ‘the proper conduct, etiquette’, = OJ. In MdS it means ‘ceremony’ = Mal.</note> of others adequately, it may well be internalized<note>Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw note two meanings of this word. The first is ‘to be ignorant’ or ‘to be miserable’, as in MdS = OJ <foreign>kalesan</foreign> ‘afflicted by misfortune’. The second is ‘to be aware of, to become acquainted, to acquaint oneself’. In this passage, the second meaning seems to make more sense. It is attested in RR 729–730 <foreign>aiṅ hayaṅ kalihasan</foreign>, <foreign>təhər dek neaṅ dayəhna </foreign>“I want to acquaint myself personally, and after that I wish to visit their city”. In the Indonesian version of the edition of BM (l. 210) we have <foreign>timburu nu kalihasan</foreign>, but in the english version <foreign>timburu nu kahiasan</foreign>. Since the usage here is transitive, I propose the meaning ‘to internalize’. Cf. SKK 18.5.</note> by our feelings. If we cannot follow the advice, it is called stupid.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.05"><foreign>Jambaṅan </foreign>means an object giving reflection.<note>Hardjadibrata gives ‘to be reflected in the water’ as the meaning of <foreign>muruy</foreign>, but I rather follow KUBS which paraphrases <foreign>muruy</foreign> as meaning <foreign>ngeunteung kana cai</foreign> ‘to look into water as mirror’. Hardjadibrata glosses MdS <foreign>pamuruyan</foreign> as ‘an object which is reflected’ whereas I consider that it means ‘a place for using water as mirror’. The word is not found in OJ.</note> The mind of the one who is accomplished is like clear water. That is the reason why we should regard [it] attentively, then the heart will be pleased.<note>The meaning of <foreign>rame</foreign> is based on the reference in OJ (&lt; Skt <foreign>ramya</foreign>) ‘to be enjoyed, pleasing, delightful, beautiful’; in MdS it means ‘lively, busy, noisy; pleasant, cosy, animated (discussion), much frequented; closely populated; exciting, thrilling (story, book, film)’ = Mal. <foreign>ramai</foreign>. Cf. SKK 11.7 <foreign>heraṅ tinəṅ, rame ambək</foreign>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.06"><foreign>Desa</foreign> means settlement. If the settlement is empty, there is nothing to be followed. Words are like that: if they are not substantial, they are considered deceitful. But if the residence is filled, that is to be followed. Likewise are words: they should be meaningful, so that they be considered truthful in character.<note>This seems to be a compound of the type <foreign>sakit hati</foreign> in Malay, so I translate it as ‘truthful in character’. See the second meaning of <foreign>lakṣaṇa</foreign> in OJED ‘action, doing (as opp. to inaction, words, thinking, etc), taking action, proceeding, operating, performing, practice’.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.07">Likewise are we humans here. If we wish to know the source of the joy and happiness, we should remember the word of the Darma Pitutur. This is the verse:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#skk_11.08">‘The pond is the habitat of the goose;<note>The metaphor of the goose and pond also occurs in VG 2 <foreign>lamunna bahe ka keñca ṅaranna talaga haṅsa, asih voṅ sajagat, pañudana pacar pimula di pahoman</foreign> “if the land is sloping to the left, it is called the pond and the goose, all people will give compassion. The means of purification: <foreign>pacar</foreign> should be planted in the worship place”.</note> the forest is the elephant’s habitat; the sea is the habitat of fishes; flowers are the habitat of the bee’.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.09">The meaning is: if we are going to imitate behavior (<foreign>cəta</foreign>), we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about the clear pond, fresh water,<note> I choose the B reading, because <foreign>taman heraṅ</foreign> does not make sense; See also <foreign>talaga heraṅ</foreign> at the end of the section. Several OS texts relate the adjectives <foreign>heraṅ</foreign>, or its synonym <foreign>həniṅ</foreign> ‘clear’, with <foreign>talaga</foreign>, viz. PNJ 142–142 <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ talaga heraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>saṅ hyaṅ talaga həniṅ</foreign>; BM 52–53 (as toponym): <foreign>nəpi ka Talaga Həniṅ</foreign>.</note> [we should] ask the goose. The meaning is: if there is a person who is firm in steering,<note>The word <foreign>apraniti</foreign> is derived from Skt. <foreign>praṇīti</foreign> ‘conduct, leading, guidance’. Cf. OJ <foreign>pranīti</foreign> and MdS <foreign>praniti</foreign>. However, the prefixed form <foreign>apranīti</foreign> is not recorded in OJED.</note> whose mind is clear, [and] whose heart is pleasant, that is indeed comparable to the goose on the clear pond.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.10">If we seek to know about the depth of the sea, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask a fish. The meaning is: like the man who knows about the mind of the divine king and about the mind of the great scholar.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.11">If we seek to know about the remoteness of  forests, [we should] ask the elephant. This is its meaning: what is comparable to the remote<note>The word <foreign>lvar</foreign> literally means  ‘exterior’. In MdS, <foreign>luar</foreign> as an adjective for a place often means beyond control: <foreign>urang luar</foreign> ‘outsider’, <foreign>nagara luar</foreign> ‘foreign country’. It is worth noting that MdS <foreign>liar</foreign> means ‘go out, go away from home, wander (roam, rove) around (e.g. of animals seeking food)’. The interchangeability of <foreign>u</foreign> and <foreign>i</foreign> in <foreign>lvar</foreign> and <foreign>liar</foreign> is comparable to such a pair as <foreign>kulon</foreign>/<foreign>kilen</foreign> ‘west’. Cf. RR 963–964 <foreign>sadataṅ ka təgal luar, məntasiṅ di na Saṅ hiaṅ</foreign> ‘Having reached the outer fields, they crossed the Saṅ Hiaṅ’. BM 1381 has Tigal Luar as a toponym, but I think it should be emended to <foreign>təgal luar</foreign>, and probably it is not a toponym: <foreign>ṅalalar ka mulah bǝṅhar, ñaṅlandǝh ka təgal luar</foreign>. Thus, I translate <foreign>ləvəṅ lvar</foreign> as ‘remote forest’ (cf. Mal. <foreign>hutan liar</foreign>). ASD translate <foreign>lvar</foreign> as ‘isi’ (content).</note> forest is knowing other people’s minds;<note>The relation of the metaphor remote forest (<foreign>ləvəṅ lvar</foreign>) with knowing about people’s mind (<foreign>ñaho di tinǝṅ nu reya</foreign>) is hard to understand. It seems to make more sense if the remote forest refers to the peoples mind, so perhaps we need to make conjecture by omitting  <foreign>ñaho di</foreign>.</note> what is comparable to the elephant is the power<note>The partial reduplication <foreign>bǝbǝdas</foreign> ‘power’ is from <foreign>bǝdas</foreign> adj. ‘strong, powerful’. The word <foreign>bedas </foreign>can be found in MdS, the reduplicative form <foreign>bǝbǝdas</foreign> is no longer exist.</note> of Majesty the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.12">If we seek to know about the fragrance and sweetness of flowers, [we should] ask the bee. The meaning is: what is comparable to the bee is the skillful man, who is wandering, roaming, [so that he] knows other people’s habits. What is comparable to the fragrant flower is the person who has good conduct, sweet <foreign>baruṅusan</foreign>,<note>The word <foreign>baruṅusan </foreign>is a hapax, not found in dictionaries, perhaps derived from <foreign>buṅus</foreign>. The closest word seems to be OS <foreign>baruṅut </foreign>(cf. MdS <foreign>berengut</foreign> and OJ <foreign>muruṅut</foreign>), but it connotes a negative attitude ‘look surly, look angry, grim’. MdS <foreign>barangasan</foreign> is also similar, but again has a negative connotation ‘grumpy, ill-tempered (by nature), short-/quick-/hot-tempered, irascible, irritable’.</note> smiling expression, pleasing attitude.<note>On the combination of <foreign>tiṅkah suka</foreign>, cf. SA 240 <foreign>tiṅkah suka budi suka </foreign>‘pleasure in behavior and in mind’.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.13">The meaning is: we should not ask from the wrong people. If we seek to know about every kind of story,<note>In this list, we can discern two types of stories: the first are known in the OJ tradition, such as <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign>, <foreign>Rāmāyaṇa</foreign>, <foreign>Ādiparva</foreign>, <foreign>Koravāśrama</foreign>, <foreign>Bhīma Svarga</foreign>, <foreign>Raṅga Lave</foreign>, <foreign>Bhomāntaka</foreign>, <foreign>Sumanasāntaka</foreign>, and <foreign>Tantri</foreign>. The <foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Hayu</foreign> is also a known OJ work, but it is clearly not a narrative text, and this fact causes doubt about the reading to be adopted here. The other titles, such as <foreign>Darma Jati</foreign>, <foreign>Jayasena</foreign>, <foreign>Sedamana</foreign>, <foreign>Kalapurbaka</foreign>, and <foreign>Jarini</foreign> seem to designate Sundanese-language works or the names of protagonists in known texts. Except for Kalapurbaka, which presumably refers to the text about the birth story of Kala in Old Sundanese (ed. Aditia Gunawan &amp; Agung Kriswanto 2009), the other narratives are difficult to identify among transmitted Old Sundanese works. For the relationship between these stories as one of the frameworks for analyzing the dating, see Chapter 5.</note> such as<note>For the meaning of <foreign>gəs ma</foreign> as ‘such as, for instance’, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> <foreign>Darma Jati</foreign>,<note>Darma Jati is difficult to identify. However, we recognize this name in the main protagonist in Tutur Bvana. In this story, Darma Jati is the Supreme God in cosmology. He fights against Kala Sakti, the representation of evil. As a name of a supreme deity, Darma Jati also appears in Kavih Paniṅkəs.</note> <foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Hayu</foreign>, <foreign>Jayasena</foreign>,<note>Jayasena is another name for Bhīma in the Virātaparva. Could it contain a story of Bhīma other than the Bhīma Svarga?</note> <foreign>Sedamana</foreign>,<note>Sedamana is attested as one of a character in the Fragment of Carita Parahyaṅan, as a person who built the palace of Pakuan.</note> <foreign>Kuñjarakarna</foreign>, <foreign>Ramayana</foreign>, <foreign>Adiparva</foreign>, <foreign>Koravasrama</foreign>, <foreign>Bima Sorga</foreign>, <foreign>Raṅga Lave</foreign>, <foreign>Boma</foreign>, <foreign>Sumana</foreign>, <foreign>Kalapurbaka</foreign>, <foreign>Jarini</foreign>,<note>Jarini could not be confirmed, although this name also appears as a text in Svavar Cinta.</note> <foreign>Tantri</foreign>, all types of stories, [we should] ask the performer (<foreign>memen</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.14">If we seek to know about all kinds of songs (<foreign>kavih</foreign>):<note>For <foreign>kavih</foreign> as a specific genre in Old Sundanese literature, see Chapter 4.</note> songs for the elderly,<note>The combination <foreign>bvat tuha </foreign>literally means ‘for old age’. The  <foreign>Kavih Mahañana</foreign> begins with opening lines <foreign>ini kavih mahañana, pikavihən bvat maṅkuk</foreign> “This is the song of great mind, to be sung for living”. </note> long songs, amusement songs,<note>I render <foreign>lalaṅuan</foreign> from OJ <foreign>laṅ</foreign>ə̄ ‘subjectively) the feeling of longing or being entranced (by beauty or love), aesthetic experience, romantic feelings, the raptures of love’. In MdS, we only find the derivative form <foreign>kalangenan </foreign>‘amusement, pleasure, sport, entertainment’.</note> advice songs,<note>The title <foreign>kavih pañaraman</foreign> is mentioned as a title of the Old Sundanese poem published as <foreign>Sevaka Darma</foreign>. See Chapter 4.</note> allusive songs,<note>In MdS, <foreign>sisindiran</foreign> has two meanings, one from <foreign>sindir</foreign> ‘allusion’, the other a technical term for verse with rhyme, like the Malay <foreign>pantun</foreign>.</note> <foreign>peṅpeledan </foreign>songs,<note>Danadibrata notes <foreign>péléd</foreign>, <foreign>méléd</foreign> ‘<foreign>mundur bari nyisi sabab di hareupeun rék aya nu ngaliwat</foreign>’ (move backward while tilting the body to the side because someone wants to pass). If the OS word <foreign>peled</foreign> is the same as MdS <foreign>péléd</foreign> which refers to movement, then <foreign>kavih peṅpeledan</foreign> presumably refers to a kind of singing along while rocking the body.</note> rafter hole (<foreign>boṅboṅ kaso</foreign>) [songs], <foreign>pore rane </foreign>[songs]<foreign>, </foreign>sword-grass track (<foreign>porod ərih</foreign>) [songs]<foreign>, babahanan </foreign>songs<foreign>, </foreign>bearish (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>) songs<foreign>, taṅtuṅ </foreign>songs<foreign>, </foreign>lament songs<foreign>, </foreign>dancing songs, all types of songs, [we should] ask the virtuoso (<foreign>paraguna</foreign>).<note>In OJ, the term <foreign>paraguṇa</foreign> means ‘(Skt.) the virtues (talents, etc) of others’, but it does not seem to fit the context. In Sanskrit, we find several meaning of <foreign>guṇa</foreign> related to music ‘the string of musical instrument, the merit of composition (consistency, elegance of expression)’. It is difficult to decide whether the <foreign>paraguna</foreign> is the virtuoso composer of music or of its lyrics, or the virtuoso performer. Since AG 3r contains <foreign>paraguna</foreign> in a list with <foreign>memen</foreign>, the latter option seems preferable: <foreign>panday bǝsi panday omas, memen paraguna, hambha lavak </foreign>“blacksmith, goldsmith, performer, virtuoso, [and] joker”. Cf. KaMan 1491–1492 <foreign>pahi dəṅən paraguna</foreign>, <foreign>kumbakara</foreign> (ms. <foreign>hambakara</foreign>) <foreign>palukisan </foreign>“All together with the <foreign>paraguna</foreign>, jar maker, painter”; see also lines 1496–1498: <foreign>kasorgaan hamba da … dək</foreign>, <foreign>citrakara</foreign> (ms. <foreign>cətakara</foreign>) <foreign>paṅlukisan</foreign>, <foreign>mara gǝndiṅ</foreign> (ms. <foreign>gidiṅ</foreign>) <foreign>patumeṅan</foreign>. Cf. OJ where Zoetmulder notes <foreign>prakavi</foreign> ‘the poets (= <foreign>para kavi</foreign>); versed in poetry’. In this case, I take <foreign>para</foreign> as a prefix (see my comment on <foreign>prətələm</foreign> in SKK 7.3; cf. Chapter 3, §Morphology).</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.15">If we seek to know about the jesters (<foreign>para macəh</foreign>):<note>In MdS <foreign>maceuh</foreign> means ‘extreme(ly), excessive(ly) (given over to bad habits)’, but in OJ, Zoetmulder interprets <foreign>pacəh</foreign> as ‘(prob. with an open mouth &gt;) merry, laughing, hilarious; astonished, amazed’. The personal article <foreign>para</foreign> seems to indicate that <foreign>macəh</foreign> is a noun, so I interpret it as meaning ‘jester’ in the present context. Cf. <foreign>mirus</foreign> below.</note> the performance of a jester (<foreign>cəta macəh</foreign>), the performance of a buffoon (<foreign>mirus</foreign>),<note>My emendation of transmitted <foreign>nirus</foreign> to <foreign>mirus</foreign> is based on the parallel passage in <ref target="#smg_10.02">SMG 10.2</ref> where we find <foreign>mirus</foreign>. Although it seems to be an active derivation from base <foreign>pirus </foreign>(attested in OJ), the word functions as a noun in OS. I interpret <foreign>mirus</foreign> as synonymous with <foreign>pirus</foreign> ‘buffoon’ (cf. Acri 2014).</note> the mask show (<foreign>tatapukan</foreign>), the bear show (<foreign>babaroṅan</foreign>), <foreign>bakutrak</foreign> show (<foreign>babakutrakan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>Cf. MdS <foreign>bakutrak</foreign> = <foreign>baketrak</foreign>, <foreign>ngabaketrak</foreign> ‘adj. hard; <foreign>teuas ngabaketrak</foreign> very hard’. It is noteworthy the resemblance of onomatopoeia words <foreign>kutrak</foreign>, <foreign>ketrok</foreign>, <foreign>kétrok</foreign>, <foreign>kotrék</foreign> in MdS which indicate a sound of knocking two or more hard items, viz. <foreign>pakotrék</foreign> ‘with a click or a bang knock against each other, give sound when touching each other (e.g. of two sticks, of two teeth growing towards each other)’; <foreign>ketrok</foreign> ‘vi. knock (esp. with the hand on a door etc.); <foreign>ngetrok</foreign> knock or strike a blow on st. (e.g. on so.’s head with a ladle); <foreign>ngetrokkeun</foreign> knock on/against with st.; kutrak-ketrok and ketrak-ketrok keep on knocking; <foreign>keketrok</foreign> knock (at the door); <foreign>pangetrok</foreign> (door-) knocker’. I interpret <foreign>babakutrakan</foreign> as a kind of performance that involves combat with wooden sticks.</note> <foreign>abaṅ-abaṅan</foreign> (?)<foreign>,</foreign><note>In MdS, <foreign>abang</foreign> means ‘1 n. term of address for men coming from Jakarta and surrounding areas whose mother tongue is Malay. <foreign>abang</foreign> 2 adj. Jav. red; <foreign>abang panatas</foreign> term to indicate the reddish colour of a cert. type of rooster; <foreign>abang-abang lambé</foreign> flattery (behind which o. hides his true feelings or intentions), blarney, (sl.) soft sawder’. I am inclined to interpret that it is probably connected to <foreign>abang-abang lambé</foreign> ‘flattery’ which alludes to a kind of performance involving the act of flattering.</note> swallowing a pointed bamboo (<foreign>nərəy pañcaṅ</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>My emandation pañcaṅ is based on a connection of this word with Mal. pancang n ‘potongan bambu (kayu dan sebagainya) yang pangkalnya runcing, ditancapkan atau dihunjamkan ke tanah (untuk tanda batas, tambatan, penguat pinggir parit, dan sebagainya)’ (KBBI, s.v. pancang). This word is not attested in OS, however, it occurs in pantun Lutung Kasarung 8: ku dalem henteu ditolih, ja dalem pancang ngombara ‘[It is] not regarded by the dalem, because the dalem is the illuminating pole’. My emendation is also supported by the occurrence of MdS pancan ‘n. crossed slats of bamboo (to fortify scaffolding, etc.)’.</note> the sleight of hand (<foreign>munikən ləbur</foreign>),<note>The literal meaning of this phrase is ‘hiding [something and causing it to] disappear’.</note> the pounding block competition (<foreign>ṅadu ləsuṅ</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>I interpret this performance as an equivalent of what is nowadays called gondang, ngagondang ‘rhythmically pound on the rice-stamping block accompanied by singing (by several women esp. during moonlight, also on the occasion of circumcision feast and in the past as a homage to arriving and departing dignitaries); lagu gondang k.o. rice-pounding alternate singing’.</note> entering the <foreign>lantar</foreign> (?)<foreign>,</foreign><note>I wonder whether <foreign>lantar </foreign>should be emended to <foreign>lintar </foreign>‘casting net’. Cf. some meanings of <foreign>lantar</foreign> in MdJ ‘bamboo bridge railing; bamboo pole used for plucking fruit from a tree’.</note> the competition of elder women (<foreign>ṅadu nini</foreign>), all kinds of amusement, [we should] ask the actor (<foreign>həmpul</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.16">If we seek to know about <foreign>pantun</foreign>s<note>It seems that these four pantun titles are related to the Pajajaran cycle. Laṅga Laraṅ reminds us of Angga Larang, who is referred to in the Carita Varuga Guru as the father of King Sili Vaṅi: <foreign>prəbu aṅga laraṅ puputra prəbu sili vaṅi, jumənəṅ ñakravati pajajaran</foreign>. Bañak Catra is a character in Banyumas folklore, considered as the ancestor of the local people. The story of this figure occurs, for example, in the Babad Pasir, a Banyumas chronicle, which narrates how Bañak Catra (or Kamandaka), the ancestor of Banyumas people, came from Pajajaran (Knebel 1900). While Hatur Vaṅi is not found in the corpus of pantun narratives, one of the well-known pantun titles is Gantangan Wangi, after the name of the protagonist, a son of Prabu Sili Wangi. So perhaps Hatur Vaṅi can be identified as Gantangan Wangi, or at least as a hero belonging to Sili Wangi’s family. We can infer the existence as early as the 15th century of a tradition of pantun performance inspired by a narrative cycle centered on the Pajajaran kingdom. On <foreign>pantun </foreign>narrative in general, see Chapter 2, §Pantun.</note> [such as] <foreign>Laṅga Laraṅ</foreign>, <foreign>Bañak Catra</foreign>, <foreign>Sili Vaṅi</foreign>, <foreign>Hatur Vaṅi</foreign>, [we should] ask the <foreign>pantun</foreign> bard (<foreign>prəpantun</foreign>).<note>On the prefix <foreign>prə</foreign>-, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.17">As for all kinds of<note>All occurrences of <foreign>salvirniṅ</foreign> in this text, which are located as a first word in 11.15–19, is an emendation. Manuscript A consistently has <foreign>savaliraniṅ</foreign> or <foreign>savalviraniṅ</foreign>, while B <foreign>savaluraniṅ</foreign> or <foreign>savaliraniṅ</foreign>. It seems that the scribes have confused the words <foreign>sarva</foreign> and <foreign>lvir</foreign> and they intend to write <foreign>sarva lviraniṅ</foreign>?</note> decorative patterns (<foreign>tulis</foreign>)<note>See Aditia Gunawan 2019: 88–89 for the interpretation of these motifs. Some of these names are still known from modern batik and the chance is very high that the context of their use was mostly textile also at the time of the SKK’s composition — though we cannot exclude that some patterns were also used on other materials.</note> [such as] the spiral motif (<foreign>pupuñjəṅan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>the writhing motif (<foreign>hihiṅgulan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>the flower motif (<foreign>kəkəmbaṅan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>the forest motif (<foreign>alas-alasan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>people motif (<foreign>uraṅ-uraṅan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>Here I interpret <foreign>uraṅ</foreign> as ‘people’, while ASD translate it as ‘shrimp’. We only find <foreign>huraṅ</foreign> and never <foreign>uraṅ</foreign> in the meaning shrimp’ in OS. Cf. RD 18 <foreign>mətu banaspati niṅ avaṅ-avaṅ, tavur na bələm huraṅ hayu</foreign>; SC 165 <foreign>təhər pelag olah-olah, na paray dikəmbaṅ lvapaṅ, huraṅ ta dikəmbaṅ dadap</foreign>. On this point, I revise my interpretation in Aditia Gunawan 2019: 88–89.</note> picture motif (<foreign>məmətahan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>the diagonal motif (<foreign>sisiraṅan</foreign>), the climbing fern motif (<foreign>taruk hata</foreign>), lotus flower, any kind of decorative pattern, [we should] ask the painter (<foreign>lukis</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.18">As for all kinds of forging, the three weapons are what differentiates them. As for the weapons for the king, they are sword, sickle (? <foreign>abət</foreign>),<note>Previous editors have interpreted the word <foreign>abət</foreign> as meaning ‘whip’, based on its resemblance to the verb <foreign>sabət</foreign>. In OJ and MdS, <foreign>sabǝt</foreign> means ‘to whip, slap’. Zoetmulder glosses <foreign>abət</foreign> as ‘sweeping stroke, slash; a striking weapon?’ I prefer to relate <foreign>abət</foreign> to Mal. <foreign>sabit</foreign> ‘sickle’ which is more plausible as a weapon produced by a blacksmith.</note>, <foreign>pamuk</foreign>, cleaver (<foreign>golok</foreign>), stabbing knife (<foreign>peso təndət</foreign>), kris. The Raksasas are their deities, for they are utensils to kill everything. As for the weapons of the peasants, they are machete (<foreign>kujaṅ</foreign>), hatchet (<foreign>baliuṅ</foreign>), big axe (<foreign>patik</foreign>), weeding hook (<foreign>kored</foreign>), tapping [knife] (<foreign>sadap</foreign>).<note>The context suggests that the word <foreign>sadap</foreign> refers to <foreign>peso sadap. </foreign>See Hardjadibrata (2003), s.v. <foreign>péso</foreign>, a kind of knife to tap the sap of areca (sugar) palm. On Balinese drawings representing a figure of a tapper bearing a knife, see Jákl (2021: 27–36). Cf. Mal. <foreign>sadap </foreign>‘to tap’, <foreign>penyadap </foreign>‘tapper’.</note> The Detyas are their deities, for they are utensils to obtain things to eat and things to drink. As for the weapons of the scholar (<foreign>pandita</foreign>), they are the [betelnut] cutter (<foreign>kalakatri</foreign>),<note>According to Tom Hoogervorst (personal communication, 5 November 2019), the word appears as Makasar <foreign>kalakatti</foreign>, Bugis <foreign>kalakatti</foreign>, Gayo <foreign>klati</foreign>, Karo Batak <foreign>kalakati</foreign>, Minangkabau <foreign>kalakati</foreign>. We also find similar words that mean ‘areca nut cutter’ in various Indian languages, both New Indo-Aryan (e.g. Oriya <foreign>khilikāti</foreign> [Turner 1962–1966: 203]) and Dravidian (e.g. Malayalam kiḷikkatti [Gundert 1872, s.v. kiḷi and katti]). In the light of this evidence, it is likely that the word was borrowed into Nusantaran languages from some Indian sources, and it is clear that the OS reflex is an example of intrusive <foreign>r</foreign>. See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> whittling knife (<foreign>peso raut</foreign>), <foreign>doṅdaṅ</foreign> knife, <foreign>paṅot </foreign>knife, spike (<foreign>pakisi</foreign>). The Danavas are their deities, for they are utensils to cut everything. That is, once again, why the three weapons are differentiated: for the king, for the peasant, for the scholar. Thus, if we wish to know all of that, [we should] ask the blacksmith (<foreign>panday</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.19">As for all kinds of carvings: made like snakes, made like bears, modeled after birds, modeled after monkeys,<note>The word <foreign>vǝre</foreign> is only attested in this OS text. It is surely equivalent with OJ <foreign>vre </foreign>‘monkey’.</note> modeled after lions — every kind of carving, [we should] ask the scabbard carver (<foreign>maraṅguy</foreign>).<note>The word <foreign>maraṅguy</foreign> is a variant spelling of <foreign>maraṅgi</foreign> (cf. <foreign>suruy</foreign> vs. <foreign>suri </foreign>in SKK 11.1). In MdS (as also in OJ) <foreign>maraṅgi</foreign> is ‘a kris scabbard maker’. However, the present context suggests a more general meaning than a <foreign>kris</foreign> scabbard maker. Since this section follows a list of weapons, it seems plausible that the word could mean more generally ‘scabbard carver’. </note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.20">All kinds of preparations:<note>See Riadi Darwis 2019 for general interpretations of these techniques.</note> <foreign>ñupar-ñapir,</foreign><note>The reduplication word <foreign>ñupar-ñapir</foreign> is unidentified. The word <foreign>cupar</foreign> in MdS denotes ‘vi. not on (of st. that should have taken place etc.); <foreign>nyuparkeun</foreign> make that st. does not take place, cancel st., undo st., nullify st., annul st., upset (so.’s plan)’, which is unlikely to be the semantic range intended in the present context. I am inclined to relate <foreign>capir</foreign>, the base word of <foreign>ñapir</foreign>, with MdS <foreign>cewir</foreign> (with change of vowel <foreign>a</foreign> to <foreign>ə</foreign> and <foreign>p</foreign> to <foreign>v</foreign>) which means ‘n. (torn off) piece, strip (of paper, fabric, meat); (esp. used with the prefix <foreign>sa</foreign>-, e.g.) <foreign>sacewir kertas</foreign> a strip/sheet of paper; <foreign>nyewiran</foreign> tear off strips or pieces somewhere; <foreign>cecewir</foreign> kp. ear’. Cf. Mal. <foreign>suwir</foreign> which is mainly used to designate dishes such as <foreign>ayam suwir</foreign>. </note> <foreign>rara mandi,</foreign><note>The combination <foreign>rara mandi</foreign> literally means ‘bathing girl’; in SC 174, the food that is processed with this technique is fish scales: <foreign>sisitna dirara-mandi</foreign>, <foreign>tulaṅna dibatcu-raṅu</foreign>. The meaning indicates that the food is processed with gravy. In OJ, <foreign>mandi</foreign> or <foreign>maṇḍi</foreign> means ‘effective; poisonous’, which seems unsuitable with the context.</note> make <foreign>cobek</foreign> (<foreign>ñocobek</foreign>),<note>In MdS <foreign>cobék</foreign> means ‘k.o. spiced dish (baked or cooked), (further indicated by the main constituent) e.g. <foreign>cobék belut</foreign> a <foreign>cobék</foreign> of rice-field eel; <foreign>cobék hurang</foreign> a <foreign>cobék</foreign> of prawns’.</note><foreign> ñopoṅ koneṅ,</foreign><note>In MdS, <foreign>copong</foreign> means ‘with a (running) hole/opening in it (e.g. coin, needle); (of so.’s mind, heart:) clarified, cleared, relieved. However, there is no nasal form *<foreign>nyopong</foreign> in MdS. If we take the base meaning from MdS, then <foreign>ñopoṅ</foreign> seems to mean ‘to make a hole’. Meanwhile, <foreign>koneṅ</foreign> is in MdS the common name of saffron (Mal. <foreign>kunyit</foreign>). What these words could mean together is unclear to me.</note> <foreign>ñaṅlarkən,</foreign><note>The verb <foreign>ñaṅlarkən</foreign> is not recorded in dictionaries. I leave the word without interpretation.</note> <foreign>ñarəṅsəṅ,</foreign><note>We find <foreign>disarəṅsəṅ</foreign> in SC 178 <foreign>hayam bərəm disarəṅsəṅ</foreign> ‘red chicken prepared with <foreign>sarəṅsəṅ</foreign>’, but the context does not give a clear meaning. The base word seems to be <foreign>səṅsəṅ</foreign>. In MdS <foreign>nyeungseung</foreign> (from <foreign>seungseung</foreign>) indicates ‘beginning to shape, beginning to swell (of the breasts of a girl)’, while in OJ <foreign>səṅsəṅ</foreign> means ‘radiant, radiating, aglow’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>söṅ</foreign>).</note><foreign> ñəsəṅit,</foreign><note>The word <foreign>ñəsǝṅit</foreign> seems to be connected with MdS <foreign>seungit</foreign> ‘fragrant’, so <foreign>ñəsəṅit</foreign> could yield a meaning ‘to make fragrant’. Could it be synonymous with <foreign>diruruum</foreign>? </note><foreign> ñayaṅ ku pədəs</foreign>,<note><foreign>ñayaṅ ku pǝdǝs</foreign> literally means ‘build a nest with the pepper’.</note> roasting (<foreign>bəbələman</foreign>), grilling (<foreign>papaṅgaṅan</foreign>), <foreign>kakasian,</foreign><note>Cf. OJ <foreign>kasyan</foreign> ‘food prepared in a particular way’, attested exclusively in the list of food items found typically in the inscriptions of 10th-c. King Sindok. SKK seems to confirm that the base word would be <foreign>kasi. </foreign>Alas, the meaning remains obscure.</note> mincing (<foreign>hahañaṅan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>The form <foreign>hahañaṅan</foreign> is a hapax in OS, but the base <foreign>hañaṅ</foreign> is recorded in OJED, meaning ‘unsalted’, listed among the types of dried meat (<foreign>ḍeṅ</foreign>); cf. the Mantyasih I inscription (907) B.3:<foreign> ḍeṅ hasin, ḍeṅ hañaṅ, ḍeṅ taruṅ</foreign>. However, a Balinese dictionary records <foreign>anyang</foreign> as ‘lauk dari daging cincang, dicampur dengan kelapa’. I choose to translate it as ‘mincing’, based on the Balinese sense of <foreign>anyang</foreign> and a close semantic meaning with <foreign>raraməsan</foreign> ‘mixing’.</note> mixing (<foreign>raraməsan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>perfuming (<foreign>diruruum</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign> sweetening (<foreign>diamis-amis</foreign>) — every kind of preparation, [we should] ask a <foreign>harəp catra</foreign>.<note>While <foreign>harəp</foreign> means ‘the front, fore part’, and <foreign>catra</foreign> is probably based on Sanskrit <foreign>chattra</foreign> ‘parasol’, the way in which the combination of these two words would yield the meaning ‘cook’ that we expect here is obscure. Cf. <ref target="#smg_15.06">SMG 15.6</ref>.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.21">All kinds of (woven) textile:<note>For the interpretation of motifs/types of woven textile, see Aditia Gunawan 2019: 89–92.</note> candlenut flower (<foreign>kəmbaṅ muñcaṅ</foreign>), <foreign>seṅgaṅ</foreign>’s stem (<foreign>gagaṅ seṅgaṅ</foreign>), moon-alike (<foreign>same leg</foreign>), group of səmat (<foreign>səmat sahurun</foreign>), plaited cage (<foreign>añam cayut</foreign>), <foreign>sigəji</foreign> motif, stone motif (<foreign>pasi-pasi</foreign>), <foreign>kalaṅkaṅ ayakan</foreign>, <foreign>poleṅ raganis</foreign>, <foreign>jayanti</foreign>, <foreign>cəcəmpaan</foreign>, <foreign>paparanakan</foreign>, <foreign>maṅin haris</foreign>, <foreign>siliganti</foreign>, <foreign>boeh siaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>bəbər natan</foreign>, <foreign>papakanan</foreign>, <foreign>surat avi</foreign>, <foreign>parigi ñeṅsoh</foreign>, <foreign>gagañjar</foreign>, <foreign>lusiyan bəsar</foreign>, <foreign>kampuh jayanti</foreign>, <foreign>hujan riris</foreign>, <foreign>laris</foreign>, <foreign>boeh alus</foreign>, <foreign>ragen paṅanten</foreign> — every kind of textile, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the weaver (<foreign>paṅəyək</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.22">If we seek to know about all kinds of laws: established customs (<foreign>acara</foreign>) are under codified law (<foreign>adigama</foreign>),<note>In Skt., as well as in OJ, <foreign>adhigama</foreign> means ‘ the act of obtaining, acquisition; mastery, study, knowledge) study, knowledge; the knowledge of right conduct (according to the law); name of a work on law’. I prefer to interpret it as ‘a work on law or codified law’.</note> <foreign>adigama</foreign> is under teacher’s regulations (gurugama), teacher’s regulations are under elders’ regulations (tuhagama), elders’ regulations are under approval (satmata),<note>Attested in OS and OJ, the word <foreign>satmata</foreign> is a variant of <foreign>sanmata</foreign> ‘Skt. agreed to, approved; thought highly of, esteemed; opinion; consent, assent) approval, assent; kind (benevolent) disposition towards others, favour, sympathetic reception; (adj.) kindly disposed, sympathetic’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>sanmata</foreign>).</note> approval is under public outcry (surak loka), public outcry is under court proceedings (vicara). High people<note>I consider <foreign>utama-janma</foreign> as a Sanskrit compound ‘high people, high birth’. Cf. Ślo 31j <foreign>kaliṅanya, saṅ sādhujana sira saṅ vvaṅ uttama-janma, yadyapi sira nirdhana</foreign>, <foreign>kasyasiha tuvi, agaveha ta sira salah kārya, salah hiḍəp, taha tan maṅkana saṅ vvaṅ uttama-janma</foreign> “The meaning is: <foreign>saṅ sādhujana</foreign> is one of high birth. Even if he is poor and also pitiable, will he do a wrong act [and will he have] wrong thoughts? No, the one of high birth is certainly not like that”. TK 24j.2<foreign> mapan ikaṅ sinaṅguh uttama-janma </foreign>“for he is considered to be one of high birth”; KM 248<foreign> riṅ voṅ aṅucap-ucap lāvan rabiniṅ voṅ tumuli kapiṅhit dene lakine voṅ uttama-janma</foreign>, <foreign>iku strīsaṅgrahaṇa arane </foreign>“If someone speaks with a married woman and then she is isolated in the house by her husband [and the latter is] one of high birth, that is called adultery”<foreign>.</foreign></note> are outside of guilt, people outside<note>The word <foreign>vaheya</foreign> seems to correspond to Skt. <foreign>bāhya</foreign>/OJ <foreign>vāhya</foreign> ‘(being) outside, outward, external, outwardly visible, pertaining to the world of the senses’.</note> are of high guilt<note>I have attempted to give a literal translation but must admit that at the present state of our knowledge of the social system in 15th-century Sunda, the meaning of the phrase utama-janma vaheya dosa, vaheya-janma utama dosa remains quite obscure.</note> — every kind of law, [we should] ask the tandas.<note>For the use of the personal article <foreign>para</foreign> marking <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign> as plural in OJ context, see, e.g., <foreign>Ghaṭotkacāśraya</foreign> 5.5, 48.7, and <foreign>Sumanasāntaka</foreign> 15.10, 19.4 (cf. Jákl 2019). In contrast with OJ <foreign>taṇḍa</foreign>, <foreign>tanda</foreign> in OS is related with a legal, not a military context.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.23">If we seek to know about the strategies of war: <foreign>makara</foreign> formation,<note>In this paragraph there are six terms containing the word <foreign>bihva</foreign>. This word is obviously a localized spelling of Sanskrit <foreign>vyūha</foreign>. In OJ, both <foreign>vyūha</foreign> and <foreign>byūha</foreign> are attested. I choose the reading <foreign>bihva</foreign> of A instead of <foreign>byiha </foreign>found in B based on phonological reasons: from <foreign>vi-yu-ha</foreign> &gt; <foreign>bi-yu-ha</foreign> &gt; <foreign>bi-hu-va</foreign> &gt; <foreign>bihva</foreign>. The term <foreign>makara-bihva</foreign> is a localized spelling for <foreign>makarabyūha</foreign>, and designates a kind of battle formation. In OJ, this battle array occurs in the BY 13.24:  <foreign>hetu śrī nr̥pa dharmasūnu maṅutus magəlara makarabyūhādbhuta</foreign>|<foreign>dhr̥ṣṭadyumna ghaṭotkacāgrani supitnya makatutuka vīra sātyaki </foreign>| <foreign>saṅ mādryātmaja netra pāndavasutā suṅuta saṅ abhimanyu nāsikā </foreign>| <foreign>śrī dharmātmaja təṇḍas aṅga valakaṅ para ratu tinata təkeṅ vugat </foreign>“And so Yudhiṣṭhira had his troops drawn up into the wonderful <foreign>makara </foreign>battle array: Dhr̥ṣṭadyumna and Ghaṭotkaca were ensconced on the tips of the pincers, the heroic Sātyaki on the mouth, the sons of Madrī were on the eyes, the [five] sons of the Pāṇḍawas were on the tentacles, Abhimanyu on the nose, Yudhiṣṭhira on the head, and on the body, the back and the tail were the allied kings” (Supomo 1993: 82–83; 187). See also Jákl 2014: 48.</note> chariot formation,<note>The term <foreign>sakata-bihva</foreign> means ‘chariot formation’ (cf. Skt. <foreign>śakaṭa</foreign>). In OJ, this formation is attested in RY 9.76, when the troops of Aleṅka seek to kill Hanoman: <foreign>dinānan ikaṅ rākṣasānuṅ pravīra, asiṅ tan surud riṅ musuh śūra sāra, ya muṅgvi harəpniṅ rathānuṅ paṅəṇḍas</foreign>, <foreign>ṅaranyāhaləp śākaṭabyūhanāma</foreign> “They were extremely courageous demons, who would not retreat in the face of a powerful and brave opponent. They were re-arranged in front of his wagon to form the advance guards, of the excellent battle array <foreign>śākaṭabyūha</foreign> (wagon-battle array)” (Soewito Santoso 1980: 269).</note> <foreign>linsang</foreign> formation,<note>The term <foreign>lisaṅ-bihva</foreign> is a hybrid. It is true that <foreign>lisaṅ</foreign> in not found in MdS, but it is likely related to Mal. <foreign>linsang</foreign>, a kind of carnivorous mammal (Prionodon gracilis).</note> lion formation,<note>The ‘lion formation’ (<foreign>siṅha-bihva</foreign>) is attested in the <foreign>Sumanasāntaka </foreign>147.11 as <foreign>singhāṅantī guhā byūha </foreign>‘lion waiting in the cave formation’, in the episode when Prince Aja is surrounded by seven kings who use this battle array.</note> <foreign>garuda</foreign> formation,<note>The ‘eagle formation’ (<foreign>garuda-bihva</foreign>) occurs under the synonymous name <foreign>khagendrabyūha</foreign> in Sutasoma 99.8: <foreign>khagendrabyūhānuṅ gəlarira patuk bāṇa matəguh, həlar kānan śaṅkottara kiva muvah salva janaka, ri təṇḍas saṅ vīrāpatih ika mahācūra suyaśa, narendre pr̥ṣṭhāṅgəhnira milu dhīra māya ri vugat </foreign>“His battle-array was that called the <foreign>garuḍa</foreign> formation, with the strong Bāṇa as his beak, on the right wing were Śaṅka and Uttara, on the left Salva and Janaka; at the head was the courageous prime minister, very powerful and very famous. The king’s place was to the rear at the tail assisted by the fearless Māya” (Soewito Santoso 1975 I: 155; 1975 II: 195).</note> wheel formation,<note>This formation is mentioned in BhY 13.22, in the episode of Abhimanyu’s death. This character died because he was trapped in the wheel formation made by the Koravas:<foreign>yekan garjita saṅ varadvija harəp ri hilaṅanira Pāṇḍaveśvara </foreign><foreign>nāhan marma nirāgave gəlar anindya vəkas iṅ atidurgamārusit </foreign><foreign>cakrabyūha ṅaranya nora vənaṅ aṅrusaka ri taya Bhīma Phalguna </foreign><foreign>Karṇa Droṇa Kr̥pādi Korava sukinya makakipiṅ ikaṅ vatək ratu </foreign>“Desiring the destruction of the Pāṇḍawas, the eminent brahmin was delighted, and he drew up his army into a perfect formation that was most difficult to penetrate. It was called the discus battle array, which, in the absence of both Bhīma and Arjuna, would be indestructible. Karṇa, Droṇa, Kr̥pa and the Koravas were stationed on the hub, while all the other kings were on the rim” (Supomo 1993: 187).</note> needle point (<foreign>suci-muka</foreign>), iron cage (<foreign>bajra-pañjara</foreign>),<note>Although in Sanskrit studies, it is customary to associate the word <foreign>vajra</foreign> with the meanings ‘thunderbolt’ or ‘diamond’, I choose to interpret the loanword <foreign>bajra</foreign> as ‘iron, steel’. Rigg (1862: 364) defines <foreign>waja</foreign> as ‘a kind of hard iron or steel’ and explicitly connects it to Skt. <foreign>vajra</foreign>. Hoogervorst (2017: 386) notes that the meaning of ‘steel’ also manifests itself in Skt. through such compounds as  <foreign>granthivajraka</foreign>, <foreign>śaivalāvajra</foreign>, <foreign>śoṇavajra</foreign> and <foreign>svarṇavajra</foreign>, all denoting types of steel<foreign>. </foreign>The precise term <foreign>bajra-pañjara</foreign> also occurs in the Bukit Gombak I inscription from 14th-century West Sumatra (Krom 1912: 51; Brandes 1913: 258–259), in the royal epithet <foreign>saraṇāgatabajrapañjara</foreign> ‘iron (or diamond) cage for those who come to seek refuge’. Cf. the terms combined with <foreign>vəsi</foreign> or <foreign>bəsi</foreign> in OS and OJ: <foreign>koñjara vəsi</foreign> ‘iron-cage’ in CVG 226 (in Pleyte 1913: 376), <foreign>ruji bəsi</foreign> ‘iron fencing’ in SC quoted in fn. 345, and further <foreign>kandaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>pagar</foreign>, and <foreign>rajəg </foreign>in the toponyms Kandaṅ Vəsi in CP, Pagar Vəsi and Rajəg Vəsi in OJ inscriptions.</note> surrounding dog (<foreign>asu maliput</foreign>), grazing peacock (<foreign>mərak simpir</foreign>),<note>The term <foreign>mərak simpir</foreign> also occurs in KaPang 89 as a name of a textile motif.</note> tailless crow (?, <foreign>gagak saṅkur</foreign>),<note>In Malay, <foreign>sangkur</foreign> means ‘bayonet’, but in Balinese it means ‘have a small tail or no tail at all’. It seems that the Balinese meaning is intended in the text. Zoetmulder (OJED, s.v.) gives a meaning of <foreign>saṅkur</foreign> ‘a part. type of shield (<foreign>ḍaḍap saṅkur</foreign>)? perh. “without tassels”'? Cf. Bal. (KBW): “tailless”’.</note> descending civet (<foreign>luvak maturun</foreign>), climbing deer (<foreign>kidaṅ suməṅka</foreign>), crocodile hole (<foreign>babah buhaya</foreign>),<note>The base word <foreign>babah</foreign> is not found In MdS, but the verb <foreign>ngababah</foreign> means ‘make a hole in st. (a bamboo wall etc. to break in), break through st., break in; <foreign>babahan</foreign> (in a wall etc.) made hole; body opening’. It seems that the base <foreign>babah</foreign> itself has the meaning ‘hole’. Cf. OJ <foreign>babahan</foreign> ‘door, gate, entrance, opening, aperture’. Cf. also Mal. term <foreign>lubang buaya</foreign>, used as a toponym. This suggests that <foreign>babah buhaya</foreign> in this list probably refers to a battlefield landscape, not a battle formation.</note> taking the <foreign>liṅga</foreign> jewel form (<foreign>ṅaliṅga manik</foreign>),<note>In other OS texts (such as SC 1009, BM 1405, and VL 6), <foreign>liṅga manik</foreign> is a term for a specific type of land. This suggests, in the present context, that the term does not designate any kind of battle array, but rather a particular type of battlefield.</note> the victorious land (<foreign>ləmah mrəvasa</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>mrəvasa</foreign> is derived from <foreign>prəvasa</foreign>, related to <foreign>pravasa</foreign> in OJ. OJED only gives the derived form <foreign>kapravasa</foreign> ‘overpowered’. It is clearly from <foreign>paravaśa</foreign> ‘(Skt) subject to another's will, subdued, obedient; overpowered, destroyed’. In OJ we find <foreign>amaravaśa</foreign>/<foreign>pinaravaśa</foreign> to overpower, destroy’, which seems to be an equivalent of <foreign>mrəvasa</foreign> in our text. I interpret it as an adjective of <foreign>ləmah</foreign>.</note> ruling (<foreign>adipati</foreign>), dominating power (<foreign>prəbusakti</foreign>),<note>The term <foreign>prəbusakti</foreign> (Skt. and OJ <foreign>prabhuśakti</foreign>) ‘sovereignty’ is often attributed to Śiva as one of his four powers (<foreign>caduśakti</foreign>). Based on OJ treatises, the elements of <foreign>prabhuśakti</foreign> are: 1. fearlessness (<foreign>abhītaḥ</foreign>), 2. undecaying (<foreign>akṣayaḥ</foreign>), 3. unaging (<foreign>ajaraḥ</foreign>), and undying (<foreign>amaraḥ</foreign>) (DhP 282.18–284.16 in Acri 2017; Tjñ 4 in ​​Sudarshana Devi Singhal 1962; see also Chapter 10 §<foreign>Cadu-śakti</foreign>: The Four Powers of the Teacher).</note> the application of war and battle, the effort of <foreign>sapətrik</foreign> (?)<note>One would expect <foreign>siṅ savatək tiṅkah praṅ ma</foreign> between <foreign>savətrik</foreign> and <foreign>saṅ</foreign>. Probably it occurs an eye-skip from <foreign>siṅ</foreign> to <foreign>saṅ</foreign>?</note> — [we should] ask the commander (<foreign>hulu jurit</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.24">If we seek to know about of all kinds formulas and mantras:<note>The words aji and mantra often occur as a twin form. In OJ, aji has broad meanings ‘holy writ, the scriptures, sacred text; authoritative text (containing e.g. rules of conduct for a brahman; instructions on administration, politics, the practice of arms, the writing of poetry, etc); sacred or magically powerful formula’. In OS, this word is oftenly juxtaposed with mantra, and our context in SKK implies that this word refers to ‘the sacred or magically powerful formula’ rather than ‘scriptures’. Cf. KaPani 664–665 sesedaan sasaktiyan, ṅagǝralakǝn aji mantra “performing supernatural powers, applying formula and mantras”. We also find the combination aji mantra in several passages in SHH (3.2, 3.2, etc.). Cf. SHH 3.3 kajñāna ṅaranya ajñāna ginavay-gavay, apan ginavay ikaṅ aji mantra huṅkara padkara “kajñāna means artificial knowledge, because the formulas [and] mantras of huṅ syllable, of pad syllable are made up (artificially)”.</note>  mutterings and prayers (<foreign>jampa jampiya</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>The combination <foreign>jampa-jampya</foreign> is attested in SHH 3.3 <foreign>ginavay taṅ gəlar pūjā, aji mantra, veda śānti, mvaṅ jampa-jampya samādhi </foreign>“the ceremony, the worship, the formulas, the  mantras, the Vedas, the pacifications, as well as the spells and incantations [and finally] meditation are produced”. It seems that <foreign>jampa-jampya</foreign> is a localized representation (with spontaneous nasalization) of Skt. <foreign>japa-jāpya</foreign> ‘muterings and prayers’. Cf. MdS <foreign>jampé</foreign> ‘magic spells for remedy<foreign>’</foreign>. See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> restoring consciousness (?, <foreign>gəgəiṅ</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>diagrams (?, <foreign>susuratan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>The base word <foreign>susuratan</foreign>, <foreign>surat</foreign>, means ‘(drawn) line, writing, drawing, letter’ (OJED, s.v.). It probably refers to a kind of written/drawing formulas or mantras.</note> protections (<foreign>sasaranaan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>I interpret <foreign>sarana</foreign> in Skt. meaning: <foreign>śarana</foreign> ‘refuge, protection’.</note> distance vision (? <foreign>kaseraṅan</foreign>)<foreign>, pavayagahan,</foreign><note>Not found in dictionaries, probably related to OJ <foreign>vayakah</foreign>, which Zoetmulder notes “is this the base-word? <foreign>kawayakah</foreign> one on top of the other, in layers?” (OJED, s.v. <foreign>wayakah</foreign>).</note> (mantras) with flowers (? <foreign>pupuspaan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>purification mantras (<foreign>susudaan</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>life giving mantras (?, <foreign>hurip-huripan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>I take the meaning of <foreign>hurip-huripan </foreign>as an equivalent of MdJ <foreign>urip-uripan </foreign>‘dipitulungi lsp. supaya urip’ (Poerwadarminta 1939: s.v. urip).</note><foreign> tunduk iyəm </foreign>(?)<foreign>, </foreign>astrological formulas (<foreign>pararasen</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>It occurs as a title of an OJ text on astronomy. On manuscripts from the Merapi-Merbabu area containing this text, see Kartika Setyawati et al., 2002: 36, 37, 139, 165.</note> gnomon (<foreign>pasaṅkvan</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>In OJ, saṅku means ‘I bowl, dish’. It is also a Sanskrit-derived śaṅku ‘peg, nail, spike; arrow, spear, dart; pin or gnomon of a dial)’, but in the OJ context, it usually refers to a 'particular weapon (spear)’ (OJED, s.v.). According to Zoetmulder, the last meaning of śaṅku is ‘the appointed time (lit. “the time indicated by the pointer on the sundial”)’. Being placed after pararasen, which is related to astronomy, I tend to interpret pasaṅkvan according to the last meaning, as the astronomy formulas based on the sun, in contrast with pararasen (based on the moon).</note> — every kind of sacred formula, [we should] ask the <foreign>brahmana</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.25">If we seek to know about making offerings in the shrine (<foreign>saṅgar</foreign>): the drawings,<note>I understand <foreign>patah </foreign>as Skt <foreign>paṭṭa</foreign> ‘drawing’ (= OJ <foreign>pəṭa</foreign>), attested in SHH 28.3 apa ta katuduhaniṅ gavay saṅ manon ri sakala, ri sədaṅnyan rakut ikiṅ bhuvana śārīra samaṅke, nyaṅaji kāvya sāṅkhya prakaraṇa kalpa purāṇa nyāya viniścaya chanda gaṇita, ṅuniveh tāṅgəlar pūja dhyāna samādhi, mvaṅ paṭṭa liṅga liṅgir pratimā bimba, vihāra śāla kamūlān, parhyaṅan, cetya caṇḍi prasāda stūpa, nahan sakvehniṅ gavay saṅ manon ri sakala kabeh “What are the visible aspects of the activities of the Witness in the manifest, while he is involved in the physical world like this? Here: scriptures, poetry, Sāṅkhya, grammar, ritual, mythology, logic, decision, meter, mathematics; moreover, he performs worship, meditation, absorption. And drawings, liṅgas, statues, images, vihāras, hospices, kamūlāns, sanctuaries, caityas, caṇḍis, towers, stūpas. Such are all the works of the Witness in the manifest”.</note> the leaf offering, <foreign>palajaṅ</foreign> offering,<note>The word palajaṅ is obscure. However, I notice the occurrence of pulajaṅ in GS 121.3–8, which likely refers to a kind of plant. It occurs in the context of offering: ameta pulava maṅke, ki putut amintuhu, tandyaṅ mintar antuk sariñjiṅ, pulajaṅ sampun madaṅ, sampun maṅkva katur, lah ta ninva mumujaa “‘Now you should seek pulavas!’ The putut disciple obeys her. He immediately left, acquiring one basket. Pulajaṅs are ready, now they are already given. ‘Here, Nini! [Requisites] to perform the offering’”. In OJ, pulava is ‘a part. kind of tree (the white fragrant flowers are used in offerings); offering-flowers (KBW s.v. plava II)’, so there are two possibilities: either palajaṅ should be emended to pulajaṅ so we can render it as a synonym of pulava, or palajaṅ is another type of flower used for offering.</note> flower offering, putting a cloth on <foreign>liṅga</foreign>, maintenance of deities — every kind of offering, [we should] ask the <foreign>jaṅgan</foreign>.<note>The term <foreign>jaṅgan</foreign> denotes some kind of religious practitioner and appears frequently in OJ sources. Zoetmulder defines the word <foreign>jaṅgan </foreign>as <foreign>‘jaṅga</foreign> field?’, and <foreign>jaṅga</foreign> as ‘a part. kind of climber with fragrant flowers, prob. = gaḍuṅ’ (OJED, s.v. jaṅga). In MdJ and Bal., jaṅga is a kind of flower = gaduṅ. It seems that term jaṅgan is derived from the name of the flower. It is noteworthy that in Bali, the gadung flower is used for worship. However, jaṅgan as a person occurs in Par 4.27: kaget sira jaṅgan aṅiḍəpakən katunon “The jaṅgan was surprised while watching [it] burn down”. Pigeaud translates this term as ‘rural doctor’ in DV 78.7d: akveh iranya maṅasrayeṅ thani lavan jaṅgan prasiddheṅ jagat “Over many places is their spreading, looking for support in the peasants lands, with the <foreign>janggan</foreign>s (<foreign>rural doctors</foreign>) officiating to the world (the public in general)”, while Robson translates it as ‘rural curer’ (“Numbers of them are found roundabout and they seek the support of the villages and ‘rural curers’ as is well known”). Cf. Kuñj (591–595 in van der Molen 1983), which mentions kajaṅgan along with other places for religious practitioners: kategan kajaṅgan kadevagurvan paṅabətan (K paṅabəkṭan H; om. A) pamaṅuyon paguntuṅan paṅubonan. Supomo (1977: 65–66) notes that jaṅgan also occurs not only in the meaning of person, but also as an establishment in the Arjunavijaya. </note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.26">If we seek to know about the descent of time, month of the quake,<note>The meaning of the combination <foreign>bulan grəmpa</foreign> is unclear. The most plausible hypothesis is to take it as a phrase, not as a compound, and to interpret <foreign>bulan</foreign> as ‘month’, and not ‘moon’. This may refer to the earthquake augury found in texts such as <foreign>paliṇḍon </foreign>or <foreign>paliliṇḍon</foreign>, which describe month-based augury. The ceiling of the Kr̥ta Ghoṣa pavilion in Klungkung, painted in the mid-20th century, contains a <foreign>paliṇḍon</foreign> illustration with text corresponding to each month, e.g. an earthquake in the second month is associated with the goddess Gaṅgā (Sastrawan 2022: 18).</note> year without neck, [year] without head, walking world, immobile world, buried earth, earthquake<note>I take <foreign>bumi-grəmpa</foreign> as a localized spelling of Skt. <foreign>bhūmikampa</foreign> ‘earthquake’<foreign>. </foreign>In the recently discovered Warunggahan inscription (issued in 1305), which describes loss of a land title document in an earthquake, the term <foreign>bhūmikampa</foreign> is used for earthquake (Sastrawan 2022: 20).</note> — every kind of knowledge of ancient accounts (<foreign>carek nu bəhəla</foreign>),<note>Cf. SKK 15.1 where we encounter the similar expression <foreign>carita nu bəhəla</foreign>.</note> [we should] ask the <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.27">If we seek to know about the precepts of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> (<foreign>darma-siksa</foreign>), the precepts of the community (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), becoming an ascetic (<foreign>pasuk tapa</foreign>),<note>My translation of <foreign>pasuk tapa</foreign> as ‘becoming an ascetic’ follows Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw’s translation of SA 213 <foreign>avakana pasuk tapa </foreign>“you should devote yourself to asceticism”.</note> the meditation (?, <foreign>padonaan</foreign>),<note>I interpret <foreign>padonaan</foreign> as an equivalent of <foreign>padhyānan</foreign>, from <foreign>dhyāna </foreign>‘meditation’, even if the form <foreign>pa</foreign>- -<foreign>an</foreign> of <foreign>dhyāna</foreign> is unattested. Cf. SC. 500–503<foreign> patra dəṅ darmasonya, rudamala dəṅ askara, maṅləvi darmaprətuti, darmaveya padonaan. </foreign>In OJ, <foreign>paṅdonan</foreign> means ‘expedition’. I presume that this is due to the interchangeability of phonemes /y/ and /v/: <foreign>padyanaan</foreign> &gt; <foreign>padvanaan </foreign>&gt; <foreign>padonaan</foreign>. Cf. the use of <foreign>ivǝ</foreign> (Kawa6.4) for MdS <foreign>ieu</foreign>, more commonly spelt <foreign>iyǝ</foreign> in OS manuscripts.</note> the very pure (act?) (<foreign>mahapavitra</foreign>), the precepts of the teacher, the ten virtues (<foreign>dasa-sila</foreign>), the five teachings (<foreign>pañca-siksa</foreign>), foot sole of the teacher (<foreign>guru-talapakan</foreign>), misfortune of the world (<foreign>jagat-upadrava</foreign>), four powers (<foreign>cadu-sakti</foreign>), the reality of the world (<foreign>tato buvana</foreign>), the reality of the body (<foreign>tato sarira</foreign>), the reality of knowledge (<foreign>tato ajñana</foreign>) — every kind of contents of the books, [we should] ask the scholar.<note>See my analysis of the order and the meaning of these doctrines in Chapter 10.</note> </p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.28">In the first place the blessings (<foreign>kasorgaan</foreign>) in the manifest world: the kingship, the nobility, the eminence, the authority, the supremacy, <supplied reason="subaudible">we should</supplied> ask the king.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.29">If we seek to know about the organization of land (<foreign>patitis bumi</foreign>):<note>In OJ, <foreign>patitis</foreign> means ‘aiming at; direction in which st. moves, goal, target’, while in MdS it means ‘just struck, precisely (as it should), exact.’ Cf. SA 281–282 <foreign>siar sariniṅ ajñana, əsi patitisniṅ rasa </foreign>“You should seek the essence of knowledge, the aim of the feeling”. Literally meaning ‘the aim of land’, <foreign>patitis bumi</foreign> seems to mean here the way land is organized.</note> keeping the land apart,<note>In MdS, <foreign>ngampihkeun</foreign> means ‘have st. kept/stored somewhere (e.g. a car in the garage, animals in the pen or the corral for the night)’. Cf.  RR 1112–1114 where we encounter <foreign>ṅampihan</foreign>, translated as ‘give direction’ by Noordyn &amp; Teeuw: <foreign>adiiṅ na Puspa Lava, ku sia gǝra jǝnǝṅan, gǝra nu ṅampihan rama, na dayǝh gǝra pagǝhan</foreign> “My younger brother, Puspa Lawa, you must quickly take command, give direction to the chief, quickly fortify the town”.</note> consulting all people, ordering [or] discussing (<foreign>marin masini</foreign>), cutting<note>See Hardjadibrata (2003: s.v. <foreign>déngdéng</foreign>), <foreign>ngadéngdéng</foreign> ‘cut similarly, cut/chop straight (e.g. of a piece of wood or bamboo); <foreign>ngadéngdéng jukut</foreign> cut straight the edge of lawn’.</note> and trimming on a level,<note>I interpret <foreign>maras pade </foreign>as two words: maras, from paras, meaning ‘to trim’, and <foreign>pade</foreign> ‘on a level’. I believe that the last word is a variant of <foreign>pada</foreign> ‘equal’. Cf. SA 545 where the active form of pade, made, is attested: <foreign>hañjuaṅ sasipat mata, handələm salaput hulu, </foreign>mañara made paparas<foreign>, javer kotok made toṅgoṅ</foreign>. In MdS, we have a nasal between syllables <foreign>mandé </foreign>(Hardjadibrata 2003: s.v. <foreign>pandé.</foreign> Cf. SC 709 <foreign>mo kadeṅdeṅ kaparas pade, mo karaksa kaopeksa ika</foreign>; PR 36r <foreign>salaran tapa, pakǝn ṅavastu sa(ṅ)hyaṅ hayu, ka madiya ka vindu puhun rahayu, sahur nu visesa, agǝs saṅkup paksa tuṅgal sampak deṅdeṅ paraspade, krǝta uraṅ sajagat. </foreign></note> measuring and making equal, fining and punishing.<note>In OJ Pdg 6.1, we find <foreign>sipat</foreign> and <foreign>pīḍana</foreign> among royal punishments, together with more common list of <foreign>śukha-duhkha</foreign>s: <foreign>muvah lvirniṅ rājadaṇḍa, tan kavnaṅ tumibā riṅ saṅ vatək kr̥ta, ndya ta daṇḍa kudaṇḍa, reka, lūdan, tūtan, aṅśa pratyaṅśa, paraḍah, </foreign>sipat, pīḍana<foreign>, vākcapala, hastacapala, duhilatən, idu kasirat, mijilakən vuryaniṅ kikir, ikaṅ daṇḍakrama samaṅkana, tan dadi tumibāheṅ saṅ kr̥ta, apan sira luput riṅ valat vali rājavali, tan katapaka sira riṅ rājaśāsana </foreign>“Moreover, it is a characteristic of the royal punishments that they do not apply to the consecrated ones. As for instance: punishments and physical assault, treachery (<foreign>reka</foreign>), repeated attack (?, <foreign>lūdan</foreign>), pursuit (<foreign>tūtan</foreign>), contested dividing up of shares (?, <foreign>aṅśa pratyaṅśa</foreign>), <foreign>paraḍah</foreign> fines, <foreign>sipat</foreign> fines, oppressing, verbal assault (<foreign>vākcapala</foreign>), physical assault (<foreign>hastacapala</foreign>), defamation (?, <foreign>duhilatən</foreign>), spraying spittle (lit. “spittle that is sprayed”, <foreign>hidu kasirat</foreign>), producing “the trace of a file” (<foreign>mijilakən vuryaniṅ kikir</foreign>), all of this series of punishments, it is impossible that they would apply to the consecrated ones, for the latter are exempt from the use of violence in retribution, [especially retribution] by the king, they will not be subject to <foreign>Rājaśāsana</foreign>”. Cf. Sva sipat, ya ta lvir, 40000, tuvi pinaten kavnaṅ, ndah tan kneṅ lokika:, sajatya nir sipat; SC 300 k<foreign>asamur bənaṅ mitutur, roṅod bənaṅ nu ṅadeṅdeṅ, maraspade ñipat midana</foreign>.</note> If it is highland, it is made to be flat, headland is made to be equal<note>The word <foreign>pakpak</foreign> is not found in MdS, but probably it is clearly related to MdS <foreign>papak </foreign>‘level, equal’. In OJ <foreign>pakpak</foreign> means ‘to flatter, address with soothing words, persuade gently, coax’, which clearly does not fit the context. Here <foreign>dipakpak</foreign> probably means ‘to be made equal’. Cf. Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> (with the shore?), all kinds of dependent villages (? <foreign>ampih-ampih</foreign>),<note>The reduplicated form <foreign>ampih-ampih</foreign> is probably equivalent with OJ <foreign>ampihan</foreign> ‘dependent villages’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>ampih </foreign>2). In MdS <foreign>ampih-ampih</foreign> means ‘put away the tools, clear the table (to eat etc.);  save some pennies aside’.</note> we should ask the Maṅkubumi.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.30">If we seek to know about all sorts of anchorages, especially sandbanks (<foreign>gosoṅ</foreign>), channels (<foreign>goroṅ</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>I assume ‘channel’ as the meaning of <foreign>goroṅ</foreign> based on the meaning of <foreign>gorongan</foreign> or <foreign>gurungan</foreign> in MdJ (Robson 2002, s.vv.); not in MdS.</note><foreign> kabua </foreign>(?),<note>The meaning of <foreign>kabua</foreign> is obscure. The meaning of MdJ <foreign>kabwa</foreign> ‘all’ is unlikely. It is noteworthy that <foreign>karang kabua </foreign>is recorded as the name of a small island in Banten. Can we speculate that <foreign>kabua </foreign>is a kind of reef? The B has <foreign>kabuAn· riAk·.</foreign></note>, ripples, i.e., ripples from all directions (<foreign>ryak mokprok</foreign>), deceitful ripples (<foreign>ryak maliṅ</foreign>), big waves (<foreign>alun aguṅ</foreign>), headlands (<foreign>tañjuṅ</foreign>), promontories (<foreign>hujuṅ</foreign>), islands (<foreign>nusa</foreign>), islets (<foreign>pulo</foreign>),<note>My choice to distinguish between <foreign>nusa</foreign> and <foreign>pulo</foreign> (rather than to assume they are synonyms juxtaposed as a ‘twin form’) is based on occurrences of these words in BM, where <foreign>pulo</foreign> seems to refer only to small islands, while <foreign>nusa</foreign> refers to a bigger island or territory. Cf. BM 1248–1253 on the description of the islets in Sunda strait: <foreign>itu ta pulo saṅ hiaṅ, hǝlǝt-hǝlǝt nusa lampuṅ, ti timur pulo tampuruṅ, ti barat pulo rakata, gunuṅ di tǝṅah sagara </foreign>“That one there was the islet Sang Hiang, halfway the realm of Lampung, to the east the islet Tampurung, to the west the islet Rakata, a mountain in the middle of the sea”. See Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> barrier reefs (<foreign>karaṅ nuṅgul</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>nuṅgul</foreign> is from <foreign>tuṅgul</foreign> ‘(tree)stump, trunk stripped of its branches’, cf. Mal. <foreign>tunggul</foreign>, which according to KBBI means ‘tonggak (untuk menambatkan perahu dan sebagainya)’. I interpret karaṅ nuṅgul as ‘barrier reef’.</note> south-easterly [winds] (<foreign>tuṅgara</foreign>), south-westerly [winds] (<foreign>barat daya</foreign>), all kinds of sea travel [and] sailing, [we should] ask the sea captain (<foreign>puhavaṅ</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.31">If we seek to know about all kinds of prices: three million, three hundred thousand, thirty thousand, three thousand, six hundred, three hundred, thirty all the more so a half (<foreign>karo bəlah</foreign>), a third (<foreign>katəlu bəlah</foreign>), a quarter (<foreign>kapat bəlah</foreign>), a fifth (<foreign>kalima bəlah</foreign>), a sixth (<foreign>kanəm bəlah</foreign>), a seventh (<foreign>kapitu bəlah</foreign>), an eighth (<foreign>kavolu bəlah</foreign>), a ninth (<foreign>kasaṅa bəlah</foreign>) — every kind of price, [we should] ask the <foreign>citrik byapari</foreign>.<note>The word <foreign>citrik</foreign> is a hapax, while <foreign>byapari</foreign> is ultimately related to Skt. <foreign>vyāpāra </foreign>‘occupation, employment, business, profession; doing, performance, action’. We expect the meaning ‘trader’ in this context. However, in MdS, as in MdJ, <foreign>catrik</foreign> means ‘disciple of a hermit (teacher in mythical wisdom, etc.); <foreign>nyatrik</foreign> be a disciple (with a hermit etc.). So the sense is possibly ‘a trader’s apprentice’.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.32">If we seek to know about the esoteric sciences (<foreign>sandhi</foreign>), asceticism, posture, direct perception, detachment, epitome, liberation,<note>Instead of <foreign>kaləpasan</foreign>, the authors of OS texts seem to be consistent in spelling <foreign>kaləpasən</foreign>, especially in the discussion of the <foreign>vuku lima</foreign>. On the use of the suffix -<foreign>ən</foreign> without irrealis meaning, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> ancestor metaphysics, deity metaphysics, elemental accounts, epochal accounts — every kind of deity metaphysics,<note>See the analysis of these terms in Chapter 10.</note> [we should] ask the hermits of the people (<foreign>viku para loka</foreign>).<note>I render <foreign>viku para loka</foreign> as a synonymous expression to <foreign>viku sabhuvana</foreign> in SHH. MsB has <foreign>para loka kabeh</foreign>, indicating that <foreign>loka </foreign>is more likely to be interpreted as ‘human, people’, not ‘world’. In this case, the interpretation of <foreign>viku para loka </foreign>as ‘otherworldly hermit’  given in Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 175 should be revised.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_11.33">If we want to act, we should not ask the wrong person. If we seek to know about the languages of various countries<note>On the analysis of the topographical names in this list, see Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006: 156), West (2021: 188–194).</note> — the languages of China (<foreign>cina</foreign>), South India (<foreign>kəliṅ</foreign>), Persia (<foreign>parasi</foreign>), Egypt (<foreign>məsir</foreign>), Samudra,<note>The toponym Samudra is also recorded in DV ​13.2 i lvas lāvan samudra mvaṅ i lamuri batan lāmpuṅ mvaṅ i barus, yekādinyaṅ vatək bhūmi malayu satanah kapvāmatəh anūt “Lvas and Samudra, as well as Lamuri, Batan, Lampung and Barus. Those are the main ones among the Malay lands; all these countries are subject and obedient”. Samudra is the name for the whole island of Sumatra, given by the foreigners of the 14th century (e.g. Nicolo de Conti, Ludovico de Varthema). Samudra (or Pasai), located near present-day Lhokseumawe, was at that time the rising power in the island. Krom (1941: 22–5) argues that the success of Samudra/Sumatra as the name for the whole island also owed something to the older Sanskrit term Suvarṇabhūmi (‘Gold-land’) occasionally applied to Sumatra, notably by a Singasari inscription of 1286. Cf. also Reid 1987: 27–28.</note> Bengal (<foreign>baṅgala</foreign>), Makassar, Pahang, Palembang, Siam, Kelantan (<foreign>kalantən</foreign>), Bangka, Buwun, Béten,<note>Béten is perhaps equivalent to <foreign>batan</foreign> mentioned in DV 13.2 (see fn. 302).</note> Tulang Bawang, Sela, Pasai (<foreign>pasay</foreign>), Pariaman (<foreign>parayaman</foreign>), <foreign>ṅara</foreign> Rokan (? <foreign>ṅara dəkan</foreign>),<note>Previous scholars (e.g., Griffiths 2019: 216), interpreted this toponym as referring to the Indian region called Deccan, but this was based on the ASD reading nagara dəkan. Jarrah Sastrawan (p.c., January 2023) proposes that <foreign>dəkan</foreign> may refer to <foreign>rəkan</foreign> (= present-day Rokan), based on DV 13.1: lvirniṅ nūṣa pranūṣa pramukha sakahavat kṣoṇī ri malayu, naṅ jāmbi mvaṅ palembaṅ karitaṅ i təba len dharmāśraya tumūt, kaṇḍis kahvas manaṅkabva ri siyak i rəkān kāmpar mvaṅ i pane, kāmpe harv āthave maṇḍahiliṅ i tumihaṅ parlāk mvaṅ i barat “The islands and lesser islands, in the first place coming under the territory of the Malay lands. Are Jambi and Palembang, Karitang, Teba and Dhanasraya following them, Kandis, Kahwas, Manangkabwa, Siyak, Rəkan, Kampar and Pane, Kampe, Haru and Mandahiling, Tumihang, Parlak and Barat”<foreign>. </foreign>This interpretation seems likely not only because interlinguistic fluctuation between the sounds /r/ and /d/ is imaginable (OJ rəṅə̄, OS deṅe, MdS dangu/déng<foreign>é</foreign>), but also the previous typonyms are situated in Sumatra. For the word <foreign>ṅara</foreign>, we can only rely on ms. A. This word is unattested elsewhere, and should perhaps be emended to <foreign>ṅare</foreign>. Cf. OJ  <foreign>ṅare</foreign> ‘a plain (at the foot of the mountain)?’, OS <foreign>uraṅ are</foreign> ‘people from the valley’, MdJ <foreign>are</foreign> or <foreign>ṅare</foreign>, ‘low, level and open, of land in contrast to mountain and wood’, Mal. <foreign>ngarai</foreign> ‘canyon, ravine’. Another option is to consider <foreign>ṅaradigan</foreign>/<foreign>ṅaradəkan</foreign> as corrupt for <foreign>arakan</foreign>, i.e. what is nowadays known as Rakhine State in Myanmar.</note> Dinah (?),<note>Previous scholars such as Atja &amp; Saleh Danasasmita (1981) and Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw (2006) have interpreted Dinah as Madinah, i.e. Medina. I must agree and add that Madinah is attested in another OS text, viz. CRP 359–361 <foreign>haris bañcana, ahis patih gajah biṅbaṅ, putri ti nusa madinah</foreign> “Haris Bancana, the younger sister of vizir Gajah Bingbang, the princess from the country of Madinah”.</note> Andalas (<foreign>andələs</foreign>), Tego, Moluccas (<foreign>moloko</foreign>), Bandan (<foreign>badan</foreign>), Bago (<foreign>pego</foreign>), Minangkabau (<foreign>malaṅkabo</foreign>), Mecca, Buretet, Lawai (<foreign>lave</foreign>), Sasak (<foreign>saksak</foreign>), Sumbawa (<foreign>səmbava</foreign>), Bali, Jenggi,<note>According to Jákl (2017: 3), the term <foreign>jəṅgi</foreign> may refer to the wider area of the east African coast, extending from the river Juba in southern Ethiopia down to Cape Delgado, a coastal promontory on the border of Tanzania and Mozambique. Jákl, who consistently translated ‘Black Africans’, does not allow the possibility that this term could refer to any Southeast Asian indigenous populations. However, our context places Jenggi after Sumbawa and Bali, so probably it refers to the eastern region of Indonesia.</note> Nusa Bini (<foreign>sabini</foreign>),<note>My interpretation of Sabini as a short form of Nusa Bini is based on its occurrences in BM 1267 <foreign>nusa dilih nusa bini </foreign>“Dilih and Nusa Bini” and KaKat 17 <foreign>parasi dəṅ nusa bini </foreign>“Persia and Nusa Bini”. However, the location of this toponym is uncertain. On Nusa Bini in BM, West (2021: 189) furnishes interesting information: “Nusa Bini presents some difficulties (cf. SSKK’s ⟨sabini⟩). No place with this name can be identified, although Coolsma (1913: 82) says it refers to a mythical ‘Island of the Amazons’ (cf. OJv, Malay <foreign>bini</foreign> ‘wife’). This is not an uncommon motif in medieval texts; Polo describes an <foreign>ysle de femes</foreign> ‘Island of Women’ (f.90v) in the Indian Ocean, and on the Catalan Atlas it is said that Java (ILLA IANA) is itself home to a ‘kingdom of women’ (<foreign>recn͠o femarum</foreign>). Jordanus says there are women’s and men’s islands in the Indian Ocean, and that men cannot live on the women’s island and vice versa (1839[~1330]:57). Zhào Rŭkuò (c.1225) also mentions a ‘land of women’ (女人國) with the same characteristics, and Pires says that local folklore told of an island near Nias (Maruz Minhac) where only women lived (Cortesão 1944:162). BM’s <foreign>Bini</foreign> is not exceptional in this context”.</note> Ogan (<foreign>ṅogan</foreign>), Kanangen, Komering (<foreign>kuməriṅ</foreign>), Sampang Tiga,<note>The reading is based on ms. A. While ms. A reflects the correct reading of toponyms with the cluster <foreign>mp </foreign>such as <foreign>sampaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>lampuṅ</foreign>, and <foreign>cəmpa</foreign>, ms. B systematically has <foreign>mara</foreign>, so the latter has <foreign>samaraṅ</foreign>,<foreign> lamaruṅ</foreign> and<foreign> cəmara</foreign>. This is due to the scribal misinterpretation of the ligature <foreign>mp</foreign> as consisting in the <foreign>aksara</foreign>s <foreign>ma</foreign> and <foreign>ra</foreign>. The toponym <foreign>sampaṅ tiga</foreign> seems to be synonymous with <foreign>simpaṅ tiga</foreign>, since the OS word <foreign>sampaṅ</foreign> means  ‘road crossing’. Several instances of the toponym Simpang Tiga exist in Sumatra Selatan and Sumatra Utara.</note> Gumantung, Manubi, Bubu, Nyiri, Sapari, Patukangan, Surabaya, Lampung, India (<foreign>jambudipa</foreign>), Seram (?, <foreign>seran</foreign>), Kedah (<foreign>gədah</foreign>), Salaut (?, <foreign>solot</foreign>), Solodong, Indragiri, Tanjungpura,<note>The <foreign>Deśavarṇana</foreign> (13.2) mentions Tañjuṅnagara, which probably refers to Tañjuṅpura and listed among the Malay territories, was ‘subject and obedient’ to Majapahit. Barbosa places Tourjoãopura in Borneo (2000 [1516]: 407). It is the place where diamonds are produced. Pires calls this place Tamjompura (Cortesão 1944: 223–224).</note> Sakampung, Atas Angin, Campa (<foreign>cəmpa</foreign>), Baluk, Java — all kinds of countries, [we should] ask the interpreter who is a reliable guide to <foreign>dharma</foreign> (<foreign>darma-murcaya</foreign>).<note>The meaning of <foreign>darma-murcaya</foreign> is obscure. It seems that this compound is related to Skt. <foreign>dharmapratyaya</foreign>. Sanskrit <foreign>pratyaya</foreign> has a range of senses, growing out of its etymological meaning ‘going to’ &gt; ‘resorting to’, ‘accepting’, ‘recognizing’, ‘explaining’ &gt; ‘(basis for) trust, belief, confidence, certainty’. In the literary (<foreign>kawi</foreign>) form of MdJ, we find an expression <foreign>dadya caya-murcaya</foreign> ‘kw. minangka dadi tandhaning panuwun’ (as a token of gratitude). We find one occurrence of caya murcaya in the Kuṭarāgama: <foreign>caya murcaya, cayane kaṅ ṅala lan kaṅ bəcik </foreign>“<foreign>Caya murcaya</foreign>: the <foreign>caya </foreign>in the bad and the good”, but the sense remains obscure. Since a connection between <foreign>darma-murcaya</foreign> and <foreign>dharma-pratyaya</foreign> seems plausible in itself, but the other evidence about <foreign>murcaya</foreign> in Javanese is not obviously compatible with a derivation from <foreign>pratyaya</foreign>, we have to admit that the interpretation of <foreign>darma-murcaya</foreign> remains uncertain in the present state of our knowledge. My translation of <foreign>juru basa darma-murcaya</foreign> as ‘the interpreter who is a reliable guide to <foreign>dharma</foreign>’ is therefore tentative. I thank Tim Lubin for the information on <foreign>dharmapratyaya</foreign> in Sanskrit corpus.</note></p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_12">
<p corresp="#skk_12.01">That is what should be known, as to their reliability and appropriateness. If there is one who says that he does not know, he is one who is not faithful to his own function, is very ignorant<note>My emendation of <foreign>mo təiṅ</foreign> to<foreign> moha təiṅ</foreign> is based on the occurrence of <foreign>moha təiṅ</foreign> in BM 967 <foreign>moha təiṅ nu ti həla</foreign> “the confusion was more than before”. Here I take <foreign>moha təiṅ</foreign> as an adjective ‘very ignorant’ referring to the implicit subject <foreign>nu. </foreign>Cf. AG 3v <foreign>mulah koyo moha di carekna kolot pun </foreign>“Don’t be difficult, ignorant to the words of elders”; KaPani 848–849  <foreign>hamo ñaho di pamali, moha di sabda halimpu </foreign>“Doesn’t know about the forbidden act, ignorant to the suitable speech”.</note> as to the words of our Gods, does not fear misfortune (<foreign>upadrava</foreign>), the cycle of worlds (<foreign>jagat-ganti</foreign>)<note>On the extra nasal in <foreign>ganti </foreign>&lt; <foreign>gati</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> [and] the four powers (<foreign>cadu-sakti</foreign>) of the scholar. [He] is certainly<note>On <foreign>tan avuruṅ</foreign>, cf. OJ <foreign>tan vuruṅ</foreign> ‘without fail, certainly, unremittingly’, and also MdS <foreign>mo burung</foreign> ‘id’.</note> awaited by the cauldron.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.02">Regarding the works, they should not be performed; regarding the actions, they should not be carried out — except (<foreign>sahiṅaniṅ</foreign>) virtuous works, for that is the thread of the ancestors [and] the thread of the gods, the memorial of the Lord of the world, when He made the unmanifest world prosperous.<note>The expression <foreign>ṅrətakən bumi</foreign> is also found in the Huludayeuh inscription (Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 176–179). Cf. SKK 16.2: <foreign>taṅkalniṅ bumi krəta</foreign>.</note> When Brahma, Wisnu, Isora, Mahadéwa, Siwa are devoted to the Lord; when Indra, Yama, Baruna, Kowéra, Bésawarna<note>Besavarna corresponds to Skt. Vaiśravaṇa. In Inscriptions from Bali, this deity is called Bāsava (van Stein Callenfels 1926: 5). </note> are devoted to the Lord; when Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusa, Patanjala are devoted to the Lord — [when] all of the gods together are devoted to Lord Séda Niskala, [then] all of them find the one who is true with direct perception.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.03">This is what must be found in the manifest world, the thread of the Lord for the world, so that [we are] firm in becoming ‘jewels in one cage’ (? <foreign>manik sakuruṅan</foreign>);<note>The meaning of <foreign>manik sakuruṅan</foreign> is obscure. It is attested in CP 39a: <foreign>saṅ vrǝti kandayun adǝg di galuh, ti iña lumaku ṅarajarǝsi, ṅaṅaranan maneh rahyaṅta ti mǝnir, basana aṅkat sabumi jadi manik sakuruṅan, iña nu ñiyǝn na purbatisti </foreign>“Wreti Kandayun reigned in Galuh, from where he performed the <foreign>rajarəsi</foreign>, calling himself Rahyangta of Menir. When he departed from the whole world to become ‘a jewel in one cage’, he was the one who made the sacred rules”<foreign>.</foreign> It should be noted that in OS texts, <foreign>kuruṅan</foreign> also means ‘body’, as separate from the soul (<foreign>atma</foreign>). I suppose that the metaphoric expression <foreign>manik sakuruṅan</foreign>, which can be translated in this context as ‘a jewel in one body’, expresses that the ascetic has reached the highest state. ASD, however, translate it as ‘<foreign>berumah tangga</foreign>’ (to be married).</note> so that we are shining [in] the whole world: the servant is devoted to his master, the wife is devoted to her husband, the child is devoted to his father, the pupil is devoted to his teacher, the <foreign>mantri</foreign> is devoted to the <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign>, <foreign>maṅkubumi</foreign> is devoted to the king, the king is devoted to the Gods. They are ordered to stabilize their bodies, directing the breath, the speech [and] the mind. </p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.04">If those [actions] are not performed and [not] carried out by the humans, of low, middle, and high class, each of them is thrown into the cauldron called ‘Bull Headed Copper [Cauldron]’.<note>On the visualization of <foreign>tambragomuka</foreign> (OJ <foreign>tamragohmukha</foreign>), see Teeuw <foreign>et al.</foreign> 1981: 204–216 who analyze the relief based on the <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> in Candi Jago.</note> Because the human is overpowered by the Gods. <foreign>Pun</foreign>.<note>Cf. <foreign>pun </foreign>in 23.2 and my comment on this word. Actually we do not expect <foreign>pun </foreign>at the end of this paragraph. </note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.05">Darma Pitutur spoke, reporting the words of the precursors: There is another comparison, like [when] we went to Java, [we] are unable to follow its language and its manners, we felt confused. After [we] returned home to Sunda, we were unable to speak Javanese. It felt as if we had not come [back] from a journey, “what we bought as a result of visiting was worthless”,<note><foreign>poos tukuna bənaṅ tandaṅ </foreign>‘what we bought as a result of visiting was worthless’ seems to be an idiomatic expression. It seems to be more or less similar with MdS expression <foreign>luput teu beubeunangan </foreign>‘gone wrong, not gained anything’<foreign>. </foreign></note> because of inability to follow its language. </p>
<p corresp="#skk_12.06">That is how we are, as humans, continually<note>I interpret <foreign>haṅər </foreign>as an equivalent to <foreign>haṅgər </foreign>(= MdS <foreign>angger</foreign>). We find several words which show similar cases in MdS: <foreign>panger</foreign> is equivalent to <foreign>pangger</foreign>, <foreign>tetengger </foreign>is to <foreign>tetenger</foreign>.</note> descending from the unmanifest, [but] not finding the manners of the Gods, rushing to be incarnated as humans, because their appearance is silly, their behavior is ignorant, [and they are] incapable of following the acts of the ones who know. There are acts committed that are unfaithful, that are improper. [They] start to do evil, to trespass, to have affairs in secret (<foreign>bubunyan</foreign>) with younger and older relatives. That is why a woman enjoying a man who is not her husband is considered improper; a man enjoying a woman who is not his wife (? <foreign>əsi imahna</foreign>)<note>The expression <foreign>əsi imah</foreign> literally seems to mean ‘household’,  but here we expect it to refer to the ‘wife’. Or does it rather indicate any woman present in the household, including personnel, concubines, etc.?</note> is [likewise] considered improper. [They] are liable to be thrown into the cauldron called ‘The Victorious Deer’ (Si Mrəga Vijaya),<note>The association of hell with deer is rather unusual. However, it should be noted that there is a relief at Candi Sukuh, called the Kala-mr̥ga by Hariani Santiko (2011), which depicts an arch with a Kala figure at the top center and two deer facing the outside at the bottom (see Aditia Gunawan 2019: 47, fig. 2.1, for the image). This arch encircles the main focus of the relief, namely the conversation between Lord Guru and Bhīma in the story of <foreign>Bhīma Svarga</foreign>, which takes place in hell. The arch in this relief may thus represent the gates of hell.</note> because humans prefer what is wrong. </p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_13">
<p corresp="#skk_13.01">These are the symbolic terms (<foreign>siloka</foreign>)<note>The word <foreign>siloka</foreign> is an OS term derived from Skt. <foreign>śloka</foreign> ‘stanza’, but in this context it seems to mean ‘symbolic term, symbolic expression’, as in MdS.</note> for the behavior of wrong people: lawless (<foreign>buraṅkak</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>buraṅkak</foreign> is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but it is attested in OJ ‘daring, lawless’, taken from its occurrence in Kuñj 62.17 (or line 1175–118 in van der Molen edition), as one of the behavior of the sinful Purṇavijāya: <foreign>saṅ pūrṇavijaya ṅaranya, sakiṅ kendran saṅkane, agəṅ dvaṣanya, atyanta həṅkaranya, vgig, buraṅkak, aṅalāpi stri laraṅan </foreign>‘Who is called Purṇavijāya from the heaven of Indra, his sins are enormous, his selfish is perpetual, naughty, lawless, tooking the forbidden womens’.</note> anxious (? <foreign>marende</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>marende</foreign> in MdS is an active form of <foreign>paréndé</foreign> ‘to put a child to sleep by laying down for a moment’. Probably there is an allusion to the child's condition when they are anxious before sleeping? The explanation of this term in 13.4 seems to fit this interpretation.</note> sulky (<foreign>mariris</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>mariris</foreign> ‘sulky’ is equivalent to OJ <foreign>ariris</foreign> ‘id’. Not in MdS.</note> shameful (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>). They are called the four demons. The meaning is: <foreign>buraṅkak</foreign> means shuddering. What is horrifying,<note>I render <foreign>gila</foreign> as in MdS ‘shudder at st., abhor st., be horrified at st’. On the prefix <foreign>maha- </foreign>(<foreign>paha</foreign>-) resulting in causative meaning, see Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> as it were, is the behavior of the person who is envious, surly, staring, coarse (?, <foreign>gasoṅ</foreign>),<note>Unrecorded in Sundanese dictionaries, <foreign>gasoṅ</foreign> may be related to Mal. <foreign>gasang </foreign>‘lecherous person; incontinent lustful, passionate’.</note> rude in speech, ugly in behavior, hot of heart. [Such behavior] is considered improper. That is what the behavior of such men is like, horrifying as it were. He becomes a demon, Durga, Durgi, the demon Kala. His place is in the dirt of the earth.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.02">The dirty soils are: hollows, clusters (? <foreign>saroṅge</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>saroṅge</foreign> is not found in any dictionary, but it is known as a toponym. In MdJ we find <foreign>rongge</foreign> ‘<foreign>wuli</foreign>. <foreign>ronggean pari: wulèn pari</foreign>. <foreign>nanging ing Kêndhal sarongge </foreign>= <foreign>saombyok</foreign>’ (‘a stalk. <foreign>ronggean pari </foreign>‘a stalk of paddy’, but in Kendal <foreign>sarongge</foreign> = a bunch’; only recorded in De Nooy &amp; Padmasoesastra 1893: 24). B has  <foreign>soṅgeṅ</foreign>, which seems to be an equivalent of MdJ <foreign>suṅgiṅ</foreign> ‘to paint’, but this does not fit our context. Cf. also the similar meaning expressed by <foreign>ṅararaṅgeyan</foreign> in SKK 4.1 which corresponds to MdS <foreign>ranggeuy</foreign> ‘bunch, cluster’.</note> lime-stone cliffs (<foreign>cadas gantuṅ</foreign>), scattered stones,<note>I consider <foreign>pateṅgaṅ</foreign> to be an equivalent of <foreign>patenggang</foreign> ‘stand/lie far apart (from each other), lie scattered (of houses etc.)’. Cf. one of the meanings of <foreign>tenggang</foreign> ‘equally divided’ in Malay (Wilkinson, s.v.). See Chapter 3, §Phonology</note> gorges, swamps,<note>On the word <foreign>rañcak</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> rhinoceros ponds, tree trunks upside down<note>I interpret <foreign>nuṅgaṅ</foreign> (from <foreign>tuṅgaṅ</foreign>) as ‘upside down’ on the basis of one of its meaning in Mal. ‘upside-down, Inversion’, besides ‘to ride’. Only the latter meaning is found in MdS. Cf. OJ <foreign>tuṅgaṅ </foreign>which has the same meaning as MdS ‘to mount, ride on, sit on’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>tuṅgaṅ</foreign>).</note> and aslant (<foreign>cataṅ nuṅgaṅ cataṅ noṅgeṅ</foreign>), mine tunnels (<foreign>garuṅguṅan gareṅgeṅan</foreign>),<note>The words <foreign>garuṅguṅan</foreign> and <foreign>gareṅgeṅan</foreign> are not found in any dictionary, but are probably related with MdS <foreign>garung</foreign> ‘left unused, uncultivated’ or with <foreign>gurung</foreign> ‘culvert’. Cf. also MdS <foreign>garungsang</foreign> and <foreign>gurangséng</foreign> ‘very steep’ (the wall of a ravine, rock-face, etc.). I presume that <foreign>garuṅguṅan gareṅgeṅan</foreign> is equivalent to <foreign>garungsang-gurangséng</foreign>. Cf. Mal. <foreign>geronggang</foreign> ‘cavity; hollow’.</note> dangerous lands (<foreign>saṅhar</foreign>),<note>Cf. MdS. <foreign>sangar</foreign>. On the unexpected <foreign>h</foreign> at the start of the second syllable, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> burning grounds,<note>The interpretation of <foreign>daṅdaṅ</foreign> as ‘burning ground’ is based on the meaning of <foreign>dangdangan</foreign> in MdS ‘​​cleaned up strip of ground around an area to be burnt (to prevent the flames from jumping over); ring around fire lane’. However, MdJ has <foreign>dangdang</foreign> ‘crow’ which may suggest a plausible alternative interpretation of <foreign>daṅdaṅ</foreign> because it is juxtaposed with <foreign>varian</foreign>, which seems to be related to OJ <foreign>varya-varya</foreign> ‘crawling animal’ (see fn. 331). If the later interpretation is correct, then we need to interpret <foreign>daṅdaṅ varian</foreign> as ‘[lands] of crows and crawling animals’</note> [lands of] crawling animals (<foreign>varian</foreign>),<note>Many interpretations can be imagined for the word <foreign>varian</foreign>. In MdS we find  <foreign>kawarian</foreign> ‘<foreign>kalakuan nu teu umum cara nu kurang saeundan</foreign>’ (abnormal behavior like that of a crazy man)’ and <foreign>wawarian</foreign> ‘<foreign>kadaharan sésa di nu tas hajat</foreign>’ (leftover food during a celebration). In Skt., <foreign>vāri</foreign> means ‘water’, so <foreign>varian</foreign> could mean ‘watery land’. Skt. also has <foreign>varīyas</foreign> (nom. sg. <foreign>varīyān</foreign>) ‘wider, broader (`than abl.); freer, easier’ and ‘wider space, free space, freedom, comfort, ease’. In OJ, a similar word that fits our context is <foreign>varya-varya</foreign> ‘a kind of crawling animal’, which occurs in a list of despicable animals: <foreign>hiri-hiris poh, caciṅ, varya-varya</foreign>. So <foreign>[ləmah] varian</foreign> could mean ‘[lands of] crawling animals’. With reference to this OJ word, I choose to interpret <foreign>varian</foreign> as ‘crawling animals’.</note> hillocks, male soils (<foreign>ləmah laki</foreign>),<note>The compound <foreign>ləmah laki</foreign> is a hapax. There seems to be some kind of analogy with <foreign>nusa bini</foreign> which literally means ‘female Island’. In MdS, <foreign>laki</foreign> also means ‘pounder’, but it seems to be a secondary semantic development from ‘male’. For the time being, I keep the literal translation of <foreign>ləmah laki</foreign> as ‘male soils’.</note> pigsties, gutters (<foreign>kalomberan</foreign>),<note>Cf. MdS <foreign>kolombéran</foreign>, MdJ <foreign>klombèran</foreign>, Mal. <foreign>comberan</foreign>.</note> rubbish dumps, cremation grounds (<foreign>səma</foreign>)<note>See OJED, s.v. <foreign>səma </foreign>‘cemetery, graveyard’, not in MdS.</note> — every kind of soil avoided.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.03">What those who are obstinate in their ugly behaviors become is like that, because the behavior of men is what gives horror.<note>I presume that <foreign>mere gila</foreign> is equivalent to <foreign>makagila</foreign> and <foreign>mahagila</foreign>. See Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note> They become every sort of horrifying thing, because they do not follow the holy instruction of the accomplished one,<note>See my comment on <foreign>krəta</foreign> in 11.2.</note> because they transgress the Hermits’ Holy Precepts for Society. That is why they become horrifying. That is the meaning of <foreign>buraṅkak</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.04"><foreign>Marende</foreign> means: being cooled down<note>My emendation <foreign>dibeka</foreign> into <foreign>dibere</foreign> is based on the resemblance of the <foreign>aksara</foreign>s <foreign>re</foreign> (<foreign>ra</foreign> + <foreign>panéléng</foreign>) and <foreign>ka</foreign>, whether in <foreign>gebang</foreign> manuscripts or in <foreign>lontar</foreign>s.</note> and yet feeling hot; being given pity,<note>The passive word <foreign>dikahemankən</foreign> seems to be formed by the circumfix <foreign>di- -kən</foreign> with the secondary base <foreign>kaheman</foreign> (noun derived from verb <foreign>heman</foreign> ‘pity’). It seems that the literal meaning would be ‘being the object of pity’, so <foreign>dikahemankən</foreign> means ‘being given pity’. Cf. MdS <foreign>mangnyaahkeun</foreign> (from <foreign>nyaah</foreign>) ‘to take pity on so. else, feel pity for so’.</note> being given sympathy, being taken care of, being coddled, being given pleasures [and] enjoyments,<note>Cf. <foreign>ku suka ku boga</foreign> in SKK 9.1.</note> servants [and] slaves, and yet mistrusting [them]. It is clear that he is affected by the misery of which the field [called] Patana is full.<note>For other descriptions of hell, cf. Kuñj 13–14 and 26, KuñjDhK (especially stanzas 7 and 8), and the OS CaPur 75–245, discussed at length by Teeuw <foreign>et al</foreign>. 1981: 32–33. The expression <foreign>təgal si patana</foreign> refers to a place in hell mentioned in the OJ <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> as <foreign>bhūmipatana</foreign>. It seems that <foreign>patana</foreign> itself is a local development from Skt. <foreign>pātāla</foreign>. The development of /l/ to /n/ is quite common in the languages of Indonesia: Skt. and OJ <foreign>janma</foreign> = MdS <foreign>jalma</foreign>, Skt. <foreign>vanāntara</foreign> &gt; Mal. <foreign>belantara</foreign>, Skt. <foreign>janatā</foreign> = Mal. <foreign>jelata</foreign>. Cf. CaPur 79 which uses the term <foreign>bumipatala</foreign>.</note> Its length is one <foreign>yojana</foreign>.<note>The word <foreign>yojana</foreign>, from Skt (=OJ) ‘a measure of distance (= 4 krośas or about 9 miles?)’. Not in MdS.</note> In the east is the Sword Tree.<note>The compound <foreign>kalapa kandaga</foreign> ‘sword-tree’ is an equivalent of OJ <foreign>kalpa kaṇḍaga </foreign>which has simmilar meaning (OJED, s.v.). Cf. Kuñj 26 which gives a hint that this word refers to only one tree located in the middle of hell: <foreign>ikaṅ havan katvan tejānya sake ṅke, ya tika riṅ ayah bhūmipatāna ṅaranya, kunaṅ ikaṅ katvan āṅuṅgul riṅ tṅah ya tika kalpa kaṇḍaga ika, kunaṅ ikāṅ atpi kidul aṅadəg ahirəṅ agəṅ katvan, yeka parvvasaṅgata ṅaranya, gunuṅ vsi matakəp lavan rvavaṅnya.</foreign> In MdS, <foreign>kandaga</foreign> means a small box for valuables, a jewelry box; (C.) a kind of basket of woven leaves (with a lid). ASD translate <foreign>kalapa kandaga</foreign> as ‘<foreign>bersenjatakan pedang</foreign>’ (has a sword as weapon). Cf. the term <foreign>kayu curiga</foreign> ‘knife-tree’ in ms. K of Kuñj (l. 2624, ed. van der Molen 1983). See Bernet Kempers (1981: 203; fig. 5 and 6) on the depiction of hell in the reliefs of Candi Jago.</note> One hundred thousand men are struck [by its swords] there. In the south is the Stone Mountain. One hundred thousand evil men are suffering there together. In the west are the Fire-Headed ghosts.<note>Cf. Kuñj 14 hana ta yakṣāgnimukha, apiy ataṅān asuku. ya tika maṅusī ikaṅ pāpa “There are Five-Headed ghosts, (i.e.), fire with hands and feet. They attack the sinners”.</note> Humans cannot fathom how much suffering is there. In the north, there are one hundred people suffering together there, like grass-hoppers on a skewer. In the middle is the crow of the Patana,<note>SC 801–805 contains descriptions of hell-dwelling animals, such as the crow and the dog. In SC we encounter the <foreign>santana</foreign> crow, described as having blade wings (<foreign>maṅhəlar curiga</foreign>): <foreign>əntasniya sakeṅ kavah, diparabkən ka asu di pañcasora, asu maṅtəndas iyaksa, gagak maṅhəlar curiga, təhərna mava ruji bəsi, dəṅ na gagak santana</foreign> “After being lifted up from the cauldron, he is given as food to the Five-Sounded dogs, dogs with <foreign>yakṣa</foreign>s as their head, the crow with blade wings, then they take the iron fencing, together with the crow [called] Santana”. The word <foreign>santana</foreign> is probably none other than <foreign>patana </foreign>(see fn. 339).  This passage runs parallel with Kuñj 13: <foreign>hana ta pākṣi yakṣa si ṣantana ṅaranya, gagak </foreign>(all mss. AHK; <foreign>gālak </foreign>Kern) <foreign>mahəlar curigā, kaṇḍaga pinakākukunya, kukunya bajra </foreign>(H and K;<foreign> kuku mānval bajra </foreign>A and Kern)<foreign> mahəlar kaṇḍaga, mavulu </foreign>(H;<foreign> mamava hru </foreign>K; <foreign>mavaruṅ </foreign>A and Kern) <foreign>tajī</foreign> “There are the ghost-birds called Santana, the crows with blade wings, having swords as their nails, their nails are made of iron, having blades as wings, having spikes as feathers”. In <foreign>Uttarakāṇḍa</foreign> 32, the crow is Yama’s incarnation when he faces Rāvaṇa. The crow mentioned together with the dog, both representing sinners, is also found in SHH 5.12: <foreign>hilaṅa ikaṅ bāyu śabda hədap sakeṅ śārīranya məne, ndatan mulya pih asiṅ vvaṅ magaməl, tinimpalakən raśmi, pinarəbutakən deniṅ gagak mvaṅ asu iku </foreign>“When the breath, the speech, and the mind are now gone from their body, whatever people do is worthless. The beauty (of the body) is turned off, as the crow and the dog fight over it”.</note> with the Dog ghosts. Thousands of evil people are suffering there. That is the misery of those called <foreign>marende</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.05"><foreign>Mariris</foreign> means defiled, disgusting like excrement, defiled like a reeking carcass. Such is the conduct of people who are kleptomaniac, who seize indiscriminately, or even take indiscriminately, without asking, stealing, plundering, deceiving, pilfering — all kinds of lying<note>The word <foreign>curavəda</foreign> is clearly derived from Skt. <foreign>curavāda</foreign> (= OJ) ‘speaking untruths’.</note> to good persons. When he dies, his soul<note>I take -<foreign>na</foreign> in <foreign>atmana </foreign>as a possessive suffix, even though the word <foreign>atmana</foreign> as a synonym of <foreign>atma</foreign> is attested. Cf. Kuñj 2306 (van der Molen 1983: 229) <foreign>piraṅ kee hatmana riṅ sarira, limma kvehnya, mapa lvirnya</foreign> “How many numbers are the soul in the body? Its number is five. What is the form”?</note> will suffer, for one thousand [and] one hundred years afflicted by the curse of the gods. That is why<note>The conjunction <foreign>mana </foreign>is suspicious here, and should possibly be emended to <foreign>atmana</foreign>. If this is the correct emendation, then the translation would be ‘his soul is far from rebirth’.</note> birth as a human is not in sight. As for what he becomes: <foreign>koter</foreign>,<note>Unidentified animal. In SC 825–830, we read <foreign>oter</foreign> instead of <foreign>koter</foreign>: <foreign>təmah saṅ hyaṅ atma papa, jadi oter jadi jaṅgel, jambəloṅ limus sakərət, kararamu hapur muṅkal, satva kinaririsan, satva kinavədian</foreign> ‘the consequence of the sinful soul, [is that] it becomes<foreign> oter</foreign> and <foreign>jaṅgel</foreign>, <foreign>jambəloṅ </foreign>and leatherleaf slug, <foreign>kararamu </foreign>and <foreign>hapur muṅkal</foreign>, despised [and] disgusting animals’. Is it equivalent to OJ <foreign>kulir</foreign>? Cf. also MdJ <foreign>bolèr</foreign> ‘small fruit worm’.</note> <foreign>jaṅgel</foreign>,<note>Unidentified animal. In MdS, <foreign>jaṅgel</foreign> means ‘corn cob’, but here probably refers to a kind of worm or leech whose appearance is resembled corn cob?</note> crop-worm,<note>The species <foreign>hiləd tahun</foreign> is likely to refer to a kind of caterpillar. Kompas 30 May 2011 reported a high population of caterpillars in Gunung Kidul, one of the species being called <foreign>ulat tahun</foreign> (see <ref target="https://amp.kompas.com/ekonomi/read/2011/05/30/0533052/policy.html">https://amp.kompas.com/ekonomi/read/2011/05/30/0533052/policy.html</ref>). Cf. OJ <foreign>ulər tahun</foreign>. See SKK 1.2 where <foreign>tahun </foreign>means crop. Is it related to Mal. <foreign>ulat daun</foreign>?</note> horse-fly,<note>The word <foreign>pitək</foreign> ‘horse-fly, gadfly, warble-fly’, as in MdS. Cf. Mal. <foreign>pikat</foreign>, OJ <foreign>caṭak</foreign>.</note> <foreign>titiṅgi</foreign>,<note>In MdS, <foreign>titiṅgi</foreign> refers to a kind of millipede. Cf. Mal. <foreign>kaki seribu.</foreign></note> <foreign>jambəloṅ</foreign>,<note>The word <foreign>jambəloṅ </foreign>is not found in MdS, but is probably equivalent with MdS <foreign>katélong</foreign> (a kind of big centipede). Tien Wartini <foreign>et al</foreign>. 2011 interpret <foreign>jambəloṅ</foreign> as ‘lintah kerbau, lintah besar dan hitam yang tempat hidupnya di tanah lembab’. Cf. MdJ <foreign>təmbalong </foreign>‘a certain large centipede’ (Horne 1974, s.v.)<foreign>. </foreign></note> leatherleaf slug,<note>On <foreign>limus sakərət</foreign>, see my comment on the OJ word <foreign>hiris pvah</foreign> in <ref target="#siksaguru_08.04">SiGu 8.4</ref>.</note> <foreign>mear</foreign>,<note><foreign>mear</foreign> is not recorded in MdS, but I googled it and found that in Bogor people still recognize it as a kind of leech. This word is also known as the toponym of <foreign>kampung</foreign> in Jasinga, Bogor.</note> <foreign>pacet </foreign>(blood sucking haemadipsa),<note><foreign>pacet</foreign> = Mal. (also <foreign>pacat</foreign>). Cf. OJ and MdJ <foreign>pacət</foreign> ‘kind of leech’ (<foreign>Haemadipsa teylandica</foreign>).</note> leech, <foreign>ləhəṅ</foreign>, <foreign>gərəṅ</foreign><note>Both <foreign>ləhəṅ</foreign> and <foreign>gərəṅ</foreign> are unidentified animals.</note> — everything that is despised by people in general, that is what is called <foreign>mariris</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_13.06">Disgrace (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>) means unwilling to be sincere, unwilling to truthful, unwilling to be proper, unwilling to be frank, unwilling to be polite. If his anxiety (?, <foreign>harən</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>harən</foreign> is not found in dictionaries, and my translation ‘anxiety’ is based on the tentative assumption of a connection with MdS <foreign>hara-haraeun</foreign> ‘present difficulties, raise objections, unfavorable (of a place or time where all kinds of things are lacking, a place difficult to pass, a bad and dangerous road, etc.)’. Hardjadibrata relates <foreign>hara-haraeun</foreign> to MdS <foreign>ara</foreign>, <foreign>aru-ara</foreign> and <foreign>uru-ara</foreign> ‘commotion, stir, disquiet, unrest, uproar’. In KS 6.11–26 we read<foreign> sakti atma ləpas, ləñəpniṅ rupa bayu, revaca saṅ harən saṅ harəsa, </foreign>“Strongly, the soul has vanished, the dissolution of the breath’s form, the anxiety and lust are <foreign>revaca </foreign>(?)”.</note> passion, love [or] astonishment is deceitful, [then] when he dies, his soul will meet with suffering, [i.e] a wobbly bridge, a slanting plank bridge, clashing stones. When they are made into being in the world, they become everything that is horrifying: rhinoceros, tiger, crocodile, great snake, everything that is horrifying. That is called disgrace (<foreign>viraṅ</foreign>).  So much for the four demons.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_14">
<p corresp="#skk_14.01">This is like a man who travels to China, spends a long time in China. [He] knows Chinese customs, Chinese habits, Chinese language, Chinese manners, Chinese etiquette. [He] meets with three [levels] of language, [namely] low, middle, and high. [He] knows all<note>In this sentence, <foreign>pahi </foreign>cannot have a meaning ‘all’ referring to the subject like we have in other contexts, but serving as an adverb. Cf, Mal. <foreign>serba tahu</foreign>. Another adverbial meaning is attested in RR 1480–1481 <foreign>padoyoṅ pahi daékna, silih taña kahayaṅna</foreign> “matching each other with equal strength, asking each other what they wanted”.</note> about the speech of the king, the elder, and the hermit; is able to direct the breath, the speech, and the mind. That is the reason why [he] knows about the consciousness (<foreign>gəiṅ</foreign>), the higher consciousness (<foreign>upagəiṅ</foreign>), the ultimate consciousness (<foreign>parigəiṅ</foreign>). They are called the three forms of consciousness.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.02">Consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to taste, to drink, [and] being able to have pleasure; that is called consciousness. What is called higher consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to dress, able to wear clothes, able to wear a lower garment, able to wear festive attire; that is called higher consciousness. What is called ultimate consciousness is [a person endowed with it] being able to instruct, able to command, because his speech is sweet [and] fragrant,<note>The author uses the combination <foreign>arum mavaṅi</foreign> instead of <foreign>ruum avaṅi</foreign>, reflecting a Javanese code switching; cf. Kuñj 335–336 (ms H in van der Molen edition): <foreign>śammida dupa</foreign> (em. <foreign>śammi dadupa</foreign> ed.) <foreign>mrabukk arum pavaṅi</foreign>. In Old Sundanese corpus, see KaPañ 719 <foreign>ruum buṅbuṅ gandavaṅi</foreign>, SA 824 <foreign>ruum miṅiṅ ganda vaṅi</foreign>, SC 316 <foreign>ruum səṅit rumavaṅi. </foreign>The word <foreign>rumavaṅi</foreign> in SC 316 seems to be a brief variant of <foreign>ruum avaṅi</foreign>.</note> such that the one who is commanded does not become angry, because he is touched by the impact<note>I choose the reading B <foreign>bənaṅna</foreign> instead of <foreign>bənaṅ</foreign> by comparing this passage with SKK 8.3 <foreign>ku bənaṅna ilik di guna sakalih</foreign>. Cf. <foreign>bənaṅna ñaho</foreign> in SKK 18.4.</note> of applying expressions with a deeper meaning (<foreign>siloka</foreign>).<note>The expression of <foreign>labuh siloka</foreign> is attested in SC 310 <foreign>misi na labuh siloka</foreign> ‘having endowed (<foreign>misi</foreign>) with suitable words’. In MdS, <foreign>labuh</foreign> means ‘fall (because of slipping, bumping against st., etc.); <foreign>ngalabuhkeun</foreign> let so. fall (on his face); balabuh be (lie, ride) at anchor’. Cf. OJ <foreign>alabuh</foreign> ‘to cast os. down (on or into st.) and seek one’s death’. I presume that <foreign>milabuh siloka</foreign> is similar in meaning to the expression <foreign>manibakən sastra</foreign> ‘to execute the writing’, from <foreign>tiba </foreign>‘to fall’.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.03">If his words (<foreign>basana</foreign>)<note>The word <foreign>basana</foreign> is at first sight ambiguous. In MdS, <foreign>basa</foreign> can have two meanings: first, it can be a conjunction ‘when, at the time of’; second, it can be a noun, ‘language, word’. In OS, the first meaning is more common (cf. SKK 12.2). But here the word <foreign>basana</foreign> appears between the particle <foreign>ma</foreign> and the punctuation mark, followed by a list of vocative words to the relatives, indicating that the meaning intended by the author must have been ‘his words’.</note> are [addressed] to a youngster, [he addresses him or her as] ‘boy’ (<foreign>utun</foreign>),<note>In MdS <foreign>utun</foreign> means ‘(a friendly term of address for boys and young men) boys, lads; utun inji (name of an unborn foetus) boy-girl; cf. <foreign>inji</foreign>’. In OS, most occurrences are vocative, although the use as common noun also appears in the combination with <foreign>si</foreign> (<foreign>si utun</foreign> ‘the child’).</note> ‘girl’ (<foreign>eten</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>eten</foreign> is exclusively used as a vocative in the OS corpus at my disposal. It is attested in KaPaṅ <foreign>passim</foreign>, used by Jayakeling to address his wife, and by Batara Guru to his daughter Sri in KaKat. </note> ‘baby’ (<foreign>orok</foreign>), ‘my child’, ‘my little sibling’. [If they are addressed] to an elder, [he addresses him or her as] ‘my elder brother’,<note>The word <foreign>lañcək</foreign> ‘elder brother’ is not necessarily gender-specific, but it tends to be used for male addressees. Cf. MdS <foreign>pun lanceuk</foreign> ‘my husband’ (a wife when addressing her husband). The presence of <foreign>əcə</foreign> in the list also suggests that the author intended to list both a term for a male and for a female elder sibling.</note> ‘my elder nephew or niece’, ‘my elder sister’, ‘my senior’, and ‘my grandfather’. His exclamations are:<note>Cf. <foreign>vastu</foreign> in OJ (OJED s.v. <foreign>vastu</foreign> 2) ‘to declare that something will or must certainly happen, to lay down (also by means of a blessing or curse), to settle (give a pronouncement with <foreign>vastu</foreign>)’; also <foreign>pamastu</foreign> = <foreign>paṅastu</foreign> (from <foreign>vastu</foreign>?) KHWj 2.116b: <foreign>ḍuh pukulun dumadak pamastu paduka saṅ mahamuni</foreign>. I interpret <foreign>paṅvastu</foreign> as ‘salutation, blessing’ in the light of the meaning of <foreign>pangésto</foreign> or <foreign>pangéstu</foreign> in MdS, namely ‘blessing, exclamation of blessing, opening term; (esp. used as a polite term when replying if asked how he, the family is’.</note> are ‘be well!’ (<foreign>sumaṅər</foreign>), ‘what a pity!’ (<foreign>tətəiṅ amat</foreign>). As numerous are the ten pacifying acts,<note>The <foreign>dasa-pasanta</foreign> in this passage seems to be a localization case from the concept <foreign>daśa-pāramitā</foreign> found in SiGu 11. For the notion of <foreign>dasa-pasanta</foreign> influenced by Buddhist teachings, see Chapter 10, §Borrowing Buddhist Doctrines.</note> namely: being virtuous,<note>The translation of <foreign>guna</foreign> as ‘virtuous’ is based on the explanation in <ref target="#smg_22.01">SMG 22.1</ref> <foreign>ini ma iña hayu na təmən, diṅaranan saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila, dasa ta ma sapuluh, sila ta ma ṅaranna guna </foreign>“As for this one, it is the essence of goodness, called the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>). <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten, <foreign>sila </foreign>means virtuous”<foreign>.</foreign></note> reverent (<foreign>nama</foreign>),<note>In OJ and OS, the word <foreign>nama</foreign> in the meaning ‘salutation, reverential’ only occurs in invocations. The base form in Skt. is <foreign>namas</foreign>, probably the OJ and OS derivation <foreign>nama</foreign> from <foreign>namas</foreign> is similar to OJ <foreign>tapa </foreign>&lt; Skt. <foreign>tapas</foreign>.</note> sympathetic,<note>In MdS, we find <foreign>hook</foreign> only in the suffixed form <foreign>hookeun</foreign> ‘stand looking dumbfounded/ disconcerted’. The context suggests a meaning like ‘sympathy’ or ‘enthusiasm’. No other occurrence is found in OS texts.</note> forgiving,<note>On the meaning of <foreign>pesok</foreign>, See my comment on this word in  <ref target="#smg_20.05">SMG 20.5</ref>.</note> loving, compassionate, generous,<note>See my comment on the word <foreign>mukpruk</foreign> in <ref target="#smg_20.05">SMG 20.5</ref>. For the /k/ ~ /ø/ variation, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> gentle,<note>In MdS, <foreign>ulas</foreign> means  ‘to polish st., coat st., spread st. (e.g. with paint, whitewash, ointment, salve, oil, etc., also in conjunction with moistening of materials with water in the traditional way of weaving). I suggest that it should be related to MdS and Mal. <foreign>elus </foreign>‘handle so. tactfully, talk to s.o. quietly, softly, sooth, calm, appease s.o.’.</note> tranquil, ingratiating. That is why someone who is given an order is happy [and] joyful, bright [and] shining. That is called the ultimate consciousness.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.04">These are the metaphors for it:<note>Based on the context, this metaphor seems to refer to <foreign>parigəiṅ</foreign>.</note> gold, silver, jewel, diamond. They are called the four holy courtesies. This is its meaning: gold means the speech which is right, accurate, clear, [applying] the formula of five syllables.<note>The occurrence in this context of the word <foreign>pañcaksara</foreign>, designating the Skt. phrase <foreign>namaś śivāya</foreign>, or ‘Homage to Śiva!’<foreign>,</foreign> seems to imply that it was in common use as a polite greeting to interlocutors. See examples of salutations <foreign>nama sivaya </foreign>in Chapter 10, §God among gods.</note> Silver means the mind which is accomplished, proper, good. Jewel means his consciousness is bright [and] shining, wide [and] broad.<note>The occurrence of <foreign>loganda</foreign> in this context is comparable to Mal. compounds with similar imitative reduplication:  <foreign>porak-poranda, karut-marut</foreign>. See Sneddon 2010: 26.</note> Diamond means cheerfully laughing,<note>On the word <foreign>caṅciṅ</foreign>, see my comment on <ref target="#smg_21.02"/>; cf. SKK 8.1.</note> visibly smiling,<note>The word <foreign>imuc</foreign> corresponds to MdS <foreign>imut</foreign> ‘smile’. See Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> pleasant of heart. They are called the four courtesies.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_14.05">They are the people who originate from the pure ones among lands. The pure ones among lands are the offering place, the place of rolled offerings (? <foreign>pabuntəlan</foreign>),<note>The base word of <foreign>pabuntəlan</foreign>, viz. <foreign>buntəl</foreign>, means ‘to wrap, to roll’ in MdS. Cf. OJ <foreign>vuntəl</foreign>, <foreign>avuntəlan</foreign> ‘with a wrapping of..., with… intertwined’ attested in KY 31.2: <foreign>dyah maṅken pasavit gaḍuṅ rari gəluṅta linaraṅan avuntəlan səkar </foreign>where Soewito Santoso translates it as ‘decorated’: “Milady, now you must wear a necklace of  <foreign>gadung </foreign>flowers and your hair knot may not be decorated with flowers anymore”. Seeing the relation of <foreign>vuntəl</foreign> with flowers, it may be that <foreign>pabuntəlan</foreign> refers to a place where rolled objects — probably leaves with flowers  like we find in Bali nowadays — are offered. Pabuntelan is also recorded as a toponym in south Bandung (Lasmiati 2016: 389).</note> the worship place, the sturdy house (? <foreign>imah manəh</foreign>),<note>The term <foreign>imah manəh</foreign> only occurs in this text and in <foreign>Sri Ajñana</foreign>. In the latter, <foreign>imah manəh</foreign> occurs five times, referring to the abode of the Five Gods (<foreign>pañca-devata</foreign>), located in the upper world. Could it be referring to<foreign>caṇḍi</foreign>-type shrines?</note> the sanctuary, the temple tower, the <foreign>liṅga</foreign>, the statue,<note>The word <foreign>liṅgir</foreign> is a variant of <foreign>liṅir</foreign> ‘carved or chiseled image’ (OJED, s.v.). Cf. <foreign>haṅər</foreign> = <foreign>aṅgər</foreign>.</note> the <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> stone (<foreign>batu gaṅsa</foreign>),<note>Zoetmulder defines <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> as ‘bell-metal’ (OJED, s.v.). He mentions its occurrence in SD 29.8: <foreign>kəṇḍaṅ goṅ gaṅsa gubar asahuran </foreign>“<foreign>kendang</foreign> drum, <foreign>gong</foreign>, <foreign>gangsa</foreign>, and small gong (<foreign>gubar</foreign>) are sounding alternately”, in which <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> clearly refers to a music instrument, but it is unclear whether it is distinct from <foreign>goṅ</foreign>, or is a particular kind of <foreign>goṅ</foreign>. SC 1110–1114 also mentions <foreign>batu gaṅsa</foreign> among objects in a shrine: <foreign>aṅgəs ma eta sakitu,  ditəndən liṅga liṅgir, candi baṅ candi putih, candi hejo candi kuniṅ, harəca dəṅ batu gaṅsa</foreign> “After [mentioning] all of that, <foreign>lingga</foreign> and statue are placed [in] the red and white sanctuaries, green and yellow sanctuaries, [along with] sculptures and the <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> stones”. Cf. BM 98–99 <foreign>iṅ na gooṅ braṅ na gaṅsa, seah na gǝndaṅ sarunay</foreign> which Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw translate as “the gongs droned, the cymbals sounded, the drums and the shawms were played”. West (2021) prefers to translates <foreign>gaṅsa</foreign> as ‘flat gong’. In MdS, <foreign>gangsa</foreign> means ‘bronze’ (for basins, gongs, etc.). In MdJ, it means ‘1 classical Javanese musical instrument or ensemble of instruments (kr for gamelan). 2 bronze. 3 gamelan gong’. The term <foreign>batu gaṅsa</foreign> is perhaps equivalent to what is called <foreign>batu goong</foreign> in the Sundanese-speaking area nowadays. Examples of this kind of stone, scattered around a <foreign>lingga</foreign>, are found at Situs Citaman, Pulosari, Banten, known as Batu Goong.</note> land with statues, where human figures are created [and] sweeping [is performed]. So many are all lands which are maintained, waters that are strained [and] purified. It is indeed a good person, a kind person. He is an accomplished person. The one who is considered to originate from the pure ones among lands is aware of the holy precepts, heeding the advice of mother, father, grandfather and great-grandfather, knowing the teachings of the great scholars, upholding the words of the accomplished ones.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_15">
<p corresp="#skk_15.01">This is the account of the ancient ones who instated the holy instructions of the accomplished ones: the deified ancestor Déwaraja, the deified ancestor Rawung Langit, the deified ancestor at Medang, the deified ancestor at Menir.<note>These figures occur (with some variant readings) in the <foreign>Carita Parahyaṅan</foreign> among the ultimate ancestors of Sundanese kings. According to this chronicle, Rahyangta Déwaraja and Rahyangta ri Medang refer to one figure, Kandiawan. Déwaraja is the name he bore before he became an ascetic, while Rahyangta ri Medang is the name he took after becoming a <foreign>rajarəsi</foreign>. In the same narrative, Rawung Langit is the fourth of the five sons of Kandiawan, who ruled as king before Mandimiñak. The last figure, who also seems to be the most important, is Rahyangta ri Mənir, the other name of Wreti Kandayun, the incarnation of the fifth <foreign>kusika</foreign>, Patañjala. He is attributed as the creator of Purbatisti and Purbajati, the two main scriptures of the ascetic group (<foreign>karəsian</foreign>).</note> They are called the four accomplished ones. That is why in the present, men who are aware of the holy supreme <foreign>dharma</foreign>, knowledgeable about the secret teachings of men, they are called esoteric men.<note>In OJtexts, <foreign>janmarahasya</foreign> means ‘the secret of life’, but here it seems to be used of menn who have secret knowledge, so we are dealing with a local reinterpretation of the term. For an occurrence of <foreign>janmarahasya</foreign> in the OJ corpus, see KuñjDhK 21.1 <foreign>yekin janmarahasya mūlya pavarahkv iri kita pituhun, ndah yatneriya paṅrəṅə̄ varavarahku tan imanimanən </foreign>“This is the sublime secret of human life — take to heart these teachings of mine to you, listen attentively to my lessons and do not treat them lightly”.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_15.02">If they die, their soul will find a beautiful heaven, finding daytime that does not turn into night, joy that does not turn into sorrow, heaven that does not turn into into [the hell of] sinners, pleasure that does not turn into pain, good that does not turn into into bad, fortunate that does not turn into unfortunate, subtle that does not turn into gross, being gone that does not turn into being present, ancestors that do not turn into gods. That is what is called the supreme liberation.<note>The word <foreign>ləñəp</foreign> is a synonym of <foreign>mokta</foreign>. Cf. <ref target="#smg_33.03">SMG 33.3</ref> i<foreign>ni kaləpasənana ṅaranya, saṅ hyaṅ nirmala, ya catur-mokta ṅaranya, ləpas, ləñəp, mokta, hilaṅ, ya ta catur-mokta ṅaranya </foreign>“This is called the release, the holy purity. It is called the four final liberations (<foreign>catur-mokta</foreign>): release, disappearance, vanishing, dissolution. That is called the four final liberations”. Cf. also Mal. <foreign>lenyap</foreign> ‘diminished’.</note></p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_16">
<p corresp="#skk_16.01">Likewise are the people in the present.<note>Based on the context, what is meant by ‘people in the present’ here refers to deified ancestors mentioned in 15.1.</note> Compare us taking a bath, the choices of the water to be touched by us are only two: the one which is turbid and the one which is clear. Likewise are the behaviors of people, two (types) being put into practice: the bad and the good. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated badly is that bad behavior of theirs. Likewise are the people: the cause of their being treated well is that good behavior of theirs. That is why people are bad by their behavior, why they are good by their behavior.<note>Cf. the similar expression in <ref target="#siksaguru_06.01">SiGu 6.1</ref> <foreign>ndya ya nihan saṅ hyaṅ jagat upadrava ṅaranya, ndya ya, nihan, hala tuməmu halanya, hayu tuməmu hayunya, vilut tuməmu vilutnya, bənər tumemu bənərnya, sukha tuməmu sukhanya, duhkha tuməmu duhkhanya. </foreign>This expression alludes to the notion of <foreign>karma</foreign>. See Chapter 10, §Siksa Kurung.</note></p>
<p corresp="#skk_16.02">Water is like that, insofar as the choices of it are said to be two. Water that is refreshing and clear is the holy supreme <foreign>dharma</foreign>, that is what is practiced by the great scholars. Water that is haunted and turbid is the emotional conduct (<foreign>rasa-carita</foreign>), which is practiced by all the <foreign>viku</foreign>s for whom the <foreign>nec plus ultra</foreign> is worldly.<note>The mss. AB spell <foreign>paramarata </foreign>instead of <foreign>paramarta</foreign> (Skt./OJ <foreign>paramārtha</foreign>). This is common in the OS corpus: cf. RD 45 <foreign>tuturnya paramarata </foreign>“His consciousness is prominent”, PR 19r4 <foreign>ləvih balik alit sarira sunya-paramarata </foreign>“superior while returning to the subtle element, the body whose <foreign>nec plus ultra</foreign> is the void”<foreign>. </foreign>I take <foreign>paramarta</foreign> with <foreign>lokika </foreign>as compound, <foreign>lokika-paramarta</foreign>. It is an attribute to the <foreign>viku</foreign>, so that <foreign>viku lokika-paramarta </foreign>means ‘the <foreign>viku</foreign>s for whom the <foreign>nec plus ultra</foreign> is worldly’.</note> That is why it (i.e., water) is comparable to consciousness<note>It is noteworthy that ms. A consistently spells <foreign>centana</foreign> and <foreign>acentana</foreign>. These spelling variants are also attested in ms. A of the <foreign>Kuñjarakarṇa</foreign> (also of West Javanese provenance): Kuñj 808 <foreign>centanātma</foreign>;  1805 <foreign>centāna</foreign> (ed. van der Molen 1983).</note> as well as unconsciousness. Consciousness is aware and mindful of memories without turning into forgetfulness. It is the root of a favorable rebirth, the cause of a prosperous earth.<note>See my comment on a similar expression <foreign>ṅrətakən bumi</foreign> in SKK 12.2.</note> Unconsciousness is forgetfulness [and] confusion, not endowed with memory. It is the cause of destruction, the starting point of the Kali era, the base of deviation, the root of falsehood.<note>In the Old Sundanese context, the word <foreign>liñok</foreign> is only found once in this text and nowhere else. Even in OJ, this word only appears in later texts such as <foreign>Koravāśrama, Bhīma Svarga</foreign>, and <foreign>Pararaton</foreign>.</note> It is the cause of people going to hell. That should not be taken as truth by those who wish to be sincere.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_17">
<p corresp="#skk_17.01">These are the words of the holy man, when he maintains his possessions.<note>The word <foreign>drəbya</foreign> ‘possession’ in this context refers to the internal possessions of the holy man, i.e., the macrocosmic and microcosmic world (<foreign>bhuvana lavan śārīra</foreign>), and the three instruments (<foreign>bāyu</foreign>, <foreign>śabda</foreign>, <foreign>hədap</foreign>). Cf. SHH 18.1 <foreign>sira ta sinaṅguh saṅ hyaṅ pramāṇa, makadrabya bhuvana lavan sarva śārīra, ṅuniveh bāyu śabda hədap </foreign>“He is considered as The Authority, having the world and body as possessions, also the breath, the speech, [and] the mind”. It seems that the author intends to associate <foreign>bāyu</foreign>, <foreign>śabda, hədap</foreign> to the three rulers. On <foreign>mahayu</foreign> as a transitive verb, cf. <foreign>mahayu na kadatvan</foreign> ‘to beautify the palace’ in the inscription Kawali 1a (Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 184–185).</note> These are the three threads in the world.<note>On the concept of <foreign>tri-tantu</foreign>, see Chapter 10.</note> Our (<foreign>kita</foreign>)<note>The pronoun <foreign>kita</foreign> only appears here in the whole SKK. See Chapter 3, §Pronoun.</note> breath is the ruler, our speech is the elders, our mind is the hermits. Those are the three threads in the world, which are considered as the support of the world.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.02">These are the group of three in the distant [world]:<note>Cf. <foreign>bumi lamba </foreign>in SKK 1.3 and 1.4.</note> Wisnu is considered as king, Brahma is considered as elder, Iswara is considered a hermit. It is the reason why the three threads are the support of the world, [while] the group of three are the life of the world. They are considered as the three threads for all people. [We] should hold [them] up, hold [them] fast until they are straight, true, evident, [and] present.<note>The word <foreign>vartamanah</foreign> is from Skt. <foreign>vartamāna</foreign> ‘present, existing; the present, in the present time’. On unetymological -<foreign>h</foreign> and -<foreign>k</foreign>, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> The reason why the world is prosperous, why the earth is affluent, is because the actions of people are well maintained.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_17.03">Likewise, the scholars who are firm in their scholarship will prosper; the monk who are firm in their monkhood prosper; the <foreign>maṅuyu</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>maṅuyu</foreign>-ship will prosper; the <foreign>palikən</foreign><note>The word <foreign>palikən</foreign> is not recorded in dictionaries. It seems implausible to emend it to <foreign>palika</foreign> ‘diver’ (found in SKK 7.3)  since it is mentioned along with the list of people related to religious institutions. Might there be any connection with the Skt. term <foreign>kāpālika</foreign>? See OJED <foreign>kapālikabrata</foreign> ‘of the observance of the Kapālikas’ (the correct spellings would have been <foreign>kāpālika</foreign>- and Kāpālikas).</note> who are firm in their <foreign>palikən</foreign>-ship will be prosper; the monks who are firm in their monkhood will be prosper; the wandering ascetics (<foreign>aməṅ</foreign>)<note>My interpretation of <foreign>aməṅ</foreign> as wandering ascetics is based on Bujaṅga Manik, the protagonist of the eponymous text. Another name for the protagonist is <foreign>aməṅ layaran</foreign>, attributed when the ascetic stepped off a boat, anchored in Kalapa during his first return from pilgrims as a hermit in eastern Java.</note> who are firm in their wanderership will be prosper; the <foreign>vasi</foreign>s<note>On the interpretation of the term <foreign>vaśi</foreign>, see Appendix 1.</note> who are firm in their <foreign>vasi</foreign>-ship will be prosper; the nuns (<foreign>əbon</foreign>)<note>For an explanation of the term <foreign>əbon</foreign>, see Chapter 11.</note> who are firm in their nunship will be prosper; the renouncers (<foreign>tiagi</foreign>) who are firm in their renunciation will be successful; even more so the aspirants (<foreign>valaka</foreign>) who are firm in their aspirantship<foreign>i</foreign> will be successful; the peasants who are firm in their peasantship will be successful; the thieves (<foreign>əvah</foreign>)<note>My translation assumes that<foreign>əvah</foreign> is equivalent to MdS <foreign>euwah-euwah</foreign> ‘scoundrel, thief, robber; <foreign>manuk euwah-euwah</foreign> (C.) bird of prey’. Without proposing any gloss, OJED records <foreign>aṅəvah</foreign> as attested in Sum 10.9 <foreign>solah bhāvanirāmaṅun sih aṅəvah bapa-bapa juga denirāṅucap</foreign>. This has been translated as “Everything she did aroused affection, even if she could only sigh ( <foreign>aṅəvah</foreign>) and say ‘da, da’”. (ed. and trans. Worsley <foreign>et al</foreign>. 2013). Worsley <foreign>et al</foreign>. have taken the word <foreign>aṅəvah</foreign> to be a variant of <foreign>aṅəhah</foreign> (cf. OJED <foreign>uməhah</foreign>, s.v. <foreign>əhah</foreign>), meaning ‘to sigh, moan’). This OJ evidence does not seem to furnish a more promising angle of interpretation than MdS <foreign>euwah-euwah</foreign>.</note> firm in their thievery will be successful; the <foreign>gusti</foreign> firm in their <foreign>gusti</foreign>-ship will be successful; the minister firm in their ministership will be successful; the <foreign>masaṅ</foreign>s (?)<note>In the light of <ref target="#smg_19.02">SMG 19.2</ref> it is clear that <foreign>masaṅ</foreign> refers to an agricultural activity: <foreign>tani ma ṅaranya, paka dibuat ñadap masaṅ ñavara, cocooan, pəpəlakan, ya tani ṅaranya</foreign> “The farmer (<foreign>tani</foreign>) means: [they] are advanced (<foreign>paka</foreign>) in harvesting rice (<foreign>dibuat</foreign>), in tapping, in putting the yoke, in planting paddy (? <foreign>ñavara</foreign>), in taking care of the livestock, in planting the crops”.</note> who are firm in their <foreign>masaṅ</foreign>-ship will be successful; the <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>bujaṅga</foreign>-ship will be successful; the seamen who are firm in their seamanship will be successful; the <foreign>disi</foreign>s who are firm in their <foreign>disi</foreign>-ship will be successful; the elders who are firm in their eldership will be successful; the hermits who are firm in their hermitship will be successful; the rulers who are firm in their rulership will be successful. Formerly, the scholars, together with the divine king who were firm in making the world prosperous, so that the north, south, west [and] east — everything which is held by the earth [and] covered by the sky — prospered, all beings are alive, all of them.<note>I supply a comma after <foreign>maṅhurip</foreign>, since in OS this word is usually placed at the end of a clause or a sentence. Cf. FCP 26r3: <foreign>kita tuturkǝnǝn voṅ sakabeh, pinakadǝdǝlan bvana, pinakadasarniṅ prǝtivi, andǝlan sarva maṅhurip </foreign>“you are the person to be followed by all people, serving as the support of the world, as the foundation of the earth, the stabilizer of all living beings”. In this case, <foreign>maṅhurip </foreign>‘to live’ seems to be intransitive, and it corresponds to OJ <foreign>(m)ahurip</foreign> ‘to live, living’, not to <foreign>(m)aṅhurip </foreign>‘to give life, to grant life’.</note> </p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_18">
<p corresp="#skk_18.01">All kinds of beings means: plant beings, animal beings, human beings, individual beings (<foreign>si voṅ</foreign>), the substance of the individual (<foreign>vastu si voṅ</foreign>).<note>In this context, <foreign>vastu</foreign> probably means ‘substance’. Cf. the name of the Sundanese King, Wastu Kancana, literally meaning ‘the substance of gold’ or Lingga Wastu ‘whose essence is the <foreign>lingga</foreign>’ in CVG; cf. KaPaṅ 202 <foreign>ṅaranna vastu muliya</foreign> ‘its name is the priceless essence’.</note> That is the reason that all of them are called all beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.02">Plant beings are grass, trees, creepers, shrubs, all that is alive, fresh green, wild. They are called plant beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.03">Animal beings are all kinds of animals, big or small, on land or in the water. They are called animal beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.04">Human beings are human [only] in appearance, for their character is not good.<note>This sentence and the one that follows are syntactically problematic because of the conjunction kena, whereas we expect a conjunction that expresses the meaning ‘only’ or ‘but’, such as ṅan, heṅan, or OJ words like kunaṅ, kintu which mean ‘but’ and have the same consonants as kena despite being unattested in OS. Another way to fix the syntax of this sentence would be to skip ruana janma in the first sentence and rampes yuni and rampes baṅsa in the second sentence, so that kena would make sense in the expected meaning ‘because’. Cf. The similar syntax in SKK 8.2 and 8.3.</note> Individual beings (<foreign>si voṅ</foreign>) have good character, good family, for they do not know yet the holy <foreign>dharma</foreign>. The substance of the individual is the one who is firm in the impact of knowing, knowing the holy <foreign>dharma</foreign>, knowing the reality of holy knowledge. Those are called real human beings.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_18.05">May this be sought to be internalized by the inhabitants of the world,<note>We find several occurrences where the word <foreign>əsi</foreign> refers to the person. Cf. <foreign>aya ma nu ṅəsi dayəh ivə</foreign> ‘If one resides here’ in Kawali 6 (Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 188). Cf. <foreign>əsi imahna</foreign> ‘wife’ in SKK 12.6.</note> four in number. These are <foreign>kurija, mataja, bagaja, payuja</foreign>. <foreign>Kurija</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the mouth;<note>In the corresponding SMG passage (17.1), we have <foreign>urija </foreign>(or <foreign>vurija </foreign>in ms. B)<foreign>. </foreign>See my comment on <foreign>urija</foreign> in SMG 17.1.</note> <foreign>mataja</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the eyes; <foreign>bagaja </foreign>means all kinds which appear from the vulva; <foreign>payuja</foreign> means all kinds which appear from the anus. Those are called the holy four origins.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_19">
<p corresp="#skk_19.01">These are the 6 abilities of people in the world: to count (<foreign>ṅaṅka</foreign>), to chain yarns (<foreign>ñigi</foreign>), to tie (<foreign>ṅikət</foreign>), to touch (<foreign>ñigəṅ</foreign>), to bury (<foreign>ṅaruaṅ</foreign>), to heap up (<foreign>ṅaromboṅ</foreign>)<foreign>.</foreign><note>I interpret <foreign>ṅa</foreign>romboṅ based on one of the meanings of rombong in Malay, viz. ‘piling or heaping up’. This word is clearly connected to Mal. rombongan ‘a group’. Wilkinson also notes rombong as ‘Malacca basket; this is a basket of fine <foreign>pandan</foreign> matwork made usually in a set to nest one within the other; in shape round, triangular or polygonal; each basket having a separate overlapping cover. But the older <foreign>rombong</foreign> was of larger size and used for storing rice; <foreign>tĕrubong</foreign>. The small sizes (known also as <foreign>kĕmbal</foreign>) are used as work-baskets, sireh-baskets, etc.’.</note> To count means estimating; <foreign>ñigi</foreign><note>The verb <foreign>ñigi</foreign> is not recorded in dictionaries. However, Hardjadibrata notes its base <foreign>sigi</foreign> in the dialect register which means ‘end of warp yarns (hanging like a fringe)’.</note> means twisting;<note>Cf. OJ <foreign>unte</foreign>, <foreign>aṅunte, inunte, aṅunte-hunte</foreign> ‘to twist together, wind (cf. MdS <foreign>untay</foreign>)’. Cf. Mal. <foreign>untai</foreign> ‘a chain; numeral coefficient for necklace, etc.’.</note> <foreign>ṅikət</foreign> is various bindings; <foreign>ñigəṅ</foreign> is centering (? <foreign>məṅpəṅ</foreign>),<note>My interpretation of <foreign>məṅpəṅ</foreign> is based on the meaning of <foreign>pəṅpəṅ</foreign> in OJ ‘(subst.) being used at the right moment’. Cf. MdS <foreign>meungpeung</foreign> ‘while it is still ... (do st. that is not possible later, make the best while o. can)’. This word hence seems to be synonymous with OJ <foreign>səḍəṅ</foreign> ‘right time (not too early or too late), right moment, right measure (not too big or too small)’. I presume that <foreign>məṅpəṅ</foreign> is not only related to time, but also to measure or position. </note> splitting (<foreign>məlah</foreign>), using a wedge (<foreign>mañcir</foreign>),<note><foreign>mañcir</foreign> can be recognized from MdS <foreign>pañcir </foreign>‘wedge’, while <foreign>mancir</foreign> means ‘use a wedge (e.g. in splitting wood), drive a wedge in somewhere’.</note> halving, evaluating, calculating (<foreign>ṅaṅgit aṅka</foreign>),<note>My emendation of <foreign>ṅagitaka</foreign> to <foreign>ṅaṅgit aṅka</foreign> is based on the explanation of <foreign>ñigəṅ</foreign> which seems to be related to the activity of measuring and apportioning. In MdS, <foreign>ṅaṅgit</foreign> means ‘to compose/write st. (a story, speech, etc.) in beautiful form/in elegant style; write st. in verse form)’, while in OJ we only find its passive form <foreign>inaṅgit</foreign> meaning ‘to interlace, make into a garland’. It seems that the latter is the original meaning, while MdS reflects a secondary development. In OS, only the base form is attested in SC <foreign>aṅgit artati dəṅ prəlabi</foreign> ‘the composition of Artati and Prelabi’. The word <foreign>aṅka</foreign> also occurs in OS, e.g. in BM 1300 <foreign>bǝnaṅ aiṅ adu aṅka </foreign>which Noorduyn &amp; Teeuw translate as “what was the result of my weighing inten­tions”. I prefer to translate this phrase as “as the result of my calculation”. The compound  <foreign>ṅaṅgit aṅka</foreign> (litt. ‘to compose numbers’) seems to be synonymous with <foreign>adu aṅka </foreign>(litt. ‘to match numbers’), involving a verb and a noun. On this basis, I interpret <foreign>ṅaṅgit aṅka</foreign> as ‘to calculate.</note> measuring, equating; to bury means all kinds of digging; <foreign>ṅaromboṅ</foreign> is all kinds of spaces (<foreign>hələt-hələt</foreign>). Those are called the six abilities (<foreign>sad-guna</foreign>),<note>The number of skills (guna) listed here is six, which is reminiscent of the Skt. and OJ concept of ṣaḍguṇa. What is remarkable is that the six gunas here are entirely different from those we find in OJ sources, where the same terms refer primarily to the ability of the king: sandhi ‘peace’, vigraha ‘war’, āyana ‘marching’, āsana ‘sitting encamped’, dvaidhībhāva ‘dividing his force’, and saṅśraya 'seeking the protection of a more powerful king' (OJED, s.v. ṣaḍguṇa). The OJ tradition is in conformity with Sanskrit sources, such as Arthaśāstra 7.1.6–12 where the six are listed in prose (transl. Olivelle 2013), while they are listed in verse-form at MDhŚ 7.160: saṁdhiṁ ca vigrahaṁ caiva yānam āsanam eva ca | dvaidhībhāvaṁ saṁśrayaṁ ca ṣaḍguṇāṁś cintayet sadā “He should constantly think about the sixfold strategy: forging alliances, waging war, marching into battle, remaining stationary, pursuing a double stratagem, and seeking asylum” (ed. and transl. Olivelle 2005). In our text, the ṣaḍguṇa is recontextualized, being applied to servants.</note> so many are all the abilities of the people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.02">These are the 4 desires of the people: the wish to be pure (<foreign>yun suda</foreign>), the wish to be happy (<foreign>yun suka</foreign>), the wish to ascend (<foreign>yun muṅgah</foreign>), the wish to be liberated (<foreign>yun luput</foreign>). This is what it means: <foreign>yun suda</foreign> is desiring to be healthy (<foreign>purna</foreign>),<note>For the interpretation of <foreign>purna</foreign> as healthy, see OJED (s.v. <foreign>pūrṇa</foreign> 4) ‘restored to its former condition’. Cf. <ref target="#smg_19.02">SMG 19.2</ref> <foreign>purna ṅaranya, hantə dibogakahivaṅan, kativasan</foreign> “the one who is healthy (<foreign>purna</foreign>) means [the one who] does not have defects and diseases”.</note> refusing to suffer from any disease; <foreign>yun suka</foreign> is desiring to be rich, refusing to be deprived of possessions; <foreign>yun muṅgah </foreign>is desiring heaven, refusing to obtain [another rebirth in] the world; <foreign>yun luput</foreign> is desiring release, refusing to be taken by<note>Probably <foreign>kabava ku</foreign> should be emended to <foreign>kabava ka</foreign>, but <foreign>kabava ku</foreign> is very common, while <foreign>kabava ka</foreign> never occurs in the OS corpus. Cf. KaPani 440 <foreign>saṅkan jalma kalolita, kabava ku para yuga</foreign> “It is the reason why people are convulsed, [and] taken by various <foreign>yuga</foreign>s”. The term <foreign>yuga </foreign>here seems to have a negative connotation.</note> all heavens.<note>The noun <foreign>sorga</foreign> preceded by the word <foreign>para</foreign> occurs several times in the OS corpus, e.g. in SA 1083–1084 nu ṅəsi rahina sada, pañaraman para sorga “who lives in Rahina Sada, the lessons of all celestials”; PR 63v pahi mijil ti niskala, lain ti na para sorga “All appears from the unmanifest, but not from all kinds of heavens”. The meaning of <foreign>para sorga </foreign>seems to vary with the contexts, sometimes indicating celestial beings, sometimes a celestial place. I believe that the latter is intended in this context. This meaning also occurs in KaMah 1455–1457<foreign> eboh ta aiṅ magahan, eta tu na para sorga, kasorgaan voṅ sajagat</foreign> “Here I would like to give [you] advice, that is all kind of heavens, heavens for all people in the world”. Cf. <foreign>para nusa</foreign> ‘all kinds of countries’ in SKK 11.31. See Chapter 10, §Cosmology.</note> That is why so many are all the desires of the people.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_19.03">These are the 4 who bathe in the river, that is to say: male, female, effeminate man, unfeminine woman.<note>The expression <foreign>kədi malavadiṅ</foreign> is undoubtedly equivalent to OJ <foreign>kəḍi valavadi. </foreign>OJED glosses <foreign>kəḍi</foreign> as ‘emasculated, eunuch’ and <foreign>valavadi </foreign>as ‘a woman and not yet a woman. Prob. Skt <foreign>abala</foreign>, impotent, and <foreign>vadhri</foreign>, castrated’. On the OJ expression, Acri (2017: 229, fn. 47) notes as follows: “ <foreign>kəḍi valavadi </foreign>is used in an identical context in the <foreign>Vr̥haspatitattva</foreign>, the <foreign>Tattvajñāna</foreign> and the <foreign>Ślokāntara</foreign> (11–12.2). The last text employs the two words to explain the Sanskrit sequence <foreign>klīvo ’balo vadhriḥ</foreign>, as follows: <foreign>ṅaranya kəḍi, valavadi ṅaranya strī tan strī—‘klīva</foreign> (from <foreign>klība</foreign>, emasculated) means eunuch, <foreign>valavadi</foreign> means a woman and yet not a woman’. <foreign>Vr̥haspatitattva</foreign> 33.64 explains <foreign>kəḍi</foreign> and <foreign>valavadi</foreign> as <foreign>janmāntarapuruṣa</foreign>, which would translate as ‘transsexual’”.</note> That is the number. How many are the [types of] earmarked goods? [There are] 2, that is to say: ripe and raw, bad and good, small and big. How many are the flavors? [There are] 6, that is to say: salty (<foreign>lavaṇa</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>hot (<foreign>kaṭuka</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>bitter (<foreign>tikta</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>The spelling <foreign>kaduka</foreign> (for Skt. <foreign>kaṭuka</foreign>) is also found in the SiGu parallel. As for <foreign>tikta</foreign>, none of the witnesses of SiGu has a correct reading according to Sanskrit spelling. However, ms. C reads <foreign>tritta</foreign>, which could be interpreted as a small error for <foreign>trikta</foreign> (due to the resemblance of <foreign>aksara</foreign>s <foreign>ka</foreign> and <foreign>ta</foreign>). It should be noted that the word <foreign>trikta</foreign> was probably the common OS spelling for Skt. <foreign>tikta</foreign>. However, since it is intended as a gloss, I normalize both terms according to Sanskrit spelling in SKK and SiGu. On the spontaneous /r/, see Chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> sour (<foreign>amla</foreign>)<foreign>, </foreign>astringent (<foreign>kaṣāya</foreign>)<foreign>,</foreign><note>‘Astringent’ is the meaning of kaṣāya in Skt. and OJ, but the gloss shows that our author understood it differently. The currency of his interpretation in West Java is confirmed by <ref target="#siksaguru_02.05">SiGu 2.5</ref>.</note> sweet (<foreign>madhura</foreign>). <foreign>Lavaṇa</foreign> means salty, <foreign>kaṭuka</foreign> means spicy,<note>On <foreign>lada</foreign> as meaning ‘spicy’, see my comment on <ref target="#siksaguru_02.05">SiGu 2.5</ref>, where the word <foreign>lada</foreign> is used in the same meaning and in the same context, even though that text is formulated in OJ.</note> <foreign>tikta</foreign> means bitter, <foreign>amla</foreign> means sour, <foreign>kaṣāya</foreign> means savory, <foreign>madhura</foreign> means sweet. So many are all the things tasted by the people.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_20">
<p corresp="#skk_20.01">These are for us to take into possession ourselves, in order that they descend continuously (<foreign>pativah-tivah</foreign>) to children [and] grandchildren, to great grandchildren, to great-great grandchildren, to <foreign>muniṅ</foreign>, to<foreign> aṅgasantana</foreign>, to <foreign>pratisantana</foreign>;<note>Cf. the similar list in AG 1v <foreign>rakeyan darmasikṣa, siya ṅavarah anak, əñcu, umpi, cicip, muniṅ, aṅgasantana, kulasantana, prətisantana, aṅgasaṅ parigal vit vəkas kulakadaṅ sakabeh</foreign> “The venerable Darmasiksa instructs his children, grandchildren, great-grandchildren, great-great-grandchildren, <foreign>muniṅ, aṅgasantana, kulasantana, prətisantana</foreign>, <foreign>aṅgasaṅ parigal, </foreign>ultimate descendants, his entire family”<foreign>. </foreign>Cf. also OJ lists of descendants, mainly found in inscriptions, such as the Lintakan charter (841 Śaka) 3r20–21: <foreign>maṅkanā lavasanyan· tmuAkan· sāṁsāra, Avaknya rabinya Anaknya putunya puyutnya Aṅgasnya nāhan· liṁnirar paṅhanākan· sapatha matəhər· mamantiṅakan· hantlū manətək· gulūniṁ hayam</foreign>· “‘That is how long they will find suffering, themselves, their wives, their children, their grandchildren, their great-grandchildren, and their great-great-grandchildren’. Those were his words as he set the curse. Then he smashed the egg, slit the chicken’s throat” (draft ed. and transl. by Tyassanti Kusumo Dewanti, Wayan Jarrah Sastrawan &amp; Arlo Griffiths). ​​Gandhakuti (964 Śaka) 2v2–2v3 <foreign>katmva de santāna prātisantānira, Anak putu buyut· cicik muniṁ pituṁ Aṅśa siraji pādukā mpuṅku </foreign>“would be obtained by his offspring and offspring’s offspring: children, grandchildren, great-grandchildren, great-great-grandchildren, the seven [generations of] descendants of Aji Pāduka Mpuṅku” (draft ed. and transl. by Arlo Griffiths &amp; Eko Bastiawan). On the term <foreign>aṅśa</foreign>, see Griffiths 2020: 118–122.</note> all ultimate descendants (<foreign>putu vəkas</foreign>)<note>I interpret <foreign>putu vəkas</foreign> as compound. In OJ and MdS, <foreign>putu</foreign> means grandchild, while OJ <foreign>vəkas</foreign> means ‘1. the last of a stretch in time or space, end, limit, final aim; finally; 2. the highest point, top, height, what surpasses all others, paramount, non plus ultra, first, best or worst’. Cf. <foreign>vit vəkas</foreign> in OJ.</note> of [our] family — those which are suitable be given in inheritance<note>The word dipikakolotan, which I translate as 'to be given in inheritance’, is not found in the dictionary. The meaning is based on context. The circumfix dipi- -an is used to form verbs with a causative meaning. The basic form is kakolotan, from kolot ‘old, parents’, which probably means the same as kabuyutan ‘sacred’, also ‘heirloom’, which is derived from buyut ‘great-grandfather, elder’. Cf. <foreign>dipikabuyutan</foreign> in SMG 3.7.</note> as well as those which are not suitable.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_20.02">Gains from impudence are not suitable to be given inheritance: they are called “gifts of the demons”. Gains from gambling, from subletting (?, <foreign>babalañjaan</foreign>)<note>In MdS as in Mal., <foreign>balañja</foreign> means ‘shopping’, but Rigg notes <foreign>babalanja</foreign> ‘to do marketing, to make purchases of household commodities’. It makes more sense to take it from <foreign>lañja</foreign> ‘add a second layer to the first one, cover in (over/up) st.; repeat a job or action; take a second one to a woman; take a second one to a moneylender/supplier’. So probably <foreign>babalañjaan</foreign> is a nominal derivation which means something like ‘leasing, leasehold, subletting’. The last meaning is attested in a small number of OJ inscriptions. In the Palepangan inscription, for instance, we find: len· sumaṅkā rika hana ta savaḥ bhaṭāra kmitan· rāmanta lamvit· 1 dmak·ni p⟨ū⟩ja [em., pāja insc.], mūla lamvit· 1 tan inukur· Ikā Āpan· hĭnanyan· svabhāvanya, muAṁ lañjān· pirak· dhā 14 patukan· pirak· dhā 4| panurat· pirak· mā 4 | “Besides them there was 1 lamvit of paddy field of the deity kept by the elders as endowment for the cult (pūja) — the value (mūla) of 1 lamvit was not measured, because of the destituteness of its condition — with the income from subletting (lañjān) of 14 dhāraṇa of silver; the patukan of 4 māṣa of silver; the panurat of 4 dhāraṇa of silver” (draft ed. and transl. by Griffiths 2020; cf. Bosch 1917, Bijlage M: 88–98; Boechari 1985–1986: 124–126). However, the reduplication babalañjaan seems unnatural: should we emend it to babak lañjaan? In MdS, the word babakan means newly founded hamlet.</note> are not suitable to be given in inheritance: they are called “gifts of an egocentric mind”.<note>Instead of <foreign>aṅkara</foreign>, may be it should emend <foreign>ambara</foreign> into <foreign>saṅhara </foreign>based on <foreign>ṅahara</foreign> in H? So <foreign>cipta saṅhara</foreign> yield a meaning ‘destructive mind’.</note> Nevertheless, gifts from the mother, gifts from the father, gifts from teachers, they can be given in inheritance: they are called “gods that protect us”. Profits from agriculture can be given in inheritance: they are called “jewels produced from the earth”. Profits from weaving [and] products of husbandry can be given in inheritance: they are called “rubies fallen from the sky”.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_21">
<p corresp="#skk_21.01">If there are rich people, then [they] redeem a woman, without knowing about her parents. [Such a woman] should not be taken as purchased servant (<foreign>dipikaritakən</foreign>),<note>My emendation <foreign>dipikaritakən</foreign> is proposed in the light of the occurrence of <foreign>krīta</foreign> ‘purchased slave’ in an OJ legal text that comments on MDhŚ 8.415: dhvajāhr̥to bhaktadāso gr̥hajaḥ krītadattrimau | paitriko daṇḍadāsaś ca saptaite dāsayonayaḥ || “There are seven kinds of slaves: a man captured in war, a man who makes himself a slave to receive food, a slave born in the house, a purchased slave, a gifted slave, a hereditary slave, and a man enslaved for punishment”. This śloka is paraphrased in BAV (5v): <foreign>ka, panaṅkaniṅ kavulā, tavan, kavula saṅke pinaṅan, krīta, ulihiṅ anuku, datrimah, ṅa, kavula paveveh</foreign> “The meaning is: the origins of the slave are the captive, the slave from lack of food, the krīta, i.e. the result of purchase, the <foreign>datrimah</foreign>, i.e. gifted slave”. In Skt. <foreign>krīta</foreign> means ‘bought, purchased; purchased from his natural parents (as a son; one of the twelve kinds of sons acknowledged by the ancient Hindū law)’. In this light, it seems plausible that the base form to which the circumfix <foreign>dipi- -kən</foreign> is applied was a word deriving from Skt.  <foreign>krīta</foreign>, and <foreign>karita</foreign> seems to be the closest fit with the ms. readings. The context of <foreign>nəbus vadon</foreign> ‘to redeem a woman’ strengthens my hypothesis. It is also possible that <foreign>dipikaritikǝn</foreign> is the intended reading, if we can postulate a locally prevalent form <foreign>kariti</foreign> as feminine of <foreign>karita</foreign>  (although the fem. of <foreign>krīta</foreign> would actually be <foreign>krītā</foreign> in Skt.).</note> lest we become involved in something wrong. </p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.02">There is more — when we do know about her parents, where the servant’s origin is —, if the behavior of her parents is good, the person (in question, <foreign>janma</foreign>) is still good. It is called “being defeated (kapapas) by <supplied reason="subaudible">ones</supplied> parents’ behavior”. <supplied reason="subaudible">She</supplied> can be taken as purchased servant. But if <supplied reason="subaudible">she is defeated</supplied> by their deceitful behavior, she should not be tolerated. It is called “a person wandering around in hell”.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.03">There is more, [if] there is a person of good behavior, of good foundation,<note>I interpret <foreign>susuk</foreign> as ‘foundation’ based on the usage of the verb <foreign>ñusuk</foreign> which can imply the meaning ‘to build, to open up, to found’. For a discussion of the word <foreign>ñusuk</foreign>, see Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 152–153.</note> of good origin, [we should] not fail to redeem [her], but [we] should not immediately (<foreign>tuluy</foreign>)<note>The meaning ‘immediately’ is not recorded for <foreign>tuluy</foreign> in Sundanese dictionaries and GNT. However, in OJ, <foreign>tuluy </foreign>has this meaning. See OJED s.v. <foreign>tuluy </foreign>‘immediate continuation’, <foreign>tumuluy</foreign>, <foreign>tumulvi, tumul</foreign> ‘to continue immediately, to proceed from one thing to the next; to go straight on, penetrate; thereupon, straight away’.</note> take [her] as wife, lest the descendant be a servant. [We] should not fail to tell [it] to our family. After that, we should propose [to marry her], bring a betel quid and serve it.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_21.04">Those are the powerful words (<foreign>jaṅjavokan</foreign>) so that [her] family returns to its caste,<note>The use of the word <foreign>jati</foreign> in this context is intriguing since it seems to imply the meaning that <foreign>jāti</foreign> typically has in India, namely ‘caste’. The notion of caste is absent in Old Sundanese sources. However, in SKK we see a clear social hierarchy placing the <foreign>hulun</foreign> below the <foreign>tohaan</foreign>. It may therefore be that <foreign>jati</foreign> means ‘caste’ in a loose sense, referring to the low status of the <foreign>hulun</foreign>.</note> so that [she] avoids, escapes from imprisonment,<note>Instead of reading the phrase as <foreign>bətəṅ diri ti pañjara</foreign>, another possibility is to render it as <foreign>bətəṅ di riti-pañjara</foreign>, which can be interpreted as ‘ceased from the bronze cage’. The word <foreign>riti</foreign> is indeed unattested in OS, but it occurs in OJ as a kind of metal. OJED glosses uncertain meanings: ‘a certain metal (bronze, brass?). Cf. PYñ 8.3 <foreign>hana vəsi riti tambaga matahi-tahi </foreign>“there are the rusty iron, bronze (? <foreign>riti</foreign>), [and] copper”; Tk 1.101b <foreign>makadi dhātu riti tambaga mvaṅ vəsi vaja rajata kañcan</foreign>a “especially the mineral, bronze, copper, and also iron, steel, silver, [and] gold”; TK 62.35 <foreign>dhātu vəsi riri (r. riti) tambaga salaka </foreign>“mineral, iron, bronze, copper, silver”<foreign>.</foreign></note> so that [she] mingles with our good family, so that [she] avoids calamity.</p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_22">
<p corresp="#skk_22.01">This is for us to arrange our children’s marriage. They should not be matched<note>The word <foreign>dipitotohkən</foreign> is from <foreign>toh</foreign>, which in OJ has the meaning ‘stake (in game, gambling, wager, competition, combat); main stake (in combat)’ (OJED, s.v.  <foreign>toh</foreign> II). However, it seems that the meaning intended by the author is more related to OJ <foreign>taruh</foreign>, <foreign>anaruh</foreign> ‘to compete with, vie with, challenge’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>taruh</foreign>), so that in our context it can be rendered as ‘to match’. In MdS, the only related word is <foreign>bobotoh</foreign>, meaning ‘the pers. who leads in a cockfight or gambling’. Cf. also OJ <foreign>adu </foreign>which has the double meaning ‘to put face to face, bring into contact, make clash, have fight, pit against; to vie in, measure’ and ‘to mix, blend ingredients’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>adu</foreign>).</note> too early unless [the other family] is as proper as ours, the majority of us. As for the venereal disease<note>The word <foreign>leṅkeṅ</foreign> with the meaning of ‘venereal disease’ is only recorded in Rigg (1862, s.v. <foreign>léngkéng</foreign>).</note> of a father, it descends to the sons; as for the venereal disease of a mother, it descends to the daughters; if all die, they ascend from earth. It is called the demon entering into the Kali (epoch). It is improper to match infants (with each other), lest we become involved in something wrong, lest the [parents] who made the arrangement get cornered.<note>The word <foreign>kaparisədək</foreign> is a passive <foreign>ka-</foreign> form derived from the secondary base <foreign>pisədək</foreign>, with the infix -<foreign>ar</foreign>-. See Chapter 3, §Morphology.</note></p></div>
<div corresp="#skk_23">
<p corresp="#skk_23.01">Thus far the instruction of the holy men, the words of the Darma Pitutur, who utters the words of the ancestors, which should be given due attention. Follow [their] action, use [these] words:<note>The form <foreign>pakasabda</foreign> is remarkable. In OJ, it occurs in <foreign>Bhomāntaka</foreign> 100.12c <foreign>dhvaniniṅ gəlap śatasahasrakoṭi pakaśabdaniṅ prəp anitir</foreign>, translated by Teeuw &amp; Robson as “The din of a hundred thousand thunderclaps was the sound of the repeated punches”. Their comment on this form is as follows: “<foreign>pakaśabda </foreign>‘was the sound’: a remarkable construction with the prefix <foreign>paka- </foreign>literally ‘served as’. Does the author simply mean the sound of the repeated punches was like the din...?”. I rather choose to take it as imperative, based on the occurrence of <foreign>turut tvah </foreign>in the previous clause.</note> Homage to Siwa, homage to Buddha, homage to the fulfilled and perfect soul.</p>
<p corresp="#skk_23.02">Happy shall be the reader who intends that the good words be absorbed completely (<foreign>kasukma</foreign>),<note>I interpret <foreign>kasukma</foreign> as an equivalent of <foreign>sinūkṣma</foreign> in OJ ‘to absorb completely (make into the <foreign>sūkṣma</foreign>, the essence, of one's heart)’. Another possibility is to take <foreign>kasukma</foreign> as a noun, then the alternative translation would be ‘those who expect the secret of the good words’.</note> [and] who is firm in his pure mind. Please be attentive O servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>. This is the completion of what are called ‘The Hermits’ Precepts for Society’, the title of the book. <foreign>Pun.</foreign><note>For a discussion of <foreign>pun</foreign>, see Aditia Gunawan &amp; Griffiths 2021: 150–151.</note></p>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>