<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng"  type="translation" corresp="#sasanamahaguru">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI encoding</resp>
                    <!--TBM-->
                    <persName ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSasanaMahaguru_transEng01</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p corresp="#"/>
                        <p corresp="#"/>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p corresp="#"/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p corresp="#"/>
                <p corresp="#"/>
            </projectDesc>
            <schemaRef type="guide" key="EGCv01" url="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15HFxHJTOzIU1UDyVrB2yQYJ5wI6JyEshEkYgg5qwj8M/edit#"/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:axja" when="2022-11-24" status="draft">creation of the file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01">
                
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.01">Here is the name of the holy book: The Holy Instruction of the Great Teacher (<foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</foreign>). <foreign>Sasana</foreign> means the legacy of the ancestors, <foreign>maha</foreign> means more superior than the superior of the world, <foreign>guru</foreign> means the source of all the universe.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.02">There is your analogy: like the priceless jewel and the most desirable gem, it is the source of the joy and sorrow, the bad and the good. Its explanation is as follows: world (<foreign>buh</foreign>),<note>MsA has <foreign>bvah</foreign>, but I render it as <foreign>buh</foreign> since the context is quite clear. Cf. <foreign>bvar</foreign> for <foreign>bur</foreign> in SMG 1.4.</note> intention, knowledge, determination, total willingness.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.03">The meaning is: The world is the Holy Earth. When it is beautified, degraded, upgraded, littered, mingled, it does not fall and it is not indignant, it is not weak and it is not restless, forcefull and firm in performing earthiness (<foreign>kaprativian</foreign>). That is indeed the thing that the servant of the dharma should practice.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.04">Intention means the water. Its benefit is when [it] emerges from its upstream. It gushes clear, and it feels cool. Moreover, it also had no obstacles, reaching the ocean. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.05">Knowledge means the wind. Its benefit is when it blows from the west. It blows with coolness, [and] feels smooth on our bodies. Moreover, it will not be obstructed when it appears at the right moment in the world. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.06">Determination means fire and weapons. Because of their natures (<foreign>ti iña</foreign>), they are to be used by people whose minds are determined.</p>
                    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_01.07">Willingness means the Holy Sun. When it rises from the east, it is not impeded by clouds, rain, smoke, and fog until it reaches the west, because of the concentration on one action [only]. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate. We should not fail to be mindful toward the holy original cause. The following are called The Five Knowledges (<foreign>pañca-vedani</foreign>). <foreign>Panca</foreign> means <foreign>five</foreign>, <foreign>ve</foreign> means water, <foreign>dani</foreign> means broomstick.</p>
                </div>
                
<div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02">

    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.01">This is called the precepts for society (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), the precepts of religious groups (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>), the root’s precepts (<foreign>siksa dapur</foreign>). The meaning is: the precepts for society are around yourself. To encounter the adultery, the adultery of ‘The Journey’ [and] of ‘The Sitting Place’. That is what we should keep in mind. Then let us be careful, in case we enter the yard, entering the inner place, it is not comfortable [if we are] not their inhabitants.  That is called the precepts for society.</p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.02">When we are on a journey, it is not proper to commit a deceitful act because of the commodity of someone else’s farm, or someone else’s vegetable grove. Therefore, “hiris will smash the ear when the bean smashes the forehead”: to collect what people put down temporarily (<foreign>tunda</foreign>), to collect a clear ownership, [or] to bring down someone else’s tap (<foreign>sadapan</foreign>). It is improper to defecate on the side of the road, for it would be smelt by those who are careless, for it is possible that you will be cursed and be blamed [by] mother, father, and teachers. We should not fail to wear loincloths and full attire; if we meet a gusti or a minister, we should be on their left [and] bow. Those are called the precepts for society.</p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.03">The precepts of the religious group (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>) are to be one action with the scholar. After all, it is not good to make trouble of which has been deliberated, violating the holy precepts. If we are aware of the sections (of the books) and their binding cords (<foreign>lǝkǝr-lǝkǝr</foreign>), their dandas, lines (<foreign>sipat</foreign>), enclosures (<foreign>galǝṅ</foreign>), their strokes, their compositions, their boundary, their limits, all the imprints of the God Brahmā and Viṣṇu when they delimited the world. That is called the precepts of the religious group.
    </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_02.04">As for the precepts of the root is to reach the core, to obtain the origin by his devoted and truthful mind toward the scholar. That is called the precepts of the group. Those are called the precepts of the community, according to the great scholar.</p>
</div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03">
  
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.01">As follows is what the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should be aware of, [that is] the original cause of the holy scripture, the form of stain in the past until present.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.02">Here is the beginning of the holy scripture. Its form is as follows: after the sun had set, the night replaced [it]. Satisfaction and pleasure are the cause of the way of appearing, [thanks to] the reality of time of the Goddess Durgi. The God Gana’s instrument (<foreign>jantra</foreign>) trumpeted, so that it was sprayed towards humankind in the middle realm, and it turned into gebang and lontar. [When] the time came for the gebang and lontar to form young leaves, they followed precisely the same pattern with respect to their width and length, [so that they could have] <foreign>asta gaṅga vira tanu</foreign> applied.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.03">What is the <foreign>asta gaṅga vira tanu</foreign>? <foreign>Asta</foreign> means hand, <foreign>gaṅga</foreign> means water, <foreign>vira</foreign> means pen and brush, <foreign>tanu</foreign> means ink. They are used for writing by the scholar, for reading by one without knowledge to increase the range of the sounds, which is constrained [according to the rules] by the poet.</p>
                   
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.04">In the first place, the ten origins will be narrated. <foreign>Oṅ</foreign> Saraswati the excellence mind and the thought-gem. Let the eyes of God Bayu widely open. Let there be the embodiment of Lord Guru, the accomplished former master from the earth, the accomplished former master from the sky: Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusya, Patañjala; also breath, sound, and mind; let alone The Witness, for He is the one who counts.</p>
                    
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.05">As follows are what are called the ten origins (<foreign>dasa-purva</foreign>). <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten, <foreign>purva</foreign> means the origin. Those should be taken notice by the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, according to the scholar.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.06">Postphone! All that emerges from the narrative (<foreign>carita</foreign>) should be followed; [yet] the essence of The One (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ tuṅgal</foreign>) is inactive. For what purpose am I uttering this mantra? Well, it is because I know that I wish to produce letters: writing on gold, writing on silver, writing on copper, writing on knives (?, <foreign>cudiga</foreign>), writing on iron, writing on stone, writing on wooden strips, writing on bamboo (?, <foreign>pəjva</foreign>), writing on <foreign>lontar</foreign>, writing on <foreign>gebang</foreign>.</p>

                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_03.07">Writing on gold is called ‘transcendent ruby and gold’; its form and its result is beautiful, for it may not be stored. Perhaps many do not know this, so once again it is passed down: writing on silver is called ‘silver’ (<foreign>kanaka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on copper is called ‘thin plates of beaten gold’ (?, <foreign>paripih</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on steel is called ‘pressed’ (?, <foreign>prəka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on iron is called ‘family’ (?, <foreign>gvatraka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on stone is called ‘dead heirs’ (?, <foreign>tras pati</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on wooden boards is called ‘a bench’ (<foreign>salə</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on bamboo is called ‘folded’ (?, <foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), which may not be kept for it may cause danger. It is passed down again: writing on lontar is called incising (<foreign>carik</foreign>), indeed it has its virtues for it is not to be used for sacred texts (<foreign>kabuyutan</foreign>). Let’s go down again: writing on gebang is called black (<foreign>cəməṅ</foreign>), and this is for the sacred texts. For such texts referred to as manuscripts (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ ripta</foreign>), [the means for attaining] emptiness (<foreign>sunya</foreign>), folded books (<foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), the weapons (?, <foreign>mastra</foreign>), the smearing (of ink, <foreign>lepakarana</foreign> ?), these are the [types of] books enumerated one by one. Those are called ten advancements. 
                </p>
                </div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04">
                
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.01">The One said, “What is the purpose of this holy book? Because I know that I will produce the composition, being the emergence of The Teacher’s Precepts (<foreign>Siksa Guru</foreign>), from the holy precepts.”</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.02">Here, as follows, is the pure circle of three bodily domains. This is what should be thrown out; the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should not follow that (i.e. <foreign>tri-mala</foreign>) — [for it is] the source of sadness, the origin of the sins leading to misery, the beginning of the <foreign>kali</foreign>’s era, the cause of the sins leading to hell — the three stains so it's called.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.03">[As far as the] categorizations [are concerned], their comparisons are as follows: what is called the three defects is like bronze and wax, copper and tin. What is comparable to copper and tin? The meaning is the three evils: improper speeches, improper acts, improper minds. Evil speeches, evil acts, and evil minds are performed.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.04">These are the manifestations of the evil acts: flicking with the knuckle of finger, tapping, stabbing, punching, striking, knocking, hitting, slapping, spanking, all kinds of hand’s actions, those are called the evil acts.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.05">The evil speeches are: furious and angry without reason, talking rudely, cursing, blaming, condemning, uttering black magic, backbiting the teacher, all kinds of improper speeches, those are called the evil speeches.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.06">The evil minds are: plotting, pretending, slandering, using black magic, offending, bewitching, poisoning, being envious of what is right, including plundering, stealing, trespassing, infiltrating, way laying, anything that is improper is performed [and] intended, those are the evil minds. That is called the three defects.</p>
                <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_04.07">As follows are three ultimate defects (tri-mala visesa), possessed by the king, the elders, the hermits, the ritual expert, the sailor. This is the explanation: there is someone seen in sorrow, [then he] is sold, enslaved, robbed, and murdered. Those are called the five sinful [men], all such things are considered the three ultimate defects, according to the scholar, 3.</p>
</div>    
                
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05">
                
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.01"> </p>
    
    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.02"/>
   
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.03"> </p>
   
      <!--CB.184.I.26.27a.jpg-->
<!--<pb n="27r" xml:id="pb003"/>
<lb n="27r1"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>puji kukuḥ puji puji vihikan· puji puji viryi, yaḥ ta sinaṁguḥ dos:a ṅaranyi, dəm·ba ṅaranyi, Ana ta <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>
<lb n="27r2"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>dek· mitinəṁkən:a pi<space type="binding-hole"/>ram·pesə<add place="below">n</add>·, ya ta dəm·ba, loba, ṅaranyi, nu dipitinəṁ, ø dipitvaḥ dipikarma <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>
<lb n="27r3"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/><unclear>r</unclear>uḥ ku bənana ṅa<space type="binding-hole"/>ñahvakən·, ya mət:a, ṅa, macaryi, ṅa, timburu manvan· raḥhayu, ñəqəṁ nu <del rend="ui">saka</del>, ra<del rend="ui">ma</del><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>
<lb n="27r4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>habimanaṁ, ṅa, murka, ṅa, han·tə dek· nurut· carek· Iduṁ bapaḥ paṁgurya, ya ta si<unclear>n</unclear>aṁ <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>
-->
   
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_05.04"> </p>


</div>
    
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06">
                
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.01"> </p>
    
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.02"/>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.03"> </p>
    
 
 <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_06.04"> </p>

</div>


            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07">

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.05"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.06"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.07"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.08"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.09"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.10"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.11"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_07.12"> </p>
</div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08">

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.01"> </p>

    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.02"/>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_08.03"> </p>

</div>
                
            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09">


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.01"> </p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.02"/>    

    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_09.03"> </p>

</div>

            <div corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10">

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.01"> </p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.02"/>
    <!-- SiGu: śalākāñjanam suravile, paṇadantagharsādhyasta ceva, 
maprayāsamagama, ceva masva ceva mibuḥ 
kr̥ma viduḥ ceva nervayude, Uddatayudena kaL̥m suparigrahaste, 
-->
                    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_10.03"> </p>

</div>

<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.01"> </p>

    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.02"/>
 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_11.03"> </p>
</div>
                             
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.01"> </p>
    <p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.02"/>

<!--621 hinavakyima siharupañ ca grəhaste, guru saṁgasanəm· prətəm· grəhaste namanəmte-->
<!--Reconstructed SiGu: anāma hīnavākyam ahi, siṁharūpañ ca grahaste, 
gurusaṁghāsanam prītam, gr̥hate namaniṁmate, 
-->
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_12.03"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_13.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_13.02"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_14.01"> </p>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_14.02"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.02"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.03"> </p>
    
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.04"> </p>
        
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.05"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.06"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_15.07"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_16.01"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_16.02"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_17.01"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_18.01"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_19.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_19.02"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.05"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_20.06"> </p>
</div>
            
            
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.01"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_21.03"> </p>
</div>
           
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_22.01"> </p>
</div>
                
                
           
<!--Old Javanese-->                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_23.01"> </p>    
</div>
                <!-- <lb n="28v4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>hi<add place="below">da</add>pa, gərna In·driya haneṁ Iruṁ, sanika ri panan·ta ya ta karana saṁ hyi Atma, Aṅabuṁ pakən:anyi pamətvan·nikaṁ-->
<!--<!-\-CB.174.I.26.17a.jpg-\->                   
<pb n="17r" xml:id="pb023"/>
<lb n="17r1"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>tma mañabda pakənanya, pamətonika h<add place="below">da</add>p, jiho I<add place="above">na</add>dryi haneṁ lida, sanikari pananta, ya ta karana saṁ hyi A<add place="below">ha</add>tma, ṅara
<lb n="17r2"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/><unclear>ni</unclear>ka ri panan·ta,<space type="binding-hole"/> ya ta karana saṁ hyi Atma, maṁgaməl· pakənanyi, pamətvan·nikaṁ hi<add place="below">da</add>p, təvək Idriya ha
<lb n="17r3"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>pamətvannikaṁ<space type="binding-hole"/> hipda, pasṭā Idriya haneṁ pəlat· sanika ri pananta, ya ta karana saṁ hyi Atma, Anada Aṅəyə pa 
<lb n="17r4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>saṁ hyi Atma, pamaṅətut lavan· maṁṅisiṁ pakən:anya, paməton·nikaṁ hidəp·, pada Idriya haneṁ<gap reason="lost" unit="character" quantity="2"/>-->
            
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.03"> </p> 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.05"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.06"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.07"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.08"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.09"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_24.10"> </p>

<!--pasṭā Idriya haneṁ pəlat· sanika ri pananta, ya ta karana saṁ hyi Atma, Anada Aṅəyə pa 
<lb n="17r4"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>saṁ hyi Atma, pamaṅətut lavan· maṁṅisiṁ pakən:anya, paməton·nikaṁ hidəp·, pada Idriya haneṁ<gap reason="lost" unit="character" quantity="2"/>-->
    
    <!--CB.174.I.26.17b.jpg-->
<!--<pb n="17v" xml:id="pb024"/>
<lb n="17v1"/>ta sinaṁguḥ dasa Idriya, ṅa, //Ø Ini dasa paṁṅaku, ṅa, Inakunyi Ata ya paṁruṅunyi panvan·tvanya paṅabuṁnya pa<gap reason="lost" quantity="1" unit="character"/>
<lb n="17v2" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>ya Ø hana saṅ maṅa<space type="binding-hole"/>buṁ, hana saṁ maṅR̥ṅə, hana saṁ hyi manikumaṁbaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṅ manon·tvan· ha
<lb n="17v3" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>mabuṁ, hana visesa<space type="binding-hole"/>ku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ mañabda hana saṅ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ ṅa
<lb n="17v4" break="no"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown"/>məl· hana saṁ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prəmanaku, hana saṁ maṁrasa, hana saṁ hyi manikumabaṁ, hana visesaku, hana prə 
    -->
</div>
            
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_25.01"> </p>
</div>


<div>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_26.01"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_27.01"> </p>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_27.02"> </p>
            </div>
            
<div>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.01"> </p>
    
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.02"/>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_28.03"> </p>

</div>
                
<div>
 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_29.01"> </p>


</div>
                
<div>
 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_30.01"> </p>

</div>
                
<div>
 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_31.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_31.02"> </p>

</div>

<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_32.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_32.02"> </p>

</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_33.03"> </p>

</div>

                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_34.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_34.02"> </p>

</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.04"> </p>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.05"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.06"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.07"> </p>
 
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.08"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.09"> </p>

  
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.11"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.12"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.13"> </p>
 
     
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.14"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.15"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.17"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.18"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_35.19"> </p>

</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.02"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_36.03"> </p>
    
</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_37.05"> </p>
    </div>
                
<div>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.02"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.03"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.06"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.07"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.08"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.09"> </p>
    <p corresp="#"/> 
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.11"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.12"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.13"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.14"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_38.15"> </p>
    </div>
                
<div>

    
 <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.02"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.04"> </p>


    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.05"> </p>
       
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.06"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.07"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_39.08"> </p>
    
    
    </div>
                
<div>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.03"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.04"> </p>
<p corresp="#"/> 
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.05"> </p>
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_40.06"> </p>
        </div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.01"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.02"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.03"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.04"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.07"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_41.08"> </p>


</div>
                
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.01"> </p>

   
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.02"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.03"> </p>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.04"> </p>
 
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.05"> </p>


    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.06"> </p>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.07"> </p> 
    

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.08"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.09"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.10"> </p> 
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.11"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.12"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.13"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_42.14"> </p>
</div>
                
<div>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.01"> </p>
  
            
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.02"> </p>
 
    
    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_43.03"> </p>
</div>
            
<div>


<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.02"> </p>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.03"> </p>
       
    

    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.04"> </p>
    
   
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.05"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.06"> </p>
    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.07"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_44.08"> </p>




</div>
                <!-- mari saṁsaya ta kita denya, mari meliḥ na<space type="binding-hole"/> ta kita, saṁ hya pramana, manilvalita saṁ hya visesa, ka, tan· na svaga, tar nahala, tar na hayu, tar na su<lb 
  n="35v4" break="no"/>ka, tar na duka, Iya ta rasaniṁ pati ṅaranya, katəmvan ikaṁ manivan·, ri sala niskala, Apa ta maryikən·n ika hala, hala hayu, suka duka, ṅəkeri bvana sarira, ṅaniveḥ Ikaṁ sarvvajan·ma kabeḥ

<!-\-SSMG_L621_36r.JPG-\->
<pb n="36r"/>
<lb n="36r1"/>Ana saṁ hyaṁ pramana, juga tan· hana vaneḥ nihan· sinaṁguḥ rahasye pandi ṅaranya, -->
            
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.01"> </p>

    <p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.02"> </p>

    
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_45.03"> </p>
</div>
               
<div>

<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.01"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.02"> </p>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_46.03"> </p>


</div>
                <!--Ø, tləs· sinurat· riṁ vulan· kapat·, manibakən· sasṭā, ri de<space type="binding-hole"/>sa mahapaviṭā, riṁ gunuṁ jədaṁ pun·, Uliḥ sabian· ṅeca pun·, saṁṅ anurat· bvacaḥ nu ṅaheraṁ nibaṁ kaca<lb 
  n="36v3" break="no"/>na pun·, // // Ø malapaḥh iṅapura, ku na sasṭā 2cek· kadi tapak· yuyu riṁ tacaṁ pun·, Ø L̥viḥ<space type="binding-hole"/> lvaṅan· kuraṁ tinabəhan· kena bənaṁ nu IR̥g· pun // , //,,,,,,,,,, -->
<div>
<p corresp="#sasanamahaguru_48.01"> </p>
                   </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>