<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#smg">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</title>
                <editor ref="part:adgu">
                    <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI encoding</resp>
                    <!--TBM-->
                    <persName ref="part:adgu">
                        <name>Aditia Gunawan</name>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>DHARMA</authority>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSasanaMahaguru_transEng01</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p/>
                        <p/>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <schemaRef type="guide" key="EGCv01"
                url="https://docs.google.com/document/d/15HFxHJTOzIU1UDyVrB2yQYJ5wI6JyEshEkYgg5qwj8M/edit#"
            />
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="part:axja" when="2022-11-24" status="draft">creation of the file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:space="preserve">
        <body> <div n="1" corresp="#smg_01"><p corresp="#smg_01.01">Here is the name of the holy book: The Holy Instruction of the Great Teacher (<foreign>Saṅ Hyaṅ Sasana Mahaguru</foreign>). <foreign>Sasana</foreign> means the legacy of the ancestors, <foreign>maha</foreign> means more superior than the superior of the world, <foreign>guru</foreign> means the source of all the universe.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.02">There is your analogy: like the priceless jewel and the most desirable gem, it is the source of the joy and sorrow, the bad and the good. Its explanation is as follows: world (<foreign>buh</foreign>),<note>msA has <foreign>bvah</foreign>, but I render it as <foreign>buh</foreign> since the context is quite clear that <foreign>bvah</foreign> is the earth <foreign>prətivi</foreign>. Cf. <foreign>bvar</foreign> for <foreign>bur</foreign> in SMG 1.4.</note> intention,<note>I interpret <foreign>paksa</foreign> as ‘intention’, according to one of the meaning in OJ; see OJED, s.v. <foreign>pakṣa</foreign> IV.</note>  knowledge,<note>In OS texts, for instance in for instance in KaPañ 6–7, we find that <foreign>huniṅ</foreign> is a verb ‘to know’: <foreign>avakanən saṅ sisya, nu huniṅ sevaka darma</foreign> “to be practiced by the disciple, who knows how to serve <foreign>dharma</foreign>”. but in this context it is clearly substantive.</note> determination,<note>Based on the explanation that <foreign>tǝmǝn</foreign> is related to fire, maybe it means determination. OJED does not record substantive meaning, but cf. <foreign>anəməni</foreign> ‘to be serious about, set about doing st. in real earnest (determinedly)’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>təmən</foreign>).</note> total willingness.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.03">The meaning is: The world is the Holy Earth. When it is beautified, degraded, upgraded, littered, mingled, it does not fall<note>The meaning of fall is taken from MdS, <foreign>nyusutkeun</foreign> ‘throw so. down forward on the ground’; <foreign>tisusut</foreign> ‘fall forward’. Cf Mal. <foreign>susut</foreign> ‘to decrease; to shrink’. It is different from OJ <foreign>susut</foreign> ‘entangled, confused.’</note> and it is not indignant, it is not weak<note>I interpret <foreign>gərah</foreign> as ‘weak, powerless’ as in OJ. In MdS, it has a positive nuance ‘cheerful, buoyant, in high spirits; rejoice, glad, pleased, happy’.</note> 
 and it is not restless,<note><foreign>bijah</foreign>: in MdS dictionaries, <foreign>mijah</foreign> is considered as the base word. Clearly in OS we have the base word <foreign>bijah</foreign> ‘restless’.</note> forcefull and firm in performing earthiness (<foreign>kaprativian</foreign>). That is indeed the thing that the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should practice.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.04">Intention means the water. Its benefit is when <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> emerges<note>The word <foreign>bvar</foreign> is not in the dictionaries, but cf. MdS <foreign>bur</foreign>. ‘ant. for: hurry off, hasten away, scamper off, fly away, strew (flowers), scatter, sow (seed), sprinkle (sand), pour out, empty (contents of st.), etc’.</note> from its upstream. It gushes clear, and it feels cool. Moreover, it also had no obstacles, reaching the ocean. That is what the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> must emulate.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.05">Knowledge means the wind. Its benefit is when it blows <note>Like the word <foreign>bvar</foreign>, a single syllable word <foreign>hir</foreign> is also, following Hardjadibrata’s terminology, an anticipator. However, <foreign>hir</foreign> in this sense is not recorded in MdS dictionaries, but the present context makes clear that it refers to ‘air motion, wind etc’. Cf. MdS <foreign>hiliwir</foreign>, <foreign>ngahiliwir</foreign> ‘(come in) blowing softly (of the breeze, of the scent of flowers filling the air); <foreign>humiliwir</foreign> s.m. (in lit. lang.); (the root is used as ant.)’.</note> from the west. It blows with coolness, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> feels smooth on our bodies. Moreover, it will not be obstructed when it appears at the right moment in the world. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.06">Determination means fire and weapons. Because of their natures (<foreign>ti iña</foreign>),<note>I take the conjunction <foreign>ti</foreign> in <foreign>ti iña</foreign> as the reasoning. Cf. Skt. <foreign>tasmat</foreign>.</note>
 they are to be used<note>The passive form <foreign>dipipakǝnakən</foreign> is from <foreign>pakən</foreign> ‘for, so that’, cf. an equivalent construction in Mal. <foreign>diperuntukkan</foreign>.</note> by people whose minds are determined.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_01.07">Willingness means the Holy Sun. When it rises from the east, it is not impeded by clouds, rain, smoke, and fog until it reaches the west, because of the concentration on one action <supplied reason="subaudible">only</supplied>. That is what the servant of the dharma must emulate. We should not fail to be mindful toward the holy original cause. The following are called The Five Knowledges (<foreign>pañca-vedani</foreign>). <note>The word <foreign>vedani</foreign> ‘knowledge’ is probably being understood by the author as a neutral form of Skt. <foreign>veda</foreign>. Another possibility is that the author tends to relate <foreign>vedani</foreign> with the OJ compound, <foreign>ve dani</foreign> ‘clear water’, from OJ <foreign>ve</foreign> ‘water’, and <foreign>dani</foreign> ‘(of the mind) to become clear, no longer darkened by emotions, etc?’.</note> <foreign>Panca</foreign> means <foreign>five</foreign>, <foreign>ve</foreign> means water, <foreign>dani</foreign> means broomstick.</p></div>
<div n="2" corresp="#smg_02"><p corresp="#smg_02.01">This is called the precepts for society (<foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>), the precepts of religious groups (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>), the root’s precepts (<foreign>siksa dapur</foreign>). The meaning is: the precepts for society are around yourself. To encounter<note>The initial reduplication form <foreign>jǝṅjǝəṅ</foreign> means ‘to encounter’, from <foreign>jəəṅ</foreign> ‘to see’. We find another variant <foreign>jəjəəṅ</foreign> in OS corpus. Cf. SKK 7.2.</note> the adultery, the adultery of ‘The Journey’ <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> of ‘The Sitting Place’. That is what we should keep in mind.<note>One would expect <foreign>ku uraṅ</foreign> instead of <foreign>dəṅ uraṅ</foreign>. This combination is unusual. However, cf. the attested use of conjunction <foreign>mvaṅ</foreign> in OJ (equivalent to OS <foreign>dəṅ</foreign>) as a mark of agent, e.g. in JS 19 <foreign>kapāśa mvaṅ triguṇa</foreign> ‘to be fettered by the <foreign>triguna</foreign>s’.</note> Then let us be careful, in case we enter the yard, entering the inner place, it is not comfortable <supplied reason="subaudible">if we are</supplied> not their inhabitants. That is called the precepts for society.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_02.02">When we are on a journey,<note>The word <foreign>paparan</foreign> is from <foreign>paran</foreign> ‘destination’, meaning ‘to go, in journey’, cf. OJ <foreign>apara-paran</foreign> ‘to journey, wander abroad, roam’. This form is not recorded in MdS, however, some dialects have <foreign>maparan</foreign> ‘go to see so., going to look so. up’ (Hardjadibrata, s.v. <foreign>paran</foreign>). Cf. SKK 5.3.</note> it is not proper to commit a deceitful act because of the commodity of someone else’s farm, or someone else’s vegetable grove. Therefore, “<foreign>hiris</foreign> will smash the ear when the bean smashes the forehead”:<note><foreign>hiris məbət cəli, lamun kacaṅ məbət taraṅ</foreign> “hiris will smash the ear when the bean smashes the forehead” seems to be an expression. It possibly refers to the cause and consequence of someone’s action. In MdS, <foreign>hiris</foreign> refers to various kinds of plant, ‘leguminous plant (s.m. kacang h., see <foreign>kacang</foreign>); <foreign>ki hiris</foreign> I k.o. shrub, Budleia asiatica Lour., member of the Loganiaceae (also called: <foreign>ki kadal</foreign>, <foreign>ki kérését</foreign>, ki <foreign>monyényén</foreign>); II (H.) k.o. shrub or small tree (wood useful for charcoal; also called: <foreign>ki hurung</foreign>). Since it is mentioned along with <foreign>kacaṅ</foreign>, I take <foreign>hiris</foreign> as a kind of nut.</note> to collect what people put down temporarily (<foreign>tunda</foreign>),<note>In MdS, <foreign>tunda</foreign>, <foreign>nunda</foreign> means ‘put st. down temporarily (with the purpose of taking it up again later on the way); stop st. (work, case, subject) temporarily (with the intention of picking it up again at a later stage)’. Combined with the verb <foreign>ṅala</foreign>, I prefer to render <foreign>tunda</foreign> as a substantive.</note> to take something clearly owned <supplied reason="subaudible">by another</supplied>,<note>In MdS, <foreign>kantenan</foreign> is a high (<foreign>lemes</foreign>) register of <foreign>puguh</foreign> ‘(adv) of course, certainly, sure, positive’; or is it a <foreign>lemes</foreign> register of <foreign>kari</foreign> ‘remain, residue’? If it is the case, then the alternative translation of <foreign>ṅala kantənan</foreign> would be ‘to collect the remains’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> to bring down someone else’s tap (<foreign>sadapan</foreign>). It is improper to defecate on the side of the road, for it would be smelt by those who are careless,<note>The reduplicated form <foreign>buṅah-baṅah</foreign> is not found in dictionaries. MdS has <foreign>balaṅah</foreign> ‘careless’, probably from <foreign>baṅah</foreign> with infix <foreign>-al-</foreign>. The base word <foreign>bangah</foreign>, however, is not recorded in dictionaries.</note> for it is possible that you will be cursed and be blamed<note>The passive word <foreign>kapadahkǝn</foreign> is not found in MdS. Its occurrence is always with <foreign>kasumpah</foreign> ‘to be cursed’ in OS texts. I render it as equivalent to OJ <foreign>amāda</foreign> ‘to find fault with, judge harshly’, from the base <foreign>vāda</foreign> (OJED, s.v.). It should be noted that MdS also has <foreign>ngawada</foreign> ‘to criticize’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">by</supplied> mother, father, and teachers. We should not fail to wear loincloths and full attire; if we meet a gusti or a minister, we should be on their left <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> bow.<note>The word <foreign>paṅadoṅkoṅkən</foreign> is clearly related to OJ <foreign>joṅkoṅ</foreign> 'squatting’. Cf. SKK 4.16. See the discussion on <foreign>paN- -kən</foreign> in Chapter 3. Cf. also MdS  <foreign>dongko</foreign> vi. ‘bend the upper torso forward’, but MdS also has <foreign>dongkong</foreign> ‘id.’ <foreign>mangdongkokeun</foreign> ‘take a bent forward posture for so’.</note> Those are called the precepts for society.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_02.03">The precepts of the religious group (<foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>) are to be one action with the scholar. After all,<note>Based on the context, <foreign>aṅgəs ma</foreign> here seems to mean ‘after all’. </note> it is not good to make trouble of which has been deliberated, violating the holy precepts. If we are aware of the sections (of the books) and their binding cords (<foreign>lǝkǝr-lǝkǝr</foreign>),<note>The reduplication form <foreign>ləkər-ləkər</foreign> is not attested in OS, but we find <foreign>ləkər</foreign> in OJ ‘coil, encircling rope (etc) to provide firmness’ (OJED, s.v.). I interpret it as an allusion to the binding cords on the palm leaf manuscripts.</note> their <foreign>danda</foreign>s,<note>The word <foreign>daṅda-daṅdi</foreign> probably refers to Sanskrit term <foreign>daṇḍa</foreign> or punctuation mark in writing. It seems to be a twin form. Cf. <foreign>trəpti-trəptva</foreign> on SMG 3.2.</note>lines (<foreign>sipat</foreign>), enclosures (<foreign>galǝṅ</foreign>), their strokes, their compositions, their boundary, their limits, all the imprints of the God Brahmā and Viṣṇu when they delimited the world. That is called the precepts of the religious group.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_02.04">As for the precepts of the root is to reach the core, to obtain the origin by one’s devoted and truthful mind toward the scholar. That is called the precepts of the root. Those are called the precepts for society,<note>One expected <foreign>siksa kandaṅ</foreign>, <foreign>siksa kuruṅ</foreign>, <foreign>siksa dapur ṅaranya</foreign> in this sentence. Probably manuscript is corrupted in this part.</note> according to the great scholar.</p></div>
<div n="3" corresp="#smg_03"><p corresp="#smg_03.01">As follows is what the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should be aware of, <supplied reason="subaudible">that is</supplied> the original cause of the holy scripture,<note>For the interpretation regarding the writing supports and instruments in manuscript production, see Aditia Gunawan 2015.</note> the form of stain<note>Maybe <foreign>mala-murti</foreign> refers to the shape of the ink stains in the book? But <foreign>mala</foreign> can also mean ‘curse’, which in this connection probably displays the sacred nature of the book.</note> in the past until present.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.02">Here is the beginning of the holy scripture. Its form is as follows: after the sun<note>The sun with the personification attribute is also found in SHH 24.6, <foreign>śrīvikramāditya</foreign>: <foreign>hana maṇik sarveṣṭa sakārja paripūraka ṅaranya, cinaritakən ri carita kumara mvaṅ saṅ murti mvaṅ śrīvikramāditya</foreign>.</note> had set, the night replaced <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied>. Satisfaction and pleasure<note>I consider <foreign>trǝpti-trǝptva</foreign> as a twin form, equivalent to OJ <foreign>trǝpti</foreign> and <foreign>trǝpta</foreign>, both mean ‘contentment, gladness, well-being; content, glad, pleased’ (OJED, svv.).</note>  are the cause of the way of appearing, <supplied reason="subaudible">thanks to</supplied> the reality of time of the Goddess Durgi. The God Gana’s instrument (<foreign>jantra</foreign>) trumpeted, so that it was sprayed towards humankind in the middle realm, and it turned into <foreign>gebang</foreign> and <foreign>lontar</foreign>. <supplied reason="subaudible">When</supplied> the time came for the gebang and lontar to form young leaves, they followed precisely the same pattern with respect to their width and length, <supplied reason="subaudible">so that they could have</supplied> <foreign>asta gaṅga vira tanu</foreign> applied.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.03">What is the <foreign>asta gaṅga vira tanu</foreign>? <foreign>Asta</foreign> means hand, <foreign>gaṅga</foreign> means water, <foreign>vira</foreign> means pen and brush, <foreign>tanu</foreign> means ink. They are used for writing by the scholar, for reading by one without knowledge to increase the range of the sounds, which is constrained <supplied reason="subaudible">according to the rules</supplied> by the poet.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.04">In the first place, the ten origins will be narrated. <foreign>Oṅ</foreign> Saraswati the excellence mind<note>The combination <foreign>tara-jñana</foreign> is unattested elsewhere. My interpretation of <foreign>tara</foreign> as ‘excellent’ is based on the meaning in OJ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>tara</foreign> 1).</note> and the thought-gem. Let the eyes of God Bayu widely open. Let there be the embodiment of Lord Guru, the accomplished ancient masters<note>The compound <foreign>panditatita</foreign> is from <foreign>pandita</foreign> (Skt <foreign>paṇḍita</foreign>) and <foreign>atita</foreign> (Skt <foreign>atīta</foreign>) ‘former’.</note> from the earth, the accomplished ancien masters from the sky: Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusya, Patañjala; also breath, speech, and mind; let alone The Witness,<note>On the interpretation of The Witness (Saṅ Manon), see chapter 11, §The God and The Soul.</note> for He is the one who counts.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.05">As follows are what are called the ten origins (<foreign>dasa-purva</foreign>). <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten, <foreign>purva</foreign> means the origin. Those should be taken notice by the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, according to the scholar.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.06">Postphone! All that emerges from the narrative (<foreign>carita</foreign>) should be followed; <supplied reason="subaudible">yet</supplied> the essence of The One (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ tuṅgal</foreign>) is inactive. For what purpose am I uttering this mantra? Well, it is because I know that I wish to produce letters: writing on gold, writing on silver, writing on copper, writing on knives (?, <foreign>cudiga</foreign>),<note>In BM 1565–1569, <foreign>cudiga</foreign> seems to refer to one of the metal materials, however, Noorduyn & Teeuw translate <foreign>cudiga</foreign> as ‘spout’: <foreign>pañcuran tambaga sukla, caṅkorah salaka pirak, dituṅtuṅ ku cudiga, pesek dipopokan omas, pañimbǝh undǝm salaka</foreign> “The bathing place is of light copper, with a silver basin, ending in a spout, a washing place coated with gold, its scoop a silver vessel”. I rather consider that <foreign>cudiga</foreign> is derived from Skt. <foreign>churikā</foreign> ‘knife’, with the interchangeability of /r/ with /d/ and /k/ with /g/, which is not extraordinary. I wonder if there is a semantic shift from a knife into a general material of metal like ‘steel’, since it is placed after copper and before iron</note> writing on iron, writing on stone, writing on wooden strips, writing on bamboo (?, <foreign>pəjva</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>pəjva</foreign> could not be found in dictionaries. But this word may be related with OJ <foreign>peñjor</foreign> ‘bamboo pole decorated at the top’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>peñjor</foreign>), the changement of vowels /e/ gt /ə/, while the omission of a nasal and the addition of final /r/ are imaginable. However, the connection with <foreign>ləpihan</foreign> which, according to Jákl (2016a), means ‘folded’ is also problematic. I do not exclude the possibility that <foreign>pəjva</foreign> may mean bark tree (<foreign>daluwang</foreign>), which is also used as a writing support for manuscripts.</note> writing on <foreign>lontar</foreign>,<note>Regarding the word <foreign>taal</foreign> (= <foreign>lontar</foreign> palm-leaf), we find several cases of the hiatus usage in OS which is comparable to long vowels in OJ counterpart: OS <foreign>vaas</foreign> vs. OJ <foreign>vās</foreign>, OS <foreign>duum</foreign> vs. OJ <foreign>dūm</foreign>. See chapter 3, §Phonology.</note> writing on <foreign>gebang</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_03.07">Writing on gold is called ‘transcendent ruby and gold’; its form and its result is beautiful, for it may not be stored. Perhaps many do not know this, so once again it is passed down: writing on silver is called ‘silver’ (<foreign>kanaka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on copper is called ‘thin plates of beaten gold’ (?, <foreign>paripih</foreign>).<note>The word <foreign>paripid</foreign> seems to be related to Skt. <foreign>paripīḍ</foreign> ‘to press all round, press together, squeeze’. However, I interpret this word to be equivalent OJ <foreign>paripih</foreign>, meaning ‘thin plates of beaten gold’. Should it be better to emend it to <foreign>paripih</foreign>? However, the difference between OJ /h/ and OS /d/ is difficult to understand. Cf. Mal. <foreign>pipih</foreign> ‘thin and flat’.</note> It is passed down again: writing on steel is called ‘pressed’ (?, <foreign>prəka</foreign>).<note>The interpretation of <foreign>prəka</foreign> as ‘to be pressed’ is tentative. I relate this word to OJ <foreign>prək, maprək, umrək</foreign> ‘pressed up close, to press against’.</note> It is passed down again: writing on iron is called ‘family’ (?, <foreign>gvatraka</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on stone is called ‘dead heirs’ (?, <foreign>tras pati</foreign>).<note>The compound <foreign>tras pati</foreign> literally means ‘dead heirs’; I wonder whether this contains an allusion to the more durable nature of the inscription on stone and is intended for heirs?</note> It is passed down again: writing on wooden boards is called ‘a bench’ (<foreign>salə</foreign>). It is passed down again: writing on bamboo is called ‘folded’ (?, <foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), which may not be kept for it may cause danger. It is passed down again: writing on lontar is called incising (<foreign>carik</foreign>), indeed it has its virtues for it is not to be used for sacred texts (<foreign>kabuyutan</foreign>). Let’s go down again: writing on gebang is called black (<foreign>cəməṅ</foreign>), and this is for the sacred texts. For such texts referred to as manuscripts (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ ripta</foreign>), <supplied reason="subaudible">the means for attaining</supplied> emptiness (<foreign>sunya</foreign>), folded books (<foreign>ləpihan</foreign>), the weapons (?, <foreign>mastra</foreign>),<note>My interpretation of <foreign>mastra</foreign> as ‘weapon’ is tentative, probably it should be read <foreign>makastra</foreign>? Cf. PM 41b <foreign>makastra tanah lǝpihan eñjiṅ mahas andon laṅu pañji</foreign></note> the smearing (of ink ?, <foreign>lepa-karana</foreign>),<note>The activity of smearing (<foreign>lepa-karana</foreign>) probably refers to the smearing of palm leaves manuscripts as we find its practice in Bali nowadays? This combination is not found in OJ.</note> these are the <supplied reason="subaudible">types of</supplied> books enumerated one by one. Those are called ten advancements.</p></div>
<div n="4" corresp="#smg_04"><p corresp="#smg_04.01">The One said, “What is the purpose<note>The word <foreign>piǝnanana</foreign>, which I interpret tentatively ‘purpose’, is not found in MdS dictionaries and in the OS corpus at my disposal, but I wonder whether the semantic meaning is generated from the morphological process of <foreign>pi- -ǝn</foreign> meaning ‘things to be’ or ‘purpose’ and it becomes the base word <foreign>piən</foreign> with suffix <foreign>-an</foreign> and the enclitic -<foreign>ana</foreign>; cf. <foreign>pikavihən</foreign> ‘things to be sung’.</note> of this holy book? Because I know that I will produce the composition, being the emergence of The Teacher’s Precepts (<foreign>Siksa Guru</foreign>), from the holy precepts.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.02">Here, as follows, is the pure circle of three bodily domains. This is what should be thrown out; the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should not follow that (i.e. <foreign>tri-mala</foreign>)<note>The allusion to the <foreign>tri-mala</foreign> can only be understood in the light of the source of this text, SiGu 8.3; cf. also SMG 4.3 below.</note> — <supplied reason="subaudible">for it is</supplied> the source of sadness, the origin of the sins leading to misery, the beginning of the <foreign>kali</foreign>’s era, the cause of the sins leading to hell — the three stains so it is called.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.03"><supplied reason="subaudible">As far as the</supplied> categorizations <supplied reason="subaudible">are concerned</supplied>, their comparisons are as follows: what is called the three defects is like bronze and wax, copper and tin. What is comparable to copper and tin? The meaning is the three evils: improper speeches, improper acts, improper minds. Evil speeches, evil acts, and evil minds are performed.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.04">These are the manifestations of the evil acts: flicking with the knuckle of finger, tapping, stabbing, punching, striking, knocking, hitting, slapping, spanking, all kinds of hand’s actions, those are called the evil acts.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.05">The evil speeches are: furious and angry without reason, talking rudely, cursing, blaming, condemning, uttering black magic, backbiting the teacher, all kinds of improper speeches, those are called the evil speeches.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.06">The evil minds are: plotting, pretending, slandering, using black magic, offending, bewitching, poisoning, being envious of what is right, including plundering, stealing, trespassing, infiltrating, way laying, anything that is improper is performed <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> intended, those are the evil minds. That is called the three defects.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_04.07">As follows are three ultimate defects (<foreign>tri-mala visesa</foreign>), possessed by the king, the elders, the hermits, the ritual expert, the sailor. This is the explanation: there is someone seen in sorrow, <supplied reason="subaudible">then he</supplied> is sold, enslaved, robbed, and murdered. Those are called the five sinful <supplied reason="subaudible">men</supplied>, all such things are considered the three ultimate defects, according to the scholar, 3.</p></div>
<div n="5" corresp="#smg_05"><p corresp="#smg_05.01">Again, as follows is what should be carefully noticed by the servant of the Truth. There are what are called the ten defilements.<note>On the concept of <foreign>dasa-kalesa</foreign>, see chapter 11, §Ten Stains and Defilements.</note> What is the evidence? Here is the verse, the statement is as follows:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_05.02">“This <supplied reason="subaudible">condition of</supplied> defilement and sin having disappeared, and those who are afflicted having disappeared, they do great meritorious conduct.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_05.03">The meaning is: you should be able to purify the ten defilements. If comes to you, namely: vice (<foreign>doṣa</foreign>), ignorance (<foreign>moha</foreign>), cupidity (<foreign>lobha</foreign>), madness (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>), jealousy (<foreign>mātsarya</foreign>), arrogance (<foreign>abhimāna</foreign>), stupidity (<foreign>mūrkha</foreign>), cheat (<foreign>kuhaka</foreign>), idle talk (<foreign>sambhinnapralāpa</foreign>), calumny (<foreign>peśuna</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_05.04">The meaning is: the vice (<foreign>doṣa</foreign>) is deeming oneself superior in happiness, deeming oneself superior in knowledge, deeming oneself strong, that is called the vice. Ignorance (<foreign>moha</foreign>) means not having affection toward fellow human beings. Cupidity (<foreign>lobha</foreign>) means addicted to eating, addicted to drinking, and continuously sleeping, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> does not want to think of goodness, that is called cupidity. Having a lot of things to think of, something to carry out, something to act on, that is called cupidity. Madness (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>) is being difficult<note>The word <foreign>ivuh</foreign> is not found in OS texts, but it is clear from OJ <foreign>ivuh</foreign> ‘difficult’. In OJ, <foreign>ivuh</foreign> is attested in a later text, {hv</foreign> 1.58a: <foreign>tuhv evuh təmah iṅ nagara</foreign> (OJED, s.v. <foreign>ivuh</foreign>).</note> by his wealth, being difficult by his expertise, being difficult by his qualities, being difficult by his knowledge, that is called madness (<foreign>mǝta</foreign>). Jealousy (<foreign>matsārya</foreign>) is being jealous to see the welfare <supplied reason="subaudible">of others</supplied>, jealous watching someone kind, jealous watching someone happy, that is called jealousy. Arrogance (<foreign>abhimāna</foreign>) means not willing to give lessons and advice, that is called arrogance. Stupidity (<foreign>mūrkha</foreign>) means not willing to obey mother, father, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> teachers, that is called stupidity. Cheat (<foreign>kuhaka</foreign>) means to claim the work of others. Idle talk (<foreign>sambhinnapralāpa</foreign>) means constantly talking about the pleasure of those who have the pleasure, the wealth of those who have wealth, that is called idle talk. Calumny (<foreign>peśuna</foreign>) means easily to be jealous, easily to be deceitful, to provoke <supplied reason="subaudible">others</supplied>. Those are called ten defilements.</p></div>
<div n="6" corresp="#smg_06"><p corresp="#smg_06.01">Furthermore, the following are called the ten defects (<foreign>dasa-mala</foreign>). As follows is the verse:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_06.02"><foreign>vigatah maladuhkhinaḥ, kurvanti kuśalam mahat</foreign>| <foreign>gavayakən sutəm citəm, budi hiyəm maguh narakəm</foreign> |</p>
<p corresp="#smg_06.03">The meaning is: would you have the same probability of misfortune (<foreign>marakarma</foreign>), if <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> comes to you? Misfortune means sleep (<foreign>supta</foreign>), fear (<foreign>bhaya</foreign>), laziness (<foreign>tandrī</foreign>), irresolution (<foreign>kleda</foreign>), shame (<foreign>lajjā</foreign>), lust for women (<foreign>rāgastrī</foreign>), adultery (<foreign>paradāra</foreign>), eating of food (<foreign>bhakṣabhojana</foreign>), dishonest consideration (<foreign>kuṭilaviveka</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_06.04">The meaning is: sleep (<foreign>supta</foreign>) means continuously sleeping, forgetting to ask what is the good and the best for oneself, forgetting to occupy oneself with the good mind, and speaking the goodness to many people, those are called sleep. Fear (<foreign>bhaya</foreign>) means being afraid to ask for oneself, being afraid to ask because he feels senior, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> being afraid to speak goodness, those are called fear. Laziness (<foreign>tandrī</foreign>) means being lazy to ask because he feels ignorant, being lazy to act with a joyful mind, and to speak of goodness to many people, those are called laziness. Irresolution (<foreign>kleda</foreign>) means being hesitant to act with good mind to the people, being hesitant to ask about oneself, those are called irresolution. Shame (<foreign>lajjā</foreign>) means he finds it difficult to to ask because he feels stupid, he finds it difficult to render service because he feels senior, he finds it difficult to render service because he feels rich. Lust of women (<foreign>rāgastrī</foreign>) means being keen on desiring to have an intercourse and wish to be rich, <supplied reason="subaudible">those</supplied> are called lust of women. Adultery (<foreign>paradāra</foreign>) means desiring a widowed girl, the forbidden woman of other people, those are called adultery. Eating the food (<foreign>bhakṣabhojāna</foreign>) means he does not do the goodness; that is bhakṣabhojāna, namely, always eating, always drinking, †<foreign>dəṅ hjǝ</foreign>†,<note>I cannot reconstruct <foreign>dəṅ hjə</foreign>. Probably it should emend to <foreign>dəṅ hǝjǝn</foreign>, in the light of MdS <foreign>heujeun</foreign> ‘bowel motion’, in the sense of someone who is being too full? </note> for his desire being fulfilled by the six tastes (<foreign>ṣaḍrasa</foreign>), those are called eating the food. Dishonest consideration (<foreign>kuṭilaviveka</foreign>) means to postpone to act with joyful mind and to speak the goodness to the people. Those are called the ten stains, according to the learned master.</p></div>
<div n="7" corresp="#smg_07"><p corresp="#smg_07.01">Again, the following are called the ten hells (<foreign>dasa-naraka</foreign>). This is its manifestations: ears, eyes, nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hand, anus, genital, feet.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.02">The meaning is: the ears<note>I interpret <foreign>taliṅa</foreign> as ‘ear’, following the meaning in OJ. This word rarely appears in OS, but is very productive in SMG. The meaning in other OS texts is unclear because it only appears as the name of a god: <foreign>taliṅa jati</foreign> (KaPaṅ 321). In MdS, <foreign>talinga</foreign> means ‘to watch’. In this paragraph, the author uses both OS <foreign>cəli</foreign> and OJ <foreign>taliṅa</foreign>.</note> should not hear wrongly, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> quickly react<note>I consider <foreign>vaṅvaṅ</foreign> as an equivalent of OJ <foreign>vavaṅ</foreign> ‘directly, at once, straight away, forthwith’. However, I wonder whether it could be related to OS <foreign>humarivaṅvaṅ</foreign> ‘be worry’ = MdS <foreign>hariwang</foreign> ‘apprehensive, anxious, concerned, worried’?</note> when hearing <supplied reason="subaudible">something</supplied>. The consequences are: having imperfect hearing (<foreign>havar</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>havar</foreign> is not recorded in MdS as an ear disease. In MdS, its reduplicated form <foreign>hawar-hawar</foreign> means ‘faintly audible (sometimes: visible), vague (of sounds coming from afar, also fig. of rumors etc.); (of so. 's hearing) vague, indistinct, unclear’.</note> purulent ear (<foreign>coṅe</foreign>), deafness, <foreign>cadaṅ</foreign>,<note>The word <foreign>cadaṅ</foreign> is unclear and is not found in the dictionaries. Probably related to Mal. <foreign>radang</foreign> ‘disease in severe form’?  those would be the miseries of the ears.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.03">The eyes should not look wantonly, for instance the widow of someone else, the forbidden woman of someone else, if they are not ours. The consequences are: being blind in one eye (<foreign>pecak</foreign>), poor eyesight (<foreign>bolor</foreign>), <foreign>putikǝn</foreign>,<note>The word <foreign>putikǝn</foreign> is not recorded in MdS. This word is also attested in OJ SHK in the same meaning: <foreign>kadyaṅgān ikanaṅ vvaṅ lara matan putikən, ramun matanya</foreign> “like a man, whose eye is afflicted by <foreign>putikən</foreign>”. Probably related to Mal. <foreign>putik</foreign> ‘<foreign>buah yang masih muda dan kecil</foreign>’ (fruit that is still young and small) (Kamus Dewan, s.v.)?</note> white spot in the eye (<foreign>ceaṅ</foreign>), color-blindness (<foreign>buta loroṅǝn</foreign>),<note>The disease <foreign>buta loroṅǝn</foreign> seems to be an equivalent with <foreign>buta rorongeun</foreign> in MdS. It is a kind of eye disease. Danadibrata defines <foreign>buta rorongeun</foreign> as ‘teu bisa ngabédakeun warna’ (can not differentiate the color) = Mal. <foreign>buta warna</foreign>.’ Dadan Sutisna showed me an earlier publication in the 20{abad</foreign> century, that <foreign>buta rorongeun</foreign> refers to the person who is incapable of seeing during the night, but I am inclined to interpret it as color-blind in this context, since we have <foreign>mata kotokən</foreign> for night-blindness. Cf. SMG 14.2.</note> night-blindness (<foreign>mata kotokǝn</foreign>), <foreign>bilas susuhǝn</foreign>,<note><foreign>bilas susuhən</foreign>: <foreign>susuh</foreign> is a kind of freshwater snail (lime is burned from the shells) (Hardjadibrata, s.v), while <foreign>bilas</foreign> in MdS only attested in the form <foreign>bibilas</foreign> ‘dessert’, probably the basic meaning is ‘to wash’, cf. Mal. <foreign>cuci mulut</foreign>. The relation between ‘wash’ and a kind of snail is strange. I am inclined to relate <foreign>bilas</foreign> with MdS <foreign>balas</foreign> ‘parasitic growth on the skin, cyst, outgrowth (three types are distinguished: <foreign>balas bogo</foreign>, <foreign>balas bulé</foreign>, <foreign>balas reunghas</foreign>); <foreign>babalasan</foreign> s.m.; (also) name of destructive rice-plant disease.’ From the context, I guess we should relate it with a kind of eye disease that resembles a snail?</note> those would be the miseries of the eyes.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.04">The nose reacts quickly to all kinds of smell. If <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> smells stink, mouldy smell, rancid, burning smell, those provoke him to sneeze,<note>The word <foreign>bumarǝsin</foreign> is only attested in SMG, the possible base word is <foreign>barəsin</foreign>, which seems related to MdS <foreign>bersin</foreign> ‘to sneeze’, also in Malay ‘id.’.</note> to blow the nose (?, <foreign>ṅahubus</foreign>).<note>The meaning of <foreign>ṅahubus</foreign> ‘to blow the nose’ is a guess. This word is found nowhere in dictionaries, but it seems to be related to MdS <foreign>ngahébos</foreign> ‘struck against somewhere (in an outbreak of flames, heat radiation of a striking thunder flash or exploding gas, the hot breath of a demon, etc.)’ or Mal. <foreign>(h)embus</foreign> ‘to blow’.</note> The consequence is <foreign>mekmek</foreign>, that would be the misery of the nose.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.05">The tongue reacts quickly to all kinds of tastes. When <supplied reason="subaudible">it tastes the flavor of</supplied> stale, cold, foul-smelling, acidic, spicy, salty, it is used to taste everything (? <foreign>usuh-asahan</foreign>).<note>The meaning of reduplication with suffix <foreign>usuh-asahan</foreign> is obscure. My interpretation is based on the phonological resemblance with MdS <foreign>asa</foreign> ‘to taste’.</note> The consequences are: mute, tongue defect (?, <foreign>petal</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>petal</foreign> is unrecorded in dictionaries. Probably it is synonymous with <foreign>cadel</foreign> ‘lisp’?</note> lisp, all of those would be the miseries of the tongue.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.06">The mouth is used to gripe, only to be used to talk and whine,<note>We find a base word <foreign>kumapang</foreign> in MdS, which means ‘talk while crying’. It seems that the base is <foreign>kapaṅ</foreign>. The reduplicated form <foreign>kumapaṅ-kapaṅ</foreign> seems to mean ‘talk and whine’.</note> and also to be used for cursing and blaming, inviting others to do deceitful <supplied reason="subaudible">acts</supplied>.<note>I interpret <foreign>ṅajak ṅapus</foreign> as ‘inviting others to do deceitful acts’; cf. OJ <foreign>aṅapus</foreign> ‘to deceive’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>apus</foreign>, <foreign>aṅapus</foreign> 4).</note> The consequences are: harelips, wry lips, open mouth disease (?, <foreign>dǝda</foreign>),<note>The meaning of <foreign>dǝda</foreign> is dubious. I relate this word to Mal. <foreign>dedah</foreign> ‘exposed, opened, reveal’ but the meaning in the context of disease remains obscure.</note> those would be the miseries of the mouth.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.07">The skin is used to touch wantonly. If it is affected by hot, cold, itchy, tingling, <supplied reason="subaudible">then</supplied> it is tossed and turned. The consequences are: malignant boil (<foreign>tibar</foreign>), boil (<foreign>bisul</foreign>), foot-sole skin disorder (<foreign>boloṅǝn</foreign>), skin rash (<foreign>radaṅ</foreign>), smallpox (<foreign>kuris</foreign>), reddish skin (<foreign>beaṅ</foreign>),<note>The word <foreign>beaṅ</foreign> ‘reddish skin’ is equivalent to OJ <foreign>vyaṅ</foreign> ‘reddish colour’. Cf. the expression MdS <foreign>biang karinget</foreign>, also Mal. <foreign>biang keringat</foreign>.</note> including cyste (<foreign>balas</foreign>) <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> itchy skin eruption (<foreign>galigata</foreign>), those would be the miseries of the skin.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.08">The hand is used to grab wantonly, especially the property of others, the plants of others.<note>The preposition <foreign>ka</foreign> in <foreign>ka tatanəman</foreign> seems to indicate the direct object, because of the verb with motion <foreign>cokot</foreign> ‘to take’. We find several cases where the transitive verb of motion is followed by the preposition which functions to be the mark of a direct object, such as <foreign>ṅala</foreign> ‘to take, to collect’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> also used to clench the fist, to stab, to knock, to clasp, to slap, to pull hair, to pinch, to lash (?, <foreign>ṅagǝtil</foreign>).<note>The word <foreign>gǝtil</foreign> is probably related to MdS <foreign>gitik</foreign> ‘hit so./an animal (with a cane, whip, etc.), lash, whip; strike (the cymbals); impose st. on so. (a fine or a sentence); <foreign>ngagitikkeun</foreign> a. strike so. with st. (a cane etc.)’, or is it related to Mal. <foreign>sentil</foreign> ‘to flick’?</note> The consequences are bent fingers, arms that are stiff, cut off, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> difficult to move. Those would be the miseries of the hand.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.09">The anus<note>In MdS, <foreign>tumbung</foreign> means ‘germinating hole of a coconut; mouth of the vagina’. Rigg (1864) notes an interesting explanation: “<foreign>Tumbung</foreign>, pudendum muliebre. In Malay <foreign>Tumbung</foreign> means: the seed of plants, evidently from <foreign>Tumbu</foreign>, to shoot up. Thus the Sunda word will literally convey the idea of the place whence the human race springs. In Malay also Crawfurd gives Tumbung, <foreign>prolapsus uteri vel ani</foreign>. The final <foreign>ng</foreign> thus modifies the sense a little. <foreign>Tumbong</foreign> in Malay also, Marsden, page 81, is a hole in the surface of anything hollow; a vent or spile-hole; <foreign>the anus</foreign>. <foreign>Tumbong kalapa</foreign>, the hole in a cocoa-nut from whence it sprouts”. Not in OJ.</note> is used to fart wantonly, to defecate wherever one wants, on the side yard of somebody else’s house, let alone let off a fart against someone. The consequences are constipation (?, <foreign>kabǝratan</foreign>),<note><foreign>kabəratan</foreign>: in MdS, one of the meaning of <foreign>kabeuratan</foreign> is ‘to defecate’, it is a <foreign>lemes</foreign> register of <foreign>ngising</foreign>. My tentative interpretation ‘constipation’ is based on the context.</note> diarrhea (<foreign>tuju pañcar</foreign>),<note>I interpret <foreign>tuju pañcar</foreign> as diarrhea, based on the connection of <foreign>tuju</foreign> and <foreign>pancer</foreign> in MdS. In MdS, <foreign>tuju</foreign> means ‘(as the first member in the popular name of certain mostly connected with magically caused-sickness or afflictions); <foreign>tuju deleg</foreign> (O.) sickness that comes out in stomach pain and an inclination to vomit; <foreign>tuju rancah</foreign> s.m. fluid loss shortly before giving birth; (O. also mentioned: <foreign>tuju rawayan</foreign>, <foreign>tuju roroké</foreign>)’. The word <foreign>pañcar</foreign> seems to be equivalent to MdS <foreign>pancer</foreign> ‘cascading, shoot out’.</note> bleeding anus (<foreign>kaliṅsir</foreign>), sediment (?, <foreign>uirǝn</foreign>).<note><foreign>uirən</foreign>: in MdS, <foreign>uwir</foreign> means ‘torn piece (of paper, material, etc.); short note (accompanying letter, temporary license in lieu of the original, et.); <foreign>sauwir</foreign> a (torn) piece, etc., a leaf of paper’; cf. MdS <foreign>cewir</foreign>, <foreign>ewir</foreign> ‘id.’. In the context of stomach disease, probably it refers to urine sediment, but it remains a hypothesis.</note> Those would be the miseries of the anus.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.10">The genitals are used to pee wherever one wants. They are also used to seek boys and girls, transgress with younger siblings, elder siblings, children of younger siblings (<foreign>suan</foreign>), children of elder siblings (<foreign>kaponakan</foreign>). The consequences are hernia (<foreign>burut</foreign>), deformed <supplied reason="subaudible">genitals</supplied> (<foreign>petot</foreign>), <foreign>lañjo</foreign> (?),<note>The meaning of <foreign>lañjo</foreign> is unclear, but it is attested in OJ among the kinds of defects or diseases. Cf. Kuñj 63.19: <foreign>kǝḍi, kumiṅ, lañjo, kasesih, ayan, edan</foreign>. This context makes clear that it refers to a kind of genital disease. However, in MdS the similar word <foreign>lanjung</foreign> meand ‘light in the head, dizzy, giddy, confused’.</note> impaired sexual desire (<foreign>halaṅ visaya</foreign>), impotence (<foreign>pǝluh</foreign>). Those would be the miseries of the genitals.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.11">The feet are used to step wantonly, to walk carelessly, for instance when you walk to the north, south, west, east; if the feet happen to stumble, bump, or if they are used to kick. The consequences are weak feet (?, <foreign>lisuh</foreign>),<note>The translation of <foreign>lisuh</foreign> as ‘weak feet’ is tentative. I interpret this word as an equivalent of MdS <foreign>lusuh</foreign> ‘decreased, diminished, lessen, decline (of physical strength)’.</note> broken <supplied reason="subaudible">feet</supplied>, dog-like feet (?, <foreign>añjiṅǝn</foreign>), feet with outgrowth (?, <foreign>caniran</foreign>).<note>In MdS, <foreign>canir</foreign> means ‘buttress (boardshaped running outgrowth below the trunk of certain trees like the canary and ficus etc.; of which disc-wheels were made in the past)’. I guess that <foreign>caniran</foreign> refers to a kind of foot disease like a <foreign>plantar fibroma</foreign> (a fibrous knot, or nodule, in the arch of the foot).</note> Those would be the miseries of the feet.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_07.12">Thus are what are called the ten hells. The servants of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention, those <supplied reason="subaudible">actions</supplied> should not be followed.</p></div>
<div n="8" corresp="#smg_08"><p corresp="#smg_08.01">As follows are the five objects of attention. How so? The verse is as follows:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_08.02">“Non-anger, obedience to the teacher, purity, moderation in food, and non-inattentiveness are the five well known as particular commandments.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_08.03">The meaning is: <foreign>akrodho</foreign> means it does not happen to the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, that he shows his anger in front of the elder (teacher), let alone in front of all people. <foreign>Āhāralāghavam</foreign> means being unhurried<note>I render <foreign>sumari</foreign> to mean ‘to wait, to postpone, unhurried, leisurely, passing away the time with’ according to the meaning in OJ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>sari</foreign>), not in MdS.</note> in making preparations<note>My interpretation of <foreign>sumarəmbah</foreign> ‘to make preparation’ is based on an attested word in OJ <foreign>sārəmbha</foreign> (from Skt. <foreign>sārambha</foreign> ‘having made a beginning, ready to start, preparatory’). The term <foreign>āhāralāghavam</foreign> is related to the meal or food, so it seems that this is the meaning in this context. </note> for <supplied reason="subaudible">the meal</supplied>; it is improper to eat and to drink in front of the scholar. <foreign>Apramādas ca pañca vaite</foreign> means when there is something needed<note>The word <foreign>dipikən</foreign> seems to mean ‘to be intended, to be needed’, from <foreign>pikən</foreign> ‘intended for’. Cf. <foreign>piənan</foreign> in SMG 4.1.</note> by others, his attitude follows the one who is short-tempered and surly: one doesn’t want to think about oneself, and does not want to seek what will bring goodness <supplied reason="subaudible">for oneself only</supplied>. Those are called the five objects of attention.</p></div>
<div n="9" corresp="#smg_09"><p corresp="#smg_09.01">As follow are called the four means, as follows is the meaning:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_09.02">“Writing, laughing, singing, yawning, and pure <supplied reason="subaudible">from</supplied> the secret of fruit (?), shall not do in the front of the teacher”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_09.03">The meaning is: <foreign>ālekhyam</foreign> means it is improper if we scratch the ground, to write the board <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the couch in front of the teacher. <foreign>Hasitam</foreign> means it is improper to laugh when starting <supplied reason="subaudible">activity</supplied> in front of the teacher, and also to play around<note><foreign>ñiar pikaulinanən</foreign> ‘to play around’, literally means ‘look for things to play’. The circumfix <foreign>pi- -ən</foreign> from the secondary <foreign>ka- -an</foreign> in <foreign>pikaulinanən</foreign> form is rather rare in OS, but it is attested in SMG, for instance, <foreign>pikabuyutanən</foreign>.</note> in front of the scholar <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> in front of all people. <foreign>Gītam</foreign> means not singing <foreign>kiduṅ</foreign>, <foreign>kavih</foreign>,<note>I consider <foreign>kiduṅ</foreign> and <foreign>kavih</foreign> as two distinguished method of singing. See chapter 4, §Genres.</note> to sing loudly, let alone to claim oneself skilled, expert, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> wise in front of people. <foreign>Jr̥mbhanam</foreign> means it is improper to declare oneself thirsty and hungry, even though one is excessively full in front of the scholar, let alone of all people. <foreign>Kaṇṭhāravāñ</foreign> means, it is improper if we call <supplied reason="subaudible">someone</supplied> out loud, and also to stretch oneself in front of the people. <foreign>Śuddham</foreign> means it is improper if the mind and speech are disturbing<note>For the interpretation of <foreign>hura-hura</foreign>, cf. OJ <foreign>vurah</foreign> and <foreign>hurah</foreign>, in which their derivatives <foreign>mavurahan</foreign>, <foreign>ahurahan</foreign>, <foreign>pavurahan</foreign> mean ‘tumultuous, with a confused noise and/or motion’. Cf. Malay <foreign>hura-hara</foreign> ‘disturbance’ and later development <foreign>huru-hara</foreign>. Another meaning of <foreign>hura-hura</foreign> in Malay is ‘having a good time, happy’, also ‘party’ which seems unlikely in this context.</note> and false. <foreign>Phalarahasyam</foreign> means it is improper to mention the genitals<note>In MdS, <foreign>bobogaan</foreign> literally means ‘(various) things that some one possess, possessions (collect.)’, but also an euphemism for ‘genitals or private parts’.</note> of others. <foreign>Na karotu gurumukhe</foreign> means, it is improper if our mind and speech are careless (?, <foreign>rumagodeh</foreign>)<note>The interpretation of <foreign>rumagodeh</foreign> as ‘careless’ is a conjecture based on context, also by taking into account the phonological resemblance to MdS <foreign>lalawodéh</foreign> ‘careless, casual, off-hand (when working)’.</note> in front of the scholar. These are called the four means. The servants of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention, <supplied reason="subaudible">those actions</supplied> should not be followed.</p></div>
<div n="10" corresp="#smg_10"><p corresp="#smg_10.01">The following are called the five explanations. As follows is the verse:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_10.02"><foreign>selajanəm suravile, panatargasudya ceva, prayagamanəm, cevamasva cevamibuh, karmavidu, cevayude, danakaləm ma suprəgrahaste</foreign>.<note>10.1 I cannot reconstruct the Sanskrit stanzas in this <foreign>śloka</foreign>. The readings of SMG ms. A as well as manuscripts containing SiGu are corrupted in this part.</note></p>
<p corresp="#smg_10.03">The meaning is: <foreign>selajanəm</foreign> means to be indifferent and denying when talking and deliberating in front of the elder <supplied reason="subaudible">teacher</supplied>. <foreign>Suravile</foreign> means to be indifferent: especially when talking and deliberating, one does not apply good manners towards the scholar. Also, it is improper to use powders that are smelled by a lot of people, or <supplied reason="subaudible">when one</supplied> welcomes (<foreign>asvagatah kunaṅ</foreign>) <supplied reason="subaudible">them</supplied>. <foreign>Panatarga</foreign> means it is improper to brush teeth and to show teeth in front of people.<note>On the word <foreign>masaṅgereṅ</foreign>, cf. MdS <foreign>nyanggéréng</foreign> (from <foreign>sanggéréng</foreign>) ‘show clearly (the teeth of man or animal)’. It is noteworthy that <foreign>masanggéréng</foreign> (prefix <foreign>ma</foreign>- + <foreign>sanggéréng</foreign>) does not exist in MdS.</note> <foreign>Sudyacava</foreign> means it is improper to imitate the play of actors (<foreign>hǝmpul</foreign>) and buffoons (<foreign>mirus</foreign>). <foreign>Prayāsamāgama</foreign> means, it is improper if we stare at each other with other people, let alone to be face to face, to be face to face with the elders staring at each other, also to claim <supplied reason="subaudible">to have been</supplied> eating and drinking in front of people. <foreign>Ceva masvateh</foreign> means having wrong minds and intentions towards fellow humans. <foreign>Ceva mibuh</foreign> means having bad appearance, bad behaviors, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> not following advice. <foreign>Karmavidu</foreign> means having a wrinkled face,<note>The word <foreign>kǝsit</foreign> means ‘quick’ in MdS (cf. Mal. <foreign>gesit</foreign>), but does not seem to fit the context. Probably the meaning is ‘wrinkled (of face)’ (s.m. MdS <foreign>kusut</foreign>), a quasi-synonym of <foreign>tuṅi</foreign> ‘aloof, standoffish, surly, unfriendly’ = MdS <foreign>tungi</foreign>. Cf. one of the meanings of <foreign>kesit</foreign> in Mal. ‘<foreign>berkerut (tentang kulit tubuh dan sebagainya)</foreign> (wrinkled (about skin etc.)’.</note> being surly, wry-faced, sullen, <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> frowning<note>The word <foreign>baruṅut</foreign> is a hapax, my interpretation is based on a similar word in MdS <foreign>berengut</foreign> ‘frowning, gruff (of facial expression), surly, grumpy, churlish, ill-mannered’.</note> <supplied reason="subaudible">when</supplied> interacting with people. <foreign>Ceva yude</foreign> means having a bad appearance, bad behaviors, bad results,<note>The interpretation of <foreign>pupuna</foreign> as ‘his result’ is a guess. I take it from the verbal <foreign>mupu</foreign> ‘to collect, to take’, and a substantive form <foreign>pupu</foreign> is expected to have a meaning ‘result, something to be taken’. Or should it be emend to <foreign>pupulihna</foreign> ‘his words’?</note> those are called the lowest among people. <foreign>Ceva yude</foreign> means beset with troubles<note>The word <foreign>suraṅ</foreign> is not found in MdS and OJ. However, MdJ has <foreign>surang</foreign> ‘beset with troubles’ which is suitable to the context.</note> by making a joke, being fond of playing with <foreign>pariambul</foreign> words toward others. <foreign>Danakalǝm</foreign> means not willingly helping, having compassion, and love to fellow human beings. The mind is full of hate. <foreign>Suprigrǝhasta</foreign> means having too much desire, talking about our intention, bring it to the discussion wishing to realize it quickly, although it will not be achieved. Those are called the five explanations (<foreign>pañca-byakta</foreign>), those <supplied reason="subaudible">actions</supplied> should not be followed, 5.</p></div>
<div n="11" corresp="#smg_11"><p corresp="#smg_11.01">As follows are called the four devotions (<foreign>catur-paṅabakti</foreign>). The verses are as follows:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_11.02">“<supplied reason="subaudible">Through which</supplied> bad luck is left behind, having bowed down to the Lord of the Universe, I will recite the foot sole of the teacher.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_11.03">The meaning is: <foreign>gurutalam</foreign> means it is improper to speak and converse in haste in front of the scholar. <foreign>Pravakṣyāmi</foreign> means it is improper to talk about righteousness in front of the scholar, also in front of people, especially <supplied reason="subaudible">in front</supplied> of mother, father, and teachers. <foreign>Mahāyānam</foreign> means that one forgets to think about oneself. <foreign>Hi tiṣṭhati</foreign> means it is improper if we look at the elders with arrogance. <foreign>Durbhagahīne sarveśaṁ</foreign> means that one forgets what is in front of him, does not think of things which bring goodness. <foreign>Griyapa praṇamyāsīt</foreign> means one wish to quickly get rich and have everything,<note>My interpretation of <foreign>vaya-vaya</foreign> as ‘have everything’ is based on the context. Cf. Mal. idiom <foreign>orang berada</foreign> (from the base <foreign>ada</foreign> = OS <foreign>vaya</foreign>), denoting ‘the rich people’.</note> i.e. to have servants, subordinates,<note>The word <foreign>kuriṅ</foreign> ‘servant, slave’, also spelled <foreign>kuri</foreign> in some OS texts. It is noteworthy that In MdS <foreign>kuring</foreign> is a 1st singular pronoun, but the meaning ‘servant’ is not attested in MdS. This word is unattested in OJ.</note> workers, and livestock, and yet this <supplied reason="subaudible">wish</supplied> is not fulfilled. Those are called the four devotions, as told by the scholar.</p></div>
<div n="12" corresp="#smg_12"><p corresp="#smg_12.01">As follows are called the five objects of attention (<foreign>pañca-prayatna</foreign>). The verse is as follows:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_12.02"><foreign>hīnavākyam siṅharupañ ca grahaste</foreign> | <foreign>gurusaṅghāsanam prətanəm</foreign>, <foreign>grəhaste nāmani mate</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_12.03">The meaning is: <foreign>hīnavākyam</foreign> means it is improper to speak of goodness, to teach in front of the elder <supplied reason="subaudible">teacher</supplied>. <foreign>Siṅharupañ ca grahaste</foreign> means it is improper that we are seen angry by the elders and <supplied reason="subaudible">showing</supplied> dislike. <foreign>Guru saṅgasanǝm prītam</foreign> means it is improper if we <supplied reason="subaudible">shot that we</supplied> are happy, frolicking, joyful and pleased<note>I consider <foreign>grəjita</foreign> to be equivalent to OJ <foreign>garjita</foreign> ‘delighted, joyful, pleased, elated.’ (OJED, s.v.), from Skt. <foreign>garjita</foreign> ‘sounded, roared, bellowed; boasted, swaggered, vaunted’.</note> when we are on the street, <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> when we go to the forest to take trees and leaves, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> we sit there with legs wide,<note>The verb <foreign>ṅaduṅkak</foreign> seems to be equivalent with MdS <foreign>ngadéngkak</foreign> ‘spread the legs wide, sit straddling, sit with legs wide apart (like sitting on horseback, also of children carried on the hip: one leg at the front and one leg at the back)’. MdS has <foreign>dungkak-déngkak</foreign>, considered that <foreign>déngkak</foreign> is the base of intervocalic reduplication <foreign>dungkak-déngkak</foreign>, but in OS we find that the base <foreign>duṅkak</foreign> has an active form.</note> then we are seen by the scholar. Also, it is unpleasant for us <supplied reason="subaudible">to be</supplied> ahead in walking, and to be in the shadow of the elders.<note>The interpretation of <foreign>maṅka dinapak maya</foreign> as ‘to be in the shadow of’ is reasonably clear from the context. However, the verbal form <foreign>dinapak</foreign> is unusual since the prefix <foreign>di-</foreign> in OS and MdS is intransitive. It is clearly a translation of <foreign>anapak maya</foreign> in SiGu 5.3. Another possibility is to emend this phrase to <foreign>makadi napak maya</foreign>, but the conjunction <foreign>makadi</foreign> is extremely rare in OS. It is only attested in Kebantenan inscriptions.</note> <foreign>Prǝtanǝm</foreign> means it is <!-- until here 23 february from gdoc--> improper to smell the food of the teacher, let alone to use the utensils of the scholar, to take marked properties (<foreign>savenan</foreign>), and to take stored <supplied reason="subaudible">properties</supplied>. <foreign>Grǝhaste namaniṅ mate</foreign> means it is improper to mention the name of mother, father, as well as the teacher, and especially the elders, not to mention the name of king, village elders, hermits, ritual experts (<foreign>disi</foreign>), and sailors (<foreign>tarahan</foreign>). Those are called the five objects of attention (<foreign>pañca-prayatna</foreign>), according the scholar.</p></div>
<div n="13" corresp="#smg_13"><p corresp="#smg_13.01">The following are called three elements (<foreign>tri-buta</foreign>). These are the explanations: bad meets its bad,<note>On the word <foreign>goce</foreign>, cf. MdS <foreign>goté</foreign> ‘(coarse word for) bad; see <foreign>goréng</foreign>., but some dialects have <foreign>goté</foreign> ‘ugly’.</note> crooked meets its crooked, misery meets its misery.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_13.02">The meaning is: <foreign>hala</foreign> means bad; that the outcome<note>I interpret <foreign>pisampakǝn</foreign> as ‘outcome, what will be available or present’, from <foreign>sampak</foreign> ‘to be present’.</note> is bad because what has been practiced is bad. <foreign>Vilut</foreign> means crooked: that the outcome is crooked because what has been practiced is crooked. <foreign>Duka</foreign> means terrified: that the outcome is terrifying because what has been practiced is terrifying. Those are called the three elements. The servants of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention, those <supplied reason="subaudible">actions</supplied> should not be followed.</p></div>
<div n="14" corresp="#smg_14"><p corresp="#smg_14.01">As follows are called the four pacifiers (<foreign>catur-pasanta</foreign>). The following are its explanations: the formula of <foreign>jalakuna</foreign>, the formula of <foreign>jalapaksa</foreign>, the formula of <foreign>sambarana</foreign>, the formula of <foreign>taraṅgabahu</foreign>.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_14.02">The formula of <foreign>jalakuna</foreign> is the sun. Things which cause miseries to the body are: weak vision, monocular blindness, bilas, eye disease, color blindness, night blindness, dazzlement.<note>My interpretation of <foreign>hulap</foreign> ‘dazzlement’ is based on its meaning in OJ. This word is not recorded in MdS.</note> The formula of <foreign>jalapaksa</foreign> is the water. Things which cause miseries to the body are shivering<note><foreign>gumigil</foreign>: the word <foreign>gigil</foreign> is not found in MdS. The meaning ‘shivering’ is taken from OJ <foreign>gumigil</foreign> ‘ague, a fever’. Cf. Mal. <foreign>menggigil</foreign> ‘id.’.</note> and chills. The formula of <foreign>sambarana</foreign> is the wind. Things which cause miseries to the body are reddish skin, skin eruptions, skin fungal disease (?, <foreign>pipisisan</foreign>), every kind of skin disease. The formula of <foreign>taraṅgabahu</foreign> is the mountain. Things which cause miseries to the body are: headache, stomach ache, abdominal distention (<foreign>mǝdu</foreign>), abscess of the liver (<foreign>kavayaan</foreign>), every kind of disease in the stomach. Those are called the four pacifiers, that should be made of attention by the servant of the dharma, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> should not be kept secret.</p></div>
<div n="15" corresp="#smg_15"><p corresp="#smg_15.01">As follows are called the five misfortunes. These are the explanations: sorrow from the elements, sorrow from gods, sorrow from three worlds.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.02">The sorrows from the elements are: died from being bitten by the snake, being struck by lightning, bitten by the crocodile, crushed by branches, devoured by the tiger, death in battle, intercepted, attacked by many <supplied reason="subaudible">enemies</supplied>, died of falling <supplied reason="subaudible">from above</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">by</supplied> all kinds of weapons in the battle. That is called the sorrow from the elements.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.03">The sorrows from the gods are: diarrhea (<foreign>tajam bǝtǝṅ</foreign>), cold shivers, headache, sore eyes, <foreign>jaroṅ</foreign>-like disease,<note>See my comment on <foreign>jaroṅən</foreign> in SiGu 13.2.</note> <foreign>sumbilaṅ</foreign>-like disease,<note>See my comment on <foreign>sumbilaṅən</foreign> in SiGu 13.2.</note> madness, abdominal distention, fever. Those are called the sorrow from the gods.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.04">The sorrows from the body are: monocular blindness, cleft lip, crippled, blind, deaf, rash, cut (off ears?, <foreign>rumpuṅ</foreign>), cut off <supplied reason="subaudible">limbs</supplied>. Those are called the sorrow of the body. As for what is called the sorrow of the three worlds are all kinds <supplied reason="subaudible">of persons</supplied> who are affected by misfortune in the world.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.05">These are the examples of those who are affected by the miseries: kings, elders, hermits, ritualists, and sailors, for in the <foreign>kali</foreign>’s era, they are the roots of the sins that lead to suffering (i.e., hell), <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> become: the demon Kāla, the dogs called Jamproṅ and Karavǝlaṅ; <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> become a pair of cauldrons, strips of iron lances and spikes, in the village of destination, slanting plank bridge, <foreign>vajra</foreign>’s coconut (i.e, sugar palm?), the dirty mud, standing aslant branches, clutching rocks, the <foreign>rayang-rayang</foreign> called Prǝca Kala and Prǝca Kali, — <supplied reason="subaudible">also</supplied> the dissention and seduction (?, <foreign>beda bañcana</foreign>), a creation expert,<note>This word <foreign>siptaguna</foreign> appears twice in this paragraph: first it is applied to the goldsmith, and second to the carpenter. The meaning remains obscure since <foreign>sipta</foreign> is an unknown word. Tentatively, I relate this word with <foreign>cipta</foreign>, which means ‘to focus the thoughts on, to be of the opinion that; esp. to cause something to appear by focussing one's thought on it’. However, in the present context, <foreign>sipta</foreign> seems to mean ‘to create, to design’ as in the MdS sense of <foreign>cipta</foreign>. The change of /c/ to /s/ also occurs in the case of OS <foreign>isəs</foreign> > MdS <foreign>iceus</foreign>.</note> an iron expert, a banner expert,<note><foreign>patakaguna</foreign>: I interpret <foreign>pataka</foreign> as ‘flag, pennon, banner, sign’ according to the OJ meaning (OJED, s.v. <foreign>patāka</foreign>) The common meaning of <foreign>pataka</foreign> is ‘dissaster, misfortune’.</note> an image expert, a child (play?) expert.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.06">The meaning is precisely as follows: the balancing (?, <foreign>samya</foreign>) expert is the bracelet smith, the creation (?, <foreign>sipta</foreign>) expert is the goldsmith, the iron expert is the blacksmith, the banner expert is the cloth painter (? <foreign>pamadǝk</foreign>), the plant expert is the cultivator (<foreign>pahuma</foreign>), the creation expert is the carpenter, the composition expert is the actor (<foreign>hǝmpul</foreign>), the childsplay (? <foreign>kumara</foreign>) expert is the performer, the kala is the king’s servant, <supplied reason="subaudible">the dogs</supplied> called Jampong and Karawélang are <foreign>barat katiga</foreign>;<note><foreign>barat katiga</foreign>: in OJ, this word means ‘a strong wind in the third month’. Zoetmulder records its derived form <foreign>ambarat katiga</foreign> ‘like a strong wind in the third month’ (OJED, s.v. <foreign>barat</foreign>). This combination is also listed among military functionaries in Pdg 5.5 <foreign>ṅūni-ṅūni taṅ binoroṅ, sinəlir mvaṅ tinonton, vaju kuniṅ, vahuta, parujar, *praleki, untal-untal, barat katiga, ṅuniveh popoṇṭaṅ bhayaṅkara, popoṅo, vadvā barat</foreign> “let alone those who “are encouraged”, those who are picked and those who are watched [as they give performances?], the [wearers of] yellow garments, the <foreign>vahuta</foreign> officials, the spokesmen (?), the <foreign>pralekis</foreign>, the <foreign>untal-untal</foreign>s, the three <foreign>barat</foreign>s (soldiers?), and also the <foreign>popoṇṭaṅ</foreign> soldiers of the royal guard, the <foreign>popoṅo</foreign>s, the troops of the West (?)”. Cf. SKK 7.3.</note> the female animals (or prostitutes ? <foreign>rayang-rayang</foreign>) are those without a name, the dissention and seduction <supplied reason="subaudible">expert</supplied> is the merchant, the wide moor is the <foreign>lǝbuh</foreign>, <foreign>salaksi loñana</foreign> is the hunter, the end of the moon is the <foreign>prǝjala</foreign>, a sinful man is the gambler, a stained man is the servant (<foreign>dasa</foreign>); the one who accepts in marriage is the <foreign>calagara</foreign>, the one who extracts is the collector (<foreign>paṅuraṅ</foreign>)*, the standing branch is the provider (?, <foreign>parada</foreign>), the destination village is the helper (?, <foreign>kasasa</foreign>)*, the slanting plank bridge is the <foreign>pamǝǝṅ</foreign>*, the sugar palm* is the tapper (<foreign>pañadap</foreign>), the dirty mud* is the wet rice field farmer, the strips of thorns are the foresters (<foreign>paṅalas</foreign>), the clutching rocks are the matchmakers (<foreign>paṅavin</foreign>), the cauldron is the <foreign>pamǝñǝp</foreign>, the rice (? <foreign>naseya</foreign>) is the rice cooker, the wood-log is the pounder (<foreign>panutu</foreign>); the fire is the kitchen guardian (<foreign>tuṅgu dapur</foreign>), the one who cooks is the <foreign>harǝp catra</foreign>; the water is the one who usually takes water for bathing; the cinder is the sweeper (<foreign>pañapu</foreign>); the livestock <supplied reason="subaudible">expert</supplied>* is the chicken farmer, the boar farmer, the duck farmer; the one who <!-- finished 23 feb fn.118 google doc--> gives <supplied reason="subaudible">food</supplied> is the herdsman; the one who guards the lake, the one who guards the garden, anyone who guards domestic animals — <supplied reason="subaudible">all of them</supplied> are being enslaved by the god, <supplied reason="subaudible">they are</supplied> obstructed, used as hands and feet <supplied reason="subaudible">of the god</supplied>, do not have any power on their lives, on their destinies. That is called the misfortune from the three worlds.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_15.07">These are called the sorrow from the three worlds (<foreign>tri-bvana-loka</foreign>): the city is on fire, the harvest is failed, destroyed by disease, a long dry-season in an anomalous period, all kinds of fruit <supplied reason="subaudible">trees</supplied> do not bear fruit, all animals are scattered around <supplied reason="subaudible">dead</supplied>. That is called the sorrow of the three worlds. <foreign>ma, ṅya buku, u, sa, a</foreign>. Those are called the five misfortunes as said by the scholar, 5.</p></div>
<div n="16" corresp="#smg_16"><p corresp="#smg_16.01">Again, as follows is what should be remembered by the servant of the dharma. There are what are called the five animals (<foreign>pañca-triyak</foreign>). These are the explanations: domestic animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>), birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>), snakes (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>), fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>), <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> creeping animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_16.02">Domestic animals (<foreign>pasu</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the settlements; birds (<foreign>paksi</foreign>) are all kinds of animals on the side <supplied reason="subaudible">of the settlement</supplied>; snakes (<foreign>sarpa</foreign>) are all kinds of animals whose chest touch the ground; fishes (<foreign>mina</foreign>) are all kinds of animals in the water; creeping animals (<foreign>pepelikan</foreign>) are all kinds of animals having a shell, who crawl without being discovered. Their length of time from hell is 1100 years. Those are called the five animals.</p></div>
<div n="17" corresp="#smg_17"><p corresp="#smg_17.01">The following should also be remembered. There are what are called the four roots. These are the explanations: <foreign>mantaja</foreign>, <foreign>urija</foreign>, <foreign>payuja</foreign>, <foreign>bagaja</foreign>. <foreign>Mantaja</foreign> means all kinds <supplied reason="subaudible">of things</supplied> born from the eye; <foreign>urija</foreign> means all kinds <supplied reason="subaudible">of things</supplied> born from the mouth; <foreign>payuja</foreign> means all kinds <supplied reason="subaudible">of things</supplied> born from the anus; <foreign>bagaja</foreign> means all kinds <supplied reason="subaudible">of things</supplied> born from sexual organs. The length of time <supplied reason="subaudible">before one who has sinned with those organs comes back</supplied> from hell is 100 years. Those are called the four roots, as declared by the scholar.</p></div>
<div n="18" corresp="#smg_18"><p corresp="#smg_18.01">As follows are called the four strengths (<foreign>catur-virya</foreign>). The meaning is: what is called joy is used to be hot tempered. The wealth is used to be rich. The hot temper is used to be overcome <supplied reason="subaudible">…</supplied>. The strength is used to give <supplied reason="subaudible">excessively</supplied> to those who are far, to those who are near, to the family and relatives. Those are called the four strengths. Those should be paid attention to, <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> should not be followed by the servant of <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p></div>
<div n="19" corresp="#smg_19"><p corresp="#smg_19.01">The following are called the release (<foreign>kalǝpasǝn</foreign>). There are the holy immaculate four practices. This is the explanation: the people who are farmers, who are healthy (<foreign>purna</foreign>)*, who are very self-controlled (<foreign>sudanta</foreign>)*, who turned out well (<foreign>lastare</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_19.02">The farmer (<foreign>tani</foreign>) means: <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> are advance in harvesting, tapping, putting the yoke, making quick ripening (? <foreign>ñavara</foreign>), taking care of the livestock, planting the crops. That is called the farmer. Those who are healthy (<foreign>purna</foreign>) means <supplied reason="subaudible">those who</supplied> do not have defects and diseases, <supplied reason="subaudible">and who</supplied> do not act like ordinary people. That is called <foreign>purna</foreign>. <foreign>Sudanta</foreign> means <supplied reason="subaudible">those</supplied> who can not be redeemed <supplied reason="subaudible">as a slave</supplied>, <supplied reason="subaudible">or</supplied> be strongly obstructed by debt. <foreign>Lastare</foreign> are people of the village who do not have illness, who do not have weakness. That is called <foreign>lastare</foreign>. Those are called the four ordinances (<foreign>catur-kalpa</foreign>), as declared by the scholar. All that should be kept aside by the servant of <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p></div>
<div n="20" corresp="#smg_20"><p corresp="#smg_20.01">This is what should be prioritized, <supplied reason="subaudible">namely</supplied> what are called the three bodies (<foreign>trikaya</foreign>), which are claimed as the source of beauty, the origin of splendor. There is what is called the pure circle of three bodily domains, as declared by the great scholar. <foreign>Tri</foreign> means three, <foreign>kaya</foreign> means what makes firm, <foreign>mandala</foreign> means the body, and what is called <foreign>suda</foreign> is already well known.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_20.02">Obey to the three bodily acts, as declared by the teacher, the three bodily acts of the world and of the people. What would those that are called the three bodily acts according to the teacher be? These are their metaphors: “Like the priceless gem and the desired gem, and also the real essence of gold.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_20.03">As follows is the threefold good. These are their kinds: pacifying thought, pacifying speech, pacifying intelect*.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_20.04">That which is called good actions, the explanations of good actions is: showing respect, being faithful, honoring, being respectful, being afraid and fearful (i.e. being polite), agile, modest, careful, thorough, diligent, persevering, charitable. Those are called good actions.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_20.05">The good speeches are <supplied reason="subaudible">the words which are</supplied> friendly*, soft*, caring and loving, full of sympathy* and compassion, persuasive*, cooling the heart, praising*, polite, propitiating; all kinds of perfect speeches. Those are called good speeches.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_20.06">The good mind means: <supplied reason="subaudible">like</supplied> “a clean side yard, a bright garden, a broad yard, a wide cultivated land”; it is put in action for giving food, money, clothes, girls <supplied reason="subaudible">in marriage</supplied>, and so on. Those are the four meritorious acts. Because of that <supplied reason="subaudible">one gets</supplied> a stable intellect, a clear mind, broad thinking, a good intellect which is like a polished* jewel, like the water on the <foreign>sulang</foreign>* leaves, as a result of his good mind. That is called the pure circle of three bodily domains, as declared by the scholar.</p></div>
<div n="21" corresp="#smg_21"><p corresp="#smg_21.01">These are called the four goodness. The verse is as follows: “The gold, silver, luminous bezoar (<foreign>komala</foreign>), diamond”. The meaning is: the gold is a truthful, sincere, and correct word, the manifestation of the five sacred syllables. The silver means the perfect, meritorious, and good mind. The luminous bezoar means that his emotions are bright and shining, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> his thoughts are clear and broad. The diamond means to have a cheerful*, smiley, agile, and joyful mind.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_21.02">This is the other meaning: what is called the gold is the pure gold, what is called the silver is the most desirable jewel, what is called luminous bezoar is the priceless jewel, what is called the diamond is the glowing gold*. Those are called the four types of goodness.</p></div>
<div n="22" corresp="#smg_22"><p corresp="#smg_22.01">As for this one, it is the essence of goodness, called the ten holy virtues (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ dasa-sila</foreign>). <foreign>Dasa</foreign> means ten, <foreign>sila</foreign> means quality. These are the explanations: ear, eye, nose, tongue, mouth, skin, hand, sexual organs, anus, foot. Those are called the ten holy virtues*.</p></div>
<div n="23" corresp="#smg_23"><p corresp="#smg_23.01">These are called the ten paths (<foreign>dasa-marga</foreign>). <foreign>Śrotra</foreign> means ears. What is the sphere of ears? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should hear. <foreign>Cakṣuh</foreign> means eyes. What is the sphere of eyes? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should see. <foreign>Ghrāṇa</foreign> means the nose. What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should smell. <foreign>Jihvā</foreign> means the tongue. What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should taste. <foreign>Vāk</foreign> means the mouth. What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should speak about. <foreign>Tvak</foreign> means the skin. What is the sphere of the skin? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should touch. <foreign>Pāṇi</foreign> means hands. What is the sphere of hands? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should grasp. <foreign>Pāyu</foreign> means anus. What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should release. <foreign>Pastha</foreign> means penis. What is the sphere of the penis? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should discharge. <foreign>Pāda</foreign> means feet. What is the sphere of the feet? What is bad should be avoided; goodness is what you should step on. Those are called the ten paths.</p></div>
<div n="24" corresp="#smg_24"><p corresp="#smg_24.01">These are called the ten sense faculties. The sense of hearing resides in the ears. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The sense of sight resides in the eyes. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. It is the exit place of the mind. Its function is to perceive form and color. The sense of smell resides in the nose. It exists in you; <supplied reason="subaudible">it is</supplied> the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to smell. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The sense of taste resides in the tongue. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to taste the six flavors. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The sense of speech resides in the mouth. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to speak. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The sense of touch resides in the skin. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to touch. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The faculty of holding resides in the hands. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to seize. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The faculty of relief resides in the anus. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to fart. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. The sexual faculty resides in the penis. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to have sexual intercourse and to urinate. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. sThe faculty of walking resides in the feet. It exists in you; it is the instrument of the holy soul. Its function is to walk. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the exit place of the mind. Those are called the ten virtues.</p></div>
<div n="25" corresp="#smg_25"><p corresp="#smg_25.01">This is called the ten personalisations. What is claimed by them is the hearing, the sight, the smelling, the speaking, the releasing, the urinating, the walking. There is the one who claims for himself, there is the one who hears, there is the holy floating jewel. It is called the ten personalisations.</p></div>
<div n="26" corresp="#smg_26"><p corresp="#smg_26.01">These are called the ten highest principles. These are the explanations: there are ears, there is hearing, there is the hearer, there is the highest principle. There are eyes, there is viewing, there is the viewer, there is the highest principle. There is nose, there is smelling, there is the smeller, there is the highest principle. There is tongue, there is taste, there is the taster, there is the highest principle. There is the mouth, there is the speech, there is the speaker, there is the highest principle. There is the skin, there is the touch, there is the toucher, there is the highest principle. There is the hand, there is the grasping, there is the grasper, there is the highest principle. There is the anus, there is the releasing, there is the releaser, there is the highest principle. There are the sexual organs, there is the urinating, there is the one who urinates, there is the highest principle. There are the feet, there is the walking, there is the walker, there is the highest principle. Those are called the ten highest principles.</p></div>
<div n="27" corresp="#smg_27"><p corresp="#smg_27.01">These are called the ten pacifiers. This is their explanation: donation (<foreign>dāna</foreign>), morality (<foreign>śīla</foreign>), forbearance (<foreign>kṣānti</foreign>), strength (<foreign>vīrya</foreign>), meditation (<foreign>dhyāna</foreign>), wisdom (<foreign>prajñā</foreign>), compassion (<foreign>karuṇā</foreign>), sympathy (<foreign>mudita</foreign>), friendship (<foreign>metrī</foreign>), endurance (<foreign>upekṣā</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_27.02">The meaning is: donation (<foreign>dāna</foreign>) means to give enjoyment to others. Morality (<foreign>śīla</foreign>) means to know etiquette (<foreign>tvah</foreign>). Strength (<foreign>vīrya</foreign>) means to strive to be continuously truthful, to strive to do goodness. Meditation (<foreign>dhyāna</foreign>) means to consider his own mind. Wisdom (<foreign>prajñā</foreign>) means to be quick to get rid of the bad things of oneself. Compassion (<foreign>karuṇā</foreign>) means his heart would be weak* while thinking for himself and does not want to make others sad. Sympathy (<foreign>mudita</foreign>) means not to forget the others’ skill. Friendship (<foreign>metrī</foreign>) means to know the good deed, to make the others feel at ease. Endurance (<foreign>upekṣā</foreign>) means not being bothered by the good and the bad. Those are called the ten pacifiers (<foreign>dasa-pasanta</foreign>).</p></div>
<div n="28" corresp="#smg_28"><p corresp="#smg_28.01">This is what should be seriously done, what is called the ten grounds. These are the verses:</p>
<p rend="stanza" corresp="#smg_28.02"><foreign>agəm rahayəm gunyam</foreign> | <foreign>tvah citane haləm</foreign> | <foreign>kurvanti kuśalam mahat</foreign>*</p>
<p corresp="#smg_28.03">The excellent meritorious conduct should be carried out. The excellent meritorious conduct means: love (<foreign>asih</foreign>), devotion (<foreign>bhakti</foreign>), persevering effort (<foreign>prayatna</foreign>), respectability (<foreign>gorava</foreign>), honesty (<foreign>duga-duga</foreign>), calmness (<foreign>śānta</foreign>), compassion (<foreign>karuṇa</foreign>), sympathy (<foreign>anumoda</foreign>), consideration (<foreign>anumāna</foreign>), respectful* mutual dependence (<foreign>ālambana atəaṅ</foreign>). Those are called ten grounds.</p></div>
<div n="29" corresp="#smg_29"><p corresp="#smg_29.01">These are called the ten superiorities (<foreign>dasa-visesa</foreign>). As follows is the meaning: the Holy* hearing is not heard, because He is the one who hears, the Holy one who cannot be used as hearing. The Holy sight is not seen, because He is the one who sees, the Holy one who cannot be used as sight. The Holy smelling is not smelled, because He is the one who smells, the Holy one who cannot be used as smelling. The Holy taste is not tasted, because He is the one who tastes, the Holy one who cannot be used as taste. The Holy speech is not spoken, because He is the one who speaks, the Holy one who cannot be used as speech. The Holy touching is not touched, because He is the one who touches, the Holy one who cannot be used as touching. The Holy grasping is not grasped, because He is the one who grasps, the Holy one who cannot be used as grasping. The Holy release is not released, because He is the one who releases, The Holy one who cannot be used as releasing. The Holy urinating is not urinated, because He is the one who urinates, the Holy one who cannot be used as urinating. The Holy walking is not moving, because He is the one who moves, the Holy one who cannot be used as motion. Those are called the ten superiorities.</p></div>
<div n="30" corresp="#smg_30"><p corresp="#smg_30.01">These are the ten supreme superiorities (<foreign>dasa-mahavisesa</foreign>). The Holy organ of hearing is materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of sight is materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of taste is materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of speech is materialized in your body, it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of touch is materialized in your body; it is supreme because of the Supreme One, <supplied reason="subaudible">for the organ of touch itself</supplied> is not superior. The Holy organ of grasping is materialized in your body; it is supreme because of the Supreme One. The Holy organ of release is materialized in your body; it is supreme because the Supreme One, <supplied reason="subaudible">for the organ of release itself</supplied> is not superior. The Holy organ of urinating is materialized in your body; it is supreme because the Supreme One, <supplied reason="subaudible">for the organ of urinating itself</supplied> is not superior. Those are called the ten supreme superiorities.</p></div>
<div n="31" corresp="#smg_31"><p corresp="#smg_31.01">These are called the ten non-superiorities (<foreign>dasa-tan-kavisesa</foreign>). The meaning is as follows: There is no hearing, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no sight, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning and vice in yourself. There is no smelling, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no taste, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no speech, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning and vice in yourself. There is no touch, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no grasping, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no release, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no urinating, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself. There is no walking, nothing is materialized in your body, there is no means for sinning in yourself, none of them.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_31.02">The meaning is: there is no one who hears, no one with form, no one who smells, no one who speaks, no one who touches, no one who grasps, no one who eats, no one no one who drinks, no one who tastes, there are no divine <supplied reason="subaudible">embodiments</supplied> for them. Those are called the ten non-superiorities.</p></div>
<div n="32" corresp="#smg_32"><p corresp="#smg_32.01">Furthermore, my lesson for the servant of the dharma is as follows: There is what is called the four splendours; it is <supplied reason="subaudible">also</supplied> called the four principles. This is the meaning: <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> serve as the boat, <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> serve as the ship, <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> serve as the ark, <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> serve as the junk. What is compared to the boat is the pacified act, what is compared to the ship is the pacified speech, what is compared to the ark is the pacified thought, what is compared to the junk is the stable* <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> pacified awareness. They are called the one of Siddha-nature (<foreign>sidajati</foreign>), the lord among yogins (<foreign>yogisvara</foreign>), the scholar (<foreign>pandita</foreign>), the men of religion (<foreign>viku</foreign>). Those are called the four splendours, those are called the four principles.</p></div>
<div n="33" corresp="#smg_33">
<p corresp="#smg_33.01">These are called the four purities. The pure and transparent jewel is still, the pure jewel is clear, the pure jewel is white, those are the pure seat of thought (<foreign>cita</foreign>)*.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_33.02">The following is also to be taken into account carefully. There is what is called the origin of goodness. It is that which is extraordinary and very secret. It is the holy virtue.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_33.03">This is called the release, the holy purity. It is called the four final liberations (<foreign>catur-mokta</foreign>): release, disappearance, vanishing, dissolution. That is called the four final liberations. That should be kept in secret by the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p></div>
<div n="34" corresp="#smg_34"><p corresp="#smg_34.01">This is the six and two*. The meaning <supplied reason="subaudible">is in the words</supplied> <foreign>ndah saṅ hyaṅ hayu</foreign>. The meaning is: <foreign>nən</foreign> is like the king who thinks, who reflects carefully when he is on the sacred throne, emerges from the condition of stability. That is called <foreign>nən</foreign>. The <foreign>dah</foreign> is the willingness to present the possessions to the king, elders, hermits, ritualists, and sailors. The <foreign>saṅ</foreign> means, it is said, single; there is certainly no second, and also no third. What is called <foreign>hyaṅ</foreign> is the relic of the past. What is called <foreign>hayu</foreign> means lightweight, it is said, the body is like a flower-bud and a kapok fiber. Those are the truths. That is the one who <foreign>aroṅe</foreign>*?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_34.02">This is the meaning of two: that is one man <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> one woman, it is called two. Three means the king, the elder, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the hermit, 3. Five means Brahma, Wisnu, Iswara, Mahadéwa, Siwa Sangkara; Kusika, Garga, Méstri, Purusya, Patañjala; Indra, Yama, Baruna, Kuwéra, Bésawarna. That is called the five gods. Seven means: the seven underworlds, the seven middle worlds, the seven upperworlds, the seven voids, the Absolute. That is called the account of the creation (<foreign>kalpa-carita</foreign>)*.</p></div>
<div n="35" corresp="#smg_35"><p corresp="#smg_35.01">These are called the three in number: three categories (3), three inconclusive <supplied reason="subaudible">propositions</supplied> (3), the means of knowledge (4), the artificial knowledge* (4). These are the breath, the speech, and the people’s mind, which surround* (<foreign>narivrəta</foreign>) the world, which sink (? <foreign>ñəluman</foreign>) into the trees, into the rock, into the earth, into the water, into every kind of plant, into the animals (3).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.02">These are the three <supplied reason="subaudible">existing</supplied> in the scholar. It is called the <foreign>tiga sadana</foreign>: <foreign>tiga</foreign> means three, <foreign>sadana</foreign> means element.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.03">These are called the three truths. This is <supplied reason="subaudible">the syllables</supplied> <foreign>a</foreign>, <foreign>ña</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> <foreign>na</foreign>. That is called the three true words.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.04"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil</supplied>: “Where can the three be found in the scholar? Show your favour to your son <supplied reason="subaudible">by revealing</supplied> about the location where the <foreign>a</foreign>, the <foreign>ña</foreign>, and the <foreign>na</foreign> can be found!”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.05"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> “So be it. As follows. First I will explain the equality and the difference, your means to know the truth of the three. What is the meaning of the <foreign>vari</foreign>, <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> <foreign>asoka</foreign> flowers? You should explain! Are they identical?”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.06"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> “So be it. They are different, my lord. The <foreign>vari</foreign> flower is still the <foreign>vari</foreign> flower. The <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign> is still the <foreign>srigadiṅ</foreign>, the <foreign>asoka</foreign> is still the <foreign>asoka</foreign>, my lord. Please tell <supplied reason="subaudible">me</supplied> your words.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.07"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> “The three are like that, the means to evaluate the equality and the difference in a sincere, truthful, rightful, and clearly perceived manner.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.08"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> “First of all, here is the instrument to evaluate the equality and the difference of the <foreign>a</foreign>. What is entering and exiting by means of the nose and of your mouth, <foreign>upamāna praveśanam</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> its use in your body?”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.09"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> “The wind as breath, my lord. That is what is called <foreign>a</foreign>, according to the scholars.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.10"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> “As follows is what could also be asked regarding that <supplied reason="subaudible">issue</supplied>. What is the name that is heard, as the thunder and thunderous noise of all beings? What are the<supplied reason="subaudible">ir</supplied> names, according to you?”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.11"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> “The sound, my lord! That is called the <foreign>ña</foreign>, according to the scholars.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.12"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> “As follows is what could also be asked, there is nobody who knows about it. What is the meaning of that which is caused by you to reach the limit of the world: north, south, west, east, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> in a wink it crosses the ocean, disappears and comes back again in an instant? What is your opinion, my son?”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.13"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> “The mind, my lord! That is called the na, according to the scholars.</p> <p corresp="#smg_35.14">That is the reason why they are called breath, speech, and mind, which are spread through the world. Those are called the three instruments. They are the means to reach the world; <supplied reason="subaudible">they</supplied> are used as a support for all beings.”</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.15">These are the activities in the body. <foreign>Bayu</foreign> serves as the vital principle, entering and exiting your nose; it serves as your breath. It is considered right, correct, and clearly perceived. It is called the truth in the body. <foreign>Sabda</foreign> means the speech. It is used to define the bad and the good, to name vowels and consonants. It serves as your speech. <foreign>Hǝdap</foreign> means the mind, your thoughts directed towards the near and the far.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_35.16">The <foreign>a</foreign> is the breath, the <foreign>ña</foreign> is the speech, the <foreign>na</foreign> is the mind. <supplied reason="subaudible">They are</supplied> the content of the three knowledges (<foreign>tiga ajñana</foreign>), which are the first argument of the scholars. They should be taught <supplied reason="subaudible">as follows:</supplied> <foreign>tiga</foreign> means three, <foreign>ajñana</foreign> means the place to be reached (<foreign>kasampəran</foreign>). It is the Great Supreme (4).</p></div>
<div n="36" corresp="#smg_36"><p corresp="#smg_36.01">Furthermore, this is called the innate knowledge. It can not be given to the pupil, it can not be faked. The knowledge and the real are the origin of the Supreme One.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_36.02">This is the excellent <supplied reason="subaudible">principle</supplied>, the origin of joy and sorrow, what is pleasant <supplied reason="subaudible">and unpleasant?</supplied>. That is the reason why <supplied reason="subaudible">it is</supplied> the origin of power and strength, the origin of being respected, the origin of being endowed, the origin of being venerated in the case of the scholar. As for the existence of the breath, speech, and mind in your body: if the breath, speech, and mind vanish in your body, <supplied reason="subaudible">it means that one</supplied> ceases to be venerated, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> ceases to be worshiped.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_36.03">The mind is used as the mind by wisdom. The mind is manifold. It is the truth and correct. It is truly perceivable in the body. It is called the three truths. <foreign>Tri</foreign> means three, <foreign>tǝpǝt</foreign> means superior.</p></div>
<div n="37" corresp="#smg_37"><p corresp="#smg_37.01"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> This is their union. The “straight” is the thought, far and near. Its entire life and its targets are not hindered by the difficulties. It reaches the edges of the world-egg, <supplied reason="subaudible">including</supplied> heaven and the underworlds, unseen during day and night. It is called “to achieve the ultimate” <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>boṅboṅ botos</foreign></supplied> and “to completely dissolve” <supplied reason="explanation"><foreign>buṅbaṅ lǝpas</foreign></supplied>*. Those whose desires, all <supplied reason="subaudible">of them</supplied>, are true and <foreign>rasti</foreign> <supplied reason="explanation">?</supplied> are leaving without being noticed. What is the meaning of such <supplied reason="subaudible">teaching</supplied>?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_37.02"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> <supplied reason="subaudible">This is</supplied> the thought indeed, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_37.03"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> That is the holy knowledge, according to the scholar. It is the union of the three truths. When the beauty <supplied reason="subaudible">of knowledge</supplied> is thrown away, it is called the carcass. That is the reason why supreme knowledge is the origin of ultimate excellence.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_37.04">What is the form of what is called the truly priceless? This is your metaphor: like the court filled with the gold, jewel, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> priceless clothes of the worthy king. All of that is truly priceless. Thus <supplied reason="subaudible">far</supplied> about the existence of the holy breath, speech and mind. Thus is the supreme knowledge in your body.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_37.05">Indeed, the holy knowledge regarding the living as a householder (<foreign>momah</foreign>), of breathing, of speaking, of thinking is no other than the holy supreme knowledge. Its meaning is to be kept as a secret by the pupil of the scholar.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_37.06"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> So be it. This is fortunate.</p></div>
<div n="38" corresp="#smg_38"><p corresp="#smg_38.01"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> This is my word, the endless wisdom. Is there any breath, speech, and mind in you, my child?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.02"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> Yes, they exist, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.03"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> Is it seen by you?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.04"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> No, my lord. It is proper to regard it as existing. Anything that is felt and touched, it exists in the world and in the body, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.05"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> Such <supplied reason="subaudible">answer</supplied> is true. Does the speech exist?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.06"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> It exists, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.07"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> Such <supplied reason="subaudible">answer</supplied> is true. Is the speech seen by you?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.08"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> No, it is not seen, my lord. It is proper to regard it as existing. All that is heard, it exists in the world and in the body, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.09"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> Does the mind exist in you?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.10"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> It exists, my lord.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.11"><supplied reason="subaudible">Teacher:</supplied> Is it seen by you?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.12"><supplied reason="subaudible">Pupil:</supplied> No, it is not seen, my lord. It is proper to regard it as existing. All that is thought, far and near, exists in the world and in the body.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.13"><supplied reason="subaudible">Master:</supplied> You are right to know in this way. That is the reason why what is called the Holy Invisible <supplied reason="subaudible">essence</supplied> is clearly perceptible; it exists perpetually in the body and <supplied reason="subaudible">in</supplied> the world, there is nothing else.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_38.14">This is the activity of the breath, the speech, and the mind: the appellation of the breath, speech, and mind (3), the demonstration of the breath (6). This is the five tasks ordered by the king (5), the five organs (5), the teaching about the way to vanish (3), the highest truth (<foreign>paramarta</foreign>) (4), the ultimate isolation (4), the eight supernatural powers (8), the section of knowledge (3), <foreign>kisiñan</foreign>;(?) (8), unperceived by faculties (<foreign>anendriya</foreign>)* (3), the gross and subtle elements (4). These are the numbers of the section of knowledge; the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign> should pay attention to them.</p></div>
<div n="39" corresp="#smg_39"><p corresp="#smg_39.01">This is called the addition (2), the state of the <foreign>viku</foreign>s (4), the naming <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the personalisation <supplied reason="subaudible">of</supplied> the reverend teacher. This is what should be made an object of attention by the one who searches for the truth. <supplied reason="subaudible">It is</supplied> the holy knowledge: the reason that <supplied reason="subaudible">it is</supplied> the possession of one who possesses, the reason that it is not used as a possession, like the enjoyment <supplied reason="subaudible">of consumption</supplied> (<foreign>boga</foreign>), enjoyment <supplied reason="subaudible">of living properties</supplied> (<foreign>pariboga</foreign>), enjoyments of appearance (<foreign>rupaboga</foreign>)*. What is that which is called <foreign>boga</foreign>, <foreign>pariboga</foreign>, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> <foreign>rupaboga</foreign>?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.02">As follows: what is called <foreign>boga</foreign> is food and drink; <foreign>pariboga</foreign> is the slave, servant, buffalo, cow, any kind of livestock; <foreign>rupaboga</foreign> is gold, jewel, fine lower cloths for a worthy king, that is, the ornaments of a divine king. The possession is the supreme knowledge, to be used as the embellishment <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> as the ornament of the substance of the individual (<foreign>vastu si vvaṅ</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.03">In addition, O child of the scholar, what will be thought should be absorbed, about what is called the substance of the individual.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.04">Let it be so! <supplied reason="subaudible">I</supplied> teach you as follows: what is called a worthy person is the one of true being (<foreign>saṅ sat-hana</foreign>), <supplied reason="subaudible">which is</supplied> not created. It is the source. It is called the root of the origin and the end. It is called pure nature. It is called the source of the mother and father. It is regarded as the secret. It is called the paramount <foreign>dharma</foreign>, who carries out all the actions in the world. He creates without joining <supplied reason="subaudible">all the other beings in</supplied> being created. That is why what is called “Someone” (<foreign>si anu</foreign>) does not come from the treatises, does not come from the teacher, <supplied reason="subaudible">but</supplied> it is from oneself (<foreign>na śāstrataḥ na gurutaḥ svataḥ</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.05">The meaning is: <foreign>na śāstrataḥ</foreign> <supplied reason="subaudible">means</supplied> cannot be found by the means of scriptures and wisdom; <foreign>na gurutaḥ</foreign> is <foreign>kaimariṅun</foreign> (?). What is sought <supplied reason="subaudible">by him</supplied> is penetrated and filled. It cannot be used as a means, it cannot be instructed, by (<foreign>ri</foreign>) the teacher. It is only from oneself. It exists without being made into existence: no wife, no son, no relatives, no mother, no father: <supplied reason="subaudible">it is</supplied> from oneself. The meaning is: <foreign>na bhārya</foreign> is not having a wife, na <foreign>putraḥ</foreign> is not having child and grandchild, <foreign>na mātā</foreign>, <foreign>na pitam svataḥ</foreign> is not having a father, not having a mother.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.06"><foreign>Avismṛtidṛṣṭi</foreign> (the sight of one who is not forgetful). He sees without being seen, knows without being known, embodies without being embodied, blows the vital air <supplied reason="subaudible">into other beings</supplied> without being blown the vital air into <supplied reason="subaudible">by any other beings</supplied>, speaks without being spoken, thinks without being thought. He appears just at the same time with his body, his breath, his speech, and his mind, in the embryo-abode in the past. When he appears in the external <supplied reason="subaudible">world</supplied>, he is called “Someone”.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.07">That is the reason why the Someone else is called the one having difficulty, namely, its ignorance about the world and the universe is extraordinary, is not knowing the father and the mother of the whole world, and the child of the world. Who is the one who is knowledgeable? It is only the scholar, no one else.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_39.08">O, child of the learned master, “Someone” will emerge from what are called parents.</p></div>
<div n="40" corresp="#smg_40"><p corresp="#smg_40.01">Indeed, the following is my love for you (5). These are the <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers. The meaning is as follows: <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers means cotton, the color means a thread, the cognition (<foreign>vri</foreign>) means fabric.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.02">The meaning is: what is called <foreign>vari</foreign>s flowers is the body, what is called the thread is the mind, what is called fabric is the individualized divine emanation (<foreign>saṅ hyaṅ pramana</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.03">The meaning is: he uses his mind as the sight, he uses his two eyes as the gate, he uses his breath as the vital principle, he uses his speech as the means of realizing, he uses his body as the abode, he uses the world as the gate.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.04">The ‘red’ is a color, the meaning is that <supplied reason="subaudible">he</supplied> knows what he sees. The gate to see the varis flowers is the two eyeballs. The instrument to see the varis flowers is the mind. It means that he knows his sight. Who is the one who sees the <foreign>varis</foreign> flowers?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.05">It is you, son.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.06">The skill (3), the truth (1), its <foreign>panatab</foreign> (?) (3), the liberated soul (9), inconceivable, <foreign>icaluṅ</foreign> (?), <foreign>i</foreign> (?), to carry over the shoulder, <foreign>ba</foreign> (?), the big trees (<foreign>kayu magəṅ</foreign>).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_40.07">This is the five gross elements (5), the five forms <supplied reason="subaudible">of suffering</supplied>, (5), the five paths (5). All of that should be made the object of the attention of the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>.</p></div>
<div n="41" corresp="#smg_41"><p corresp="#smg_41.01">As follows is the esoteric teaching, the beginning of the scholar telling about the <supplied reason="subaudible">five</supplied> sections. The esoteric teaching (<foreign>sandi</foreign>) means the consciousness. It serves as the direction of the world and all beings. That is the reason why <supplied reason="subaudible">every being in</supplied> the whole world does not <supplied reason="subaudible">come to existence</supplied> with a wrong body and with a wrong condition. All the beings are following, in the right direction, their father and their mother, and their origin and particular nature: humans give birth to humans, animals give birth to animals.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_41.02">What is called penance (<foreign>tapa</foreign>) is as follows. What is the essential meaning of it? The purity (<foreign>si lilaṅ</foreign>). What is the reason it is called purity? Its explanation is as follows: it is aware to have the world and the body as properties.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_41.03">Likewise, the posture (<foreign>luṅguh</foreign>), what is the essential meaning of it? The firmness. It is true indeed that The Witness is firm in his knowledge of the manifest and unmanifest world. What is the firmness of The Witness in the manifest world? He does not follow along <supplied reason="subaudible">others</supplied> in prioritizing sacred formulas, mantras, the mantra <foreign>huṅ</foreign>, a lotus-like hand (<foreign>padmakara</foreign>)*, and also performing worship and healing spells (<foreign>jampa-jampya</foreign>). You do not follow those in prioritizing the way of penance, observances, yoga, and concentration. He is not seduced by any kind of supernatural powers (<foreign>guna</foreign>). Those are the firmness of The Witness in the manifest world. What is the firmness of The Witness in the unmanifest world? He should not be involved in demonic <supplied reason="subaudible">activities</supplied>.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_41.04">Likewise, the direct perception (<foreign>pratyaksa</foreign>), what is its essential meaning? The impossibility. What is the meaning of impossibility? This is its nature: Does The One know about the impossibility of the whole world being used as its world? No. Does The Witness know that the body is used as its body? No. Does the The Holy Dharma know that the smell is used as its smell? No. Does the Holy Virtue know that the colour is used as its colour? No. Does The Divine Emanation know that the breath, speech, and mind are used as its life? No. Does The Supreme One know that the speech is used as its means to define? No. Does The Holy Secret know that the mind is used as an instrument of thought? That is called the impossibility.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_41.05">Where does the impossibility and the application of the impossibility come from? As follows: the consciousness in the mind. There is the most desired jewel, beautiful and fulfilling. The Witness is the most desired jewel and the great unconceivable one. It <supplied reason="subaudible"><foreign>manik sarvesta</foreign></supplied> is treated with much fondness by the holy dharma.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_41.06">What is that which is called the most desired jewel, beautiful and fulfilling? It is the mind. What is the beautiful jewel belonging to ‘the creator (<foreign>anuṅ vidi</foreign>)’? It is consciousness. What is the beautiful jewel and the greatly inconceivable one? It is The Witness. Those are called the three secret words. The secret of the scholar is not found by the servant of the dharma.</p></div>
<div n="42" corresp="#smg_42"><p corresp="#smg_42.01">What are called the three secrets, that is the breath, the speech, and the mind? Those which are called the three secrets are not the three means. The meaning is: what is called the three secrets according to the great teacher?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.02">Indeed, as follows is its form: that is the mind, the consciousness, the witness. Those are called the origin of existence. What is the explanation of the origin of existence, my lord? The illustration about that is as follows: like the lamp, the flame, and the light.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.03">Are the flame and the light identical, my lord?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.04">No, they are not like that. The flame, the light, and the fire are different. The flame and the light are coming out from the fire. Their outcome dies with the fire, going back to their origin; their original condition dies.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.05">What is its explanation? Prepare the torch already! Its nature is to suddenly flame firmly, and at the same time, is to be extinguished. The appearance of the flame is <supplied reason="subaudible">also</supplied> the appearance of the light. In a similar way they are extinguished. The swallow of the flame and the light, they are swallowed and vanished simultaneously. The mind and the consciousness, as well as the witness are likewise.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.06">What is considered the fire? The individualized divine emanation. What is the flame? The mind. What is the heat and the light? The esoteric <supplied reason="subaudible">consciousness</supplied>. The meaning is: the mind, the consciousness, <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> the witness. Those are called the origin of existence (3).</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.07">This is the means of individualization, like the painter, the action <supplied reason="subaudible">of painting</supplied>, and the brush; like the bronze and the wax, along with the silver. The meaning is: the mind, the consciousness, the witness. Those are called the means of individualization of existence.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.08">This is the meaning that the fire is different. What is the explanation? Prepare the lamp, that is, its wick is set ablaze. <supplied reason="subaudible">The fire</supplied> that stands and flames, quickly shines. Its measure stands in the same direction (satuduhan). That is called the flame. What is spreading out <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> filling the house, it is called the light. What is shining as small as a fire-fly, and the red on the top of the wick, that is called the fire. This is the proof that the fire is different from the flame and the light. Where to the destination of the flame and the light? Does it go to void and non-existence? No, it is not like that.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.09">What is the meaning of all of this, <supplied reason="subaudible">about the fire</supplied> going to the void and non-existence? No, it is not like that. What is the meaning of all this, <supplied reason="subaudible">namely</supplied> the flame, along with the light and its fire, going to the void and non-existence, according to another <foreign>viku</foreign>? No, it is not according to the scholar. You should not <supplied reason="subaudible">say</supplied> like that.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.10">Where would be the destination of the torch and its light? They go to the state that exists. The meaning is: like the egg, like the seed of mango, like the rice-straw, like planting in the rice field, like the flowers and the yarn, sa, a.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.11">That is called the work of the Lord. This is the power of the Great One. This is the power of the Supreme One. Me means I, the one who truly exists, which is not created, the holy one who exists by itself, who creates which does not follow <supplied reason="subaudible">others</supplied> in being created. Because I am the life-giving power which is not the embodiment of the living power (<foreign>kapramanaan</foreign>). I am the Supreme which is not the embodiment of the Supreme. That is called the three supreme secrets.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.12">This is its means of tatab (? <foreign>panatabna</foreign>). The world has ceased to support, the body has ceased to serve as the abiding place, the breath has ceased to be the vital principle, the speech has ceased to be used as a means to put into effect, the mind has ceased to be produced, the consciousness has ceased to be the instrument of action, the witness has ceased to act upon. This is the explanation according to the noble master.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.13">This is the means of their union (<foreign>pamupul</foreign>). The mind has ceased to be created, the consciousness has ceased to be used as an instrument to create, the Witness has ceased to create. That is called the means of the union.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.14">This is the means of coloring (? <foreign>pamulas</foreign>). The mind acknowledges (? <foreign>maṅku</foreign>) that it has ceased to be made upon by that (<foreign>tutur</foreign>); the consciousness acknowledges (? <foreign>maṅku</foreign>) has ceased to create by way of that (<foreign>hədap</foreign>); the Witness, consequently, has ceased to act by way of people. It is called its means of coloring.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_42.15">This is called its fixation. It is not seen. What is made and the instrument of action, let alone the one who acts are visualized. For the mind is subtle. It has ceased to be created. The consciousness is invisible. It has ceased to be created. The Witness is inconceivable. Those are called the process of fixation, of what is called the three secrets.</p></div>
<div n="43" corresp="#smg_43"><p corresp="#smg_43.01">Likewise is the release. What serves as the secret by him to act? That is called the process of fixation. The creation (<foreign>krataka</foreign>) and the sharing task (<foreign>si dum</foreign>). The meaning is: The Witness will know the means to the act, <supplied reason="subaudible">He</supplied> will know to arrange his acts in the material <supplied reason="subaudible">and</supplied> immaterial world.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_43.02">What is your analogy? Like the goldsmith. The one who gave the order comes. <supplied reason="subaudible">He says:</supplied> “Please make for me a bracelet and a ring”. The smith says “I already abandoned my work. It was already given by me to the assistant. The occupation is abandoned by me. Already a long time that the skill was left by me.” The one who gave the order then left, he was looking for another smith.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_43.03">Likewise also the individualized divine emanation. “The painter” has ceased to create. The Witness has ceased to cause the consciousness. All of them have ceased to be constitutive elements <supplied reason="subaudible">of the human being</supplied>. That is why that is called being apportioned <supplied reason="subaudible">according to their original prerogatives</supplied>: have limit without being limited with regard to their manifest and unmanifest activities. The meaning is: that is called the release according to the scholar.</p></div>
<div n="44" corresp="#smg_44"><p corresp="#smg_44.01">What is called the epitome is like that. Seek the essence of the truth, without being turned into untruth! What is your analogy? Like the fibres of the palm rib broom. Their number being great, they are held together (?, <foreign>kasigənan</foreign>) by the single tie. All the teachings are like that.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.02">The Holy Supreme, He creates what serves as the essence with respect to the direct perception (<foreign>pratyaksa</foreign>)*. It is true that the Witness knows about the demonic substance, which serves as the sin of the posture (<foreign>luṅguh</foreign>). It is true that the Witness will know about the one who has attachment which serves as its sin. The one without attachment serves as the supreme power in the penance (<foreign>tapa</foreign>). It is true that the Witness will know the unconsciousness which serves as its sin. The consciousness serves as its supreme power with regard to the esoteric <supplied reason="subaudible">teaching</supplied> (<foreign>sandi</foreign>). Do not let the Witness join them, insofar that such <supplied reason="subaudible">involvement</supplied> is sinful. Those should be considered cautiously by the servant of the <foreign>dharma</foreign>, according to the great scholar.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.03">The following is called the beginning of writing. What is pointed out by the scholar about the beginning of writing, absolutely without any doubt whatsoever? What serves as the essence of it? As follows: the muscle of the right and left hands, the writing on the palms of the hands. Those are called the hands. There is nothing lacking in them, there is nothing that is slipping away from the moving hands.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.04">The following is the second <supplied reason="subaudible">part</supplied> of writing. Its form is as follows: the manifestation is the riddle words. It serves as the challenge of the scholar. What does it refer to? As follows: both pupils. The meaning is: the conduct of life is the conduct of speech; the meaning is: the conduct of intellect is the conduct of knowledge, the conduct of esoteric <supplied reason="subaudible">knowledge</supplied> is the conduct of mind. Likewise, the individualized divine emanation and the supreme are united with the secret, their nature is to disappear simultaneously all together. There is not <supplied reason="subaudible">even</supplied> the knowledge that they have already been released. They are the content of the second part of writing, according to the foremost master, which is paid full attention by the servant of dharma.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.05">The following is the third part of writing, the beginning of the master discussing the secret, that is the origin of the self divine emanation. If one realizes its own self, that is the Supreme Dharma. It releases from the world, it departs from the body. The breath, the speech, and the mind are not embodied. Moreover, <supplied reason="subaudible">they are</supplied> the ultimate void and emptiness, free from disturbance, pure, unobstructed. That is the perpetual dharma that exists in the body.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.06">It continuously flames and shines, not being extinguished by day and night, also in the manifest and unmanifest <supplied reason="subaudible">worlds</supplied>. It has been shown based on the true nature (vastu) by the master. You should not have any doubt! They are the content of the third part of writing, which is paid full attention by the servant of dharma, it is the word of the lord of yogins.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.07">The following is called the fixed number of four. The meaning is: life, death, sleep, and unconsciousness. Those serve as the place of the Witness in material and immaterial reality. They are shown by the scholar to the servant of the dharma.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_44.08">The gross body is death. You see the body, small and little. It is seen for an instant only. As for the subtle body, that is regarded as sleep, it serves as your body while dreaming. As for the pure body, that is called the unconsciousness which is void, absence, and the ultimate reality. These are called the fixed number of four. The Witness, the life and the Soul does not manifest: clear, silent, unhindered; perpetual, steadfast, independent. All beings are like that. Those <supplied reason="subaudible">i.e. kalakar pat</supplied> are called the king of sins. The King Witness does not manifest in material and immaterial world, meaning that it serves as the essence of the fixed number of four. It should be thought carefully by my child, the servant of the dharma, according to the lord of yogins.</p> </div> <!-- mari saṁsaya ta kita denya, mari meliḥ na<space type="binding-hole"/> ta kita, saṁ hya pramana, manilvalita saṁ hya visesa, ka, tan· na svaga, tar nahala, tar na hayu, tar na su<lb n="35v4" break="no"/>ka, tar na duka, Iya ta rasaniṁ pati ṅaranya, katəmvan ikaṁ manivan·, ri sala niskala, Apa ta maryikən·n ika hala, hala hayu, suka duka, ṅəkeri bvana sarira, ṅaniveḥ Ikaṁ sarvvajan·ma kabeḥ <!-\-SSMG_L621_36r.JPG-\->
<pb n="36r"/>
<lb n="36r1"/>Ana saṁ hyaṁ pramana, juga tan· hana vaneḥ nihan· sinaṁguḥ rahasye pandi ṅaranya, -->
<div n="45" corresp="#smg_45"><p corresp="#smg_45.01">The following is called the secret of the scholar. What is the detailed explanation of it? As follows, there is your analogy: like the Witness, after the individualized divine emanation is blissful (<foreign>hayu</foreign>), when it is released from the world, freed from the body, <supplied reason="subaudible">it</supplied> being only the everlasting consciousness and the deepest point of esoteric knowledge. What is the everlasting consciousness and the deepest point of esoteric knowledge?</p>
<p corresp="#smg_45.02">Their meanings are as follows: “As the fire <supplied reason="subaudible">which is</supplied> in every piece of wood is not perceived because of <supplied reason="subaudible">its</supplied> subtlety.” The meaning is: it is not found. You have ceased to be doubtful about it, you, the individualized divine emanation, have ceased to be hesitant, the holy supreme has ceased to be tremulous.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_45.03">The meaning is: it is not heaven, nor the bad, nor the goodness, nor the joy, nor the sorrow. That is called the essence of death. The experience of The Witness in the material and immaterial <supplied reason="subaudible">worlds</supplied>. What causes one to give up the bad and the good, the joy and the sorrow, here in the world and the body, and in all beings? It is only the individualized divine emanation, nothing else. Those are called the secrets of the scholar; they should be clearly understood by the servant of the dharma, according to the noble scholar, 4.</p></div>
<div n="46" corresp="#smg_46"><p corresp="#smg_46.01">As follows are the instruction words, the climax of the scholar who ceases to teach the servant of the dharma, the climax of the teacher who ceases to teach the pupil, the climax of the pupil who ceases to ask the teacher.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_46.02">How is it so? As follows: like the jewel with the crystal, likewise are the scholar and the servant of the dharma. If they have understood about all holy dharmas, each of them, the servant of the dharma and the teacher are one, the one who teaches and the one who asks are united. The scholar has ceased to teach the servant of the dharma, the lord of yogin has ceased to ask.</p>
<p corresp="#smg_46.03">The meaning is: if all of them already know, also, their individualized divine emanations are equally priceless, meaning that they equally return to their original nature. That is called the instruction words. It should be paid attention to by the servant of the dharma, according to the noble great scholar.</p></div>
<div n="47" corresp="#smg_47"><p corresp="#smg_47.01">This is what should be paid attention to, the holy book called Sasana Mahaguru. It has been completely written in the fourth month. Accomplishing the writing at the region Mahapavitra on Mount Jedang. The product of an ugly side job. The one who writes is an amateur boy who weighs the gold. Apologize for the ugly writing like the trace of a crab in the sand. If something is missing, please add it, if it is too much, please reduce it, because it is the work of a stupid one.</p> </div> </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
