<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSchema.rng" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/erc-dharma/project-documentation/master/schema/latest/DHARMA_CritEdSQF.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="eng" type="translation" corresp="#sarasamuccaya"> 
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main" subtype="translation">Sārasamuccaya</title>				
				<respStmt>
					<persName ref="part:ekba">Eko Bastiawan</persName>
					<resp>Typing of the Old Javanese parts (2020–2021)</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<persName ref="part:argr">Arlo Griffiths</persName>
					<resp>General supervision and quality control</resp>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>DHARMA</authority>
				<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
				<idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSarasamuccayaVararuci_transEng01</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
						<p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by John Doe.</p><!-- Replace year and name, use format "Forename1 Surname1 & Forename2 Surname2" or "Forename1 Surname1, Forename2 Surname2 & Forename3 Surname3"  if necessary — the copyright is that of the encoder(s) -->
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<date from="2019" to="2025">2019-2025</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<!-- <notesStmt><note><bibl>Digital translation of <bibl><ptr target="bib:"></ptr></bibl>.<relatedItem target=""></relatedItem></bibl></note></notesStmt>-->
			<!-- provide a notesStmt if you need to add some precision regarding the establishement of the translation -->
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull> <titleStmt>
					<title>Sārasamuccaya</title>
					<respStmt>
						<persName>Unknown</persName>
						<resp>Typing of the Sanskrit parts</resp>
					</respStmt>
					<respStmt>
						<persName>Eko Bastiawan</persName>
						<resp>Typing of the Old Javanese parts (2020)</resp>
					</respStmt>
					<respStmt>
						<persName>Arlo Griffiths</persName>
						<resp>Structuring of the TEI file and quality control</resp>
					</respStmt>
				</titleStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
						<authority>DHARMA</authority>
						<pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
						<publisher>EFEO</publisher>
						<idno type="filename">DHARMA_CritEdSarasamuccayaVararuci</idno>
						<!-- Replace by filename, e.g. DHARMA_CritEdSiksaGuru -->
						<availability>
							<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
								<p>This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Unported Licence. To view a copy of the licence, visit https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street, Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.</p>
								<p>Copyright (c) 2019-2025 by Arlo Griffiths and Eko Bastiwan.</p>
							</licence>
						</availability>
						<date from="2020" to="2025">2020-2025</date>
					</publicationStmt>
				</biblFull>
				<!-- if your translation is a copy of already published one: fill a biblStruct -->
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc> 
			<projectDesc>
				<!-- Part mandatory -->
				<p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 809994).</p>
				<p></p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="part:axja" when="2021-10-26">Adding the link for the RelxNg and the </change>
			<change who="part:axja" when="2021-06-12" status="draft">Creation of the template</change>
			<!-- replace this by a line that has you as @who, that has the @date on which you finished the first basic encoding of the file, and that has the following description of what was finished on that date: "Initial encoding of the file." Then add a <change> entry for each significant change to the file. -->
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:space="preserve">
      <body>
      	<div>

<head>May there he no impediments.</head>
<p>His Reverence Vararuci collected all the essentials of the Mahabharata, the
composition of His Reverence Vyāsa, to whom Vararuci pays homage in the
following verse.</p>
<quote>Obeisance to the Great Seer, of vast learning and supreme nobility, who dispels
the darkness of ignorance, the son whom Satyavatī begot out of her own being
from Parāśara, in the midst of an island.</quote>
<p>There was a great seer. There was nothing he did not know. He was
honoured in the three worlds. He dispelled the darkness of ignorance of all beings.
He was the son of Her Ladyship Satyavatī, begotten of her union with His Reverence
Parāśara. He was horn in the middle of the Kr̥ṣṇa island. His name is
His Reverence Vyāsa. Before this person should communicate the essence of his
wise composition, he must pay his homage to His Reverence.</p>

<p>As the very big ocean and as the Himālaya mountain are known to he the
mines of precious objects, so is the Bharata.</p>
<p>Now its superiority. As the ocean and the Himālaya mountain are the mines of gold, jewels and ol all precious things, so is this whole composition of his, i.e. the Mahābhārata, which is a dharmaśāstra. This (MBh.) is the ripe product of the superior rasas of primaeval esoteric knowledge.</p>



<p>This narrative is the eternal subsistence of master poets, just as a king of noble lineage is the subsistence of dependents who strive to rise.</p>

<p>Out of this excellent narrative are created poetic faculties. It is like the five elements out of which the mechanism of the three worlds is formed.</p>

<!-- differences in pādas cd -->

<p>There is no tale in this world which does not hang on this narration. It is like unto a body which maintains itself on food.</p>

<!-- @@@@ 2021-11-08 Arlo has revised the file using Ando2018_01 down to here -->

<p>After having heard this narrative another narrative will sound insipid. 
Just as after having listened to the notes of a male cuckoo, the harsh cries of a crow jar
on one's ears.</p>
<p>Something more about this excellence. If somebody has enjoyed the hearing
of this story how would it he possible for him to enjoy another tale or a song or a flute. 
When the music of a cuckoo has pervaded the heart with the sweetness of its melody 
then one would hardly find pleasure in listening to the cawings of a crow.</p>
<p>Thus spoke Bhagavān Vararuci while paying his obeisance to Bhagavān Vyāsa. 
Henceforth he will say what is best in this Bhārata epic. It is designated Sārasamuccaya. 
Sāra signifies essence. Samuccaya is its accumulation. It is the work of Bhagavān Vararuci. 
This didactic discourse was delivered at the time of the narration of the Bhārata epic 
by Bhagavān Vaiśampāyana to Mahārāja Janamejaya.</p>

<!-- argr: the txt file used for the Sanskrit now presents the following lines, which don't agree with anything we see in Raghu Vira 1962
	antarviṣayāḥ [gopyatām] 1 jīvanasyoddeśyaḥ 2 dharmaḥ 3 dharmaḥ 4 cāturvarṇyam 5
	trikāya 6 manaḥ 7 īrṣyā 8 kṣamā 9 krodhaḥ 10 nāstikyaṁ 11 satyam 12 ahiṁsā 13
	astenyam 14 paradāra 15 suśīla 16 dānam 17 guru 18 yamaniyamavrata 19 arthaḥ 20
	sukham 21 tīrthayātrā 22 daridraḥ 23 saṁsargaḥ 24 sādhuḥ 25 asādhuḥ 26
	pūrvakarma 27 mr̥tyuḥ 28 pitr̥yānadevayāna 29 bodhaḥ 30 strī 31 rāgadveṣa 32
	tr̥ṣṇā 33 mokṣaḥ jīvanasyoddeśyaḥ[sampādyatām] i -->

<p>You, scion of the Bharata race, in the field of dharma, artha, kāma and mokṣa, 
whatever is recorded here that is to be found elsewhere, and what is not recorded 
here is not to be found anywhere else.</p>


<p>Among all beings man alone performs good and evil acts. 
If one be engrossed in evil, he should be taken across towards good.</p>

<p>If one be devoid of prosperity one should not be unhappy about it. 
The human frame even though as a pariah is most invaluable.</p>

<p>This birth is the foremost, O King! Having acquired it one is able to save himself by noble deeds.</p>


<p>One who does not remedy the hell-disease while he is in the incarnation of man, 
what then will he do when he goes to non-human incarnations where he lacks the remedy
of doing conscious noble deeds.</p>


<p>Having acquired the human frame which is difficult of attainment and 
which forms a ladder to heaven, one should act in such a manner that 
one does not slip down again.</p>


<p>O Brahman, the human incarnation forms the domain of action. 
Beyond is the domain of enjoyments of their results. Whatever deeds are performed here,
they are enjoyed hereafter. The birth here below is the region of doing acts,
noble or ignoble.The next world is the region of enjoyment of the fruits of actions. 
The meaning is that the actions good or evil are done here while their
fruit is obtained hereafter, and when the enjoyment comes to an end, one is
again born in order to follow vāsanā for fruits of actions. Vāsanā is saṁskāra or
impression. It is the wee bit of odour that is left over. It is followed by punishment. 
He falls from beyond, which may be either heaven or hell. Now as regards
good or evil actions that may be done in hell or heaven, they yield no fruit. 
Hence one should perform actions good or evil in this world only.</p>


<p>Having attained the human body which is difficult 
to acquire and which lasts only as long as a flash of lightning, 
one should determine destroying existence and its instruments.</p>


<p>The person who having been born as a man, which is not at all easy, and who out of greed and because of having given himself up to passion, comes to disregard dharma, he indeed loses all.</p>
<!--ekba: How do we encode for the unknown item, Mas?-->

<p>Human birth is extremely difficult to attain. It resembles a flash of lightning.
If having acquired that one does not escape out of saṁsāra, one is undone.</p>

<p>I raise my arms and cry but no one listens to me. Artha and kāma flow 
from dharma. So why do people not pursue dharma?</p>

<p>Seeking kāma and artha one must start with the pursuit of dharma. 
By ignoring dharma there is neither artha nor kāma.</p>

<p>Respect is paid to a man of dharma, and not to one who is rich or given to passion. 
In riches one may find a bit of happiness, but in dharma there is absolute bliss.</p>

<p>For those sailing to heaven, dharma is the only raft. 
Dharma is the boat for merchants who must cross over to the other shore of the ocean.</p>

<p>One may make efforts for kāma, artha and mokṣa and fail, but an endeavour in dharma, even a thought, is not wasted. It bears fruit.</p>

<p>Just as the rising sun drives away all darkness, so stationing oneself in good one drives away all evil.</p>

<p>As one's mind advances in the enjoyment of doing good, so do all one's projects come to fruition. Here there is no doubt.</p>

<p>Dharma always brings benefit. It is the refuge of the noble. The three worlds, together with all that moves and that does not move, flow from dharma.</p>

<p>One, whose mind constantly treads the path of dharma and does not deviate, him they call the man of noble deeds. His kith and kin have no worry with regard to him.</p>

<p>Water that irrigates sugarcane helps the weeds too. Similarly, walking the way of dharma, one gains riches, fame and worldly desires.</p>

<p>Whatever one has sown, that one reaps—ample loveliness and charm, birth in a noble family, wealth and prosperity in high measure.</p>

<p>Men of dharma have no fear in inaccessible jungles and forests, in calamities, in difficult situations, in battle or when facing uplifted arms ready to strike.</p>

<p>Those who act nobly get as their reward lovely women after their own hearts. They reside in palaces.</p>
<!--ekba: It seems that attribute "sameAs" does not fit in this case?-->

<p>Friends and fortunes fly to men of noble acts, just like frogs hurrying to ponds and birds flying to waterful lakes.</p>

<p>The wise one accumulates knowledge and worldly goods slowly and steadily 
as if he would never come to end. But when he comes to dharma he acts as if he 
has no time to lose, as if death itself has caught hold of him by his hair.</p>

<p>If this person should perceive death which is standing on the forehead, he would have no taste even for food, let alone the taste for pursuing ignoble ends.</p>

<p>One should seek dharma, wealth and wisdom while still young. When old the blade of darbha grass bends and is unable to pierce. </p>
<!--ekba: same case as stanza 30-->

<p>One who remains unsubdued by passions in youth, he alone is termed restrained. When passions lose their fury in old age, restraint is natural.</p>

<p>A child looks forward to youth, a youth to old age, but having mounted into the lap of death, what does an old man look up to?
</p>

<p>First death, piloted by disease, breaks the human frame. So, when life declines, one must perform great good.</p>

<p>One should take to dharma while young. Life is uncertain. Who knows as to when death's armies will strike.</p>
<!-- Raghu Vira says "compare in a general way" MBh05,040.016; the correspondence is only very partial -->

<p>When one dies, his kinsmen follow him upto the burning ground, and return when the smoke has subsided. It is only his good deeds that accompany him beyond. Therefore it is these which he must cultivate.</p>

<p>People accompany the corpse, they shed tears for a moment, then they leave it as if it were a log of wood or a clod of clay, and turn their faces away.</p>

<p>Dharma alone is the highest good. Forbearance is tranquility. Knowledge is supreme satisfaction. Non-injury brings joy. </p>

<p>Had there been one single scripture, it would have been an undoubted gain. On account of the variety of scriptures good has been put into a deep cavern.</p>

<p>My child, do not insult or ignore the elders. Sit at their feet and learn. The ways of dharma are like those of the snake, fine and untraceable. </p>

<p>Śruti is the four holy Vedas. Smṛtis are the dharma scriptures. It is these two, śruti and smṛti, which have to be consulted in all matters. They hold the dharma.</p>

<p>The four divisions of society (Brāhmaṇas and others), the four worlds, as well as the four stages of life (brahmacārī, etc.), the past, the present and the future—all flow from the Veda.</p>
<!-- it would be nice to do without this punctuation -->

<p>Veda is to be supplemented with itihāsa and purāṇa. Veda is afraid of a man of little knowledge—he will strike (प्रहरिष्यति) me.</p>

<p>The highest dharma is taught by śruti. Another is the dharma laid down in smṛti. Still another is the behaviour of men of truth and piety. These three dharmas are ancient and everlasting.</p>

<p>Do not do to others what is disagreeable to your own self. This is dharma in brief. All else proceeds from kāma.</p>

<p>Follow the actions of pious men, who are well-restrained, who are devoted to truth and simplicity and who are treading the path of dharma. </p>

<p>Like a car's wheel, dharma revolves and covers an all-over domain. It is as hard to determine the exact nature of dharma as it is to determine the father of a harlot's son.</p>

<p>Listen to the quintessence of dharma. And having listened hold on to it. What you do not approve for yourself, that you must not do to others.</p>

<p>Empty grains among cereals, winged ants among birds–similar is the position among humans of those whose motivation is not dharma.</p>
<note>Kawi has misinterpreted puttikāḥ as pūtikāḥ 'rotten eggs'.</note>

<p>Common men are like weeds. They serve neither dharma nor kāma. They die so that they be born. They are born so that they may die.</p>

<p>There are persons whose minds are fogged and revile dharma. They go on the wrong path. Any one who follows them suffers torments.</p>

<p>The dull-witted have no interest in dharma. They are born as low creatures. Thus incarnated they attain no joy.</p>

<p>Earn the wealth which neither the state can demand nor the thief can take away, and again which one does not leave behind at death.</p>

<p>If one lives on alms and does not let dharma down, one should consider oneself rich. Dharma is the treasure of the virtuous.</p>

<p>If the practice of dharma should leave no scope for earning life’s requisites, water, herbs and grains can still be gleaned.</p>

<p>Herbs grow in forests. There are rivers with clean waters. The moon is the universal lamp. What more purpose can riches serve?</p>

<p>Even though engaged otherwise one attends to his interests in between. Carrying the yoke, the bull still finds occasion to make morsels of grass.</p>

<p>One should investigate the path of dharma, which is as inscrutable as the path of fish in water. To this end must be enlightened, restrained, controlled and ever active.</p>

<p>Brāhmaṇa, kṣatriya and vaiśya are the three dvi-jātis ‘twice-born.'  Śūdra is the fourth. He is eka-jāti ‘once-born'. There is no fifth.</p>

<p>A brāhmaṇa must study, perform yajña, give alms, go on pilgrimages, teach others, officiate at other’s yajñas and accept the prescribed dues.</p>

<p>Dharma and truth, penance and subjugation of passions, absence of envy and modesty, tolerance and spitelessness, yajñas and alms, firmness and forgiveness – these are the twelve great vows of a brāhmaṇa.</p>

<p>A kṣatriya must study the Vedas, organise the fire, perform yajñas, protect the people, support his dependents, kinsmen and relatives, give alms. Thereby he goes to heaven.</p>

<p>A vaiśya should study with a brāhmaṇa or a kṣatriya. He should help his dependents with monies at the due time. By maintaining the three sacred fires and inhaling their sacred fumes he attains heaven and shares the pleasures of gods.</p>

<p>A śūdra should duly serve brāhmaṇas, kśatriyas and vaiśyas. When they are pleased and satisfied his troubles are over, his sins are burnt up. After leaving his body he accomplishes what he had aspired. </p>

<p>A cowardly monarch, an omnivorous brāhmaṇa, a non-aspiring vaiśya, a lazy śūdra, a depraved man of learning, a man of high birth without high conduct, a brāhmaṇa fallen from truth, a woman gone astray.</p>

<p>A vānaprastha or saṁnyāsī who retains attachment and cooks for himself, an unwise orator, a monarch-less land, and a family man who bears no affection to his children—all of them, O king, reach a deplorable plight.</p>

<p>Straightforwardness, kindness, restraint, control over one's senses—these, according to Manu, are the virtues to be cultivated in common by all the four varṇas.</p>

<p>Non-injuring, speaking truth, sincerity towards all, patience and vigilance make for happiness.</p>

<p>Whatever is crooked leads to death, whatever is straight leads to Brahma. This is wisdom in its entirety. Prolific talk is of no avail.</p>

<p>Kindness is the highest law. Forgiveness is the greatest strength. Knowledge of self is the supreme science. The vow of truth is the noblest vow.</p>

<p>Men always avoid thorns, dry wells, fire, men of vile activity and the depraved ones.</p>

<p>Restraint is superior to alms-giving. Alms-giving makes a man proud. He becomes angry, but not so a man of restraint. Hence the superiority.</p>

<p>Wetting ones' limbs with water is not bathing. He who is bathed with restraint is really bathed. It is he who is rendered clean inside and outside. </p>

<p>One who is neither exhilarated with great prosperity nor depressed by calamity, but has his mind completely under control, he is styled dānta.</p>

<p>Heaven and hell are our own senses. When we control them it is heaven, but when we let them loose it is hell.</p>

<p>Life, good behaviour, security, power, fame, dharma and prosperity are sustained and nourished by restraining the senses.</p>

<p>There are ten roads of action—three mind, four of speech and three of body.</p>

<p>One must cultivate three attitudes—no desire for other’s goods, kindliness to all creatures and a robust faith in the fructification of deeds.</p>

<p>One should neither think nor speak evil, harsh, slanderous or false words.</p>

<p>Murder, theft and adultery—one must altogehter avoid these three bodily sins.</p>

<p>Whatever one does with body, mind and speech, that carries him along. Hence one should do only that which is beneficial.</p>

<p>Rare is the person who is virtuous in speech, action, and mind.</p>

<p>Mind makes the decision. Speech follows it. Lastly it is rendered into deeds. Thus the mind is the chief.</p>

<p>Mind is the root whence the senses derive their activity. It is this mind which is to be properly ordained to serve in all states, good or evil.</p>

<p>Mind traverses far and wide. It is full of aspirations and doubts. One who bridles mind becomes happy here and hereafter.</p>

<p>When eye is joined to the mind, it sees all. When mind is confused, though the eye be open, one sees nothing.</p>
<!-- NpU = Nārada-parivrājhaka-upaniṣad — Ch. Dikshit, The Samnyasa Upanisads ... Adyar Library, 1929, p. 80 -->

<p>There is no difference between the feminine private organ and a festering wet wound. It is the male’s mind that makes the difference and takes him astray.</p>

<p>When it is termed saliva, men recoil. But when it is termed oral wine men crave for it. Men deceive themselves by terms that they have themselves fashioned.</p>

<p>Even though action does not vary, the mind makes the differentiation. The baby and the husband both suck the breast, but their thoughts are far apart.</p>

<p>A mendicant, a lover and a dog view a woman's corpse. They take different views. One considers her just a corpse, the other a beloved, the third as food.</p>
<!-- https://archive.org/details/SarngadharaPaddhati/page/n743/mode/2up -->

<p>It is the purity of sentiments that matters in all instances. The sentiment in kissing a wife is different from that in kissing a daughter.</p>

<p>Greed for other's goods brings joy neither here nor hereafter. People should seek joy by renouncing greed.</p>

<p>One should always hold an equanimous mind towards all creatures. One should neither be greedy nor envious. One should think neither incoherent nor unrealistic thoughts.</p>

<p>Control and restrain your senses and mind from engaging in prohibited, ignoble, unattainable and evil ends.</p>

<p>One who is envious of other’s wealth, beauty, power and birth, happiness, fortune and glory, his torment is unending.</p>

<p>This world belongs to men of forbearance. That world belongs to men of forbearance. Here they are adored, thereafter they attain beatitude.</p>

<p>For one who aspires to dominate there is nothing more glorious or healthier than forbearance.</p>

<p>If men of  earth-like forbearance be not present among the people, there would be no comradeship among them. Dissensions arise out of anger.</p>

<p>He who throws out excited anger with forgiveness, in the manner of a snake moulting his skin, he is known as the man.</p>

<p>Even if one were to continue killing till the end of his days, enemies would not be exhausted. But he, who knows how to control his anger, has no hater left.</p>

<p>O great king, drink in anger and be quiet. Anger is intense headache, not born of a malady, robbing glory, evil in its consequences, to be drunk in by the very noble ones and by none else.</p>

<p>The person, who has relinquished the rod and conquered his anger, who behaves towards others as if they were himself, herefater he flourishes in joy and comfort.</p>

<p>A person with enmity in his heart sleeps uneasily. His mind remains as troubled as if there were a snake in the house.</p>

<p>There is no sleep for one who is diseased, afraid, angry, worried about money, or for one who is in love.</p>

<p>One who does not get angry is superior to the angry ones. A tolerant person is superior to the intolerant. Men are superior to non-humans. And similarly a  learned one is superior to one without learning.</p>

<p>Whatever an angry person sacrifices, whatever he gives, whatever austerities he practises, whatever he pours into sacred fires, all that Vaivasvata robs away. The endeavours of an angry person become fruitless.</p>

<p>Penance is to be saved from anger, wealth from envy, learning from adulation and reviling, and one's self from negligence.</p>

<p>Anger is utter death. Avidity is the Vaitaraṇī river (hot, fetid, filled with blood and bones). Knowledge is the cow of the gods that grants all desires. Contentment is like lndra's grove Nandana.</p>

<p>Irritated and provoked one commits sins, one may even kill elders, and even attack sages and seers with harsh words.</p>

<p>An excited person does not know the distinction between what may or may not be uttered. There is nothing that he may not do or utter.</p>

<p>O best of kings, anger is an enemy which resides in the body of men. He, who renounces wrath and greed, becomes adorable.</p>

<p>Anger is to be specially controlled with regard to gods, kings, brāhmaṇas, children, aged and diseased.</p>

<p>To one who forgives and forbears for the sake of dharma and artha, śānti is the ultimate. And śānti is cultivated by patience.</p>

<p>Atheism, reviling the Vedas and divinities, envy, hypocrisy, pride, wrath and sharpness must be avoided.</p>

<p>Even though there be doubt about the existence of the other world, the wise ought to give up evil. In the case of non-existence nothing will happen, but in case the other world does exist, the atheist is undone.</p>

<p>The wise know that the other world has neither been seen before nor is it visible to the eyes now. One has to take it on faith and not overstep the scriptures.</p>

<p>Not accepting the authority of the Vedas, overstepping the śāstras, loss of faith all over—these lead to one's annihilation.</p>

<p>Be confident and put to your left (i.e. cast out) the atheist who has broken tradition, like the wind [the trees] on a river's bank. Cast him away just one would the upraised dust.</p>
<!-- argr: checked up to here on 2020-05-26 -->

<p>The atheists perform no rites. They transgress preceptors and scriptures. They hurt and injure. They misbehave. They lose their vital power.</p>
<!--ṇi-->

<p>The utter atheists seek the increase of what pertains to this world, e.g. flesh and blood. They are oblivious to such acts as pertain to the other world.</p>

<p>In this world one becomes great by performing two kinds of deeds–uttering nothing that is harsh, and not making requests to the low and vile.</p>
<!--samya-->
<!--sā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One should talk measured and correct words with a sane mind. Speech is corrupted by love and hatred.</p>

<p>Well-formed speech brings much good. But if ill-formed it brings evil to men. </p>
<!--rātryahā?-->
<!--parasya-->

<p>When wordy arrows fly out of one's mouth and strike a person, he worries day and night. They strike at his vitals. The wise should never hurl them.</p>
<!--ṇ-->
<!--ruśatīṁ-->
<!--na?-->
<!--pāṁ-->
<!--nityaśo-->

<p>Dreadful utterances burn out the vitals, the very bones, the hearts and even the life forces of men. Therefore one devoted to dharma must ever avoid harsh and hurting language.</p>

<p>A tree cut by an axe slowly regrows. But the wound made by ugly words does not heal. </p>
<!--gā-->
<!--tān-->
<!--hīnāṁ-->
<!--pet-->

<p>Let no insult be shown to the crippled, to the man with an extra finger or toe, to the unlearned, the condemned, the ugly, the poor, the feeble.</p>
<!--yāt-->
<!--’-->

<p>One should not desire to abuse, speak what is false, or slander and gossip. If he is true and measured in speech, he protects and guards the wordy door.</p>

<p>Counting the virtues when face to face, but reviling when out of sight–such a one is like a cur, who loses the world.</p>

<p>Neither should one ever repeat or pronounce calumny. Either one should shut his ears or move on.</p>
<!--ṣā-->
<!--ko’-->

<p>Even an atheist would recoil from the untruthful and the wrathful. Much more so the man of faith.</p>
<!--not found in the text-->

<p>In the body are lodged both mortality and immortality. It is out of ignorance that death takes hold. From truth follows deathlessness.</p>
<!--yajña-->
<!--ra-->
<!--ti-->

<p>Yajñas, charity and vows do not bring about a person's deliverance in the same way as absolute truth.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Among humans the brāhmaṇa, among luminaries the sun, among limbs the head, and among dharmas truth is supreme.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A lowly person who abuses his tongue to help others, what would he not do to serve himself, free as he is of the awe of sin and hell. </p>

<p>One should utter words that are true, that neither hurt nor slander, that are replete with benevolence, that are not coarse, unkind or treacherous.</p>
<!--ta-->
<!--di-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Truth is defined as speaking exactly what has happened. Whatever one has seen or known that one should not conceal, if questioned.</p>
<!--ran-->

<p>It is not the stating of facts that constitutes truth, or the stating of non-facts that constitutes a lie. Whatever is to the absolute good of creatures that is truth, and the rest is falsehood.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Life is the basis of dharma, artha, kāma and mokṣa. One who destroys life, destroys all, one who guards it guards the good of all.</p>
<!--not found in the text-->
<!--yān-->
<!--yet-->
<!--ni-->
<!--hī-->

<p>One who himself seeks to live, how can he destroy others. What he seeks for himself, that he should think for others too.</p>
<!--nayaḥ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>What sense is there in maintaining this body through torments to others, when at its end even a dog puts his paws on its head without awe.</p>
<!--kri-->
<!--thā-->
<!--pa-->
<!--yatkathaṁ?-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The body ends as worms, ashes and excreta. Why then tyrannize over others to nurture it?</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Walking, standing, waking and sleeping, if one's activities do not benefit others, then it is a beast's motions.</p>
<!--n-->
<!--a-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A lioness brings forth just one cub, a bitch (in Skt. a she-wolf) many. The difference: one eats, the others are eaten. It is the eater, the perpetrator of sin who comes to end, and not the others.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One who does not butcher, captivate or torment creatures, one who seeks  to comfort all, he attains absolute happiness.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>By not injuring creatures one achieves without effort what one aspires, towards what one moves and wherein one puts his heart.</p>
<!--nāṁ-->
<!--jñāṁ-->
<!--ś-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Disciplined men wishing to acquire beauty, perfection, longevity, full wisdom and valour must avoid hiṃsā.</p>

<p>If out of kindness one gives protection to all living beings, then other beings afford fearlessness to him. There is no doubt about it.</p>
<!--dā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Alms and gifts to all weighed against gift of life to one, the latter is certainly weightier. </p>
<!--yāṁ-->

<p>There is nothing dearer than life. Therefore one should be as kind to others as to himself. </p>
<!--yāt-->

<p>Not given to wrath, truthful, not hurting any creatures, not slandering, following the right conduct–thereby one lives long.</p>
<!--ka-->
<!--yāt-->

<p>Lowly born, infested by ailments, following evil ways, aggressive–such sinners do not live long. Their lives are cut short by the emergence of debasing elements. </p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->

<p>Recoursing to physical force they may rob people of their possessions (artha), but in return they lose all three, dharma, possessions (artha) and pleasures (kāma).</p>
<!--a-->
<!--t-->

<p>One who does not thieve and rob lives happily. A thief is ever afraid, like a deer who has entered a village.</p>
<!--dadyā-->
<!--t-->

<p>Three are highest vows and richest treasures–non-envy, gifts and veracity.</p>
<!--tā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The loving attitude for a kin in distress and for a friend seeking refuge is the most precious tenderness.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--yaṁ-->
<!--ṇ-->

<p>Nothing is more debasing than violating others' consorts.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A wise disciplined soul, conscious of its obligations and striving for righteous living does not harbour evil with regard to others' womenfolk.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The same is the joy of touch, the same the mockery at the end. There is hardly any difference between one's own spouse and other dames. Why then run after others.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--tasya was omitted-->

<p>Let speech, body and mind not act viciously. For, every act, noble or vicious, that is done there is a corresponding reward and punishment.</p>
<!--sarvabhū-->
<!--ś-->
<!--la-->
<!--dur-->

<p>Thinking, speaking and acting without malice, positive kindness, making gifts–this is moral conduct (śīla).</p>
<!--dharmaḥ-->
<!--śrī-->
<!--pañca-->

<p>Dharma, truth and right, prowess and wealth–these are the sustaining roots of śīla. </p>

<p>With śīla one can conquer the three worlds, Śīla is the invincible instrument. </p>
<!--puruṣe-->
<!--tasya jīvi-->

<p>In man śīla is preeminent. With its loss, life loses its meaning.</p>
<!--t-->
<!--d-->
<!--t-->

<p>One superior in status but weak in śīla claims no respect. On the other hand, a śūdra, low in status, but versed in dharma and correct in conduct, is worthy of respect.</p>

<p>Conduct guards dharma, diligence guards learning, cosmetics guard beauty, śīla guards high birth.</p>
<!--na-->

<p>A man is proclaimed by his śīla, conduct or actions and their consequences. One's śīla illumines and broadcasts one's birth even though it might have been forgotten and lost.</p>

<p>Knowledge of Vedas, of their six branches and sub-branches, of Sāṅkhya and Purāṇa, high birth–all these avail not in the absence of śīla. </p>

<p>Neither kinsmen, nor money, nor learning, nor scriptures, nor mantras, nor prowess–singly or collectively–have the capacity to take one out of distress. It is only śīla that can do so.</p>
<!--r-->

<p>By coming to the aid of the poor and the depressed, one prospers in sons and cattle, and captures eternal glory.</p>
<!--nā-->

<p>It is the he-man who obliges even an enemy fallen on bad days, wretched, miserable and come in search of refuge. </p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->

<p>On a journey the caravan is the friend, while in home wife is the ally, to the ailing the doctor and to the dying alms serve as the comrade.</p>

<p>Neither the mother nor the father share one’s destiny. Alms supply health-giving provisions on the journey beyond. One can only eat the fruits of deeds done by one’s self.</p>

<p>The wise are not jealous. They are not niggardly. They restrain themselves in dharma and are equipoised. </p>

<p>By bestowing gifts one enjoys a life of plenty. Association with elders means participation in their experiences. Ahiṃsā brings longevity.</p>
<!--ṣe?-->

<p>There is nothing harder than to give away what one has earned with painful labour. Besides, one's own longing and thirst is so deep and great.</p>
<!--vayametān-->
<!--ku-->

<p>Those who donate large sums do something extraordinary. We cannot relinquish our hold even on sums that we do not possess.</p>
<!--dānamanyā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>What advantage is there in hoarding? There is only one ultimate for monies–either one expends them or they are gone.</p>
<!--ī-->
<!--t-->
<!--ni-->
<!--ti-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The intelligent soul expends its wealth and life in the cause of others. Let the spending be for a good cause, as otherwise too, the two will not endure.</p>
<!--dada-->
<!--ta-->
<!--perhaps13,121.022d*0610_02 is related?-->

<p>Endow gifts, enjoy to the brim, be not niggards, O men. Accumulations are not exhausted by enjoying them, but by the wasting away of deeds.</p>
<!--tra-->

<p>If you have cultivated the Vedas you must offer oblations into the sacred fires, if you have earned money you must donate it and use it, if you have a wife let her be your joy and a mother of your sons, if you have mastered the scriptures your śila and conduct must be perfect.</p>

<p>What good are unutilized goods, what good the valour that does not subdue the foes, what good the books that lead not to dharma, what avail the self which has not its senses under control.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>If riches ebb and flow but bear no fruit, then life is lifeless. It may be likened to a smith's bellows, which breathe but have no soul.</p>
<!--nāṁ-->

<p>The gift of fearlessness stands above all other gifts.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Proper place, suitable time, right donee, correct amount and the noble mental attitudes of the giver enhance the value of gifts.</p>
<!--only partially related?-->

<p>The two stand high above heaven–one who feeds the people in famine and the other who lavishes gold in times of prosperity.</p>
<!--ayaneṣu-->
<!--viṣuve-->
<!--reference number is not found-->
<!--vulu above akśara ka?-->

<p>Holy alms distributed during equinoctial and solsticial points, during the sun's entrance into the four signs (Pisces, Gemini, Virgo and Sagittarius) and during solar or lunar eclipses bear unending fruit.</p>
<!--mahāphalā-->
<!--pajitā-->

<p>Even gifts of small shells, earned through putting one's life in danger, bring rich harvest. On the other hand, the gift of even thousands, earned through unfair means, bring no felicity.</p>
<!--na is not found in the text-->
<!--guṇān-->
<!--cātmanaḥ-->
<!--nāsatpuruṣamā-->
<!--t-->

<p>Do not patronize the wicked. Do not recount your own virtues. Accept not gifts from good men of little means. Do not take refuge with the vile.</p>

<p>If there be not available a brāhmaṇa, at once learned and virtuous, on whom one may bestow his riches, then riches would be of no avail.</p>
<!--mahāphalam-->

<p>If, O king, one be approached by men in need, disciplined in conduct, but thin in body and meagre in means, help to them brings great merit. </p>
<!--dyaśase-->
<!--nr̥tta-->

<p>A man of dharma must not give for fame, nor out of fear, nor in return for a favour, nor to dancers, singers and buffons.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>If parents should demand even one’s life, one should not waver.  </p>
<!---RaghuVira has MBh.2.5.81, 83 but it seems that they do not match with the sloka above?-->

<p>For the pains that parents undergo in nurturing the child in the womb, the child cannot compensate even in a hundred years.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>O son of Kuntī, serve the destitutes. Do not lavish your fortune on the favoured ones. Medicament is for the ailing and ailing alone.  </p>

<p>By all means help the depressed, particularly when they are too sensitive to ask. Kindliness and aiding the non-asking ones is the noblest dharma.</p>

<p>Never insult or drive away the creature who has come to your door. Alms, even to a pariah or a dog, are not wasted.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Who would muster the heart to be rude to one who comes to one's door day after day. He serves as your preceptor. He dusts away the dirt that has settled on your souI’s mirror.</p>

<p>There is nothing more sinful than the squashing of hopes, than stating "I have not" or than demanding "give unto me".</p>
<!--śikṣayanti-->

<p>Misers advise others to be generous, but their own fists they hold tight.</p>

<p>One should give because he must. One should make offerings to the sacred fire, because he must. Fruits may or may not accrue. It has to be done as a matter of duty.</p>
<!--tārayanti-->

<p>Gifts of gold, cows and land are holy. They deliver one to the other world.</p>

<p>O King, thou a person of fortune, givest gold, silver, clothing, jewels, pearls and costly goods.</p>
<!--gām-->

<p>Let one gift away an auspicious, tawny cow, mantled, horns tipped with gold, together with a brazen milking pot. That cow comes back to the donor in the form of numerous blessings fulfilling wants and aspirations.</p>
<!--vastrāṇi-->
<!--dadyādabhīkṣnaṁ-->

<p>By bestowing fragrance, incense, unguents, clothes and garlands now and again, one attains health and beauty in the abode of gods.</p>

<p>Give sesamum oilseeds, give water, give lamps, shirk not. And thereby assure your and your kinsmen's place in heaven. (some akṣaras 'it won't go amiss')</p>

<p>Water is hard to get in heaven. By distributing free water in this world, one's thirst is quenched for ever.</p>
<!--ā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A giver of light never becomes blind. He has always bright eyes. He is enlightened. In heaven he shines with the brilliance of rows of lamps.</p>
<!---cha-->
<!--bha-->
<!--śa-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>By giving an umbrella one goes to the heaven of Indra (who rules over rains and storms). There he is looked after by fairies.</p>
<!--upāna-->
<!--n-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The giver of soft and oiled shoes proceeds toId worlds honoured by gods (some akṣaras).</p>
<!--nā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The gift of all possessions made with a foul mind does not bring one to heaven. It is the mind which matters.</p>

<p>Aspiring after inexhaustible merit one should give away to the deserving whatever one cherishes and values most.</p>

<p>The noblest gift is the one that is awarded with honours, the middle one is that which is in response to a demand.</p>

<p>What is given contemptuously is the lowest form of gift.</p>
<!--neha ca-->

<p>O son of Pr̥thā, anything done without faith and devotion, whether it be an offering to the sacred fire, a gift or a penance, is termed false and unreal. It serves neither here nor there.</p>
<!--ghāṇapiṇyā-->
<!--bhyā-->
<!--ti-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>On request one should give small things as well, oil-cakes, vegetables. When giving becomes a habit one would give even his own flesh and blood.</p>

<p>When one promises but does not give, whether the thing be small or big, his aspirations are thwarted in the same way as the actions of a weak and important man.</p>
<!--only partially related?-->

<p>If, having promised, one backs out, he is scorched by falsehood, his sacrifices and public munificence bear not the merit, otherwise due.</p>
<!--c-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Iṣṭa or yajña includes offerings into one or three fires, as well as gifts made in the yajña ground.</p>
<!--ṭakā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Pūrta includes the construction of public works, e.g. water-reservoirs, wells, tanks and temples, as well as distribution of food and providing parks and groves.</p>
<!--prāyeṇākr̥takr̥tyatvānvr̥tyo?-->
<!--kr̥takr̥tyāḥ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Generally, it is those who have not finished their life's work, that are frightened of death. Those who have done what was to be done wait anxiously for the last moment as for a dear guest.</p>
<!--kathaṁ-->
<!--tā-->
<!--yeṣāṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Having given up the right deeds, how can people sleep with ease at night. Their entry into hell is barred only by death.</p>
<!--pūrvā-->
<!--tasya-->
<!--puṇyaphalaṁ-->
<!--t-->

<p>Great merit accrues to the giver of food to a traveller on the road who is fatigued and unknown.</p>
<!--pr̥ttikṣaṁṇā-->
<!--puruṣaḥ-->

<p>None equals the feeder of an emaciated, modest person who has lost his livelihood.</p>
<!--nanaṁ-->
<!--phalam-->
<!--sarvvāṇ-->
<!--phala-->
<!--t-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The gift of food immediately creates happiness to the donor and the donee. All other gifts produce merit that is not visible. </p>
<!--mārttasya-->
<!--sthitaśrāntasya-->
<!--tasya-->
<!--nī-->
<!--kṣudhitasya-->

<p>To the distressed give refuge, to one tired of standing give a seat, to the thirsty water and to the hungry a meal.</p>
<!--surplus dyā-->
<!--kur-->
<!--cārccan-->

<p>Give a kindly glance, an attentive mind, pleasant words, courteous reception and due respect.</p>
<!--vākcaturthaṁ-->

<p>Grass, earth, water and fourthly sweet words–the homes of good men are never short in these.</p>
<!--yeṣāṁ-->
<!--pvaṣaṭ?-->
<!--n-->

<p>Those in whose homes it is neither gods, nor the aged, neither guests nor children, to whom food is served first, they are demons indeed who eat unconsecrated meals.</p>
<!--svārthān?-->
<!--si-->
<!--t-->

<p>Alone one should not eat delicious things. Alone one should not ponder over one's affairs. Alone one should not proceed on a journey. Alone one should not keep awake while others are asleep.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Those for whom neither mother nor father prepares the meal, they are happy indeed. They eat with others.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Whose valour is to serve the weak, whose fortunes are to be gifted away, whose food is for the emaciated–such is the son of whom parents may be proud.</p>
<!--vai-->

<p>To such a one resort kith and kin. He is like the cloud who is the support of living creatures or like the fruited tree on which birds find nurture.</p>

<p>If even having approached a well-to-do relative, one should sink, it redounds to the discredit of the host.</p>
<!--bhibhūta-->
<!--tya-->

<p>My dear, a highborn but poor kinsman in distress, a destitute comrade and a childless sister may go and live in the household of a relative favoured by fortune.</p>
<!--le-->
<!--veṣametān śr̥he-->
<!--sayeta-->

<p>One who is lazy, who eats much, who is hated by the people,who is crafty and cruel, who knows neither time nor place, who dresses in an undesirable way–these are not to be lodged in one's home.</p>
<!--śiṣya-->

<p>A r̥tvik, a priest and a preceptor, a disciple, a relative and a kinsman, all men worthy of respect and honour, men of learning and character.</p>

<p>Those who hate and injure a teacher, the father or the mother in thought or action, commit a sin greater than abortion.</p>

<p>Parents make the body, the preceptor raises it to brāhmaṇahood, which is non-decaying and non-dying.</p>

<p>One should be the first to greet and salute his teacher from whom he has learned secular, Vedic or spiritual lore.</p>

<p>One should never form enmity with his teacher. If the teacher be angry he is to he propitiated and cheered.</p>
<!--vr̥tte vā-->
<!--nihanty-->

<p>The behaviour towards a teacher must be correct, even if the teacher is on the wrong path. Reviling the teacher mars one's life.</p>
<!--tapa-->

<p>Keeping pure and austere, devoted to dharma and truth, one should ever and faithfully serve his parents day after day.</p>
<!--khāt tathoccataraḥ pitā-->
<!--manaḥ-->
<!--rā-->

<p>The mother is weightier than earth, the father is loftier than sky, the mind is quicker than wind, thoughts and worries are more numerous than grass.</p>
<!--yasya-->
<!--bhavati-->

<p>O king of kings, if one's parents are happy, one's fame here and hereafter lasts for ever.</p>
<!--śarīrakr̥t-->
<!--yasya-->
<!--dharma-->

<p>Three are the fathers-one is the maker of the body, the other the giver of life, the third the giver of food.</p>
<!--prītimātraṁ-->
<!--sarvvaṁ putrasya-->
<!--śarīrādīni-->

<p>The son gives only pleasure to his father. To the son the father is all. It is the father alone who bestows the body and everything else.</p>
<!--tatha-->

<p>The mother guards the child, be he capable or incapable, lean or fat. There is no one else who would look after him so well.</p>
<!--pa-->

<p>translation is not available</p>
<!--varṣaśatasyānte-->

<p>When one is devoted to his mother, even after getting sons and grandsons, he lives for a century and thereafter ascends up to heaven.</p>
<!--dā’-->
<!--bhavati-->
<!--bhavati duḥkhitaḥ-->
<!--sarvvaṁ-->
<!--mātro-->

<p>It is at the passing away of the mother that one becomes poor and miserable. The whole world becomes empty.</p>
<!--vr̥ddhamāsanaṁ-->
<!--kr̥tāñja-->

<p>Respectfully greet the aged, show him a seat, stand with folded hands and follow him. </p>

<p>At the approach of an elder, life as it were goes out of the body of the young. He gets it back by standing up and respectful salutation.</p>
<!--nityaṁ-->
<!--tasya-->

<p>Serving and revering the aged increase fame, life, reputation and power.</p>
<!--karmṇor’thasya-->
<!--śrutasyābhijabhasya ca-->
<!--sārūpya-->
<!--manunmattasya lakṣaṇam-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>It is a characteristic of the sane to establish conformity between one's age, conduct, wealth, learning and birth on the one hand, and dress, speech and talents on the other.</p>
<!--naṁ-->
<!--nitya-->

<p>A man should always console and comfort the depressed, the destitute, the hungry, the ailing, the one who has lost his possessions and the one struck by calamity.</p>
<!--śrutismr̥tyuditaṁ-->
<!--karmasu-->
<!--dharmamūlaṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One should cultivate with perseverence sadācāra, as propounded by śruti and smr̥ti. One should make it the base of his actions. Sadācāra is the root of dharma.</p>
<!--dharmaphala-->
<!--ācāreṇa-->
<!--sampūrṇaphalabhāgbhavet-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Devoid of character one does not enjoy the fruit of dharma. Dharma yoked to practice brings full fruit.</p>
<!--yāṁ-->
<!--paurṇnamā-->
<!--bhavennitya-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One who keeps celibate on new and full moon days as well as on the eighth and fourteenth days of the lunar fortnight, he is termed an amr̥tasnātaka.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--ve-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Seek not what is not given. Drink not spirituous liquors. Injure not life. Speak not untruth. Do not think of others wives. And you will enter heaven as you enter your home.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Avoiding dances and songs, musical instruments, perfumes and garlands, travel, arrogance, lying down, and liquors at the time of lunal conjunctions, and keeping to measured diet lead man to inexhaustible worlds of the Maruts. Darpa in Kawi is boyish behaviour, playing about in sheer joy.</p>
<!--kevalān-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>It is the yamas which one should pursue constantly and not the niyamas. If one should pursue only the niyamas and ignore the yamas, he falls down. </p>
<!--there is a pangkon at the end of the word-->

<p>Compassion, forbearance, truth, non-injury, control, straightforwardness, affection, graciousness, sweatness and softness form the ten yamas.</p>
<!--snānaṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Alms, offerings, penance, meditation, scriptural reading, control of sex, vows, fasts and reticence form the ten niyamas.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->

<p>One should accumulate wealth in accordance with dharma. Earned with dharma, it is divided into three parts.</p>
<!--ti-->
<!--tā-->
<!--t-->

<p>Desiring well-being one should reserve one part for dharma, one for pleasure and the third for investment.</p>
<!--ye-->
<!--ye’-->
<!--māṁ-->

<p>Money earnt with dharma is gainful (or is the true wealth). What is got with adharma, fie on that. Dharma is an eternal value. Do not discard it for money.</p>
<!--hā-->

<p>If one longs for money to serve dharma, then let him have no longing at all. Instead of washing away mud from one's clothes, it is better to keep away from mud.</p>
<!--śā-->
<!--sa-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Of all purifications monetary purity is the highest. He who is honest in money matters is pure indeed. Cleansing with clay and water is not purity.</p>

<p>Do not put your heart into the monies which demand immense exertion, transgression of dharma or the felling down of an enemy.</p>
<!--r̥-->

<p>In one born in an eminent family, greed for other's riches obscures wisdom, which further leads to the loss of glory.</p>

<p>Dharma, riches and pleasures are the three fruits of life. Let adharma not pollute them.</p>
<!--jī-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Make each day fruitful of dharma, joy and earning. With each day gone, life is less by that.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>If life is utilized neither for dharma, nor for wealth, nor for pleasure, then it has been a waste. It has served only death.</p>
<!--nān-->

<p>...</p> <!--(translation is not  available in Raghu Vira's edition)-->

<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--ihai-->
<!--nāmutrā-->

<p>Some enjoy here and not hereafter. Some hereafter hut not here. Some both here and hereafter. And there are still those who enjoy neither here nor
hereafter.</p>

<p>Those who have ample wealth, they enjoy life and its decorations. This world belongs to them, O vanquisher of mighty foes. But not always the other one.</p>
<!--prayu-->
<!--na-->
<!--ma-->
<!--mayaṁ-->
<!--nāsti parastu-->

<p>Those who are engaged in yoga, penance and studies, those who have subjugated their senses and are devoted to the good of creatures, their world is the other one.</p>
<!--tu-->
<!--loke-->

<p>Those who first engage in dharma, then gain wealth with dharma, marry and offer oblations to the sacred fires, theirs are both the worlds.</p>
<!--superfluous dānaṁ na-->
<!--sukhama-->
<!--naiva-->

<p>Those who engage neither in learning nor in penance, alms, worship or yajñas, they are the unfortunate ones, who gain no happiness in either of the two worlds.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->

<p>Free from wrath, truthful habits, resolute vows, treating others in his own measure–such a one enjoys the fruits of pilgrimage.</p>
<!--trirātreṣu-->
<!--tīr-->
<!--dhi-->

<p>Not fasting for three nights, not going on pilgrimage, not gifting gold and cows lead to a person's being born as a poor man.</p>
<!--ñai-->

<p>Even the poor can afford to take holy pilgrimages. They are superior even to yajñas.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->

<p>Dead is the poor man, dead the kingdom without the king, dead the śrāddha without a śrotriya, and dead is the yajña without the fee.</p>
<!--dapi-->

<p>The sinful poor pass on from one famine to another severer famine, from one fear to another greater fear and from one death to another greater death.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>No one heeds the advice, though it be beneficial and opportune, of a poor, dull and destitute person.</p>
<!--surplus ḥ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One who has lost his fortune, his merits and qualities shines not. Like the sun who illuminates the worlds, it is riches that illuminate merits and qualities.</p>
<!--ḍā-->
<!--na-->
<!--daridro-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A pariah and a poor person are said to be equal. From the pariah one does not accept, while the poor is incapable of offering.</p>
<!--kr̥paṇavr̥-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A miser's house is hell. There is no gold, no servants, little eatables, and no milk.</p>
<!--śo-->
<!--ma-->

<p>O king, lean in money is lean. So also the one who is lean in servants and guests. It isnot the man who islean in body who is lean.</p>
<!--jīvitān-->

<p>Having gained the desired affection, one may share the wealth of friends, But if he is unable to repay, it is better far to die than to continue to live.</p>

<p>The poor by birth does not suffer so much as one who is brought up in comfort, who has had the good things of life, but later on loses them.</p>
<!--kha-->

<p>Generally the rich have not the capacity to digest. The poor, on the other hand, can digest even wood with branches on.</p>

<p>The poor have always palatable meals. Hunger makes them savoury. And hunger is missing among the affluent.</p>
<!--saṁ-->

<p>Hunger drives away the conscienceness of dharma. It takes away patience. The tongue (or the palate) follows riches and is drawn towards savoury tastes.</p>
<!--daivaṁ-->
<!--dosaṁhi-->

<p>Encountering a difficult situation the unknowing one blames destiny. He does not know the fault of his own deeds.</p>
<!--ṅū?-->
<!--pra-->

<p>If even aftet great exertion one does not succeed in acquiring money, one should take to great penance. For nothing sprouts without the seed being sown.</p>
<!--vyarthayatneṣu karmasu-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>With the face of destiny turned away, with exertions availing not, there is no other place of comfort for a man of honour than a forest.</p>
<!--śā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Rejected by riches, mind keen on quiet rest, why should one reject the penance grove. The discomforts are not greater.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Like a tree growing in saline soil, bent, eaten by ants and its bark scorched by fire, a beggar's life has no charms.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Come here, go away, sit down, stand up, speak, be quiet–thus the rich play with those who, seized by great hopes, come to beg.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Day after day the Creator's creation goes on. But till today he has not created one being who does not repudiate petitioners and supplicators.</p>
<!--ṭha-->
<!--kha-->
<!--reference number is not found-->
<!--is there a suku under aksara L̥? -->

<p>Choking of speech, perspiration, loss of facial colour and tremors are the  marks of one approaching death as also of a begging petitioner.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--mamchas-->

<p>To make scented oil, a layer of flowers is laid on the ground. Then a sheet of cloth. It is sprinkled with water and spread over with sesamum oil-seeds. Fragrance of flowers permeates cloth, water, sesamum seeds and the earth. Similarly by association are human virtues transmitted.</p>
<!--t-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>By association with inferiors the mind becomes mean, by association with persons of equal merit it remains as before and by association with superiors the  mind is improved.</p>
<!--nr̥-->
<!--vi-->
<!--vāmcha-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Among men of virtue and eminence a lesser soul also expands. It is like a drop of oil fallen on sweet clear water.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Great expanse of virtues, transmitted to a virtueless person, is reduced to small dimensions on account of the nature of the receptor. It is like the reduction of the mighty frame of an elephant in a small mirror.</p>
<!--ri-->

<p>Hence cultivate virtues and not vices. A virtue-less fool is his own enemy.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--vā-->
<!--maitrīṁ vā-->
<!--ret-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Sit with good men, go with good men, discuss with good men, make friends with good men. Have nothing to do with bad men.</p>

<p>A saintly person is not excited with adulation, he is not distressed by blame and abuse. Angered he does not utter harsh word.</p>

<p>Saints and ideal men do not remember injuries and faults, they remember good deeds. They do not transgress social and moral  bounds.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The more the fields are ploughed, and the richer the crops, so the saint, [the more saintly he is] the more humble he becomes. He is like the branch bending low with the weight of fruits.</p>
<!--sā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Saints do not bite at one's back. They raise the distressed. Association does not breed contempt. So, O king, serve saintly persons.</p>
<!--vidyāmaiśvaryameva-->

<p>A pandit, even having attained great wealth, learning and power does not behave in a swollen way.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Even though it be not possible to follow the whole road trodden by good men, let one go a short distance. While on the road one will not come to grief.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A saint is not only adored by the people. Even the self has respect for high conduct.</p>

<p>This is the eternal way chosen by noble souls. Knowing this, good people do not look for reward in serving others.</p>
<!--saṁrakṣyaṁvi-->

<p>Strain to guard your conduct. Money comes and goes. Loss of money is not the loss of soul. Loss of conduct is devastating.</p>
<!--ki-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Let one examine his conduct each day- which of my actions has been beastly and which one saintly.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The doer, the instigator, the approver, the three share the fruit equally, whether the action be meritorious or sinful.</p>
<!--t-->

<p>Do not react to evil with evil. Be always saintly. The sinner, desiring to do evil, kills himself.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>It is a great strain to take a rock up the hill. It is easy to fell it down. So it is with one's soul in regard to merit and evil.</p>

<p>The echo of holy action touches earth and heaven. As long as this echo resounds, so long is man a man.</p>
<!--ṣaṁ-->
<!--t-->
<!--jī-->
<!--jī-->

<p>Like a mother, fame bestows life. Infamy, on the other hand, destroys life, even while the body lives.</p>
<!--t-->

<p>One should never betray friends or those who have put trust in you, neither those whose food you have eaten nor those who have given asylum.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--ne-->
<!--su-->
<!--co-->
<!--śa ṭe-->

<p>There is atonement for killing a brāhmaṇa, for drinkings pirituous liquors, thievery, breaking vows and wickedness, but none for ingratitude.</p>
<!--’-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>He, who does evil to an innocent and guileless soul, travels the hard path infested by hell.</p>
<!-- pāpaṁ na-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A sinner cannot be said to love his soul. The sin that he commits has to he paid for by him.</p>
<!--bhuyo’-->
<!--viśi-->
<!--ga-->
<!--yi-->
<!--ca nai-->
<!--tān ni-->
<!--ṣe-->
<!--ṭ-->

<p>One should not associate or serve six types of mean persons, viz., those who oppress others, those who are negligent and generally untrue, unfaithful, too much biased or enormously crafty.</p>
<!--pāpān-->
<!--t-->
<!--t-->

<p>...</p><!-- no translation is available for this stanza-->

<!--varjanīyo ma-->
<!--la-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A wise man should avoid the wicked in both peace and fight. A dog, whether he licks (in love) or bites (in anger) is liable to convey infection.</p>
<!--ṭa-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>There are two ways of dealing with wicked men and thorns. One may wield the shoe (crushing the sharp point of the thorn, and slapping the face of the wicked) or keep them at a distance.</p>
<!--viśrambhaṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Do not put trust in the wicked on the basis that he is known since long. A snake though kept and trained for a long while, still bites.</p>
<!--niṣaṇnami-->
<!--va-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A mean fellow rides the back of a saintly man bowed in courte y, making his limb serve as a stair. lt is like a seated elephant.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Good men, do not put faith in a vile person's bending low. Is there a bending of the pole which does not steal the well's water.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A good man should rejoice that he has not been wronged by the wicked. It is no mishap that though the snake coiled itself round one, it did not bite.</p>
<!--nā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Even sweet words spoken by an evil person generate fear m my heart. They are like unseasonal flowers that portend calamity.</p>
<!--’-->
<!--t-->
<!--t-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Look for untruth in sweet words. If you do not discover it, sweet words are nectar. Look for dharma in harsh words. If you do not discover it, harsh words are poison.</p>
<!--cai-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Cut the neem tree with an axe. Anoint it with honey and butter. Worship it with scents and garlands. No matter what one does the neem will remain bitter.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Learning which subdues arrogance in others, serves to create arrogance in low persons. Light, which puts the eye in action, makes the owl blind.</p>
<!--bhijanair-->
<!--surplus mada-->
<!--mada-->
<!--’-->

<p>Learning, wealth and high birth form the three intoxicants for men of arrogance. The very same three elements go to make the good humble.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>How and why should one compare soft iron with the wily heart. Iron is  bent and welded, it melts and can be heated. But the wily heart always stays hard and obdurate.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The wily are highly skilful in concealing their misdeeds. They are like the flameless fire of rice-husks that smoulders but is not visible.</p>
<!--va-->

<p>Oh, how very wrong that the world be perverse. That, at which a saintly person is ashamed, gives joy to the wicked.</p>
<!--sar-->
<!--vi-->

<p>The wicked man sees others' faults even though they be as small as grains of mustard, but his own even seeing he see not, though they be as big as a wood-apple.</p>

<p>Just as paying respect to the aged gives joy to the good, so abusing and reviling the good satisfies the wicked.</p>
<!--dha-->
<!--RaghuVira notes Cf.MBh.5.33.30-->

<p>Foolish is he, who though prosperous does not help others, who though poor is generous, and who though ignorant is proud and swollen.</p>

<p>None is more foolish than the person who accuses others of faults which pertain to himself or who gets angry without having the power to remedy.</p>
<!--lā-->

<p>Evil men take soft speech as indication of weakness. The softness of gold (as tested on the touchstone) is regarded by the touchstone as its victory.</p>

<p>If the noble man asks a favour from the mean one, the latter begins to consider himself a superior person although everybody knows him to be otherwise.</p>

<p>The wise listen to the good and evil words of the prattling mass, and take up only what is good, like the swan which separates and takes milk out of water.</p>

<p>A noble soul, though instigated to sin, does not give in. The evil soul, though prevented, goes in for it.</p>
<!--vyar-->
<!--ta-->
<!--jī-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>What good are scriptures to one without character, wealth to a miserly life, adventure to an unfortunate one or valour to a coward.</p>
<!--śvad-->

<p>As water in a skull pot, or milk in a dog's leather-bottle, so learning turns foul in a man devoid of character. The fault is of the container.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>The knowledge of a tyrant is of no avail. It is like the tail of a dog, which neither covers the privities nor kills goats and fleas.</p>
<!--this is not found in the text-->
<!--karma-->
<!--karma-->
<!--sambandhilakṣaṇaḥ-->
<!--karmā-->
<!--sarvve?-->
<!--karma-->
<!--The excat reference is not found, but I find MBh13,001.066 is quite similar-->

<p>People are the inheritors of karma. Their characteristic feature is the connection with past actions. It is the past actions which drive people. All of us are controlled by karma.</p>
<!--yatha-->
<!--ta-->
<!--karma-->

<p>As a calf spots out its mother in a herd of thousands, so good and had deeds follow the doer.</p>
<!--yathā-->
<!--phalā-->
<!--tathā-->
<!--karma-->
<!--kr̥tam-->

<p>As flowers and fruits do not transgress their appointed time, they need no goading; so it is with karma done in the past.</p>
<!--thayāṁ-->
<!--ṁ-->
<!--The Old Javanese part is not found in the file-->

<p>...</p>
<!--The whole section is not found in file -->

<p>...</p>
<!--The whole section is not found in file -->

<p>...</p>
<!--lokasya sarvo-->
<!--yathāśakti-->

<p>Everybody wishes to be high above the people, and strains himself to the limit of his powers, but does not succeed.</p>
<!--vi-->
<!--nā-->

<p>At every step honour and dishonour, gain and loss, waste and non-waste operate and cease when they are exhausted.</p>
<!--hanyate-->
<!--pūjyā-->
<!--bhavat-->
<!--yatkarmavījaṁ-->
<!--tasyānurūpā-->
<!--phalā-->
<!--ṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>If one steals he is reborn as a poor man, if one kills he is killed in a subsequent incarnation, if one does not revere those who must be revered, one becomes unworthy of reverence-whatever action a man sows as the seed, the fruit of that he reaps.</p>
<!--jaṁ-->
<!--praro-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>That what is reaped is different from what is sown, does not fit in. The seed that is sown in the ground, it is that which sprouts.</p>
<!--nitya-->
<!--duḥkha-->
<!--duḥkha-->
<!--paramaṁ-->

<p>In heaven there is eternal happiness, in this world there is both happiness and sorrow, in hell there is only pain, while in liberation there is supreme beatitude.</p>
<!--sukrtāḥ-kr̥tāh̥-->
<!--brāhmaṇa-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Water-wells, gardens, public halls, ramparts and homes for the wise-these five utility works done well take a man to heaven.</p>
<!--kārya-->
<!--pūrvāhne-->
<!--kr̥taṁ-->
<!--vāpyakr̥taṁ-->

<p>Whatever is to be done tomorrow, do that today; whatever is to be done in the afternoon, do that in the forenoon. Death does not wait, whether your work be done or undone.</p>
<!--this is not found in J-->
<!--yasya-->
<!--tasya-->
<!--tadyujyate-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>He who has made friendship with death, or he who does not grow old and is immortal, only he has a right to say-this will happen to me tomorrow.</p>
<!--aparyantasya-->
<!--kālasya-->
<!--tanmātraparamā-->
<!--kathaṁ-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>What fraction is a hundred years of limitless time. Man, whose highest expectation of life is one hundred years, how should he sleep in ease.</p>
<!--bhūtajīvita-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A creature's span of life is very small. Night robs away one half. Of the rest a half is taken away by ailments, sorrows and old age.</p>
<!--gambhīre-->
<!--tya-->

<p>Nobody realizes that this world is sinking into the profound ocean of time; senility and death are the mighty sharks that infest this ocean.</p>
<!--śāstrāṇi-->
<!--pā-->
<!--pe-->

<p>Neither medicaments nor armoury, neither fire-offerings nor prayers, save a man approached by death or old age.</p>
<!--paraṁ-->
<!--bhavari-->
<!--no-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One who sees a tottering old man, an ailing man or a dead man, and is not duly grieved, he is devoid of sensibility.</p>
<!--kaś-->
<!--krā-->

<p>One may conquer the earth up to the oceans, and still shall he not cross over old age and death.</p>
<!--jarārūpeṇa-->
<!--n-->
<!--bhū-->

<p>Death stalks over the earth in the disguise of old age. Its constituents are days and nights. It opens its mouth wide to swallow the creatures just like a snake to gulp in gusts of wind.</p>
<!--ḍi-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>An old man can neither enjoy nor eschew the pleasures of life. He is like a toothless dog who can only lick the bone.</p>
<!--dine dine-->
<!--nīyamānasya-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>As each day passes, death approaches closer and closer. Just as with every step, the condemned criminal is brought nearer to execution.</p>
<!--saṁ-->
<!--kriyate-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>I shall do this, thereafter will happen this. Death does not wait upon such resolves.</p>
<!--yathā phalānāṁ pakvānāṁ nānyatra-->
<!--tathā narānāṁ jātānāṁ nānyatra -->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>There is no other danger for ripe fruits but that of falling. Similarly for men who are born there is no other danger than dying.</p>
<!--jīva-->

<p>Even pierced by hundreds of darts one does not die because his appointed time has not arrived. On the other hand, if the time is ripe one does not survive the touch of a reed spike.</p>
<!--duḥkhaṁ-->
<!--cānekakāraṇam-->
<!--dehe-->

<p>When death, old age, disease and multicaused pain are sticking to the body, why then does man stay unconcerned.</p>
<!--tiṣṭhantaṁ-->

<p>When death pursues you whether you are standing or lying, then why, my little child, are you sleeping like a fish in a tiny shallow pool.</p>
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>How will you traverse alone the dark jungle path, without a resting place, without food, without a hold and without a guide ?</p>
<!--visaṁjñaḥ-->
<!--sthiraniś-->
<!--nā-->
<!--ṣṭi-->
<!--kva dārāḥ kva-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>When thou art being taken into the great abyss of darkness, unconscious, eyes petrified, hiccoughing, breaths approaching their last, where then thy wife, thou thyself and thy kinsmen?</p>
<!--jar-->
<!--ṅga-->
<!--hā-->
<!--ṇī-->
<!--saukr̥taṁ-->

<p>Before old age should make your body totter and rob you of strength and beauty, accumulate the treasure of noble deeds.</p>
<!--yā-->
<!--tasya-->
<!--bhavanti-->
<!--kāryya-->

<p>Accumulations of gold and jewels made honestly or dishonestly do not help when the body is wasted away.</p>
<!--anityaṅ-->
<!--yauvanaṁ rūpaṁ jīvitaṁ-->

<p>Youth and loveliness do not last. Neither do life, heaps of goods, health or the company of beloved ones. One who is greedy is not a pandita.</p>
<!--tāyā-->
<!--ṣadvi-->
<!--yā-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Trust not in the smallness of fire, diseae, poison and enemies. Though small in size they are capable of immense harm. Similarly do not trust the greatness of health, glory and age. They can be shortened or brought to an end abruptly.</p>

<p>What wise man would put faith in women, kings, snakes, studies, pleasures, life or in one who is serving an enemy.</p>
<!--bhū-->
<!--duḥkheḥ-->

<p>Observing that death and old age are natural and that all beings are tormented by pains and sorrows, the wise laud deliverance that is within one's own reach.</p>
<!--The entire line is different from that of RaghuVira, I read "jīvitaṁ ca śarīraṁ ca jātyā vai saha jāyate"-->
<!--"This line as well is different from that of RaghuVira, I read ubhe saha vivarddhete ubhe saha pinaśyataḥ"-->
<!--It seems that the reference number in RaghuVira which is 12,217.006 is not match with the presented reading,  -->

<p>Life and body are born together. Together they grow and together they perish.</p>
<!--This line is also different from that of RaghuVira, I read "yadyaccharīreṇa karoti karma śarīrayuktaḥ samupāśnute tat"-->
<!-- I read "śarīramevāyatani sukhasya duḥkhasya vāto’sya bhave na bhāve"-->

<p>Whatever action one does with the body, the fruit of that one enjoys or suffers along wiith the body. The body is the abode of joys and sorrows. So let us not be born hereafter.</p>
<!--The line is different from that of RaghuVira, I read "evamabhyāhate loke kālenābinipiḍite"-->
<!--I read "sumahad dhairyyamālambya mano mokṣe niveśayet-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>When death (or time) afflicts and torments the world like this, one should take refuge in fortitude and devote the mind to deliverance.</p>
<!--I read "panthānau pitr̥yānaśca devayānaśca viśrutau"-->
<!--I read "janminaḥ pitr̥yānena devayānena mokṣiṇaḥ-->

<p>Two are the well-known Paths-the Path of the Fathers and the Path of the Gods. Those who are to be reborn go by the Path of the Fathers, those who are
to be delivered go by the Path of the Gods.</p>
<!--I read "yajñaistapobhirniyamairvrataiśca divaṁ samāsādya patanti bhūyaḥ"-->
<!--I read "tasmādupāsyaṁ paramaṁ pavitraṁ śivaṁ vimokṣaṁ vimalaṁ bhudhena.-->

<p>By practising yajñas, austerities, disciplines and vows one reaches heaven but at the expiry of his term he falls back to earth. Hence the wise man should wait upon Śiva, the supreme, the pure, the liberator, the spotless.</p>
<!--I read "pramlāneṣu ca mālyeṣu tataḥ pipati pākṣayāt"-->
<!--I read "ābrahmanavanādete doṣā brahman sudāruṇāḥ"-->
<!--perhaps these two are related?-->

<p>The heavenly garlands fade and one descends to earth. It is a severe calamity. It continues till one reaches Brahmahood.</p>
<!--I read "patantastu mahāduḥkhaṁ paritāpaṁ sudaruṇam"-->
<!--I read "svargabhājaḥ prāpnavanti tasmāt svargaṁ na kāmaye"-->

<p>Falling down is very painful. Those who share the joys of heaven, afterwards endure intense agony. Hence, I do not long for heaven.</p>
<!--I read "narake yātanāduḥkhaṁ tiryyakaṣvanyo’nyabhakṣaṇam"-->
<!--I read"kṣuttr̥ṣāduḥkhaṁ preteṣu paryyoti vyasanaṁ nr̥ṣu"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>In hell there is the pain of tortures. Among the lower creatures there is cannibalism. Among the ghosts there is the torment of hunger and thirst. Among men calamities hold the siege.</p>
<!--I read "prātarmūtrapurīṣābyāṁ madhyāhne kṣutpipāsayā"-->
<!--I read "tr̥ptāḥ kāmena bādhyante jantapo niśi nidrayā"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Creatures are pressed by the call of nature in the morning and by hunger and thirst in the midday. When they are full cupid presses them. And at night sleep.</p>
<!--I read "uddharedātmanātmānaṁ nātmānamavasādayet-->
<!--I read "ātmaiva hyātmano bandhurātmaiva ripurātmanaḥ"-->

<p>One should raise himself. Never should one depress himself. Self is both the friend and enemy of self.</p>
<!--I read "cittameva hi saṁsāro rāgādikleśadūṣitam"-->
<!--I read "tadeva tairviyuktaṁ ca bhavānta iti kathyate"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Consciousness, defiled by excessive attachment and other affiictions, forms our world. The same consciousness, when liberated from these, is known as the end of our world.</p>
<!--I read "ekaḥ śatrur na dvitīyo 'sti śatrurajñānatulyaḥ puruṣasya rājan"-->
<!--I read "yenāvr̥taḥ kurute sampravr̥ttaḥ pāpāni karmāṇi sudāruṇāni"-->

<p>Of man there is just one enemy. There is no other enemy equal to ignorance, 0 king. Under its influence one does horrible deeds.</p>
<!--I read "ajñānaprabhavaṁ hīdaṁ yad duḥkham upalabhyate"-->
<!-- I read"lobhādeva tadajñānamajñābhāllobha eva ca"-->

<p>Pain originates in ignorance. Ignorance originates in greed. Greed originates in ignorance.</p>
<!-- I read "tasmāt samyak parīkṣeta doṣān ajñānasaṁbhavān" -->
<!-- I read "ajñānaprabhavaṁ nityam ahaṅkāraṁ parrjayet"-->

<p>Therefore one should duly keep watch on faults arising out of ignorance. Moreover one should ever avoid egoism.</p>
<!--I read "prajñayā nirmitair dhīrās tārayanty abudhān plavaiḥ"-->
<!-- I read "nābudhās tārayanty anyān ātmānaṃ vā kadā cana"-->

<p>The wise take the unwise across on wisdom's float. The unwise can ferry across neither others nor themselves.</p>
<!-- I read "netrahīno yathā hy ekaḥ kr̥cchrāṇi labhate 'dhvani"-->
<!--I read "jñānahīnas tathā loke tasmāj jñānavido 'dhikāḥ"-->

<p>Just one without eyes stumbles on the road, so in life one without know ledge. Hence those knowing knowledge are the superior ones.</p>
<!--I read "aniṣṭasaṃprayogāc ca viprayogāt priyasya ca"-->
<!--I read "manuṣyā mānasair duḥkhair yujyante ye’lpabuddhayaḥ"-->

<p>Men of little wisdom suffer mental agonies when they encounter what they desire not and lose what they cherish.</p>
<!-- I read "yathā hiraṇyakartā vai rūpyam agnau viśodhayet"-->
<!-- I read "bahuśo hyaprayatnena yatnena nacireṇa hi"-->

<p>Just as a goldsmith can purify silver or gold, without effort in a long while, but with effort iu a short while, ... ...(continued in the next stanza)</p>
<!-- I read "tadvaj jātiśatair jīvaḥ śudhyate 'lpena karmaṇā"-->
<!-- I read "yatnena mahatā capihyekajātau viśudhyate"-->

<p>(continued from the previous stanza) ... so by small actions a soul is  purified in a hundred births, though by immense effort it may be purified in a single incarnation.</p>
<!--I read "līlayālpaṃ yathā gātrāt pramr̥jyād ātmano rajaḥ"-->
<!--I read "bahu yatnena mahatā doṣanirharaṇaṃ tathā"-->

<p>A little dirt on body is removed easily, but if it is much it takes effort. So is it with the removal of faults.</p>
<!--I read "kṣamayā krodham ucchindyāt kāmaṃ saṃkalpavarjanāt-->
<!-- I read "lobhaṃ mohaṃ ca santoṣād viṣayāṃs tattvadarśanāt"-->

<p>Root out anger by forgiveness, sensuality by avoidance of thinking about it, greed and infatuation by contentment, passions by viewing the ultimate nature of objects.</p>
<!--I read "āyatyā varj jayed āśām arthaṃ saṅgavivarjanāt"-->
<!--I read "anityatvena ca snehaṃ duḥkhaṃ yogena paṇḍitaḥ"-->

<p>Hope can he avoided by appeal to destiny, wealth by avoiding attachment, affection by pondering over non-permanence and pain by yoga.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza  405 "kāruṇyenātmano mānaṃ tr̥ṣṇāṃ ca paritoṣataḥ"-->
<!-- "utthānena jayet tandrīṃ vitarkaṃ niścayāj jayet"-->

<p>One should conquer pride by compassion, greed by contentment, lassitude by energy and doubt by certainty.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza  406 which reads "mānaṃ hitvā priyo nityaṃ kāmaṃ hitvā sukhī bhavet"-->
<!--"krodhaṃ hitvā nirāghādhastr̥ṣnāṁ jitvā na tapyate"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>By giving up pride one becomes beloved, by giving up sensuality one becomes happy, by giving up anger one's obstacles are removed, by conquering greed one is never pained.</p>
<!-- The reading is found in stanza 407 above which reads "avaśyamindriyaistāta varttitavyaṃ svagocare"-->
<!-- "caṇḍarāgastu yastatra taṃ ghudhaḥ parivarjjayet"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Each sense must keep within its own field. One who is intensely impassioned should be avoided by the wise.</p>
<!--The reading is stanza 408 above "aprārthanamasaṁsparśamasandarśanameva ca"-->
<!--"puruṣasyeha niyamo bhavedrāgaprahāṇaye" -->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>For removing attachment, a person should neither think nor touch nor see the objects of attachments.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 409 above "saṁkalpājjāyate rāgaḥ sevyamāno vivardhate"-->
<!--"avādyadarśanādvyeti tattvajñānācca dhīmatām"-->

<p>By thinking is attachment born, by practising it increases, by ugly sights and philosophical knowledge it is removed.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 410 above "sarvatra sampadastasya santuṣṭaṁ yasya mānasam"-->
<!--"upānadgūdhapādasya nanucarmastr̥teva bhūḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>He whose mind is contented has wealth all over. It is like a person whose foot is guarded hy a shoe. For him the whole earth is spread over with leather.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 411 above "pr̥thivyāṁ yadvr̥īhiyavaṁ hiraṇyaṁ paśavaḥ striyaḥ"-->
<!--"nālamekasya tadvittamiti matvā śamaṁ vrajet"-->

<p>Translation is not available</p>
<!-- The reading is found in stanza 412 above "dravyeṣu samatīteṣu ye guṇāstānna cintayet"-->
<!--"tānanādriyamāṇasya snehastasya praṇaśyati"-->

<p>One should not brood over past pleasures. By disregarding them one destroys his love for them.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 413 above "prīteḥ śokaḥ prabhavati viyogārttasya dehinaḥ" -->
<!--"yadā nirarthakaṁ vetti tadā sadyaḥ praṇaśyati"-->

<p>Love produces sorrow at separation. When one realises that love is meaningless, then it disappears immediately.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 414 above "nidrā sarvvā tyājyā svapna doṣānavekṣya vai" -->
<!--"svapne hi rajasā dehī tamasā vābhibhūyate"-->

<p>Seeing the many failings caused by sleep one should resolutely withstand it in all activities. It is during sleep that mist and darkness take hold of one.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 415 "naktaṁcaryāṁ divāsvapnamālasyaṁ maithunaṁ madam"-->
<!--"dainyaṁ vīṣayogaṁ tu śreyor’thī parivarjayet"-->

<p>Wandering at night, sleeping during day, indolence, sensuality, intoxication, meanness and passions should one desirous of weal avoid altogether.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 416 "viṣayāṇāṁ ca daurātmyādindriyānāṁ ca cāpalāt"-->
<!--"manasaścānavasthānāt sarvakr̥cchreṣu tiṣṭhati"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>On account of the depravity of bodily passions, the fickleness of senses and the instability of mind one gets into all kinds of difficult situations.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 417 "viṣayān pratyavasituṁ na jātu labhate dhr̥tim"-->
<!--"śyenacchāyāmanupatan kapiñjala ivātape"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Enjoying sensual pleasures one is never satisfied. It is like a heath cock who seeks to fly in the shade of a hawk.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 418 "na jātu kāmaḥ kāmyāṇāmupabhogena śāmyati"-->
<!--"haviṣā kr̥ṣnavartmeva bhūya eva vivardhate"-->

<p>Desire does not terminate by the use of desired objects. It is like fire which increases by the putting of oblations.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 419 "na strībyaḥ kiñcidanyadvai pāpīyo bhuvi vidyate"-->
<!--"striyo mūlamanarthānāṁ manasāpi ca cintitāḥ "-->
<!--Raghu Vira notes Mbh. (Citrasala ed.) 13,038.012-->

<p>There is nothing more sinister than pursuing women. That is the root of all evils.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 420 "strīkr̥to grāmanigamaḥ strīkr̥taḥ krayavikrayaḥ"-->
<!--"striyo mūlamanarthānāṁ tasmānnaitāḥ pariṣvajet"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Women make the market, they make the sales and purchases.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 421 "antakaḥ pavano mr̥tyuḥ pātālaṁ vaḍavāmukham"-->
<!--"kṣuradhārā viṣaṁ sarpo vahnirityekataḥ striyaḥ"-->

<p>Devastating wind, death, nether-world, oceanic fire, razor's edge, poison, snake and fire on the one hand and pursuit of women on the other.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 422 "ānāyamiva matsyānāṁ pañjaraṁ śakuneriva"-->
<!--"samastapāśaṁ mūḍasya bandhanaṁ vāmalocanā" -->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A net catches fish, a cage keeps the bird captive, a lovely-eyed dame binds and imprisons the fool.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 423 "nāsāṁ kaścidagamyo’sti nāsāṁ vayasi niścayaḥ"-->
<!--"virūpaṁ vā surūpaṁ vā pumānityeva bhuñjate"-->

<p>Women run after men, not because one is worthy, young or beautiful, but because he is a male.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 424 "anarthitavānmanuṣyāṇāṁ bhayātparibhavāttathā"-->
<!--"maryādāyāmamaryādāḥ striyastiṣṭhanti bhartr̥ṣu"-->

<p>Women care not for bounds, and yet they remain in bounds, faithful to their husbands, either because there is nobody to woo, or out of fear and insult.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 425 "uśanā veda yacchāstraṁ yacca veda vr̥haspatiḥ"-->
<!--"ubhe te na viśiṣyeta strībuddhistu viśiṣyate"-->
<!--Raghu Vira notes MBh.l3.39.89 (cd are missing).-->

<p>The learning of Uśanā and Vrəhaspati do not match the intelligence of women.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 426 "nāgnistr̥pyati kāṣṭānāṁ nāpagānāṁ mahodadhiḥ"-->
<!--"nāntakaḥ sarvabhūtānāṁ na puṁsāṁ vāmalocanā"-->

<p>Fire is not satiated with fuel, ocean is not satiated with rivers, death is not satiated with creatures, a woman is not satiated with men.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 427 "yasya jihvāsahasraṁ syājjīvecca śarada śatam"-->
<!--"ananyakarmā strīdoṣānnaivoktvā nidhanaṁ vrajet"-->

<p>If there be some one who has a thousand tongues, and he should live for a hundred years, with nothing else to do but to narrate the faults of women, he would die without exhausting the narration.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 428 "aṅgārasadr̥śī nārī ghr̥takumchasamaḥ pumān"-->
<!--"ye prasaktā vilīnāste ye sthitāste pade sthitāḥ "-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A woman is like burning charcoals. A man is like a pot of ghee. When the man comes near, he melts. If he stays away, he remains solid and firm.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 429 "strī nāma māyā nikr̥tiḥ krodhamātsaryavigrahā"-->
<!--"dūrat tyajedanāryāṁ tāṁ jvalitāmedhyavadbudhaḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>A woman is magic and illusion, made up of wrath and envy.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 430 "svabhāvaścaiva nārīṇāṁ narāṇāmiha dūṣaṇam"-->
<!--"itthaṁ vai na pramādyanti pramadāsu vipaścitaḥ"-->

<p>It is in the nature of women to attract men. The wise have to he careful.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 431 "yeṣu yeṣu pradeśeṣu kāyo’tyantajugupsitaḥ"-->
<!--"teṣu teṣu janaḥ sakto vairāgyaṁ kena yāsyati "-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p><!-- no translation is avaibale-->

<!--The reading is found in stanza 432 "ko hi nāma manuṣyeṣu jānannapi vicakṣaṇaḥ"-->
<!--"hariṇīpadamātreṇa carmaṇā na khalīkr̥taḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p><!--no translation is avaibale
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 433 "prasvedamaladigdhena vahatā mūtraśoṇitam"-->
<!--"vraṇena vivr̥tenaiva sarvamandhīkr̥taṁ jagat"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p><!--no translation is avaibale
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 434 "kūlāni nāsya pātyante na kathamapi khanyate"-->
<!--"khanakaiva kṣayaṁ yāti balena ca dhanena ca"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p><!--no translation is avaibale
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 435 "yānyeva malavāhīni pūticchidrāṇi yoṣitām"-->
<!--"tānyeva khalu kāmyāni aho puṁsāṁ viḍambanā"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p><!-- no translation is avaibale
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 436 "yoṣitāṁ na kathā śravyā na nirīkṣyā nirambarāḥ"-->
<!--"kadāciddarśanāttāsāṁ durbalānāviśedrajaḥ"-->

<p>One should neither hear stories of women, nor view them undressed, Thereby passion is likely to enter the mind of the weak.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 437 "mātrā svasrā duhitrā vā na viviktāsano bhavet"-->
<!--"balavānindriyagrāmo vidvāṁsamapi karṣati"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>One should not sit alone with mother, sister or daughter. Lust is powerful.  It drags even  the learned.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 438 "koṭarāgnir yathāśeṣaṁ samūlaṁ pādapaṁ dahet"-->
<!--"dharmārthaṁ ca tathā loke rāgadveṣo vināśayet"-->

<p>As a fire in the hollow of a tree destroys the tree completely, so passions and jealousies seated inside the heart of man destroy dharma and artha.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 439 "kāmo bandhanamevaikaṁ nānyadastīha bandhanam"-->
<!--"kāmabandhanamukto hi brahmabhūyāya kalpate"-->

<p>There is only one bondage, that of kāma. When released one attains Brahma-hood.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 440 "yaḥ sandhārayate manyuṁ yo’tivādaṁstitikṣati "-->
<!--"yaśca tapto na tapati sa bhr̥śaṁ śamabhājanam"-->

<p>One who holds his ire in check and forbears abuses and revilings and does not get excited when people try to heat him up, he is the worthy repository of calmness and equanimity.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 441 "atathyenocyamānasya kaḥ kopo yanna tattathā"-->
<!--"tathyenāpi hi kaḥ kopo yadanukte’pi tat tathā"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>When one speaks what is not so, why be angry. And why be angry with what is so. Without being said it is so.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 442 "rāgābhibhūtaḥ puruṣaḥ kāmena parigamyata"-->
<!--"icchā sañjāyate cādya tatastr̥ṣṇā pravartate"-->

<p>The sequence is rāga, then kāma, then icchā, and finally trəṣṇā.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 443 "tr̥ṣṇā hi sarvapāpiṣṭhā nityodvega karī matā "-->
<!--"adharmabahulā caiva ghorā pāpānubandhinī "-->

<p>Trəṣṇā is the wickedest of all. It keeps a man excited all the while. It is infested with adharma. It is terrible. Its consequences are dire sin.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 444 "āsannānpurato bhogāndarśáyitvā punaḥ punaḥ"-->
<!--"chāgo haritamuṣṭyeva dūraṁ nīto’smi tr̥ṣṇayā"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Like a goat, whom men delude by holding in its front a tuft of green twigs, I have been tempted far out of the way by trəṣṇā, repeatedly showing me nearby pleasures.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 445 "yauvanaṁ jarayā grastamārogyaṁ vyādhibhirhr̥tam"-->
<!--"jivitaṁ mr̥tyurabhyeti tr̥ṣṇaikā nirupadravā"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Old age devours youth, disease carries away health, death pounces upon life, trəṣṇā alone has no enemies.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 446 "jīryanti jīryataḥ keśā dantā jīryanti jīryataḥ"-->
<!--"jīvitāśā dhanāśā ca jīryato ’pi na jīryati"-->

<p>When the body decays, hair and teeth too decay along with. But not so the hope to live and to gain wealth.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 447 "na talloke dravyamasti yattr̥ṣṇāmabhipūrayet"-->
<!--"samudrakalpaḥ puruṣo na kathañcana pūryate"-->

<p>There is no matter that can fulfil avidity. Like the ocean an avid person is never fully filled.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 448 "yathaiva śr̥ṅgaṁ goḥ kāle vardhamānasya vardhate"-->
<!--"tathaiva tr̥ṣṇā vittena vardhamānena vardhate"-->

<p>Just as a horn grows with the growing bull, so does avidity grow with growing possessions.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 449 "akartavyeṣvasādhvīva tr̥ṣṇā prerayate janam"-->
<!--"tameva sarvapāpebhyo lajjā māteva rakṣati"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Avidity is like a fallen woman. It instigates a person into wrongful actitivities. Modesty is like a mother. It guards a person against all sins.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 450 "tr̥ṣṇā lokatrayasyāsya nirvairaparimanthinī"-->
<!--"yaistu nirmokavattyaktā ko daridraḥ ka īśvaraḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Avidity curdles and tortures the three worlds, though the worlds have done no wrong to it. When avidity is shaken off like a slough, there is no one who is left poor or rendered rich.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 451 "yā dustyajā durmatibhiryā na jīryati jīryataḥ"-->
<!--"yo’sau prāṇāntiko rogastāṁ tr̥ṣnāṁ tyajataḥ sukham"-->

<p>Ill-minded men can hardly give up avidity. It grows with them. It isa disease which terminates in death. He who renounces it, becomes happy.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 452 "yacca kāmasukhaṁ loke yacca divyaṁ mahatsukham"-->
<!--"tr̥ṣnākṣayasukhasyaite nārhataḥ ṣoḍaśīṁ kalām"-->

<p>Pleasures of love and the great divine joys do not add up to one-sixteenth bit of the relief from avidity.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 453 "eko lobho mahāgrāho lobhāt pāpaṁ pravartate"-->
<!--"tataḥ pāpādadharmāptistato duḥkhaṁ pravartate"-->

<p>Greed alone is a great shark. From greed proceeds sin. From sin arises adharma. Thence pain and torture.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 454 "pāpānāṁ viddhayadhiṣṭhānaṁ lobha eva narottama"-->
<!--"lubdhāḥ pāpaṁ prakurvanti suvidvāṁso’pi mānavāḥ"-->

<p>0 best of men, know thou that the seat of sins is in greed. It is the greedy who sin, even though they be highly learned.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 455 "asantoṣo’sukhāyaiva lobhādindriyavibhramaḥ"-->
<!--"tato’sya naśyati prajñā vidyevābhyāsavarjitā"-->

<p>Non-contentment is painful. Greed confounds the senses. That leads to the loss of wisdom. It is like the loss of learning due to want of practice.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 456 "arthānāmarjane duḥkhamarjitānāṁ ca rakṣaṇe"-->
<!--"nāśe duḥkhaṁ kṣaye duḥkhaṁ dhigarthānduḥkhavardhanam "-->
<!--Raghu Vira notes "Cf.MBh03,002.042"-->

<p>Earning of money is painful, so is its guarding. Its loss is painful, as also its wasting away. At all stages money augments pain.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 457 "vimohayanti sampatsu tāpyanti vipatsu ca"-->
<!--"khedyantyarjanakāle kadā bhogāḥ sukhāvahāḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>In prosperity wealth turns the head,in decline it causes agony, in earning it causes strain. When is it that wealth brings undiluted pleasure.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 458 "rājataḥ salilād agneś corataḥ svajanād api"-->
<!--"bhayam arthavatāṁ nityaṁ mr̥tyoḥ prāṇabhr̥tām iva "-->

<p>Men of money are always in fear of the state, water, fire, thief and even of one's own relations. Just like the fear of death to living creatures.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 459 "yathā hyāmiṣamākāśe pakṣibhiḥ śvāpadairbhuvi "-->
<!--"bhakṣyate salile matsyaistathā sarveṇa vittavān"-->

<p>Just as in air flesh is consumed by bird, on ground by beasts, in water by fish, so a moneyed man is eaten up by all.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 460 "sañcaye ca vināśānte maraṇānte ca jīvite"-->
<!--"saṁyoge viprayogānte ko vitte praṇayenmanaḥ"-->

<p>When accumulation must end in dispersal, life in death and association in separation, who would put his mind in money ?</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 461 "parityajya priyānprāṇānpraviśanti raṇājire"-->
<!--"puruṣāḥ preṣyatāmanye nirgacchanti dhanārthinaḥ"-->

<p>While there are people who not caring for their dear life step in to the field of battle, there are others who in search for lucre stir our to serve others.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 462 "doṣāśrayamapāyāntamaiśvaryaṁ kāmayeta kaḥ"-->
<!--"yatsampattau vipattau vā janayatyeva vikriyām "-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Who would long for power that harbours faults and upsets one both in woe and weal.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 463 "trayo madā mahārāja mohyantyavicakṣaṇam"-->
<!--"striyo’nnapānamaiśvāryaṁ teṣu saktā na jāgrati "-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>There are three intoxicants, 0 great king, that confound the undiscernin–women, food and drink, power. Given to them, he sleeps, he does not wake.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 464 "sampadaḥ pramadāścaiva taraṅgotsaṅgabhaṅgurāḥ"-->
<!--"kastāsvahiphaṇachattrachāyāsviva ramedbudhaḥ"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Riches and dames are fragile like surging wave. What wise man would seek to shelter in the shade of a cobra's hood?</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 465 "mā tāta vistaraṁ kārṣīḥ sampadbhiḥ pravimohit"-->
<!--"svagātrāṇyapi bhārāya bhavanti vidhiparyaye"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>My dear one, infatuated by possessions, do not expand too far. At the turn of fate even one's limbs become a burden.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 466 "ākiñcanye ca rājye ca viśeṣaḥ sumahānayam"-->
<!--"nityodvigno hi dhanavānsarvaṁ tyaktvā sukhī bhavet"-->

<p>Between pauperhood and kingship the vast difference is this-the wealthy man is always worried.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 467 "na hi sañcayavānkaściddr̥śyate nirupadravaḥ-->
<!--"tyajeta sañcayāṁstasmātprajñaḥ kleśaṁ sahaiva ca"-->

<p>There is not to be seen a single accumulative person who is without trouble. Therefore an intelligent person should give up both accumulations and worries.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 468 "pratyūhapaṭaho rājñaḥ sāmānyapuravāsibhiḥ"-->
<!--"mā maivamiti yo bhāvaḥ sa tasya prītikārakaḥ "-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>...</p> <!--no translation is available for this stanza>
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 469 "arthāṁśca durlabhāṁloke kleśāṁśca sulabhāṁstathā"-->
<!--"duḥkhaṁ caiva kuṭumbārthaṁ yaḥ paśyati sa mucyate"-->

<p>One who realizes that looking after the famil y involves the strife for hard monies and easy afflictions, gets released.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 470 "alaṁ parigraheṇaiva doṣavānsaparigrahaḥ"-->
<!-- krimirhi koṣakāro hi badhyate svaparigrahāt"-->

<p>Enough of surrounding oneself with accumulations. They are dangerous.The silkworm making the cocoon is imprisoned thereby.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 471 "yāvataḥ kurute jantuḥ sambandhānmanasaḥ priyān"-->
<!--"tāvanto’sya vidhīyante hr̥daye śokaśaṅkavaḥ"-->

<p>Whatever affectionate ties a creature creates, so many are the nails of potential separation that are struck into the heart.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 472 "mānasaṁ duḥkhamūlaṁ tu sneha ityupalabyate"-->
<!--"snehācca sajjate janturduḥkhayogamupaiti ca"-->

<p>The psychological root of pain is affection. It is affection which ties a creature and ultimately leads to pain.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 473 "putradārakuṭumbeṣu saktāḥ sīdanti jantavaḥ"-->
<!--"saraḥpaṅkārṇave magnā jīrṇā vanagajā iva"-->

<p>Creatures attached to sons, wives and families sink down like the aged wild elephant in a mass of muddy swamp.</p>
		
<!--The reading is found in stanza 474 "etattaddurjayaṁ loke putradāramayaṁ viṣam"-->
<!--"jāyante ca mriyante ca yatpītvā mohitāḥ prajāḥ "-->
<!-- Perhaps 12,306.047 is related-->

<p>The poison exuded by sons and wife is invincible. Infatuated creatures drink this poison and are  born and die time and again.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 475 "svadehajānasvasaṁjñānyadvadaṅgātkr̥imaṁstyajeta"-->
<!--"svasaṁjñānasvajāṁstadvatsutasaṁjñānkri̥maṁstyajet"-->

<p>...</p> <!-- no translation is available 
-->
<!--The reading is found in stanza 476 "yatra sneho bhayaṁ tatra sneho duḥkhasya bhājanam"-->
<!--"snehamūlāni duḥkhāni tasmiṁstyakte mahatsukham"-->

<p>Where there is affection, there is fear. Affection is the pot of pain. Affection is the root of pain. Giving that up brings great relief.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 477 "svajane na ca te cintā karttavyā mokṣabuddhinā"-->
<!--"ime mayā vinā tāta bhaviṣyanti kathaṁ nviti"-->

<p>If you aspire after mokṣa, you have not to worry about your family members as to what will happen to them without you.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 478 "svayamutpadyate jantuḥ svayameva vivardhate"-->
<!--"sukhaduḥkhe tathā mr̥tyuṁ svayamevādhigacchati"-->

<p>By itself is a creature born, by itself does it grow, and by itself does it reach joys, sorrows and death.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 479 "yathā kāṣṭhaṁ ca kāṣṭhaṁ ca sameyātāṁ mahodadhau"-->
<!--"sametya ca vyapeyātāṁ tadvadbhutasamāgamaḥ"-->

<p>Just as in an ocean one log of wood meets another and drifts apart again, so is the coming together of creatures.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 480 "evaṁ putrāśca pautrāśca jñātayaḥ suhr̥dastathā"-->
<!--"atisneho na kartavyo viprayogo dhruvo hi taiḥ"-->

<p>Thus one should not be overfond of sons, grandsons, relatives and friends. There is bound to be separation.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 481 "mātāpitr̥sahasrāṇi putradāraśatāni ca"-->
<!--"yuge yuge vyatītāni kasya te kasya vā vayam"-->

<p>Thousands of mothers and fathers, hundreds of sons and wives have  passed away in ages gone by. Whose are they, whose are we?</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 482 "nāyamatyantasaṁvāsaḥ kadācit kenacit saha"-->
<!--"api svena marīreṇa kimutānyena kenacit"-->

<p>There is no eternity of association with any one, not even with one's body, not to mention with any other.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 483 "ādarśanādāpatitāḥ punaścādarśanaṁ gatāḥ"-->
<!--"na te tava na teṣāṁ tvaṁ kā tatra paridevanā"-->

<p>They have fallen from out of the invisible. Again they will go out into the invisible. They are not thine, thou art not theirs. What can then the wailing be ?</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 484 "naṣṭe dhane vā dāreṣu putre pitari mātari"-->
<!--"aho kaṣṭamiti dhyātvā duḥkhasyāpacitiṁ caret"-->

<p>Gone are wealth and wife, son and parents. How painful! Brooding over one should follow the path of diminishing pain.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 485 "mr̥taṁ vā yadi vā naṣṭaṁ yo’tītamanuśocati"-->
<!--"duḥkhena duḥkhamāpnoti dvāvanarthau prapadyate"-->

<p>One who laments over the dead, the lost and the past, the sorrow is doubled thereby.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 486 "bhaiṣajyametadduḥkhasya yadetannānucintayet"-->
<!--"cintyamānaṁ hi na vyeti bhūyaścāpi pravartate"-->

<p>Not lamenting is the medicament for sorrow. When one thinks about it, it does not disappear. It goes even farther.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 487 "dhanaṁ vā puruṣo rājanpuruṣaṁ vā punardhanam"-->
<!--"avaśyaṁ prajahātyeva tadvidvān nānusaṁsayet"-->

<p>Either man leaves money, or money leaves man. This cannot be helped. Knowing this why should one sing its praises.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 488 "purasatādeva te buddhiriyaṁ kāryā vijānata"-->
<!--"anityaṁ sarvamevedamahaṁ ca mama cāsti yat"-->

<p>From the very start you should fix it in your mind that all this–I and what pertains to me–will not last forever.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 489 "anityatve kr̥tamatirmlānamālyena śocati"-->
<!--"nityatve kr̥tabuddhistu bhinnabhāṇḍe’nuśocati"-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>When the mind is conscious of transitoriness, it is not saddened by the withering garland. But the mind which takes things to be eternal, even a broken pot makes it grieved.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 490 "svayamutpādyate vahniḥ parītastena vahninā"-->
<!--"dahyamānaḥ parītāpaṁ bhajate na sa paṇḍitaḥ"-->
<!--Perhaps 11,001.032 is related?-->

<p>If one should generate fire, and the fire should surround him, he would not be wise if he were to complain of having been scorched.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 491 "sukhaṁ ca duḥkhaṁ ca bhavābhavau ca lābhālābhau maraṇaṁ jīvitaṁ ca"-->
<!--"paryāyataḥ sarvamiha evāviśanti tasmāddhīro naiva tapyenna hr̥ṣyet"-->

<p>Joy and sorrow, being and non-being, gain and loss, life and death affect all, turn by turn. Let the wise be neither full of sorrow nor of glee.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 492 "sukhamāpatitaṁ sevanduḥkhamāpatitaṁ bhaja"-->
<!--"kālaṁprāptamupāsīta sasyānāmiva karṣakaḥ"-->

<p>One should nurse the happiness that befalls one, and withstand the calamity. Like a farmer the crops, so one should meet what time brings.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 493 "sukhaṁ vā yadi vā duḥkhaṁ bhūtānāṁ paryupasthitam"-->
<!--"prāptavyamavaśaiḥ sarvaṁ parihāro na vidyate"-->

<p>Be it comfort or discomfort that presents itself, all that has to be suffered. There is no release.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 494 "sukhasyānantaraṁ duḥkhaṁ duḥkhasyānantaraṁ sukham"-->
<!--"paryāyeṇopavartante naraṁ nemimarā iva"-->

<p>Pain follows joy. Joy follows pain. They come to man in turns, like the spokes attached to the felly of the wheel.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 495 "jñānavāneva puruṣaḥ saṁyuktaḥ parayā dhiyā"-->
<!--"udayāstamanajño hi na śocati na hr̥ṣyati"-->

<p>A man of wisdom, endowed with supreme intelligence, not being a fool, neither worries nor gets excited over rise or fall.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 496 -->

<p>One should not be like children. With wisdom he should cure mental troubles and with medicines physical disease. This is within the power of knowledge.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 497 -->

<p>Mental worry scorches the physical frame, like a heated iron ball the water inside a jar.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 498-->

<p>Therefore quieten mental pain with prajñā like fire with water. When mental pain is eliminated, the bodily pain will also subside.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 499-->
<!--reference number is not found-->

<p>Those who have mastered the essence of wisdom and enlightenment, they suffer neither from wrinkles nor from grey hair. Even birth does not operate.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 500-->

<p>When the mind is not agitated in disasters, when there is no longing for pleasures, when sorrow, fear and anger are gone then the ascetic is termed  inflex-ible-minded.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 501-->

<p>Day after day a fool meets thousands of occasions for grief and hundreds for danger. Not so a paṇḍita.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 502-->

<p>It is through intelligence that one crosses over sin. When cleared of sin he attains sattva. Thereafter he gets perfect serenity.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 503-->

<p>The wise man is not engrossed in objects of sense, though he lives among them. The ignorant man, though not living among them, is still engrossed by them.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 504-->

<p>Just us gold mixed with iron does not shine brilliantly on being heated, so knowledge of an immature defiled person does not illuminate.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 505-->

<p>Just as seeds burnt by fire do not sprout, so once the shortcomings are burnt by true knowledge, one is not born again.</p>
<!--The reading is found in stanza 506-->

<p>Just as the path traced by birds in the sky or by fishes in the water is not to be seen, so the path of wise men is not to be divined.</p>
      	</div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
